<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315750a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>750</spn><epn>752</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315750a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Osmotic stress mimics effects of vasopressin on learned behaviour</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>George F.</fnm><snm>Koob</snm><inits>G. F.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Robert</fnm><snm>Dantzer</snm><inits>R.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Floreal</fnm><snm>Rodriguez</snm><inits>F.</inits><super>&Dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Floyd E.</fnm><snm>Bloom</snm><inits>F. E.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Michel</fnm><snm>Le Moal</snm><inits>M.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<aff><super>&ast;</super>Division of Preclinical Neuroscience and Endocrinology, Scripps Clinic and Research Foundation, 10666 North Torrey Pines Road, La Jolla, California 92037, USA</aff>
<aff><super>&dagger;</super>Psychobiologie des Comportements Adaptatifs, Unit&eacute; 259, INSERM, and <super>&Dagger;</super>Neurobiologie des Comportements, Unit&eacute; 176, INSERM, Domaine de Carreire, Rue Camille-Saint-Saens, 33077 Bordeaux, France</aff></aug>
<hst><re year="na" month="4" day="2"/>
<acc year="1985" month="4" day="23"/></hst>
<fp><p>It has been suggested that arginine vasopressin (AVP) is involved in the retention of learned responses, in addition to its classical physiological functions of water retention and modulation of blood pressure. AVP administered subcutaneously (s.c.), intraventricularly or intracerebrally can prolong extinction of active avoidance behaviour<super>1,2</super> and can enhance retention in inhibitory (passive) avoidance<super>3&ndash;5</super>. These effects have been interpreted as a direct action of AVP on the central nervous system to facilitate memory consolidation<super>3,4</super>. AVP also has facilitatory effects on cognitive function in humans<super>6</super>, and marked deficits in AVP function have been associated with certain types of psychopathology<super>7</super>. Alternative hypotheses for the behavioural actions of AVP have involved motivational constructs such as arousal<super>8</super>, and our recent work has focused on the role of arousal resulting from the activation of peripheral visceral signals in the behavioural effects of peripherally administered AVP<super>9&ndash;12</super>. The development of a specific antagonist for AVP<super>13</super>, 1-deaminopenicillamine-2-<i>O</i>-methyl tyrosine arginine vasopressin (dPTyr(Me)AVP), which can reverse the behavioural effects of exogenously administered AVP<super>9&ndash;12</super>, has provided a powerful tool for examining the role of AVP in the behavioural responses produced by physiological challenges known to release vasopressin. However, the relationship between the behavioural effects of exogenously administered AVP and the behavioural function of endogenously released AVP has not been evaluated. We report here that a potent peripheral osmotic stimulus, the intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection of hypertonic saline, at doses known to release AVP both centrally<super>14</super> and peripherally<super>15</super>, will produce behavioural effects similar to those of exogenously administered AVP. Furthermore, the prolongation of active avoidance induced by this osmotic stimulus is reversed by pretreatment with dPTyr(Me)AVP, suggesting that endogenously released AVP may also produce behavioural effects.</p></fp></fm>
<bdy>Male Wistar rats (150-220 g), each handled and weighed once previously, were trained to avoid shock in a pole jump apparatus as described previously2. Briefly, during the initial training of the active avoidance response, the rats were subjected to 10 trials per day where a 5-s conditioned stimulus preceded a 0.3-0.5-mA footshock to the floor. A response during the 5-s conditioned stimulus (light illumination) was recorded as an avoidance and the inter-trial interval was 40,60 or 80 s, randomly assigned across trials. Following 3 days of acquisition, rats were subjected to a fourth day of extinction testing with all conditions identical except that the shock was turned off. Only those rats meeting the previously established acquisition/extinction criteria1'2 were treated; these rats all showed >14 successful avoidance responses during acquisition and >8 avoidances during the first 10 extinction trials. Only these animals were used in the experiment. This criterion was similar to that used by De Wied and associates1 and eliminated 10% of the rats. Four blocks of 10 trials each were run; after the first 10 trials, each rat was treated with either 0.9% saline s.c., 1 g of vasopressin dissolved in 0.9% saline, or different concentrations of hypertonic saline (0.25-2.0 M) injected i.p. in a volume of 2 ml.
Fig. 1 Effects of different doses of hypertonic saline on extinction of active avoidance. Rats were injected with saline i.p. immediately after the first 10 extinction trials on day 4 of testing.  Significantly different from the saline group, ? &lt; 0.05, Student's f-test following a significant overall analysis of variance for each separate extinction session. Numbers of subjects were 83, 11, 52, 34, 11 and 42 in the saline, 0.5 M, 1.0 M, 1.5 M, 2.0 M NaCI and AVP (1 g per rat, -5.4 g per kg) groups, respectively.
Extinction testing was continued for three more blocks of 10 trials, one block every 2 h. Drinking water was available during the testing period. In a second experiment, the procedure was identical except that rats received two injections immediately after the first 10 trials of extinction: 0.9% saline or the AVP pressor antagonist was injected s.c.13, followed immediately by 1.0 or 1.5 M NaCI as an osmotic stimulus. All testing was done under 'blind' conditions, that is, the experimenter did not know which rats received which treatments. Each 4-day testing series consisted of 20 rats randomly assigned to the treatment groups. Each series always contained rats receiving 0.9% saline and AVP s.c., and groups receiving hypertonic saline injections combined with the antagonist were always tested with a group receiving hypertonic saline alone. As a result, many more rats were included in the 0.9% saline (control) group and the AVP group.
The hypertonic saline was injected i.p. to replicate previous studies which measured AVP levels and plasma osmolality. These doses are similar to those used by others15 to show dose-dependent increases in plasma osmolarity and plasma AVP levels. In that study, a dose identical to our 1.0 M NaCI dose in rats of the same weight produced plasma osmolarity of 305mosm per kg and a plasma AVP level of lOpgmP1. Measurements of AVP in the blood in our laboratory (S. Deyo, W. J. Shoemaker, A. Ettenberg, F.E.B. and G.F.K., unpublished results) revealed plasma levels of 13.1 2.2 to 28.43.5 pg ml"1 20 min after s.c. injection of behaviourally effective doses of AVP (0.1-1.0 g per rat). Thus, the osmotic stimuli used here produce plasma AVP levels within the range of those produced with exogenous injection. A similar osmotic challenge (2 and 4 ml of 2 M NaCI) in anaesthetized rats provoked a dramatic increase in AVP release into a push-pull cannula localized to the lateral septum14.
Fig. 2 Effects of the AVP antagonist on the prolongation of extinction produced by hypertonic saline. Data shown represent only those from extinction session III, but results from extinction session IV were identical.  Significantly different from hypertonic saline alone, P &lt; 0.05, Student's f-test following a significant overall analysis of variance for each logical grouping; f significantly different from saline, ? &lt; 0.05. Numbers of subjects were 83, 52, 21, 34, 10 and 42 for the saline, 1.0 M NaCI only, 1.0 M NaCl + 5.0 g per rat (-27 g per kg) dPTyr(Me)AVP, 1.5 M NaCI only, 1.5 M NaCl+10 g per rat (-54 g per kg) dPTyr(Me)AVP, and AVP, respectively. Saline, 1.0 M NaCI, 1.5 M NaCI and AVP groups are the same as in Fig. 1 for extinction session III.
Hypertonic saline injection produced a dose-dependent prolongation of active avoidance, reaching significance at doses of 1.0 and 1.5 M NaCI (Fig. 1); data from 0.25 M NaCI were not different from controls and are not shown. These results were virtually identical to those produced by 1  AVP injected s.c. Following the injection of hypertonic saline, the rats showed some irritability and occasionally some vocalization, but these effects disappeared within 2-3 min. Note that the rats receiving this hypertonic saline injection showed no greater ill effects than those observed following AVP. For example, exogenously administered AVP in behaviourally effective doses produces taste aversions in rats12 and hypertonic saline at the higher doses used in these avoidance experiments (1.5 and 2.0 M NaCI) produced similar taste aversions (R.D. and G.F.K., unpublished results).
At 5 g per rat, the vasopressin antagonist produced an attenuation of this effect of hypertonic saline (Fig. 2). A similar reversal was seen with 10  antagonist after treatment with 1.5 M NaCI (Fig. 2). Preliminary results indicate that this effect may be dose-dependent, in that 2.5  antagonist did not attenuate the prolongation of extinction produced by l M NaCI (mean s.e.m., number of avoidances for extinction session III were 5.90 1.17 for 2.5  per rat compared with 5.790.49 for ?  per rat).
These results demonstrate that an interoceptive osmotic challenge (hypertonic saline), known to release AVP, can mimic the effects of exogenous AVP on learned behaviour. Further, this behavioural effect is reversed by an AVP receptor antagonist, suggesting a causal relationship between the endogenously released AVP and the behavioural change. Similar doses of the AVP antagonists have been used to reverse the behavioural effects of exogenously administered AVP in various learning tasks9'10.
It is unlikely that the antagonist effect in the present experiment is due to an action of the antagonist itself, independent of endogenously released AVP, for example by a general sedative or tranquillizing action. Except for the 100 g dose2, we have observed no effect with this antagonist in reversing prolongation of active avoidance produced by high shock levels during training. Also, the AVP antagonist did not significantly alter caffeine-stimulated locomotion at doses from 2.5 to 10 g per rat (IT-67 g per kg, see Table la). Analysis of variance of these data showed no dose effect and no dose x time interaction (both F &lt; 1). The AVP antagonist also failed to produce any sedative-like actions in an oprant Geller-Seifter conflict test16 that is very sensitive to minor tranquillizers. It did not alter high-rate responding maintained by the random interval 30-s schedule, and also failed to produce a release of punished responding in the conflict component (Table Ib). Finally, the antagonist did not reverse apomorphine-induced taste aversion (R.D., R. M. Bluthe, G.F.K. and M. Le M., unpublished observations). Although it is possible that the hypertonic saline produced elevations in blood pressure that contributed to the behavioural effects, NaCl-induced changes in blood pressure are also reversed by these vasopressor AVP antagonists17, indicating that such a role for pressor responses as an intervening variable with NaCl would be similar to that seen with exogenously administered AVP12.
Table 1    Effects of AVP antagonist dPTyr(Me)AVP on caffeine-stimulated locomotor activity (a) and performance in a multiple-schedule oprant conflict test (fe)
dPTyr(Me)AVPdose
a        Saline 1,238 103
2.5 g 5.0 g                10.0 g (17 g per kg)   (33 g per kg)   (67 g per kg)
1,032 145        1,512 283        1,487 294 dPTyr(Me)AVPdose
b    Component	Saline	(27 g per kg)   (54 g per kg)
Random interval		
30-s schedule	108 18	11718             11129
Conflict	122 30	11319             11322
	M = 5	n=5                  n=5
a, Activity was measured automatically in standard photocell activity cages in continuous ??-min epochs for 90 min following injection of dPtyr(Me)AVPs.c. and 10 mg per kg caffeine (base). For details see rf. 30. ², Food-deprived rats previously trained on the conflict multiple schedule were given dPTyr(Me)AVP s.c. 5 min before an 18-min test session. Schedule and testing procedure are described in rf. 16.
Finally, these and other recent data9"12 reopen the question of the nature of brain-pituitary interactions. One unresolved problem concerns the mechanism mediating this AVP behavioural response. For example, there is little evidence that AVP itself crosses the blood-brain barrier, particularly at doses that would be liberated from the pituitary in the conditions of the present experiment18"22. Furthermore, central AVP pathways exist independently of the classical hypothalamo-posterior pituitary projection23, and both central and peripheral AVP are released by the osmotic challenge used here14'15. De Wied and co-workers have argued for a central site of action based on the observation that a new analogue of vasopressin (pGlu4, Cyt6AVP(4-8)), when injected peripherally, is much more active than AVP itself in facilitating passive avoidance24. This analogue has no pressor activity and its effects can be reversed by an even more potent AVP pressor antagonist25 injected in nanogram amounts intracerebroventricularly. Our earlier work showed that dPTyr(Me)AVP can reverse the effects of centrally administered AVP^6, but will only reverse the behavioural effects of peripherally injected AVP when injected centrally in doses sufficient to reverse the peripheral pressor effects of the same doses27'28. From this we hypothesize an effect of AVP from both central and peripheral sources acting independently but in a homologous fashion29. Thus, in the present experiment, the behavioural change following osmotic challenge could result from a release of AVP from the pituitary and/or the central nervous system.
These results also have important implications for our conceptualization of the role of AVP in behaviour and of brain-body interactions in learning. Clearly, an AVP reserve sufficient to change or even mobilize behaviour, is available in situations of extreme challenge. It will be critical to determine whether other cues can activate this sytem, and how this mechanism works, if at all, in normal behaviour.
We thank Dr Jean Rivier for providing AVP and dPTyr(Me)AVP; Rose-Marie Bluthe, Jean Mexmain and Achim Raab for help with testing the rats; and Nancy Callahan for manuscript preparation. This work was supported by NINCDS grant NS 202912-01 to G.F.K., CNRS NSF grant INT 8215308 to M.Le.M. and G.F.K., and INSERM CL grant to M.Le.M.</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Walter</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Van Ree</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>De Wied</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>75</vid>, <ppf>2493</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2496</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Regulat. Peptides</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>153</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>164</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bohus</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ader</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>De Wied</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Horm. Behav.</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>191</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>197</ppl> (<cd year="1972">1972</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bohus</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kovacs</snm>, <fnm>G. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>De Wied</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Brain Res.</jtl> <vid>157</vid>, <ppf>414</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>417</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>LeBrun</snm>, <fnm>C. J.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Life Sci.</jtl> <vid>35</vid>, <ppf>1505</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1512</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Weingartner</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>211</vid>, <ppf>601</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>603</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gold</snm>, <fnm>P. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kaye</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Robertson</snm>, <fnm>G. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ebert</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>New Engl. J. Med.</jtl> <vid>308</vid>, <ppf>1117</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1123</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sahgal</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Psychopharmology</jtl> <vid>83</vid>, <ppf>215</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>228</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Le Moal</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>291</vid>, <ppf>491</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>493</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bloom</snm>, <fnm>F. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>A. Rev. Physiol.</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>571</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>581</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ettenberg</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Le Moal</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bloom</snm>, <fnm>F. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Pharmac. Biochem. Behav.</jtl> <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>645</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>647</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ettenberg</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>van der Kooy</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Le Moal</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bloom</snm>, <fnm>F. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Behav. Brain Res.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>231</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>250</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bankowski</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Manning</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Haldar</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sawyer</snm>, <fnm>W. H.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. med. Chem.</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>850</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>853</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rodriquez</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Demotes-Mainard</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chauveau</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Poulain</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Vincent</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Neurosci. Abstr.</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>445</ppf> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Dunn</snm>, <fnm>F. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Brennan</snm>, <fnm>T. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nelson</snm>, <fnm>A. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Robertson</snm>, <fnm>G. L.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. clin. Invest.</jtl> <vid>52</vid>, <ppf>3212</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3219</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Thatcher-Britton</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Britton</snm>, <fnm>D. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Roberts</snm>, <fnm>D. C. S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bloom</snm>, <fnm>F. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Physiol. Behav.</jtl> <vid>33</vid>, <ppf>479</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>485</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Crofton</snm>, <fnm>J. T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Hypertension</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>31</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>38</ppl> (<cd year="1979">1979</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Zaidi</snm>, <fnm>S. M. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Heller</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Endocr.</jtl> <vid>60</vid>, <ppf>195</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>196</ppl> (<cd year="1974">1974</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Reppert</snm>, <fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Artman</snm>, <fnm>H. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Swaminathan</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fisher</snm>, <fnm>D. A.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>213</vid>, <ppf>1256</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1257</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ermisch</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Landgraf</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Heinold</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Stuba</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> in <btl>Neural Plasticity and Memory Formation</btl> (eds Marsan, C. A. &amp; Matthies, H.) <ppf>147</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>152</ppl> (Raven, New York, <cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wood</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Neurosurgery</jtl> <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>293</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>305</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Pardridge</snm>, <fnm>W. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>A. Rev. Physiol.</jtl> <vid>45</vid>, <ppf>73</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>82</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Buijis</snm>, <fnm>R. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cell Tissue Res.</jtl> <vid>192</vid>, <ppf>423</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>435</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Burbach</snm>, <fnm>J. P. H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kovacs</snm>, <fnm>G. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>De Wied</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Van Nispen</snm>, <fnm>J. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Greven</snm>, <fnm>H. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>221</vid>, <ppf>1310</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1312</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>De Wied</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gaffori</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Van Ree</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>De Jong</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>305</vid>, <ppf>276</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>278</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Le Moal</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mormede</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dantzer</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bloom</snm>, <fnm>F. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Soc. Neurosci. Abstr.</jtl> <vid>8</vid> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ettenberg</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Behav. Brain Res.</jtl> <vid>14</vid>, <ppf>201</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>211</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Le Brun</snm>, <fnm>C. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Le Moal</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bloom</snm>, <fnm>F. E.</fnm></refau> <i>Regulat. Peptides</i> (in the press).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Iversen</snm>, <fnm>S. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>291</vid>, <ppf>454</ppf> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Joyce</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Koob</snm>, <fnm>G. F.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Psychopharmacology</jtl> <vid>73</vid>, <ppf>311</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>313</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></headerx>