<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "NPG_XML_Article.dtd" [
<!ENTITY figf1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f1//EN" "ncb1876-f1" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf2 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f2//EN" "ncb1876-f2" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf3 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f3//EN" "ncb1876-f3" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf4 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f4//EN" "ncb1876-f4" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf5 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f5//EN" "ncb1876-f5" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf6 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f6//EN" "ncb1876-f6" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf7 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f7//EN" "ncb1876-f7" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf8 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI ncb1876-f8//EN" "ncb1876-f8" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY ncb1876-e1 SYSTEM "edsumm/ncb1876-e1.xml">
]>
<article id="ncb1876" language="eng" relation="no"><!--ncb1876-->
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature Cell Biology</jtl>
<vol>11</vol>
<iss>6</iss>
<idt>200906</idt>
<categ id="af"/>
<pp><spn>705</spn><epn>716</epn><cnt>12</cnt></pp>
<issn type="print">1465-7392</issn>
<issn type="electronic">1476-4679</issn>
<cpg><cpy>2009</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<nvid extrefid="ncb0609-681"/>
<suppinfo id="s1">
<suppobj extrefid="ncb1876-s1" format="pdf" filesize="2M"><title>Supplementary Information</title><descrip><p>Supplementary Information</p></descrip></suppobj>
<suppobj extrefid="ncb1876-s1" format="xls" filesize="2M"><title>Supplementary Information</title><descrip><p>Supplementary Table 1</p></descrip></suppobj></suppinfo>
<doi>10.1038/ncb1876</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>A functional screen implicates microRNA-138-dependent regulation of the depalmitoylation enzyme APT1 in dendritic spine morphogenesis</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Gabriele</fnm><snm>Siegel</snm><inits>G</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a11"/></au>
<au><fnm>Gregor</fnm><snm>Obernosterer</snm><inits>G</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a11"/></au>
<au><fnm>Roberto</fnm><snm>Fiore</snm><inits>R</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Martin</fnm><snm>Oehmen</snm><inits>M</inits><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<au><fnm>Silvia</fnm><snm>Bicker</snm><inits>S</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Mette</fnm><snm>Christensen</snm><inits>M</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a4"/></au>
<au><fnm>Sharof</fnm><snm>Khudayberdiev</snm><inits>S</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Philipp F.</fnm><snm>Leuschner</snm><inits>P F</inits><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Clara J. L.</fnm><snm>Busch</snm><inits>C J L</inits><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Christina</fnm><snm>Kane</snm><inits>C</inits><orf rid="a5"/></au>
<au><fnm>Katja</fnm><snm>H&uuml;bel</snm><inits>K</inits><orf rid="a6"/></au>
<au><fnm>Frank</fnm><snm>Dekker</snm><inits>F</inits><orf rid="a6"/></au>
<au><fnm>Christian</fnm><snm>Hedberg</snm><inits>C</inits><orf rid="a9"/></au>
<au><fnm>Balamurugan</fnm><snm>Rengarajan</snm><inits>B</inits><orf rid="a6"/></au>
<au><fnm>Carsten</fnm><snm>Drepper</snm><inits>C</inits><orf rid="a7"/><orf rid="a10"/></au>
<au><fnm>Herbert</fnm><snm>Waldmann</snm><inits>H</inits><orf rid="a6"/></au>
<au><fnm>Sakari</fnm><snm>Kauppinen</snm><inits>S</inits><orf rid="a4"/><orf rid="a8"/></au>
<au><fnm>Michael E.</fnm><snm>Greenberg</snm><inits>M E</inits><orf rid="a5"/></au>
<au><fnm>Andreas</fnm><snm>Draguhn</snm><inits>A</inits><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<au><fnm>Marc</fnm><snm>Rehmsmeier</snm><inits>M</inits><orf rid="a7"/><orf rid="a10"/></au>
<cau><fnm>Javier</fnm><snm>Martinez</snm><inits>J</inits><orf rid="a2"/><corf rid="c1"/></cau>
<cau><fnm>Gerhard M.</fnm><snm>Schratt</snm><inits>G M</inits><orf rid="a1"/><corf rid="c2"/></cau>
<aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Interdisziplin&auml;res Zentrum f&uuml;r Neurowissenschaften, SFB488 Junior Group, Universit&auml;t Heidelberg, and Institut f&uuml;r Neuroanatomie, Universit&auml;tsklinikum Heidelberg</org>, <street>Im Neuenheimer Feld 345</street>, <zip>69120</zip> <cty>Heidelberg</cty>, <cny>Germany</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a2"/><org>Institute of Molecular Biotechnology, IMBA, Austrian Academy of Sciences</org>, <street>Dr. Bohr Gasse 3</street>, <zip>1030</zip> <cty>Vienna</cty>, <cny>Austria</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a3"/><org>Institut f&uuml;r Physiologie und Pathophysiologie, Universit&auml;t Heidelberg</org>, <street>Im Neuenheimer Feld 326</street>, <zip>69120</zip> <cty>Heidelberg</cty>, <cny>Germany</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a4"/><org>Wilhelm Johannsen Center for Functional Genome Research, Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine, University of Copenhagen</org>, <street>Blegdamsvej 3</street>, <zip>DK-2200 Cph N</zip>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a5"/><org>Department of Neurobiology, Harvard Medical School</org>, <street>220 Longwood Avenue</street>, <cty>Boston</cty>, <st>Massachusetts</st> <zip>02115</zip>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a6"/><org>Max-Planck-Institut f&uuml;r molekulare Physiologie, Abteilung Chemische Biologie, and Technische Universit&auml;t Dortmund, Fakult&auml;t Chemie, Chemische Biologie</org>, <street>Otto-Hahn-Strasse 11</street>, <zip>44227</zip> <cty>Dortmund</cty>, <cny>Germany</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a7"/><org>Center for Biotechnology (CeBiTec), Universit&auml;t Bielefeld</org>, <zip>33594</zip> <cty>Bielefeld</cty>, <cny>Germany</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a8"/><org>Santaris Pharma</org>, <street>Boege Alle 3</street>, <zip>DK-2970</zip> <cty>Hoersholm</cty>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a9"/><org>Max Planck Institute of Molecular Physiology, Chemical Biology</org>, <street>Otto-Hahn-Strasse 11</street>, <zip>44227</zip> <cty>Dortmund</cty>, <cny>Germany</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a10"/>Present addresses: <org>Institute for Clinical Neurobiology, ZEMM</org>, <street>Zinklesweg 10</street>, <org>W&uuml;rzburg University</org>, <zip>97078</zip> <cty>W&uuml;rzburg</cty>, <cny>Germany</cny> (C.D.); <org>Gregor Mendel Institute of Molecular Plant Biology</org>, <street>Dr. Bohr-Gasse 3</street>, <zip>1030</zip> <cty>Vienna</cty>, <cny>Austria</cny> (M.R.).</aff>
<aff><oid id="a11"/>These authors contributed equally to this work.</aff>
<caff><coid id="c1"/><email>javier.martinez@imba.oeaw.ac.at</email></caff>
<caff><coid id="c2"/><email>schratt@ana.uni-heidelberg.de</email></caff></aug>
<hst>
<re year="2008" month="12" day="18"/>
<acc year="2009" month="02" day="10"/>
<pubdate type="aop" year="2009" month="05" day="24"/></hst>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="aop">
<title></title>
<p>Mir-138, identified in a screen for microRNAs associated with synapses, regulates dendritic spine morphogenesis through APT-1, a depalmitoylation enzyme that modulates the membrane localization of the heterotrimeric G protein alpha subunit.</p></edsumm>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="issue">
<title></title>
<p>Mir-138, identified in a screen for microRNAs associated with synapses, regulates dendritic spine morphogenesis through APT-1, a depalmitoylation enzyme that modulates the membrane localization of the heterotrimeric G protein alpha subunit.</p></edsumm>
<abs>
<p>The microRNA pathway has been implicated in the regulation of synaptic protein synthesis and ultimately in dendritic spine morphogenesis, a phenomenon associated with long-lasting forms of memory. However, the particular microRNAs (miRNAs) involved are largely unknown. Here we identify specific miRNAs that function at synapses to control dendritic spine structure by performing a functional screen. One of the identified miRNAs, miR-138, is highly enriched in the brain, localized within dendrites and negatively regulates the size of dendritic spines in rat hippocampal neurons. miR-138 controls the expression of acyl protein thioesterase 1 (APT1), an enzyme regulating the palmitoylation status of proteins that are known to function at the synapse, including the &alpha;<sub>13</sub> subunits of G proteins (G&alpha;<sub>13</sub>). RNA-interference-mediated knockdown of APT1 and the expression of membrane-localized G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> both suppress spine enlargement caused by inhibition of miR-138, suggesting that APT1-regulated depalmitoylation of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> might be an important downstream event of miR-138 function. Our results uncover a previously unknown miRNA-dependent mechanism in neurons and demonstrate a previously unrecognized complexity of miRNA-dependent control of dendritic spine morphogenesis.</p></abs></fm>
<bdy>
<p>The functioning of the mammalian brain relies on the proper formation of intricate neuronal circuits. Neurons within these circuits are synaptically connected, and most excitatory synaptic connections between neurons form on dendritic spines, specialized protrusions emanating from the dendritic shaft<bibr rid="b1 b2"/>. The structural and functional plasticity of dendritic spines correlates with long-lasting changes in synaptic transmission that underlie higher cognitive functions<bibr rid="b3 b4"/>. Dendritic spine abnormalities are a hallmark of a variety of neurological diseases, including several forms of learning disability<bibr rid="b5"/>. A plethora of molecular mechanisms involved in dendritic spine plasticity have been elucidated during the last decade, including actin cytoskeletal dynamics, post-translational protein modifications, protein trafficking, gene transcription and protein turnover<bibr rid="b6 b7 b8 b9 b10"/>. The synthesis of proteins <i>de novo</i> is of particular importance for creating enduring changes in synaptic transmission that are associated with long-term memory<bibr rid="b11 b12"/>. Proteins can be either synthesized in the soma and transported to dendritic spines, or synthesized locally from a pool of dendritic messenger RNAs within or next to spines<bibr rid="b13 b14 b15"/>.</p>
<p>The local translation of dendritic mRNAs is regulated tightly by RNA-binding proteins and non-coding RNAs that bind preferentially to the 3&prime; untranslated region (UTR) of the mRNAs<bibr rid="b16 b17"/>. miRNAs, a diverse class of 20&ndash;24-nucleotide non-coding RNAs, regulate local mRNA translation in dendrites, thereby affecting the morphology of dendritic spines in rat hippocampal neurons<bibr rid="b18 b19"/>.</p>
<p>miRNAs are expressed in essentially all cell types and regulate important biological processes, including differentiation, apoptosis and cellular transformation<bibr rid="b20 b21"/>. miRNAs inhibit mRNA translation by binding to cognate sites in the 3&prime; UTR of target mRNAs<bibr rid="b22"/>. In the mammalian nervous system, miRNAs function during cell specification (miR-124a and miR-9), neurite outgrowth (miR-132) and spine development (miR-134)<bibr rid="b23"/>. Microarray and cloning experiments have shown that a large number of miRNAs are expressed in the postnatal mammalian brain at times of synapse development, but their role in synapse formation and plasticity is largely unknown<bibr rid="b24 b25 b26"/>. Here we present a functional screen that led to the identification of miRNAs that are involved in dendritic spine morphogenesis. Among these miRNAs, miR-138 was found to robustly inhibit the growth of dendritic spines, an effect that was mediated by downregulation of APT1, an enzyme catalysing the depalmitoylation of several signalling proteins<bibr rid="b27"/>. Our findings define a previously unknown mechanism by which miRNAs control dendritic spine morphogenesis and indicate a hitherto unrecognized complexity of miRNA function in the regulation of synaptic plasticity in mammalian neurons.</p>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Results</sectitle>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Large-scale identification of synaptically enriched miRNAs</sectitle>
<p>To identify miRNAs that function during synaptic development, we undertook a combination of expression profiling of miRNAs in the synaptodendritic compartment and subsequent functional inhibitory screening in primary hippocampal neurons.</p>
<p>We reasoned that miRNAs that are important for synapse function might reside primarily near the synapse, where they could locally regulate the translation of critical target mRNAs. Synaptosomes, a biochemical fraction highly enriched for synaptic membranes, preserve components of local protein synthesis, including polyribosomes, mRNAs and regulatory RNAs (ref. <bibrinl rid="b28">28</bibrinl>, <figr rid="f1">Fig. 1a</figr>, and data not shown). We therefore conclude that synaptosomes are a suitable source for synaptic miRNAs. Total RNA was extracted from postnatal day 15 (P15) rat forebrains and synaptosomes and simultaneously hybridized to microarrays that contained probes for all mouse and rat mature miRNAs listed in the Sanger database (miRBase, version 7.1; <weblink url="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/Rfam/mirna/">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/Rfam/mirna/</weblink>). In this manner we identified ten mature miRNAs that displayed an at least twofold enrichment in synaptosomes compared with whole forebrain in three biological replicates. Conversely, four mature miRNAs were strongly depleted from synaptosomes (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b, c</figr>; <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Table S1</sir>).</p>
<p>The observed enrichment of several miRNAs in RNA preparations from synaptosomes was validated for selected candidates by northern blot analysis (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2a</figr>). In accordance with the microarray data, we found higher levels of miR-218 (3.02-fold) and miR-138 (1.67-fold) in total RNA prepared from synaptosomes than in whole forebrain. In contrast, mature miR-124 was not enriched (0.96-fold) and pre-miR-124 was undetectable in synaptosomes, confirming that only specific miRNAs are enriched at the synapse.</p>
<p>To monitor the subcellular localization of miRNAs identified in our screen, we performed <i>in situ</i> hybridization (ISH) in rat hippocampal neurons at 18 days <i>in vitro</i> (DIV), using probes for miR-9, miR-218, miR-138 and miR-124 as a control (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr>). All candidate miRNAs were readily detected in cultured hippocampal neurons by using locked nucleic acid (LNA) oligonucleotides as detection probes. We confirmed the specificity of our ISH protocol by using a scrambled LNA control oligonucleotide (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr>, upper left panel). Neuronal expression of miR-138 was further confirmed by ISH in brain slices (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 1a, b</sir>), quantitative RT&ndash;PCR and northern blotting with RNA from dissociated primary neurons (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 1c, d</sir>). Whereas miR-124 was localized mainly within the cell body (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr>, asterisks), the signals for miR-138, miR-218 and miR-9 extended well into neuronal processes that were identified as dendrites by co-staining for the dendritic marker protein MAP2 (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr>, arrowheads). Quantification of the ISH signals (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr>, lower right panel) confirmed the enrichment of miR-138, miR-218 and miR-9 in dendrites relative to the cell-body-restricted miR-124. Taken together, our microarray, northern blot and ISH data show that a specific subset of miRNAs is enriched in the synaptodendritic compartment of rat neurons. These findings suggest the existence of a dendritic miRNA regulatory network.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Functional screening identifies miR-138 as a negative regulator of dendritic spine size</sectitle>
<p>To study the functional relevance of the miRNA regulatory network in dendrites, we interfered with the function of candidate miRNAs identified in the microarray analysis by transfecting cells with miRNA antagonists (2&prime;-<i>O</i>-methyl (2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me) modified antisense (AS) oligoribonucleotides)<bibr rid="b29"/>. We speculated that some of the miRNAs identified in the screen might affect dendritic spine morphology, a correlate of the maturity and strength of excitatory synapses<bibr rid="b3 b4 b30"/> (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3a</figr>).</p>
<p>Using a single cell fluorescent sensor assay<bibr rid="b31"/>, we found that transfection of 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me AS oligonucleotides significantly decreased miRNA-mediated sensor cleavage for three selected miRNAs (miR-138, miR-132 and miR-218) that are endogenously expressed in hippocampal neurons (10&ndash;18 DIV; <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 1e</sir>). Therefore, 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me AS oligonucleotides are suitable for achieving specific inhibition of individual miRNAs. We analysed candidate miRNAs that showed an at least twofold enrichment in synaptosomes compared with whole brain. In addition, miR-132 was included because it regulates dendritic outgrowth<bibr rid="b32"/>. Inhibition of miRNA function by 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me AS oligonucleotides resulted in a significant change in dendritic spine volume for two of the miRNAs tested (miR-138 and miR-132) in comparison with control transfected neurons (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b</figr>). Inhibition of miR-138 function resulted in a robust and significant increase in spine volume (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b, c</figr>) without altering the total number of synaptic puncta (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 2a</sir>). Introducing 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me AS oligonucleotides directed against the other nine candidate miRNAs or three control sequences (2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me control, 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me let7c and 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-126) did not significantly affect spine volume (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b</figr>), demonstrating that we can specifically interfere with dendritic spine morphogenesis.</p>
<p>Because inhibition of miR-138 changed dendritic spine size very robustly, and the role of miR-138 in the nervous system and synaptic development was completely unknown, we decided to focus on miR-138. To corroborate our findings, we employed another AS oligonucleotide inhibitor of different chemistry (LNA). Similarly to 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138, transfection of LNA-138 specifically increased the average spine volume of hippocampal neurons (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3d</figr>). Conversely, transfection of miR-138 duplex RNA significantly decreased average spine volume, supporting an inhibitory role for miR-138 in spine growth (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3e</figr>). miR-138 duplex RNA, but not a control RNA (let-7c), was able to completely revert the spine-growth-promoting effect observed on inhibition of miR-138, demonstrating the specificity of the effect on spine size (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3f</figr>). Overexpression of either duplex RNA had no significant effect on dendritic spine density or the dendritic branching index (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 2b, c</sir>), indicating that overall dendritic morphology was not compromised by the introduction of synthetic small RNAs.</p>
<p>We therefore identified miR-138 as a critical component of a regulatory pathway that orchestrates dendritic spine growth. Calcium influx into cortical neurons as induced by membrane depolarization led to a rapid and progressive decline of pre-miR-138 expression (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 2d</sir>) and miR-138 cleavage activity (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 2e</sir>), indicating that miR-138 could be regulated during activity-dependent spine development.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>miR-138 regulates synaptic transmission and &alpha;-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazole propionic acid receptor (AMPAR) surface staining</sectitle>
<p>We next examined whether the observed changes in spine morphology on perturbation of miR-138 are associated with corresponding alterations in excitatory synaptic function. We recorded miniature excitatory postsynaptic currents (mEPSCs; <figr rid="f4">Fig. 4a</figr>) from cultured hippocampal neurons that had been transfected with miR-138, with control duplex RNA or with a vector expressing green fluorescent protein (GFP) only. In miR-138-expressing neurons, the median amplitude of mEPSCs was significantly decreased in comparison with both control transfections (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4b, c</figr>). The frequency of events was not different between all three types of cell. This result is consistent with our previous observations that miR-138 expression leads to a 25% decrease in spine volume (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3d</figr>) but has no effect on spine density (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 2b</sir>). mEPSCs were sensitive to 6-cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline (CNQX) and were therefore largely mediated by AMPARs (data not shown). Accordingly, we found a decrease in the median size, but not in the density, of GluR2-containing AMPAR clusters in dendrites of miR-138-expressing neurons (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4d</figr> and data not shown; <i>P</i> &lt; 0.001 (Kolmogorov&ndash;Smirnov test). Thus, miR-138-mediated spine shrinkage correlates with a decrease in the amplitude of postsynaptic currents and AMPAR cluster size.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>mRNA encoding acyl-protein thioesterase 1 (APT1) is a miR-138 target in neurons</sectitle>
<p>Using the RNAhybrid program we predicted miR-138 target mRNAs that might mediate the miR-138 effect on spine morphogenesis<bibr rid="b33 b34"/>. We selected four putative miR-138 target mRNAs that seemed to be particularly interesting in terms of synaptic function: EphrinB3 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b35">35</bibrinl>), PLEKHB1 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b36">36</bibrinl>), RIMS2 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b37">37</bibrinl>) and APT1 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b38">38</bibrinl>).</p>
<p>To validate the functionality of the identified binding sites within these mRNAs, full-length 3&prime; UTRs of the candidate miR-138 targets were cloned downstream of the luciferase coding region and these constructs were transfected into cortical neurons along with miR-138 duplex RNA. The <i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR conferred the most robust decrease in luciferase activity upon miR-138 co-transfection in both HeLa cells lacking endogenous miR-138 and primary neurons (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5a</figr>; <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 3a</sir>). We therefore decided to focus on APT1 and study its regulation by miR-138 in more detail. Introduction of miR-138 into cortical neurons did not significantly alter steady-state APT1&ndash;luciferase mRNA levels (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 3b</sir>), suggesting that the inhibitory effect of miR-138 on APT1 expression is due mainly to impaired translation of <i>APT1</i> mRNA. APT1 catalyses the removal of palmitate, a lipid modification with important roles in the localization and function of proteins<bibr rid="b39"/>. The expression and function of APT1 in the nervous system were completely unknown, but the fact that dynamic palmitoylation of synaptic proteins has been implicated in the regulation of synaptic efficacy<bibr rid="b40"/> made APT1 an interesting candidate in the context of dendritic spine morphology. To test for the physiological significance of the interaction of miR-138 with the APT1 3&prime; UTR we explored the expression of <i>APT1</i> mRNA and protein with the use of brain slices and isolated primary neurons. By ISH, mouse <i>APT1</i> mRNA was detected in multiple brain regions, including the principal layers of the hippocampus (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5b</figr>, data not shown). In hippocampal neurons, <i>APT1</i> mRNA localized to the somatic and dendritic compartment (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5c</figr>). In a similar manner to the known dendritic mRNA encoding MAP2, <i>APT1</i> mRNA was concentrated in granule-like structures along the length of dendrites (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5d</figr>). APT1 protein gradually increased over three weeks of cortical neuron development <i>in vitro</i> (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5e</figr>). At the subcellular level, APT1 protein was present in both the cytosolic fractions (low-speed and high-speed centrifugation supernatants) and membrane fractions (high-speed centrifugation pellet and synaptosomes) of P15 rat brain (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5f</figr>). However, in contrast with PSD-95, most of the APT1 protein accumulated in the soluble cytosolic fractions. These results are consistent with the idea that at least part of the negative regulatory interaction between miR-138 and <i>APT1</i> mRNA occurs locally in the synaptodendritic compartment.</p>
<p>We next tested whether the predicted miR-138-binding site within the <i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR is sufficient for miR-138-mediated translational inhibition. The duplex between the target site of the <i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR and miR-138 features extensive complementarity, especially within a highly conserved region at the 5&prime; end of the miRNA known as the 'seed' region (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6a</figr>). Accordingly, point mutations within this seed region (APT1 mutant) rendered the APT1&ndash;luciferase construct insensitive to miR-138-mediated inhibition (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6b</figr>). Therefore, inhibition of APT1 expression by miR-138 is mediated through a single conserved miR-138-binding site within the <i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR.</p>
<p>To test whether endogenous miR-138 regulates the translation of <i>APT1</i> mRNA in neurons, we transfected the APT1&ndash;luciferase reporter into mature, miR-138-expressing neurons (14&ndash;16 DIV; <figr rid="f6">Fig. 6c</figr>). Inhibition of endogenous miR-138 by 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138 specifically upregulated APT1&ndash;luciferase expression in a dose-dependent manner. This inhibitory function of endogenous miR-138 on the APT1 reporter construct was dependent on a functional miR-138-binding site (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6c</figr>; <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 3c</sir>). The effect of 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138 on APT1 expression was specific, because it was effectively competed for by the transfection of miR-138 duplex RNA (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 3d</sir>). Quantitative transduction of primary neurons by bath application of cholesterol-modified 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138 led to a reproducible and specific upregulation of APT1 protein as assessed by semi-quantitative western blotting (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6d</figr>). In summary, our results establish <i>APT1</i> mRNA as a genuine miR-138 target, thereby implicating miR-138 in the regulation of palmitoylation in neurons.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>APT1 activity is required for spine enlargement caused by miR-138 inhibition</sectitle>
<p>We next explored whether the decrease in dendritic spine volume on overexpression of miR-138 might be causally linked to decreased APT1 expression. First, we monitored spine volume in neurons in which endogenous APT1 levels were decreased by RNAi. As judged by western blotting, three out of four APT1 small hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) targeting different regions of the <i>APT1</i> mRNA effectively decreased endogenous APT1 protein concentration in cortical neurons (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7a</figr>; <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 4b</sir>) and ectopically expressed APT1 in HEK293 cells (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 4a</sir>). In hippocampal neurons, APT1 knockdown by each of the effective shRNAs (<i>APT1</i> shRNA-1, shRNA-3 and shRNA-4) led to a significant decrease in the size of dendritic protrusions compared with control conditions (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7b, c</figr>, and data not shown). Reduced spine volume on APT1 knockdown was accompanied by a significant decrease in the number of spine-associated PSD-95 clusters within dendrites (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 4c&ndash;e</sir>). None of the <i>APT1</i> shRNAs had an effect on the total number of dendritic protrusions of hippocampal neurons (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 5a</sir>) or the dendritic branching index (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 5b</sir>), indicating a specific effect of APT1 knockdown on spine morphology.</p>
<p>APT1-dependent control of dendritic spine morphology required the depalmitoylating activity of APT1, because inhibition of APT1 enzymatic activity by two different small-molecule inhibitors (FD196 and FD253) similarly led to a decrease in dendritic spine volume (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7d</figr>; <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 5c</sir>), whereas an inactive control compound (RB020) had no effect.</p>
<p>We next tested whether elevated APT1 levels resulting from inhibition of miR-138 are required for the increase in spine volume. A decrease in APT1 levels brought about by <i>APT1</i> shRNA-3 in miR-138-depleted cells completely suppressed the spine-growth-promoting effect of miR-138 inhibition by 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138 (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7e</figr>) and LNA-138 (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 5d</sir>). Conversely, transfection of an APT1 expression construct harbouring a mutation in the miR-138-binding site (APT1 mut), but not a wild-type APT1 construct, efficiently rescued spine shrinkage caused by elevated miR-138 levels (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7f</figr>). Taken together, these two lines of evidence strongly suggest that APT1 is a critical downstream effector of miR-138 in the regulation of spine morphogenesis.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Membrane localization of the APT1 substrate G protein &alpha;<sub>13</sub> (G&alpha;<sub>13</sub>) counteracts spine enlargement caused by miR-138 inhibition</sectitle>
<p>We investigated the molecular mechanism that underlies dendritic spine enlargement caused by increased APT1 protein levels on inhibition of miR-138. APT1 depalmitoylates several substrates implicated in synaptic plasticity, including endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS), H-Ras and G-protein &alpha; subunits, namely G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b27">27</bibrinl>). Because G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> palmitoylation is required for plasma membrane localization and Rho-dependent signalling<bibr rid="b41"/>, we focused on this subunit. We found that a significant fraction of overexpressed Myc-G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> redistributes from the cytosol to the membrane on shRNA-mediated knockdown of endogenous human APT1 (hAPT1) in HEK293 cells (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8a&ndash;c</figr>). In contrast, transfection of an APT1 expression construct (CFP&ndash;APT1) had the opposite effect. Thus, APT1 is necessary and sufficient for proper G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> membrane localization in HEK293 cells, presumably by regulating G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> depalmitoylation. More importantly, the introduction of synthetic miR-138 duplex RNA similarly increases the membrane association of Myc&ndash;G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8d, e</figr>). miR-138 had no effect on the subcellular distribution of the cytosolic &beta;-actin or membrane-associated calnexin proteins (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8d</figr>). Redistribution of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> coincides with a decrease in endogenous hAPT1 protein levels in miR-138-transfected HEK293 cells (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8f</figr>).</p>
<p>Finally, we investigated the significance of the regulation of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> subcellular localization by miR-138 for the control of spine size. In a similar manner to APT1 knockdown (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7f</figr>), overexpression of wild-type G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> was able to suppress the spine-growth-promoting effect caused by miR-138 inhibition (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8g</figr>). A palmitoylation-deficient G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> (G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> CCSS) was ineffective in the rescue experiment, demonstrating that G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> palmitoylation is required for miR-138-mediated spine shrinkage. The effects of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> palmitoylation are probably due to a redistribution of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> from the cytosol to the membrane, because a constitutively membrane-attached, myristoylated G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> rescues spine morphology in the context of mutated palmitoylation sites (Myr G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> CCSS; <figr rid="f8">Fig. 8g</figr>). The different subcellular localization of the G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> variants was confirmed by cellular fractionation (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8h</figr>) and immunostaining (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 6a&ndash;c</sir>).</p>
<p>We conclude that miR-138 might inhibit spine growth, at least in part, by increasing the membrane localization of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub>, resulting in elevated activity of the downstream RhoA signalling pathway (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 6d</sir>).</p></sec></sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Discussion</sectitle>
<p>miRNAs have recently emerged as important regulators of nervous system function in vertebrates, for example during neuronal differentiation (miR-9 and miR-124), neuronal outgrowth (miR-132) and dendritic spine morphogenesis (miR-134)<bibr rid="b23"/>. However, a systematic assessment of miRNA function, based on their temporal and subcellular expression in the brain, has not yet been achieved. In this study we generated a comprehensive list of miRNAs residing within the synaptodendritic compartment, and subsequently probed their function in the regulation of dendritic spine morphology. In this manner we identified two neuronal miRNAs (miR-132 and miR-138) that regulate dendritic spine size in an antagonistic manner. Two recent reports suggest that miRNAs beyond those identified here might participate in local translational control in dendrites<bibr rid="b42 b43"/>. There is little overlap between those studies and ours, which might be due to the different sample materials (that is, synaptosomes versus cultured neurons, and adult brain versus P15 brain) and methodologies (microarray versus multiplex RT&ndash;PCR) used. However, we note that we might have missed low-expressed miRNAs in dendrites as a result of our very stringent selection criteria. In addition, some of the miRNAs that we identified by microarray might have a function in dendrites that we were unable to uncover with our experimental setup. A more in-depth functional analysis of individual miRNAs identified here will improve our understanding of the dendritic miRNA network.</p>
<p>On the basis of multiple lines of evidence, <i>APT1</i> mRNA is a genuine miR-138 target in neurons. Studies in other cell systems document a role for APT1 in the depalmitoylation of several signalling proteins, including H-Ras, G&alpha; subunits and eNOS. Although it was known that these APT1 substrates are important in synapse development, our results provide direct evidence for a biological function of APT1-dependent depalmitoylation in neurons during spine development. Using classical epistasis experiments, we found that G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> is one critical APT1 substrate in spine morphogenesis. Although monitoring G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> palmitoylation in neurons proved technically challenging, our results showing that miR-138 controls the membrane localization of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> in non-neuronal cells (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8d, e</figr>) and that G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> palmitoylation is required for miR-138-dependent regulation of spine size (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8g</figr>) strongly suggest that miR-138 controls the level of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> palmitoylation by means of APT1. Further work is needed to elucidate additional substrates of APT1 in neurons, and whether perturbation of miR-138 affects their palmitoylation. Obvious candidates besides G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> subunits include G-protein-coupled receptors, Fyn, Ras, eNOS and PSD-95, all of which are anchored to the spine membrane by means of palmitoylation<bibr rid="b40"/>. Given that miRNAs usually regulate many target mRNAs, miR-138 probably possesses physiologically relevant targets other than APT1. For example, EphrinB3 and RIMS2 contain canonical miR-138 seed matches in their 3&prime; UTR, but none of them showed a significant downregulation on miR-138 overexpression in neurons. The failure of these mRNAs to respond to miR-138 might be due to a low accessibility of the respective target sites in neurons (G.O., unpublished observation).</p>
<p>A major outcome of our study is that miRNA regulation in dendritic spines seems to converge on the translation of critical components of G-protein signalling pathways that impinge on the actin cytoskeleton (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 6d</sir>). For example, miR-134 inhibits the expression of Limk1, a kinase that phosphorylates cofilin, an actin-binding protein that has been implicated in the regulation of dendritic spine and growth cone structure<bibr rid="b44"/>. miR-132 has previously been shown to downregulate p250GAP, an important negative regulator of the spine-growth-promoting GTPases Rac and Cdc42 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b32">32</bibrinl>). In this study we provide evidence that miR-138 mediates its effect on spine structure, at least in part, by regulating the depalmitoylation enzyme APT1. Among the known APT1 substrates is G&alpha;<sub>13</sub>, an activator of Rho downstream of G-protein-coupled receptors<bibr rid="b45"/>. A miR-138-mediated increase in G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> palmitoylation and membrane localization could result in elevated Rho activity, which in turn could trigger spine shrinkage<bibr rid="b46"/>. This novel miRNA-dependent layer of regulation of critical actin signalling components could help to adapt cytoskeletal changes in individual spines to changes in synaptic activity<bibr rid="b6"/>.</p>
<p>Our electrophysiological measurements show that miR-138-mediated spine shrinkage is correlated with decreased postsynaptic function. Although the effects on mEPSC amplitudes are subtle, our results show a significant contribution of a neuronal miRNA to basal excitatory synaptic transmission. The method of regulation of miR-138 activity by stimuli that affect synapse morphology and function is an important topic for future studies. Our preliminary results indicate that, consistent with its spine growth inhibitory effect, miR-138 expression and activity are negatively regulated by calcium influx (<sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information, Fig. 3d, e</sir>). It remains to be determined whether activity-dependent regulation of miR-138 occurs at the level of precursor processing, as suggested by our previous results<bibr rid="b47"/>, or by a different mechanism. Nevertheless, it is an intriguing possibility that neuronal activity could regulate the expression and/or activity of a variety of synaptic miRNAs. This in turn could contribute to activity-dependent fine-tuning of signalling pathways that coordinate the structural and functional plasticity of spine synapses.</p></sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>methods</sectitle><online-methods>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Cell culture and transfection.</sectitle>
<p>Cultures of dissociated primary cortical and hippocampal neurons from embryonic day 18 (E18) Sprague&ndash;Dawley rats (Charles River Laboratories, Sulzfeld, Germany) were prepared and cultured as described<bibr rid="b48"/>. Neuronal transfections were performed with Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). For each well of a 24-well plate a total of 1 &mu;g of DNA/RNA was mixed with a 1:50 dilution of Lipofectamine 2000 in neurobasal medium, incubated at room temperature (1525 &deg;C ) for 20 min and then further diluted 1:5 in neurobasal medium. Neurons were incubated with the transfection mix for 2 h. Nucleofections were performed with the Rat Neuron Nucleofector Kit (Lonza) and program O-003. Primary cortical neurons (4 &times; 10<super>6</super>-Me-oligonucleotides ('antagomirs'; Thermo Scientific) were applied at 13DIV at 1 &mu;M in conditioned culture medium for 24 h, and cells were lysed at 18 DIV.</p>
<p>HEK293 cells were maintained in DMEM (Invitrogen) plus 10% FBS, 1 mM glutamine, 100 U ml<super>&minus;1</super> penicillin and 100 &mu;g ml<super>&minus;1</super> streptomycin. Transfections were performed with the calcium phosphate method with a final CaCl<sub>2</sub> concentration of 0.1 M and an incubation time of 6&ndash;16 h.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>DNA constructs.</sectitle>
<p>The pSUPER RNAi expression system (Oligoengine) was used for siRNA-mediated knockdown of APT1 in cell culture. Four independent pSUPER constructs (<i>APT1</i> shRNA-1&ndash;4) were generated with the <i>Bgl</i>II and <i>Hin</i>dIII restriction sites. pSUPER plasmids were used either at 10 ng ml<super>&minus;1</super> (primary neurons) or 200 ng ml<super>&minus;1</super> (HEK293 cells). An expression vector for full-length mouse APT1 cDNA was obtained from OriGene (MC201121). A version with a mutated miR-138-binding site within the <i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR (APT1 mutBS) was generated with the QuikChange Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene). For generation of an expression vector for Myc-tagged G&alpha;<sub>13</sub>, the mouse G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> open reading frame was PCR-amplified from the pCIS-G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> expression vector (provided by S. Offermanns) and then cloned into pcDNA 3.1/Myc&ndash;His A (Invitrogen) using <i>Bam</i>HI and <i>Xba</i>I. See <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Methods</sir> for primer sequences.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Preparation of synaptoneurosomes.</sectitle>
<p>Synaptoneurosomes were prepared from P15 Sprague&ndash;Dawley rat pups (Charles River, Sulzfeld, Germany) as described previously<bibr rid="b48"/>.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Microarray.</sectitle>
<p>See <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Methods</sir> for details.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Northern blot analysis.</sectitle>
<p>Northern blots to detect neuronal miRNAs and U6 snRNA were performed as described, with radiolabelled DNA oligonucleotides as probes<bibr rid="b19"/>.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Western blot analysis.</sectitle>
<p>Proteins were separated by SDS&ndash;PAGE and blotted onto a poly-vinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane. Non-specific bindings were blocked with Tris-buffered saline plus 5% milk powder and 0.2% Tween 20. The following primary antibodies were used: polyclonal rabbit anti-APT1 (1:1,000 dilution; the anti-APT1 antibody was produced in rabbit from BioGenes (Berlin, Germany) by using purified hAPT1 (provided by R. Vetter)), mouse anti-PSD95 (1:1,000; MA1-046; Dianova), mouse anti-cMyc (sc40; Santa Cruz), mouse anti-HA (1583816; Roche), mouse anti-&beta;<sub>3</sub>-tubulin (1:15,000; MMS-435P; Covance), mouse anti-EEA1 (1:10,000; 610456; Becton Dickinson), rabbit anti-calnexin (SPA-865; Stressgen) and mouse anti-&beta;-actin (A5441; Sigma). Primary antibodies were recognized either by a horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-rabbit antibody (1:20,000; 401315; Calbiochem) or an HRP-conjugated rabbit anti-mouse antibody (1:20,000; 402335; Calbiochem). Secondary antibodies were detected by enhanced chemiluminescence with the ECL Plus Western Blotting Detection System (GE Healthcare).</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Image analysis.</sectitle>
<p>For image analysis, neurons were transfected at 10 DIV or 14 DIV with indicated miRNAs, miRNA inhibitors or siRNA expression vectors in combination with enhanced GFP and processed for confocal microscopy at 18 DIV.</p>
<p>For spine analysis, high-resolution <i>z</i>-stack images of GFP-positive neurons were taken with a confocal laser scanning microscope (Zeiss). Random neurons displaying pyramidal morphology were chosen from data sets that had been blinded to the experimental condition. Spine volumes were subsequently analysed with the ImageJ software. At least 15 individual neurons derived from three independent experiments were measured for each experimental condition. For the functional screen 50 spines per neuron were analysed; for subsequent analyses more than 100 spines per neuron were analysed. For Sholl analysis, low-magnification pictures of GFP-positive neurons were taken and dendritic complexity was analysed with ImageJ software. At least ten individual neurons for each experimental condition of a total of three independent experiments were measured. For details on spine analysis and Sholl analysis see ref. <bibrinl rid="b19">19</bibrinl>. The determination of synapse density was performed by the method of ref. <bibrinl rid="b49">49</bibrinl>. The size of GluR2 surface clusters was determined with the Analyze Particle function of ImageJ, using thresholded images. Particles smaller than 0.1&mu;m<super>2</super> were excluded from the analysis.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Luciferase assay.</sectitle>
<p>Cortical or hippocampal neurons were transfected at 4 DIV or 14&ndash;16 DIV, and luciferase assays were performed one or two days later with the Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega).</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><i>In situ</i> hybridization.</sectitle>
<p><i>In situ</i> hybridization for APT1 was performed as described in ref. <bibrinl rid="b50">50</bibrinl> with a specific digoxigenin-labelled RNA riboprobe (992 nucleotides) sub-cloned into pBluescript II Sk+ (Stratagene) vector for transcription.</p>
<p>For detection of endogenous miRNAs in dissociated neurons we basically followed the <i>in situ</i> hybridization protocol described in ref. <bibrinl rid="b48">48</bibrinl>. Fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-conjugated complementary LNA probes (Exiqon) were hybridized overnight with miRNAs at 50 &deg;C. The signal intensity of the FITC probe was amplified with the Alexa Fluor 488 Signal Amplification Kit (Molecular Probes). MAP2 immunostaining (mouse monoclonal; Sigma) was used to reveal dendrites.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Quantitative real-time PCR.</sectitle>
<p>Quantitative real-time PCR was performed with the 7300 Real Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems), using the iTaq SybrGreen Supermix with ROX (Bio-Rad) for the detection of mRNAs and the specific TaqMan MicroRNA Assay kits (Applied Biosystems) for the detection of small RNAs (PE Applied Biosystems).</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Immunocytochemistry.</sectitle>
<p>Hippocampal neurons (17&ndash;18 DIV) were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 min, permeabilized with PBS plus 0.2% Triton X-100 and blocked in PBS containing 10% normal goat serum. We used a mouse monoclonal anti-PSD95 antibody (1:500; MA1-046; Dianova), a rabbit polyclonal anti-synapsin-1 antibody (1:500; Chemicon), a rabbit polyclonal anti-APT1 antibody (1:50; produced by BioGenes) or a rabbit anti-haemagglutinin antibody (1:2,000; ab9110; Abcam) together with Cy3/Cy5-conjugated anti-mouse/rabbit antibodies (1:400; Jackson Immuno Research). GluR2 surface staining was performed as described<bibr rid="b49"/>.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Cell fractionation.</sectitle>
<p>Cells were scraped into ice-cold hypotonic buffer (5 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EGTA, 0.1 mM EDTA) containing protease inhibitors (Complete Mini EDTA-free; Roche). After incubation for 30 min on ice, the lysate was passed ten times through a 20-gauge needle and centrifuged at 3,000<i>g</i> for 15 min to remove nuclear debris. The lysate was centrifuged again for 1 h at 150,000<i>g</i>. The supernatant (cytosolic fraction) was collected and the pellet (membrane fraction) was resuspended in lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% Triton-X-100, 0.2% SDS) containing protease inhibitors.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Application of APT1 inhibitors.</sectitle>
<p>Small-molecule APT1 inhibitors (FD196, FD253 and RB020) were diluted and stored in DMSO at 10 mM. Inhibitors were pre-diluted in medium and subsequently added to the cells at a final concentration of 10 &mu;M. The treatment was repeated every 60 min because of the high hydrolysis rate of the inhibitors. As control we added equivalent volumes of DMSO. A detailed characterization of the APT1 inhibitors will be published elsewhere.</p></sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Electrophysiology.</sectitle>
<p>mEPSCs were recorded in visually identified cultured neurons at DIV 18&ndash;20. Coverslips with transfected cells were constantly superfused at room temperature with bath solution containing (in mM) NaCl 156, KCl 2, CaCl<sub>2</sub> 2, MgCl<sub>2</sub> 1, glucose 16.5, HEPES 10; pH 7.3, 330 mOsM). Pipette solution for whole cell recording contained (in mM) KCl 100, NaCl 10, CaCl<sub>2</sub> 0.25, EGTA 5, HEPES 10, glucose 40, MgATP 4, NaGTP 0.1; pH 7.3, 310 mOsM. During recording, the bath solution contained gabazine (5 &mu;M) and tetrodotoxin (0.5 &mu;M). See <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Methods</sir> for further details.</p></sec></online-methods>
<p><i>Note: <sir rid="s1">Supplementary Information</sir> is available on the Nature Cell Biology website</i>.</p>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Author contributions</sectitle>
<p>G.M.S. performed microRNA profiling, M.C. analysed the microarray data, G.O., R.F. and C.J.B. performed <i>in situ</i> experiments, G.S., S.B., G.M.S. and C.K. performed and analysed spine measurements, M.O. and A.D. performed and analysed electrophysiology experiments, G.S. and G.M.S. performed and analysed immunostaining, G.S., G.O. and P.J.L. designed and performed the target validation experiments, G.O., C.D. and M.R. carried out bioinformatics, G.S. performed biochemistry, F.D., C.H., B.R. and H.W. were involved in the design and synthesis of specific APT1 inhibitors, R.F. performed sensor assays, G.S, S.B., M.C. and S.Kh. performed RNA expression analysis, K.H. and S.Ka provided reagents, M.E.G. participated in the initial stages of project planning, J.M. and G.M.S. directed the research and G.M.S. coordinated the project and wrote the manuscript.</p></sec></sec></bdy>
<bm>
<objects>
<fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
<!--ncb1848-f1-->
<figtl>Expression profiling of miRNAs in synaptososomes.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Western blot analysis of protein extracts derived from P15 rat forebrain (FB), low-speed centrifugation supernatant (S1), high-speed centrifugation supernatant (S2), high-speed centrifugation pellet (P2) or synaptosomes (SYN). Whereas synaptosomes are enriched in presynaptic (synaptophysin) and postsynaptic (GluR1) proteins, cytoplasmic EEA-1 is depleted from P2 and synaptosomes. (<b>b</b>) miRNAs that displayed an at least twofold change in expression between synaptosomes and forebrain in three different experiments, s.d. (<b>c</b>) Hierarchical clustering of miRNAs displaying significantly different expression between whole forebrain and synaptosomes in three different experiments. Colour coding: enrichment in synaptosomes versus whole forebrain on a logarithmic scale; yellow, higher level in synaptosomes; blue, lower level in synaptosomes.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
<!--ncb1848-f2-->
<figtl>A subset of neuronal miRNAs is localized in the synaptodendritic compartment.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Validation of microarray results by northern blotting. RNA was extracted from P15 rat forebrain (FB) or P15 rat synaptosomes (SYN), separated by 15% PAGE and probed for the presence of miR-218, miR-138, miR-124 or U6 snRNA. Numbers represent fold enrichment in synaptosomes. Note the absence of pre-miR-124 from synaptosomes. (<b>b</b>) Subcellular localization of synaptically enriched miRNAs in hippocampal neurons. <i>In situ</i> hybridization was performed on hippocampal neurons at 18 DIV with fluorescein isothiocyanate-coupled LNA probes directed against miR-9, miR-218 and miR-124, a digoxigenin-coupled LNA probe directed against miR-138 or a digoxigenin-coupled control LNA probe. Asterisks indicate prominent staining of miR-124 in neuronal cell bodies; arrowheads indicate dendritic staining of miR-9, miR-218 and miR-138. Scale bar, 20 &mu;m. Bottom right: quantification of ISH signal. Values are expressed as the ratio between dendritic and somatic signal intensities. Dendrite/soma ratios of miR-138, miR-218 and miR-9 are significantly higher than that of the somatic miR-124. Asterisk, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.05 (<i>t</i>-test, <i>n</i> = 3).</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
<!--ncb1848-f3-->
<figtl>Synaptically enriched miR-138 regulates dendritic spine size.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Flowchart of the functional screen for the identification of miRNAs controlling dendritic spine size. Rat hippocampal neurons (10 DIV) were transfected with GFP together with miRNA inhibitors (40 nM) or 134 duplex RNA (20 nM), and processed at 18 DIV for confocal microscopy. The fluorescence intensity of the freely diffusible GFP within three-dimensional projections was used to calculate the relative spine volume. (<b>b</b>) Quantitative analysis of relative spine volume of hippocampal neurons transfected with the indicated double-stranded RNA (20 nM) or antisense 2&prime;-<i>O</i>-methyl (2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me) oligonucleotides (40 nM). Values are shown as mean &plusmn; s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; at least 750 spines from 15 neurons). Asterisk, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.05 (compared with 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me control conditions). (<b>c</b>) Representative hippocampal neurons (18 DIV) transfected with GFP together with either 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me control (left) or 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138 (40 nM). Boxed insets show spines at higher magnification. Scale bars, 20 &mu;m (main panels); 8 &mu;m (insets). (<b>d</b>) LNA-mediated inhibition of miR-138 increases spine volume. Average spine volume of neurons treated with the indicated LNA antisense oligonucleotides (100 nM). Values were normalized to the GFP-only condition and are shown as mean &plusmn; s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; at least 1,200 spines from 15 neurons). <i>P</i> = 0.001 (ANOVA). The <i>P</i> value of a pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-test is indicated. (<b>e</b>) Overexpression of miR-138 in hippocampal neurons decreases spine volume. Duplex RNAs representing the full-length version of miR-138, a 3&prime; truncated miR-138 (miR-138 sh) or miR-134 were transfected as in <b>b</b> and the relative spine volume was determined. Values were normalized to the GFP-only condition and are shown as mean &plusmn; s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; at least 1,200 spines from 15 neurons). <i>P</i> = 0.029 (ANOVA). <i>P</i> values of pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-tests are indicated. (<b>f</b>) Restoring miR-138 function rescues increased spine size caused by miR-138 inhibition. Average spine volume was determined from neurons transfected with 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138 (40 nM) together with synthetic miR-138 duplex RNA (20 nM) or control duplex RNA (20 nM, let-7c). Values were normalized to the GFP-only condition and are shown as mean &plusmn; s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; at least 1,200 spines from 15 neurons). <i>P</i> = 0.0067 (ANOVA). <i>P</i> values of pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-tests are indicated.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
<!--ncb1848-f4-->
<figtl>miR-138 negatively regulates miniature synaptic transmission at excitatory synapses.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Original recordings of mEPSCs in cultured hippocampal neurons in the presence of tetrodotoxin and gabazine. Cells were voltage clamped at &minus;70 mV. Traces show representative data from cells expressing GFP only, GFP + miR-138 duplex RNA, and GFP + control duplex RNA. (<b>b</b>) Decrease in median mEPSC amplitudes in miR-138-expressing neurons. Results are shown as medians and s.d. for each group (GFP, <i>n</i> = 14; miR-138 <i>n</i> = 16; control duplex RNA <i>n</i> = 12). <i>P</i> values (pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-test) are indicated above the bar graph. (<b>c</b>) Cumulative amplitude distributions of mEPSCs recorded from neurons transfected as in <b>a</b>. Data were pooled from 14 cells (GFP), 16 cells (mir-138) and 12 cells (control duplex RNA). Note the leftward shift of the cumulative curve for miR-138 (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001, Kolmogorov&ndash;Smirnov test). (<b>d</b>) GluR2 surface staining of cells transfected as in <b>a</b>. Top panels: representative dendrites of neurons transfected with either miR-138 or control duplex RNA and stained for GluR2 (red) and synapsin (blue). Arrowheads depict large GluR2 clusters in spine heads of control neurons and small or absent GluR2 clusters in protrusions of miR-138-expressing neurons. Scale bar, 10 &mu;m. Bottom panel: cumulative distribution of GluR2 surface cluster sizes plotted for the indicated conditions. Kolmogorov&ndash;Smirnov test: <i>P</i> = 0.001; <i>D</i> = 0.0927 (miR-138 versus control transfected cells).</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f5" type="bmp" entname="figf5">
<!--ncb1848-f5-->
<figtl>APT1 is expressed in neuronal dendrites during synapse development.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Validation of predicted miR-138 target mRNAs by dual-luciferase reporter assay in cortical neurons (5 DIV). 3&prime; UTR regions of the indicated genes were cloned downstream of the firefly-luciferase-coding region within pGL3, and the resulting vectors were transfected into neurons together with miR-138 duplex RNA (20 nM). The percentage firefly luciferase activity, normalized to the internal <i>Renilla</i> luciferase control, of miR-138-expressing cells compared with control-transfected cells is plotted for each individual reporter construct. Results are shown as means &plusmn; s.d. (empty vector, <i>n</i> = 5; APT1, <i>n</i> = 6), each performed in duplicate. Asterisk, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.05 (pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-test; individual <i>P</i> values are indicated above each bar). n.s., not significant. (<b>b</b>) <i>APT1</i> mRNA is expressed in mouse hippocampus. ISH was performed in adult mouse hippocampal slices with the use of a probe perfectly complementary to mouse <i>APT1</i> mRNA (red signal in left panel) or a mismatch control probe (right panel). Cell nuclei were revealed with Hoechst counterstain (blue signal). DG, dentate gyrus. Scale bar, 0.1 &mu;m. (<b>c</b>) <i>APT1</i> mRNA localizes to dendrites of primary hippocampal neurons. ISH was performed in 9&ndash;10 DIV primary dissociated hippocampal neurons as described for <b>b</b>. Note the presence of multiple dendritic <i>APT1</i> mRNA-containing granules along the entire length of dendrites (arrowheads). Scale bar, 20 &mu;m. (<b>d</b>) Quantification of ISH signals obtained in <b>c</b>. Data are shown as means and s.d. for each of the indicated ISH probes (APT1 and control, <i>n</i> = 6; MAP2, <i>n</i> = 8). (<b>e</b>) APT1 protein expression is upregulated during the development of primary cortical neurons in culture. Whole cell extracts were prepared from the indicated stages of cortical neuron development and simultaneously probed with a rabbit antiserum against APT1 (lower band) and a mouse monoclonal anti-&beta;-actin antibody as a loading control (upper band). (<b>f</b>) APT1 protein is present at low levels in synaptosomal extracts. P15 rat brains were fractionated into cytosolic fractions (S1 and S2), membrane fraction (P2) and synaptosomes (SYN), and fractions were probed for the presence of PSD-95, APT1 and TuJ1 as a loading control. Protein levels in whole forebrain before fractionation (WB) are shown for comparison.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f6" type="bmp" entname="figf6">
<!--ncb1848-f6-->
<figtl><i>APT1</i> mRNA is a miR-138 target in neurons.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Top: schematic representation of the mouse miR-138&ndash;<i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR duplex as determined by RNAfold algorithm (<email>rna@tbi.univie.ac.at</email>). G&bull;C base pairs are indicated by red dots, and A&bull;U and G&bull;U base pairs by blue dots. Bottom: sequence conservation of the miR-138 target site within the <i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR across the indicated vertebrate species. Note the extensive conservation of nucleotides at both ends of the duplex that are engaged in base-pairing, and the less extensive conservation in the internal bulge structure (adopted from the University of California Santa Cruz genome browser at <weblink url="http://genome.ucsc.edu/">http://genome.ucsc.edu/</weblink>). Nucleotide substitutions in the APT1 mut construct are indicated. <i>X. tropicalis</i>, <i>Xenopus tropicalis</i>. (<b>b</b>) Importance of the 'seed' region within the <i>APT1</i> 3&prime; UTR for miR-138-mediated downregulation in primary rat cortical neurons (5 DIV). Luciferase assay was performed with wild-type APT1 (APT1wt) and mutated 3&prime; UTR constructs (APT1mut) in the presence of the indicated concentrations of miR-138 duplex RNA. Values are expressed relative to the internal <i>Renilla</i> luciferase activity and normalized to the activity of the wild-type APT1 reporter under basal conditions. Results are shown as means &plusmn; s.d. (10 nM, <i>n</i> = 6; 20 nM, <i>n</i> = 18, APT1mut, <i>n</i> = 8). Asterisk, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.00001 (pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-test between corresponding values of wild-type and mutated reporter). (<b>c</b>) Endogenous miR-138 inhibits APT1 luciferase reporter gene expression. Wild-type or mutated APT1 luciferase reporter genes were co-transfected together with increasing amounts of 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me-138 AS oligonucleotide (50&ndash;200 nM) into hippocampal neurons (16 DIV) and luciferase activity was measured two days later. Results are shown as mean &plusmn; s.d. (<i>n</i> = 5). Activity of the wild-type APT1 and mutated reporters under basal conditions was arbitrarily set to 1. Asterisk, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.01 (pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-test between corresponding values of wild-type and mutated reporter; <i>P</i> values are shown above bar graphs). (<b>d</b>) Endogenous miR-138 inhibits the accumulation of APT1 protein. Cholesterol-modified 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me antisense oligonucleotides directed against miR-138 or an unrelated sequence were introduced into hippocampal neurons at 13 DIV at a concentration of 1 &mu;M, and protein extracts were prepared for western blotting at 18 DIV. The average fold increase in the APT1 signal is indicated (<i>n</i> = 3; 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me control set to 1).</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f7" type="bmp" entname="figf7">
<!--ncb1848-f7-->
<figtl>APT1 activity is required for the control of dendritic spine size.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) shRNA-mediated knockdown of endogenous APT1 in primary neurons. pSUPER shRNA vectors (2 &mu;g) were electroporated into cortical neurons, and the expression of endogenous APT1 and &beta;-actin was determined by western blotting (7 DIV). (<b>b</b>) Interfering with APT1 expression in neurons decreases dendritic spine volume. Representative hippocampal neurons at 18 DIV transfected with enhanced GFP and either control shRNA (left panel) or pSUPER-APT1-shRNA-3 are shown. Scale bar, 20 &mu;m. (<b>c</b>) shRNA-mediated knockdown of endogenous APT1 in neurons decreases dendritic spine volume. Rat hippocampal neurons (14 DIV) were transfected with GFP alone or together with pSUPER-expressing shRNAs directed against <i>APT1</i> mRNA (<i>APT1</i> shRNA-1, shRNA-3 and shRNA-4) or an unrelated sequence (control shRNA; 5 ng each). Values were normalized to the GFP-only condition and are shown as means and s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; at least 1,800 spines from 18 neurons). <i>P</i> &lt; 0.0001 (ANOVA). <i>P</i> values of pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-tests are indicated. (<b>d</b>) Pharmacological inhibition of APT1 in neurons decreases dendritic spine volume. Hippocampal neurons (18 DIV) were treated for 6 h with either inactive control compound (RB020) or specific APT1 inhibitors (FD196, FD253, 10 &mu;M each) before analysis of spine volume. Values were normalized to the dimethylsulphoxide (DMSO)-only condition and are shown as means and s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; 1,800 spines from 18 neurons). <i>P</i> = 0.044 (ANOVA). <i>P</i> values of pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-tests are indicated. (<b>e</b>) shRNA-mediated knockdown of APT1 suppresses the increase in spine volume caused by miR-138 inhibition. Rat hippocampal neurons (14 DIV) were transfected with the indicated 2&prime;<i>O</i>-Me antisense oligonucleotides (40 nM) together with <i>APT1</i> shRNA-3 or control shRNA (5 ng of each). Values are shown as means and s.d. (<i>n</i> = 4; at least 2,400 spines from 24 neurons). <i>P</i> = 0.0075 (ANOVA). <i>P</i> values of pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-tests are indicated. (<b>f</b>) APT1 expression rescues miR-138-mediated spine shrinkage. Rat hippocampal neurons (10 DIV) were transfected with miR-138 duplex RNA (20 nM) in combination with wild-type APT1 or APT1 mut expression constructs (250 ng each). Values were normalized to the GFP-only condition and are shown as means and s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; at least 1,800 spines from 18 neurons). <i>P</i> = 0.029 (ANOVA). <i>P</i> values of pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-tests are indicated.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f8" type="bmp" entname="figf8">
<!--ncb1848-f8-->
<figtl>miR-138 regulated membrane-association of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> is required for the control of dendritic spine size.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Western blot of total lysates from HEK293 cells transfected with control shRNA or <i>APT1</i> shRNA-1&ndash;4 using anti-&beta;-actin (top) or anti-APT1 (bottom) antibodies. A representative blot is shown (<i>n</i> = 3). Note that only the <i>APT1</i> shRNA-3 target site is conserved in human and rat. (<b>b</b>) shRNA-mediated knockdown of endogenous APT1 increases the fraction of membrane-bound Myc&ndash;G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> in HEK293 cells. Western blot of membrane (M) or cytosolic (C) lysates expressing Myc&ndash;G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> together with <i>APT1</i> shRNA-3 or a control shRNA, using anti-Myc (top), anti-calnexin (middle) or anti-&beta;-actin (bottom) antibodies. (<b>c</b>) Quantification of signals obtained by western blotting in <b>b</b>. &ast;<i>P</i> &lt; 0.05 (<i>n</i> = 3; pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-test). (<b>d</b>) Expression of miR-138 increases the fraction of membrane-bound Myc&ndash;G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> in HEK293 cells. Western blot of membrane (M) or cytosolic (C) lysates expressing Myc&ndash;G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> with or without synthetic miR-138 duplex (40 nM), using anti-Myc (top) anti-calnexin (middle) or anti-&beta;-actin (bottom) antibodies. (<b>e</b>) Quantification of signals obtained by western blotting in <b>d</b>. *<i>P</i> &lt; 0.05 (<i>n</i> = 4; pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-test). (<b>f</b>) Expression of miR-138 decreases endogenous APT-1 protein levels in HEK293 cells. Western blot of whole cell lysates transfected with miR-134, miR-138 or control duplex RNA (10 nM), using anti-APT-1 (bottom) or anti-EEA-1 (top) antibodies. Quantification of independent blots is shown at the bottom (<i>n</i> = 3; control duplex RNA = 1). Note the modest decrease in endogenous hAPT1 protein levels as a result of low co-transfection efficiency of miR-138 duplex RNA (about 50&ndash;60%). (<b>g</b>) Expression of membrane-targeted G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> rescues spine enlargement caused by miR-138 inhibition. Rat hippocampal neurons (10 DIV) were transfected with the indicated LNA oligonucleotides (100 nM) together with G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> expression constructs (250 ng each). Values were normalized to the GFP-only condition and are shown as means and s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3; at least 1,800 spines from 18 neurons). <i>P</i> = 0.019 (ANOVA). <i>P</i> values of pairwise Student's <i>t</i>-tests are indicated. (<b>h</b>) Expression levels and subcellular distribution of G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> variants. Western blot of membrane (M) or cytosolic (C) lysates from HEK293 cells expressing the indicated G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> mutants.</p></caption></fig></objects>
<ack><p>We thank O. Rocks and P. Wedegaertner for providing reagents; R. Heinen for suggestions on the luciferase reporter assays; T. W&uuml;st for technical assistance; and M. Alenius and A. Keene for critically reading the manuscript. This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (SFB488; to G.M.S.), the Human Frontier Science Program (Career Development Award; to G.M.S.), the National Institute on Drug Abuse (1R21DA025102-01; to G.M.S.), the National Institutes of Health (NS045500; to M.E.G.) the Bioinformatics Initiative (to C.D. and M.R.), the Austrian Academy of Sciences (to J.M. and S.B. (DOC-fFORTE-fellowship)) and the Austrian Government, GEN-AU initiative (to G.O.). C.H. acknowledges the Alexander von Humboldt foundation for a postdoctoral fellowship. F.D. is a recipient of a TALENT-stipendium from the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO) and a Marie-Curie fellowship from the European Union.</p></ack>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hering</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sheng</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Dendritic spines: structure, dynamics and regulation</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>880</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>888</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Nimchinsky</snm>, <fnm>E. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sabatini</snm>, <fnm>B. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Svoboda</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structure and function of dendritic spines</atl>. <jtl>Annu. Rev. Physiol.</jtl> <vid>64</vid>, <ppf>313</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>353</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Matsuzaki</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Honkura</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ellis-Davies</snm>, <fnm>G. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kasai</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structural basis of long-term potentiation in single dendritic spines</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>429</vid>, <ppf>761</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>766</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Nagerl</snm>, <fnm>U. V</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Eberhorn</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cambridge</snm>, <fnm>S. B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bonhoeffer</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl>Bidirectional activity-dependent morphological plasticity in hippocampal neurons</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>759</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>767</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bagni</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Greenough</snm>, <fnm>W. T.</fnm></refau> <atl>From mRNP trafficking to spine dysmorphogenesis: the roots of fragile X syndrome</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>376</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>387</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Okamoto</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nagai</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Miyawaki</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hayashi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <atl>Rapid and persistent modulation of actin dynamics regulates postsynaptic reorganization underlying bidirectional plasticity</atl>. <jtl>Nature Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>1104</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1112</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yi</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> J. &amp; <refau><snm>Ehlers</snm>, <fnm>M. D.</fnm></refau> <atl>Ubiquitin and protein turnover in synapse function</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>47</vid>, <ppf>629</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>632</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Shi</snm>, <fnm>S. H</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Rapid spine delivery and redistribution of AMPA receptors after synaptic NMDA receptor activation</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>284</vid>, <ppf>1811</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1816</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Zhou</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Brain-specific phosphorylation of MeCP2 regulates activity-dependent Bdnf transcription, dendritic growth, and spine maturation</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>52</vid>, <ppf>255</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>269</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bingol</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schuman</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Synaptic protein degradation by the ubiquitin proteasome system</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.</jtl> <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>536</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>541</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Steward</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schuman</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Protein synthesis at synaptic sites on dendrites</atl>. <jtl>Annu. Rev. Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>24</vid>, <ppf>299</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>325</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Martin</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> C., <refau><snm>Barad</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kandel</snm>, <fnm>E. R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Local protein synthesis and its role in synapse-specific plasticity</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>587</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>592</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Eberwine</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Miyashiro</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kacharmina</snm>, <fnm>J. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Job</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <atl>Local translation of classes of mRNAs that are targeted to neuronal dendrites</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>98</vid>, <ppf>7080</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>7085</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ostroff</snm>, <fnm>L. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fiala</snm>, <fnm>J. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Allwardt</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Harris</snm>, <fnm>K. M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Polyribosomes redistribute from dendritic shafts into spines with enlarged synapses during LTP in developing rat hippocampal slices</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>35</vid>, <ppf>535</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>545</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wells</snm>, <fnm>D. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Richter</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fallon</snm>, <fnm>J. R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Molecular mechanisms for activity-regulated protein synthesis in the synapto-dendritic compartment</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>132</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>137</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kiebler</snm>, <fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bassell</snm>, <fnm>G. J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Neuronal RNA granules: movers and makers</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>51</vid>, <ppf>685</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>690</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Krichevsky</snm>, <fnm>A. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kosik</snm>, <fnm>K. S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Neuronal RNA granules: a link between RNA localization and stimulation-dependent translation</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>32</vid>, <ppf>683</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>696</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ashraf</snm>, <fnm>S. I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>McLoon</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sclarsic</snm>, <fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kunes</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Synaptic protein synthesis associated with memory is regulated by the RISC pathway in <i>Drosophila</i></atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>124</vid>, <ppf>191</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>205</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schratt</snm>, <fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>A brain-specific microRNA regulates dendritic spine development</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>439</vid>, <ppf>283</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>289</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ambros</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau> <atl>The functions of animal microRNAs</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>431</vid>, <ppf>350</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>355</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bartel</snm>, <fnm>D. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>116</vid>, <ppf>281</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>297</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Filipowicz</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bhattacharyya</snm>, <fnm>S. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sonenberg</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl>Mechanisms of post-transcriptional regulation by microRNAs: are the answers in sight?</atl> <jtl>Nature Rev. Genet.</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>102</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>114</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kosik</snm>, <fnm>K. S.</fnm></refau> <atl>The neuronal microRNA system</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>911</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>920</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Miska</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> A. <i>et al</i>. <atl>Microarray analysis of microRNA expression in the developing mammalian brain</atl>. <jtl>Genome Biol.</jtl> <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>R68</ppf> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sempere</snm>, <fnm>L. F.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Expression profiling of mammalian microRNAs uncovers a subset of brain-expressed microRNAs with possible roles in murine and human neuronal differentiation</atl>. <jtl>Genome Biol.</jtl> <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>R13</ppf> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Identification of many microRNAs that copurify with polyribosomes in mammalian neurons</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>101</vid>, <ppf>360</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>365</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yeh</snm>, <fnm>D. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Duncan</snm>, <fnm>J. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yamashita</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Michel</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl>Depalmitoylation of endothelial nitric-oxide synthase by acyl-protein thioesterase 1 is potentiated by Ca<super>2+</super>-calmodulin</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>274</vid>, <ppf>33148</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>33154</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rao</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Steward</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> <atl>Evidence that protein constituents of postsynaptic membrane specializations are locally synthesized: analysis of proteins synthesized within synaptosomes</atl>. <jtl>J. Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>2881</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2895</ppl> (<cd year="1991">1991</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Meister</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Landthaler</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dorsett</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tuschl</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sequence-specific inhibition of microRNA- and siRNA-induced RNA silencing</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>544</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>550</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Zito</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Knott</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shepherd</snm>, <fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shenolikar</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Svoboda</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Induction of spine growth and synapse formation by regulation of the spine actin cytoskeleton</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>321</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>334</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b31"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mansfield</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>MicroRNA-responsive 'sensor' transgenes uncover Hox-like and other developmentally regulated patterns of vertebrate microRNA expression</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl> <vid>36</vid>, <ppf>1079</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1083</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b32"><reftxt><refau><snm>Vo</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>A cAMP-response element binding protein-induced microRNA regulates neuronal morphogenesis</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>102</vid>, <ppf>16426</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>16431</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b33"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rehmsmeier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Steffen</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hochsmann</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Giegerich</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Fast and effective prediction of microRNA/target duplexes</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>1507</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1517</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b34"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kruger</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rehmsmeier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>RNAhybrid: microRNA target prediction easy, fast and flexible</atl>. <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>34</vid>, <ppf>W451</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>W454</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b35"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rodenas-Ruano</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Perez-Pinzon</snm>, <fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Green</snm>, <fnm>E. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Henkemeyer</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Liebl</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Distinct roles for ephrinB3 in the formation and function of hippocampal synapses</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl> <vid>292</vid>, <ppf>34</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>45</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b36"><reftxt><refau><snm>Etournay</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>PHR1, an integral membrane protein of the inner ear sensory cells, directly interacts with myosin 1c and myosin VIIa</atl>. <jtl>J. Cell Sci.</jtl> <vid>118</vid>, <ppf>2891</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2899</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b37"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ozaki</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>cAMP-GEFII is a direct target of cAMP in regulated exocytosis</atl>. <jtl>Nature Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>805</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>811</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b38"><reftxt><refau><snm>Husseini Ael</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Synaptic strength regulated by palmitate cycling on PSD-95</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>108</vid>, <ppf>849</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>863</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b39"><reftxt><refau><snm>Linder</snm>, <fnm>M. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Deschenes</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Palmitoylation: policing protein stability and traffic</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>74</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>84</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b40"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kang</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Neural palmitoyl-proteomics reveals dynamic synaptic palmitoylation</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>456</vid>, <ppf>904</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>909</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b41"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bhattacharyya</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wedegaertner</snm>, <fnm>P. B.</fnm></refau> <atl>G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> requires palmitoylation for plasma membrane localization, Rho-dependent signaling, and promotion of p115-RhoGEF membrane binding</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>275</vid>, <ppf>14992</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>14999</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b42"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kye</snm>, <fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Somatodendritic microRNAs identified by laser capture and multiplex RT-PCR</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>1224</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1234</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b43"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lugli</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Torvik</snm>, <fnm>V. I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Larson</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Smalheiser</snm>, <fnm>N. R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Expression of microRNAs and their precursors in synaptic fractions of adult mouse forebrain</atl>. <jtl>J. Neurochem.</jtl> <vid>106</vid>, <ppf>650</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>661</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b44"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bernard</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> <atl>Lim kinases, regulators of actin dynamics</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>39</vid>, <ppf>1071</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1076</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b45"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kurose</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <atl>G&alpha;<sub>12</sub> and G&alpha;<sub>13</sub> as key regulatory mediator in signal transduction</atl>. <jtl>Life Sci.</jtl> <vid>74</vid>, <ppf>155</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>161</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b46"><reftxt><refau><snm>Tada</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sheng</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Molecular mechanisms of dendritic spine morphogenesis</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.</jtl> <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>95</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>101</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b47"><reftxt><refau><snm>Obernosterer</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Leuschner</snm>, <fnm>P. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Alenius</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Martinez</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Post-transcriptional regulation of microRNA expression</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>1161</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1167</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b48"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schratt</snm>, <fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nigh</snm>, <fnm>E. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>W. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hu</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Greenberg</snm>, <fnm>M. E.</fnm></refau> <atl>BDNF regulates the translation of a select group of mRNAs by a mammalian target of rapamycin-phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase-dependent pathway during neuronal development</atl>. <jtl>J. Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>24</vid>, <ppf>9366</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>9377</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b49"><reftxt><refau><snm>Paradis</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>An RNAi-based approach identifies molecules required for glutamatergic and GABAergic synapse development</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>53</vid>, <ppf>217</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>232</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b50"><reftxt><refau><snm>Obernosterer</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Martinez</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Alenius</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Locked nucleic acid-based <i>in situ</i> detection of microRNAs in mouse tissue sections</atl>. <jtl>Nature Protocols</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>1508</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1514</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></article>
