<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315768a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>768</spn><epn>771</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315768a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Molecular characterization and expression of the gene encoding human erythroid-potentiating activity</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Judith C.</fnm><snm>Gasson</snm><inits>J. C.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>David W.</fnm><snm>Golde</snm><inits>D. W.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Susan E.</fnm><snm>Kaufman</snm><inits>S. E.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Carol A.</fnm><snm>Westbrook</snm><inits>C. A.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Rodney M.</fnm><snm>Hewick</snm><inits>R. M.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Randal J.</fnm><snm>Kaufman</snm><inits>R. J.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Gordon G.</fnm><snm>Wong</snm><inits>G. G.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Patricia A.</fnm><snm>Temple</snm><inits>P. A.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Ann C.</fnm><snm>Leary</snm><inits>A. C.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Eugene L.</fnm><snm>Brown</snm><inits>E. L.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Elizabeth C.</fnm><snm>Orr</snm><inits>E. C.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Steven C.</fnm><snm>Clark</snm><inits>S. C.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<aff><super>&ast;</super>Division of Hematology-Oncology, Department of Medicine, University of California School of Medicine, Los Angeles, California 90024, USA</aff>
<aff><super>&dagger;</super>Genetics Institute, Inc., 87 Cambridge Massachusetts 02140, USA</aff></aug>
<hst>
<re year="na" month="2" day="4"/>
<acc year="1985" month="4" day="24"/></hst>
<fp><p>Erythropoietin is the primary physiological regulator of erythropoiesis; however, <i>in vitro</i> studies have identified another class of mediators which appear to be important in stimulating erythroid progenitors. These factors have generally been referred to as burst-promoting activities (BPA), because they stimulate the growth of early erythroid progenitors referred to as burst-forming units-erythroid (BFU-E) which give rise to colonies of up to thousands of haemoglobinized cells<super>1,2</super>. We recently reported purification of a burst-promoting activity from medium conditioned by the Mo T-lymphoblast cell line infected with human T-cell lym-photropic virus type II (HTLV-II)<super>3,4</super>. This purified glycoprotein of relative molecular mass (<i>M</i><sub>r</sub>) 28,000 also stimulates colony formation by more mature erythroid precursors (CFU-E) and is therefore referred to as erythroid-potentiating activity (EPA)<super>5</super>. Purified EPA specifically stimulates human and murine cells of the erythroid lineage, unlike murine interleukin-3 (IL-3) which stimulates precursor cells from all haematopoietic lineages<super>6</super>. We report here the isolation of a complementary DNA molecular clone encoding EPA and its use in producing EPA in COS (monkey) cells and CHO (Chinese hamster ovary) cells. We also define the organization of the EPA gene in human DNA.</p></fp></fm>
<bdy>
Purified EPA obtained from two 10-1 preparations of medium conditioned by the Mo T-lymphoblast cell line was analysed in four separate samples using a gas phase sequenator. From a total of approximately 25 g of purified protein, the following partial amino-acid sequence was obtained from the NH2-terminus:
1 5 (A) T C V P P H
10 15                  20                    25 7QTAFCNSDLVIRAKFVGT
Using this sequence, three different oligonucleotide probes were prepared. The first probe consisted of all 64 possible 12-mers encoding residues 9-12 above (QTAF). The second probe consisted of 64 14-mers predicted from residues 21-25 (AKFVG). The third probe was a pool of 16 53-mers predicted from residues 9-26 based on preferred codon usage. A cDNA library was prepared from Mo messenger RNA and enriched for sequences specific to mature T cells by hybridizing the single-stranded cDNA to mRNA from B cells (Daudi) and immature T cells (CEM). One set of replicate filters containing the enriched Mo cDNA library was hybridized with the 64 12-mers and the other set with the 64 14-mers described above. DNA from 10 clones which hybridized with both probes was prepared and analysed by digestion with Pstl and hybridization to each of the three oligonucleotide probes. Three clones, each of which had at least one internal Pstl site, hybridized to all three probes, and were further characterized.
Fig. 1    Nucleotide and deduced amino-acid sequence of the cDNA clone encoding EPA.
Methods. Standard gentle lysis procedures were used to prepare RNA from 2 x IO9 lectin-stimulated Mo cells. Polyadenylated RNA was selected with oligo(dT)-cellulose and used as the template to synthesize the first strand of cDNA by reverse transcription. Approximately 1 g of single-stranded cDNA, obtained from 10  of poly(A)+ RNA, was enriched by hybridization to 10-fold excess concentrations of mRNA from a human B-cell line (Daudi) and immature T-cell line (CEM), and the unhybridized cDNA (-5% of input cDNA) was recovered by chromatography on hydroxy-lapatite. Standard techniques were used to synthesize the second cDNA strand, digest the single-stranded loop and add homopoly-meric (dC) tails. The cDNAs were annealed with G-tailed pBR322 and used to transform Escherichia coli. A final yield of 40,000 colonies was obtained from double-stranded cDNA. EPA was purified from serum-free Mo-conditioned medium using the previously published method3. Two preparations of EPA containing 25 g were subjected to Edman degradation and analysed on a gas phase sequenator. Based on the amino-acid sequence obtained, three pools of oligonucleotide probes were constructed. The pools were used to probe replicate filters containing the recombinant plasmids described above. Potential EPA clones were identified by colony hybridization. DNA from positive clones was analysed by restriction digestion and hybridization to the oligonucleotide probes. EPA cDNA clones were verified by DNA sequence analysis using the dideoxynucleotide chain termination procedure primed with the oligonucleotides described in the text19.
A pool of eight strongly hybridizing 14-mers (corresponding to amino-acid residues 21-25) was used as a primer for sequencing the three putative EPA cDNA clones. The resulting DNA sequence was that expected from the amino-acid sequence of residues 1-19, confirming that these cDNA clones encode the EPA protein.
Fig. 2 Analysis of EPA mRNA from human cells and cell lines. Polyadenylated cytoplasmic RNA (5 g) was isolated from U-937 cells cultured in the presence of lOnM dexamethasone for 20 h (lane 1); U-937 cells (lane 2); Mo cells cultured in the presence of dexamethasone (lane 3); Mo cells (lane 4); Mo cells treated for 20 h with phytohaemagglutinin (0.3%) and phorbol myristate acetate (5mgmll) (lane 5); C10-MJ2 cells (lane 6); UCD-144-MLA cells (lane 7); and peripheral blood lymphocytes (lane 8). The mRNA was fractionated on a 1 % agarose gel, transferred to nitrocellulose and hybridized with the EPA clone labelled with 32P as described previously12.
The complete nucleotide sequence of all three clones was obtained by dideoxy sequencing of M13 subclones (Fig. 1). The cDNA encodes a protein of 207 amino acids. Based on the NH2-terminal sequence of the mature protein, a signal peptide of 23 amino acids is predicted by the nucleotide sequence. Characteristic of other signal peptides, this region is rich in Hydrophobie amino acids. The predicted relative molecular mass of the mature protein is in good agreement with the apparent 18,000 Mr observed following digestion of EPA with endogly-cosidase F (rf. 4). Endoglycosidase F removes both high man-nose and complex asparagine-linked carbohydrate moieties7; two possible sites for asparagine-linked glycosylation are amino acid 53 and 101. The presence of 12 cysteine residues in the deduced amino-acid sequence predicts a protein structure which could account for the marked heat stability previously described for EPA biological activity5.
The EPA cDNA clone was used to screen a cDNA library prepared from the gibbon lymphosarcoma cell line UCD-144-MLA8, a source of numerous lymphokines including burst-promoting activity. The resulting clones were sequenced and compared with the nucleotide sequence of human EPA. Seven nucleotides within the coding region differed between human and gibbon EPA, resulting in a single amino acid change from arginine to lysine at residue 43.
Further confirmation that these clones encode EPA was obtained by Northern analysis. mRNA was prepared from cells previously shown to produce burst-promoting activity. Figure 2 shows that Mo (lane 4), C10-MJ29 (lane 6) and UCD-144-MLA8 (lane 7) mature T-lymphoblast cell lines, peripheral blood lymphocytes (lane 8) and the U-93710 (lane 2) monocytic cell line produce a 0.9-kilobase (kb) transcript which hybridizes with the EPA cDNA probe. Erythroid-potentiating activity mRNA could not be detected in samples from the immature B-lympho-blastoid cell line Daudi (data not shown). These results are in agreement with previous reports of EPA activity, as well as the presence or absence of the EPA protein in cell supernatants as determined by immunoprecipitation and radioimmunoassay (unpublished results). Treatment of U-937 (Fig. 2, lane 1) and Mo .(lane 3) cells with the glucocorticoid dexamethasone appears to decrease the level of EPA mRNA by approximately twofold. Similar results have been seen with other T-cell-derived growth factors including IL-211 and granulocyte-monocyte colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF)12. Treatment of Mo cells with phytohaemagglutinin and phorbol myristate acetate (Fig. 2, lane 5) does not greatly increase the abundance of EPA mRNA over that produced constitutively. In similar conditions, GM-CSF mRNA levels are increased approximately two- to fourfold12.
Fig. 3 Biological activity of EPA cDNA clones expressed in mammalian cells, a, Stimulation of human peripheral blood BFU-E by dilutions of supernatants containing recombinant EPA expressed transiently in COS cells (·) compared with mock-transfected COS cells (A). 6, Supernatant from CHO cells which constitutively produce high levels of recombinant EPA (·) compared with supernatant from a CHO line which does not express the EPA cDNA (A).
Methods. The expression vector 91023(B) is described in detail elsewhere17. This plasmid contains eukaryotic regulatory elements from adenovirus, simian virus 40, and the mouse immunoglobulin and dihydrofolate reductase genes. COS 7 monkey cells were trans-fected with the EPA cDNA inserted into the 91023(B) vector using a previously described procedure12. Briefly, cells were incubated for 12 h at 37 C in serum-free Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium containing DEAE-dextran (Mr 5xl06 Pharmacia, 250mgmr1) with 0.1 M Tris pH 7.3 and 2gmG1 plasmid DNA. After the incubation, cells were rinsed with serum-free medium and treated for 2 h at 37 C with 1 mM chloroquine in medium containing serum. Cells were washed and medium was collected at varying intervals. Chinese hamster ovary cells (CHO) were transfected with the 91023(B) vector containing the EPA cDNA clone and a functional dihydrofolate reductase clone subcloned into the unique Clal site. Stable transfectants were isolated by selection in growth medium without nucleosides for about 2 weeks. The transfected DNA containing the EPA sequence was amplified by repeated stepwise selection in methotrexate for 2 months. To determine the levels of recombinant EPA protein synthesized, supernatants from transiently infected COS cells and stably infected CHO cells were analysed in a radioimmunoassay for EPA (J.C. G., J. Chan and D.W.G., in preparation). Samples which were positive for immunoreactive EPA were assayed for biological activity, by measuring stimulation of the growth of human peripheral blood BFU-E in methylcellulose culture3. Peripheral blood leukocytes were plated at a density of 3 x IO5 cells ml"1 in 96-well tissue culture trays. Each well contained 0.1 ml of cells in methylcellulose and 0.01 ml of a dilution of the test supernatant. Control wells were those to which diluent alone was added, and they contained 20 colonies per well in panel a and 16 colonies per well in panel b.
To provide definitive evidence that the cDNA clone encoded EPA, it was expressed in mammalian cells. The EPA cDNA clone was inserted into the 91023(B) mammalian expression vector and transiently expressed in COS monkey cells13. The concentration of EPA in the unfractionated COS cell super-natants was estimated, by radioimmunoassay, to be approximately 1  ml"1 72 h after transfection, indicating efficient expression of the cDNA clone.
Fig. 4 Genomic organization of human EPA. a, Human DNA isolated from the HTLV-II-transformed J-LB-II T-lymphoblast cell line was digested with Xbal, Hindlll and EcoRI and hybridized with the EPA cDNA. 6, Restriction map of an EPA genomic clone in Charon 30 (???? 3) and subcloned into pBR322 (pEH 5.2) are shown. Restriction sites are: R, EcoRI; X, Xba\\ H, Hindlll; A, Aval; N, Ncol; I, Hindi. Methods. High Mr DNA was prepared from a variety of cell lines, using standard procedures. The lengths of restriction fragments containing EPA sequences were determined by the method of Southern12. ? ? phage recombinant library was constructed using Charon 30 and DNA from the J-LB-III human T-lymphoblast cell line20. The J-LB-III DNA was digested with the restriction enzyme Saw3A for various times and 10-25-kb fragments were isolated using a NaCl gradient21. The J-LB-III DNA was ligated to Charon 30 DNA which had been digested with am HI and purified on a NaCl gradient. Recombinant phage were recovered by in vitro packaging22. The recombinant phage were screened by hybridization to a probe consisting of a full-length EPA cDNA clone. Two smaller fragments of the EPA cDNA clone were isolated using PstI, gel purified and used to generate detailed restriction maps of the EPA genomic clones.
Supernatants from COS cells transiently infected with either the 91023(B) vector alone or the vector containing the EPA coding region were assayed for stimulation of human peripheral blood BFU-E. The results (Fig. 3a) demonstrate biological activity of the recombinant EPA transiently expressed in COS monkey cells. Good stimulation of erythroid bursts (>130% of control) is seen at concentrations as low as 5 pM (based on the concentration of immunoreactive EPA). In every case, the supernatant from the mock-infected or uninfected COS cells had a slight stimulatory activity on human BFU-E, apparently due to some constitutive production by COS cells of a factor that stimulates human erythroid precursors.
In addition to transient expression of EPA in COS cells, it is useful to generate cell lines which constitutively produce high levels of EPA protein. Chinese hamster ovary cells with integrated copies of the 91023(B) vector containing the EPA coding region along with the dihydrofolate reductase gene were selected in methotrexate. After approximately 2 months of selection, levels of EPA protein in supernatants from 31 CHO cell clones were estimated by radioimmunoassay. One clone was found to constitutively produce levels of recombinant EPA similar to those obtained by transient expression in COS cells. The biological activity of recombinant EPA in the medium conditioned by this cell line was compared with medium conditioned by CHO cells which had been treated in the same way, but were not producing recombinant EPA. Figure 3b shows the stimulation of human peripheral blood BFU-E by recombinant EPA produced by this stable line of CHO cells. No endogenous burst-promoting activity is seen in the supernatant from CHO cells not producing recombinant EPA. The recombinant EPA is active in the picomolar range of concentrations, as is the purified protein from Mo-conditioned medium3.
To study the molecular organization of the human EPA gene sequences, high-Mr DNA was prepared from human T-cell lines (J-LB-II, J-LB-III, J-WM-IV, Mo), B-cell lines (Wil), a myeloid line (HL-60) and a fibroblast line (143) and analysed by the method of Southern14 for hybridization to the EPA cDNA clone. In all cases the same pattern was seen (Fig. 4a). The restriction enzyme Xbal generated a strongly hybridizing fragment of 3.9 kb and a faint band at 4.7 kb. A single fragment of 5.2 kb and 12.5 kb was detected following digestion with Hindlll and EcoRI respectively.
To obtain a more detailed map of the structure of the EPA gene, a recombinant A phage library (prepared from Charon 3015 and J-LB-III DNA) was screened with the EPA cDNA clone as a probe. Three overlapping genomic EPA clones were obtained from approximately one million recombinant phage. The restriction map of one representative clone, ? EPA 3, is shown in Fig. 40. This clone contains the 12.5-kb EcoRI fragment and the 5.2-kb Hinalll fragment which was subcloned into pBR322 for further analysis (pEH 5.2). Restriction analysis of pEH 5.2 revealed that EPA appears to be encoded by a single gene approximately 3 kb in length, interrupted by at least two intervening sequences.
Human EPA specifically stimulates the growth of peripheral blood- and bone marrow-derived erythroid precursors from mouse and man. 11-3 is a 28,000-Mr glycoprotein isolated from the EL-4 mouse lymphoma cell line and WEHI-3 mouse myelomonocytic cells. Unlike EPA, IL-3 stimulates the growth of all haemotopoietic precursors, including BFU-E6. Murine IL-3 has been molecularly cloned and sequenced16'17. Comparison of the murine IL-3 sequence with the human EPA sequence, described here, reveals no homology. Thus EPA is not the human counterpart of murine IL-3, consistent with the biological observations that EPA does not stimulate pluripotent or myeloid precursor cells3'4.
A computer search for protein homology did not reveal previously described proteins homologous to EPA (R. Doolittle, personal communication). A computer search for DNA homology (Genbank) did, however, reveal that a highly homologous partial murine cDNA clone had been isolated. This clone was obtained from virally induced C243 cells using hybrid selection of mRNAs whose translation products have antiviral interferon activity18. The cDNA clone pMIF 3/10 contains about 290 base pairs that could encode that 3' 39 amino acids of a protein plus the 3'-untranslated region. This cDNA clone was reported to encode a murine /3-interferon-like protein, but the relationship between this molecule and EPA is unclear. Eryth-roid-potentiating activity has no interferon activity (our unpublished observation), and full-length cDNA clones of pMIF 3/10 have not been isolated and expressed to provide direct evidence for interferon activity.
The physiological functions of EPA in vivo are unknown. Since EPA stimulates murine erythroid precursors in vitro, as well as human, it should be possible to study in vivo effects of this modulator in the mouse. The availability of adequate quantides of recombinant protein will be critical in elucidating the role of EPA in normal haematopoiesis. Additionally, the availability of cDNA and genomic clones will make it possible to study the evolution and expression of this interesting erythroid haematopoietic growth factor.
We thank No«lle Bersch for performing the bioassays, Irvin S. Y. Chen for helpful comments on the manuscript and Hillary Merriman and Betty Koers for preparation of the manuscript. This work was supported, in part, by PHS grants CA 32737 (D.W.G., J.C.G., S.E.K.), CA 30388 (D.W.G., J.C.G.) and CA 16042 (UCLA Cancer Center Core Grant) awarded by the NCI.</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Dexter</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>309</vid>, <ppf>746</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>747</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Iscove</snm>, <fnm>N. N.</fnm></refau> in <btl>Hematopoietic Cell Differentiation</btl> (eds Golde, D. W., Cline, M. J., Metcalf, D. &amp; Fox, C. F.) <ppf>37</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>52</ppl> (Academic, New York, <cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Westbrook</snm>, <fnm>C. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gasson</snm>, <fnm>J. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gerber</snm>, <fnm>S. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Selsted</snm>, <fnm>M. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Golde</snm>, <fnm>D. W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>259</vid>, <ppf>9992</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>9996</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gasson</snm>, <fnm>J. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bersch</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> : <refau><snm>Golde</snm>, <fnm>D. W.</fnm></refau> in <btl>Stem Cell Physiology</btl> (ed. Palek, J.) (Eiss, New York, in the press).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Golde</snm>, <fnm>D. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bersch</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Quan</snm>, <fnm>S. G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lusis</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>77</vid>, <ppf>593</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>596</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ihle</snm>, <fnm>J. N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>J. Immun.</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>282</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>287</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Elder</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Alexander</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>79</vid>, <ppf>4540</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>4544</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kawakami</snm>, <fnm>T. G.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature new Biol.</jtl> <vid>235</vid>, <ppf>170</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>171</ppl> (<cd year="1972">1972</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Arya</snm>, <fnm>S. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wong-Staal</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gallo</snm>, <fnm>R. C.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>223</vid>, <ppf>1086</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1087</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ascensao</snm>, <fnm>J. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kay</snm>, <fnm>N. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Earenfight-Engler</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Koren</snm>, <fnm>H. S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zanjani</snm>, <fnm>E. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Blood</jtl> <vid>57</vid>, <ppf>170</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>173</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gillis</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Crabtree</snm>, <fnm>G. R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Smith</snm>, <fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Immun.</jtl> <vid>123</vid>, <ppf>1624</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1631</ppl> (<cd year="1979">1979</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wong</snm>, <fnm>G. G.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>228</vid>, <ppf>810</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>815</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gluzman</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>23</vid>, <ppf>175</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>182</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Southern</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. molec. Biol.</jtl> <vid>98</vid>, <ppf>503</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>517</ppl> (<cd year="1975">1975</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rimm</snm>, <fnm>D. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Horness</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kucera</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Blattner</snm>, <fnm>F. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Gene</jtl> <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>301</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>309</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Fung</snm>, <fnm>M. C.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>307</vid>, <ppf>233</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>237</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yokota</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>1070</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1074</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Skup</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>3069</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3084</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Messing</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Vieira</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Gene</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>269</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>276</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>I. S. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Quan</snm>, <fnm>S. G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Golde</snm>, <fnm>D. W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>7006</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>7009</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>O&apos;Rear</snm>, <fnm>J. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mizutani</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hoffman</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fiandt</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Temin</snm>, <fnm>H. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>423</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>430</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Becker</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gold</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>72</vid>, <ppf>581</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>585</ppl> (<cd year="1975">1975</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></headerx>