<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315773a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>773</spn><epn>776</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315773a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>The nucleotide sequences of <i>copia</i> and <i>copia</i>-related RNA in <i>Drosophila</i> virus-like particles</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Yasufumi</fnm><snm>Emori</snm><inits>Y.</inits><super>&ast;</super><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Tadayoshi</fnm><snm>Shiba</snm><inits>T.</inits><super>&ast;</super><super>&Dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Shigenori</fnm><snm>Kanaya</snm><inits>S.</inits><super>&sect;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Satoshi</fnm><snm>Inouye</snm><inits>S.</inits><super>&par;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Shunji</fnm><snm>Yuki</snm><inits>S.</inits><super>&par;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Kaoru</fnm><snm>Saigo</snm><inits>K.</inits><super>&par;</super></au>
<aff><super>&ast;</super>Laboratory of Cell Biology, Mitsubishi-Kasei Institute of Life Sciences, 11 Minamiooya, Machida-shi Tokyo 194, Japan</aff>
<aff><super>&sect;</super>Bioscience Laboratory, Mitsubishi Chemical Industries Ltd, 1000 Kamoshida-cho, Midori-ku, Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa 227, Japan</aff>
<aff><super>&par;</super>Department of Biochemistry, Kyushu University 60, School of Medicine, Fukuoka 812, Japan</aff>
<aff><super>&dagger;</super>Present address: Department of Molecular Biology, Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Medical Science, Honkomagome, Bunkyoku, Tokyo 113, Japan.</aff>
<aff><super>&Dagger;</super>To whom correspondence should be addressed.</aff>
</aug>
<hst>
<re year="na" month="3" day="5"/>
<acc year="1985" month="4" day="18"/></hst>
<fp><p>We have shown previously that <i>Drosophila</i> cells contain virus-like particles (VLPs) containing 5-kilobase (kb) RNA that hybridizes to a transposable element, termed <i>copia</i>. We have suggested that VLPs and <i>copia</i> are derivatives of viral particles and proviral forms, respectively, of &lsquo;<i>copia</i>&rsquo; retrovirus, a putative <i>Drosophila</i> retrovirus<super>1</super>. To further clarify the relationship between <i>copia</i> and <i>copia</i>-related RNA in VLPs (VLP H-RNA), we determined and compared their nucleotide sequences. VLP H-RNA was found to be an unspliced, genome-sized transcript of <i>copia</i>, and, like retroviral genome RNA, VLP H-RNA is terminally redundant with termini localized in the long terminal repeats (LTRs) of <i>copia</i>. VLP H-RNA contains two long open reading frames (ORFs), one of which includes the coding sequence for a predominant VLP protein of relative molecular mass (<i>M</i><sub>r</sub>) 31,000 (31K). Here we show that, in contrast to <i>17.6</i> ORF2 (ref. 2), ORFs of <i>copia</i> have no extensive amino-acid sequence homology to the RT region<super>2</super> of the reverse transcriptase of retrovirus in vertebrates. Because of a one-base insertion/deletion, the two ORFs in VLP H-RNA are fused and become a single, longer ORF in a genomic <i>copia</i>.</p></fp>
</fm>
<bdy>
Using cDm2055 DNA3 as a probe, we isolated 20 recombinant phage containing copia from a cloned library of Drosophila melanogaster DNA4 and made restriction maps (data not shown). As the restriction map of the copia in AcopSS was very similar to that of most of the copias that we cloned, the complete nucleotide sequence of the copia in AcopSS was determined as representative of copia sequences (Fig. 1, LI). The copia in AcopSS is 5,143 base pairs (bp) in length and terminates with 276-bp LTRs whose nucleotide sequences are identical or very similar to the published LTR sequences of other copias5. Partial nucleotide sequences of the region flanked by LTRs have been reported elsewhere6'7. The sequences in these studies are essentially identical to the counterparts described here (Fig. 1). Translation of the nucleotide sequence showed that copia contains a long ORF, ORFg (Fig. l, L2), residing on a DNA strand corresponding to the major cellular copia RNAs6.
Fig. 1 (Opposite) Nucleotide sequences of copia and cDNA of copia-related RNA in VLP ( VLP H-RNA). The complete nucleotide sequence of copia in AcopSS is shown as the putative sense strand in LI, whereas 13 and L3', respectively, show the composite cDNA nucleotide sequence of VLP H-RNA and the DNA sequence complementary to the 5' terminal sequence of VLP H-RNA determined by the dideoxy-chain termination method using VLP H-RNA as a template. The ranges of long ORFs found in both copia and VLP H-RNA are shown by L-shaped arrows labelled ORF, with amino-acid sequences shown below the corresponding nucleotide sequences (L2 and L4). Dashes, nucleotide or amino-acid sequences identical to those of copia in LI and L2. Os in L3 indicate one-nucleotide deletions in VLP H-RNA, whereas # denotes the termination codon of each ORF. Underlines, nucleotide sequences corresponding to the duplicated target DNA; a and ?, 5' start sites of cellular 2- and 5-kb RNA6; 6, expected polyadenylation signal; c, e, h, nucleotide sequence complementary to the 26-nucleotide long synthetic oligodeoxynucleotide for primer extension experiments; d, the amino-acid sequence best conserved among various polymerases10'11;/ polypurine sequence corresponding to the counterparts of other Drosophila transposons and vertebrate retroviruses (g)12. Overlines labelled w and y, respectively, show the 5' terminal region of VLP H-RNA in the 5' LTR and its equivalent in the 3' LTR. Two vertical arrows indicate 5' ends of two major VLP H-RNAs. Thin lines associated with the arrows show the degree of inaccuracy (1 nucleotide) for the determination of 5' ends. Overlines z and x exhibit the poly(A) attachment site of VLP H-RNA in the 3' LTR and its equivalent in the 5' LTR, respectively. The ranges of 5' LTR, 3' LTR and expected coding region of the predominant Mr 31,000 VLP protein (3IK) are shown by L-shaped arrows. The end of the 31K region was tentatively determined based on the relative molecular mass and amino-acid composition of the 31K VLP protein. The base substitutions and deletion found in the nucleotide sequences of copia regions 1-1,143 and 2,302-2,931 (described in refs 6,7) are shown by small letters and o, respectively, above the copia sequence (LI). Methods. The nucleotide sequence of copia was determined by digesting DNA extracted from AcopSS by various restriction enzymes and recloning the resultant DNA segments containing copia pieces using plasmid pUC9 (rf. 13) as a cloning vector. Sizes and locations of the cloned DNA segments are shown by thick lines with arrows and numbers in scheme A. After Escherichia coli cells (JM83 (rf. 13) harbouring a desired plasmid) were cultured in 5-10 ml L-broth for 12-15 h at 37 C with shaking, plasmid DNA was prepared by the alkali method14. Contaminated RNA was removed by a treatment of 10gmG1 of RNase for 30 min at 37 C and final concentration of 7.5% polyethylene glycol in 0.94 M NaCl for l h at 0 C. Nucleotide sequence was determined by the chain termination method15 modified by M. Hattori (unpublished) using the DNA cloned in pUC9. Two different kinds of synthetic oligonucleotides [Ml3 single-stranded primer (5'GTAAAACGACGGCCAGT3') and M13 reverse sequence primer (5'CAG-GAAACAGCTATGAC3') (P-L Bjochemicals)] were used as primers for sequencing. The overall strategy for sequencing is depicted by thin underlines in the lower margin illustration (A). Scale bar; 1,000 bp; the two boxes show the LTRs. Restriction enzyme cutting sites used are as follows: a, Accl; b, /tornHI; c, C/al; e, EcoRI; h, Hindlll; 1, Ball; p, Hpal; s, Psfl; t, Aatl; v, Pvull; x, Xbal. The nucleotide sequence of VLP H-RNA was determined as follows. As described previously1, VLP was purified from a 5 1 culture of GM2 cells and total VLP RNA extracted. After the VLP H-RNA was purified by gel electrophoresis, cDNA was constructed and cloned into pBR322 using the procedures described by Maniatis et al.16. Restriction mapping and blot hybridization allowed overlapping of the cDNA inserts obtained and a composite restriction map of the cDNA of VLP H-RNA to be made. The restriction map obtained was found to be very similar to that of copia. Thus, in scheme B, their relative positions are depicted using the restriction map of the copia in AcopSS as a reference. Plasmid DNA was purified essentially as described elsewhere2. The complete or partial nucleotide sequences of A-25, G-19, G-29, G-34, G-46, J-15, J-16, J-19, H-15 and 3-5 were determined by the procedures of Maxam and Gilbert17. We found no discrepancy in the nucleotide sequence in the overlapped region. The position of poly(A) attachment site in G-29 was identical to that in 3-5. Thus, in L3, the composite sequence is shown as the nucleotide sequence of the cDNA of VLP H-RNA. We consider the sequence shown in L3 to be identical to that of VLP H-RNA, apart from the DNA-RNA difference, because (1) at its 3' end, it contains a long poly(A) tract, a typical terminal structure of eukaryotic mRNA and retroviral genome RNA; and (2) a separate experiment (not shown) indicated that only the DNA strand of copia, complementary to the one whose sequence is shown in LI, is hybridizable to VLP H-RNA. The nucleotide sequence near the 5' terminus of VLP H-RNA was determined by the chain termination method15. After 3 g VLP RNA and 65 ng of 32P-labelled oligodeoxynucleotide (see Fig. 4a) in 40 ? 0.1 M NaCl, l mM EDTA and 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.3) was preincubated at 85 C for 5 min, then at 60 C for 10 min. 10 ? 500 mM Tris-HCl (/>H 8.3) containing 50 mM dithiothreitol and 80 mM MgCl2, l ? RNasin, l ? reverse transcriptase and 8 ? 25 ? dCTP were added. To each of four 14-? aliquots, 8 ? of the dNTP-ddNTP mixture of M13 sequencing kits (Takara Shuzo Ltd, Japan) was added. The resultant mixture was then incubated at 40 C for 20 min. After four dNTPs (1 mM each) in 4 ? was added, the incubation was continued for further 20 min. The reaction products were precipitated by adding 2.5 ? 3 M sodium acetate (pH 5.2) and 2 vol ethyl alcohol, and subjected to gel electrophoresis for sequencing.
Fig. 2 Genome organization of copia and its gene products shown schematically. The 5' LTR has been enlarged to make the internal structure of LTR more easily discernible. The ambiguity in the 5' end of U3 results from the three consecutive A residues at the poly(A) attachment site, whereas that of R results from the real heterogeneity in the 5' end of VLP H-RNA. Two downward arrows labelled I show the positions of the 5' ends of the two major VLP H-RNA. The locations of the putative polyadenylation signal of copia, AAATAATAAATC, are shown by the arrows labelled A. Note that one of the polyadenylation signals is near the region corresponding to the 3' end of 2-kb copia RNA. The structure of genomic copia is based on the sequence of VLP H-RNA, although a copia in AcopSS contains a single ORF covering the entire regions of both ORFs 1 and 2 (see Fig. 1). A polypurine tract similar to those of other Drosophila transposons and vertebrate retroviruses12 can be seen in the 3'-untranslated region. The expected coding sequence of the predominant 3IK VLP protein is shown by a shaded box and appears to be included in both 2- and 5-kb copia RNA (VLP H-RNA). The location of the most conservative amino-acid sequence among RNA dependent polymerases, Y(M, L, V or G)DD(hydrophobic amino acid)3, is shown by the arrow at YXDD. Association of 31K VLP protein and VLP H-RNA is considered to result in the production of VLP.
We purified VLP H-RNA by gel electrophoresis and made complementary DNA clones. We found no clones that completely covered the entire region of the VLP H-RNA; the information from the 5' end of th RNA could not be recovered because St nuclease was used. Nevertheless, the overlapping of several cDNA clones (Fig. 1) allowed us to determine 97% of the total sequence of VLP H-RNA from its 3' end (Fig. l, L3). The nucleotide sequence of the major portion of the residual 3% was determined by the chain termination method using VLP H-RNA as a template (Fig. l, L3'). These results show that the nucleotide sequence of VLP H-RNA corresponds to the copia sequence shown in Fig. 1 (LI) except for some minor base changes and a terminal poly(A) tract. Because of a deletion of an A residue located somewhere between residues 4,220 and 4,224, the ORF of copia (ORFg) is split in two, slightly overlapping ORFs 1 and 2 in VLP H-RNA (Fig. 1). The 3' end of VLP H-RNA that lacks poly (A) is located in the 3' LTR of copia. However, we found no AATAAA, a typical signal for polyadenylation, in this LTR. The sequence AAATATAAATC is present 20 nucleotides upstream from the poly(A) attachment site of the 5-kb RNA and in the region expected for the 3' terminus of the 2-kb RNA (rf. 6; Figs 1, 2). This sequence, or part of it, may function as a polyadenylation signal in copia.
To determine the location of the 5' end of VLP H-RNA, we carried out a primer extension experiment using total VLP RNA and 32P-labelled, 26 nucleotide long synthetic oligodeoxynucleotide (see Fig. 4a). Two intensive bands, 166 and 172 nucleotides in length, along with -20 less intensive bands of similar size, were observed (Fig. 3), suggesting that VLP H-RNA is heterogeneous in the location of its 5' end. By comparing the positions of these bands (Fig. 30, lane 5) with the dideoxy-chain termination pattern of the 5' terminal region of copia (lanes 1-4), we determined the range of the 5' ends of VLP H-RNA (Fig. 1, overline w). According to Flavell et al6, the 5' ends of cellular copia RNA are similarly heterogeneous in sequence and localized in an almost identical region in the 5' LTR of copia (see Fig. 1). Taking together their findings and the results described above, we conclude that VLP H-RNA is an unspliced genome-sized transcript of copia (see Fig. 2). As with vertebrate retrovirus, VLP H-RNA has terminal redundancy, 77-116 nucleotides in length, and the copia LTR can be divided into three regions, 106-142 bp (U5), 77-116 bp (R) and 54-57 bp (U3) (Fig. 2). These findings provide additional evidence for the notion that copia RNA may be reverse-transcribable1'8.
Fig. 3 Determination of the 5' end of VLP H-RNA by primer extension. The expected locations of the 5' ends of two major VLP H-RNAs are shown by arrows labelled I, whereas the arrow labelled P shows that of the 26-nucleotide-long primer used, a, pBR322 DNA was digested with Hpall, labelled with 32P by kinase treatment, denatured and used as a marker. Molecular sizes in the left margin are in bp. Using total VLP RNA (3 ) and 26-nucleotide-long synthetic DNA (65 ng) (see Fig. 4a) as a template and primer, a primer extension experiment was carried out essentially according to Treisman et a/.18. After the reaction, samples were denatured, applied to 45-cm-long 8% polyacrylamide gel in the presence of 7 M urea, and electrophoresed. Lane 1, pBR322 marker; lane 2, products of primer extension of VLP RNA with primer, ², Numbers in lanes 1-4 show the nucleotide sequence pattern obtained by the modified dideoxy-chain termination method when the DNA of plasmid 15 (see scheme a in Fig. 1) and the 26-nucleotide-long synthetic DNA identical to that used for primer extention of VLP RNA (Fig. 4a) were used as a template and primer. Lanes 1, 2, 3 and 4, respectively, show the locations of G, A, T and C residues. The sample in lane 5 is an aliquot of the reaction products shown in lane 2 in a.
VLP H-RNA has weak messenger RNA activity and can be translated into polypeptides immunologically related to VLP proteins1. To identify the coding region for the predominant 31K VLP protein1, the partial amino-acid sequence of one of the polypeptides obtained from the 3IK protein was determined and found to be identical to that of the amino-terminal region of the polypeptide expected to be derived from ORFg of copia (or ORF1 of VLP H-RNA) (Fig. 40). Furthermore, the calculated amino-acid composition of the Mr 31,000 amino-terminal portion of the putative copia ORFg (ORF1) polypeptide was found to be almost identical to that observed for the 3IK VLP protein (data not shown). Thus, we suggest that the coding region for the 31K VLP protein is located in the 5' terminal region of the ORFg (ORF1) (Figs 1, 20) and the 31K VLP protein is one of the cleavage products of the putative polypep-tide(s) expected to be produced from ORFg (or ORF1).
Fig. 4 a, Nucleotide sequence of a 26-nucleotide-long synthetic oligonucleotide used as the primer. It is complementary to a portion of copia sequence (see underline d in Fig. 1, LI) and was synthesized using a Model 380A synthesizer (Applied Biosystems). ², Comparison of the partial amino-acid sequence of the predominant 31K protein of VLP and that of the amino-terminal region of the putative ORFg (or ORF1) protein of copia. X, an unidentified amino acid.
Methods. VLP was purified from a 12-1 culture as described previously1 and the predominant 31K protein purified by large-scale SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. The 31K VLP protein was treated with cyanogen bromide19 and the resultant polypeptides separated and purified by reverse-phase liquid chromatography (RP300 (4.6x250 mm), Brown Lee). The partial amino-acid sequence of the major polypeptide was determined by stepwise Edman degradation using a gas-phase automated sequencer (Model 470 A, Applied Biosystems). The recovery of other polypeptides was low because of self-aggregation.
To determine whether copia has the coding sequence for the reverse-transcriptase-like enzyme associated with VLP1, we compared the amino-acid sequences of ORFs 1 and 2 with those of the reverse transcriptases of retroviruses9 and equivalent polypeptides of Drosophila transposons such as 17.6 (rf. 2). However, no appreciable homology could be seen except for Tyr-(Met, Leu, Val or Gly)-Asp-Asp(hydrophobic amino acid)3, the most conservative sequence among various polymerases10'11, near the carboxy-terminus of the ORFg (ORF1) polypeptide(s) (Figs 1, 2). This suggests that copia contains the coding region for the reverse-transcriptase-like enzyme, which has a different amino-acid sequence from the counterparts of other co/?ia-like elements2 and retroviruses9. Furthermore, this reduced homology partly results from the extensive rearrangement within the putative pol region of copia (the region between nucleotides 1,242 and 4,658 in Fig. 1; K.S. et a/., unpublished).
We thank Drs T. Miyake, T. Uchida, T. Miyata and T. Yamazaki for critical comments. M. Hattori for informing us of his new protocol of nucleotide sequencing and K. Hattori, Y. Suzuki and M. Kobayashi for assistance. This work was partly supported by grants from the Ministry of Education, Science and Culture, Japan to K.S.</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Shiba</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Saigo</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>302</vid>, <ppf>119</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>124</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Saigo</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>312</vid>, <ppf>659</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>661</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Saigo</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Millstein</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Thomas</snm>, <fnm>C. A.</fnm> <suff>Jr</suff></refau> <jtl>Cold Spring Harb. Symp. quant. Biol.</jtl> <vid>45</vid>, <ppf>815</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>827</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Maniatis</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>687</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>701</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rubin</snm>, <fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Cold Spring Harb Symp. quant. Biol.</jtl> <vid>45</vid>, <ppf>619</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>628</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Flavell</snm>, <fnm>A. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Levis</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Simon</snm>, <fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rubin</snm>, <fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>6267</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>6291</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Fouts</snm>, <fnm>D. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Manning</snm>, <fnm>J. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fox</snm>, <fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schmid</snm>, <fnm>C. W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nucleic Acid Res.</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>7053</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>7064</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Flavell</snm>, <fnm>A. J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>310</vid>, <ppf>514</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>516</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Toh</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hayashida</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Miyata</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>305</vid>, <ppf>827</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>829</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Toh</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> (in the press).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kamer</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Argos</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>7269</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>7282</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kugimiya</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ikenaga</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Saigo</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>3193</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3197</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Vieira</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Messing</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Gene</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>259</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>268</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Birnboim</snm>, <fnm>H. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Doly</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>1513</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1523</ppl> (<cd year="1979">1979</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sanger</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nickelen</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Coulson</snm>, <fnm>A. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>74</vid>, <ppf>5463</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>5467</ppl> (<cd year="1977">1977</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Maniatis</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fritsch</snm>, <fnm>E. F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sambrook</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <btl>Molecular Cloning. A Laboratory Manual</btl> (Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, New York, <cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Maxam</snm>, <fnm>A. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gilbert</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Meth. Enzym.</jtl> <vid>65</vid>, <ppf>499</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>560</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Treisman</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Proudfoot</snm>, <fnm>N. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shander</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Maniatis</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>29</vid>, <ppf>903</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>911</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Koike</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ikenaka</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Eur. J. Biochem.</jtl> <vid>32</vid>, <ppf>401</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>407</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl>
</bm></headerx>