<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315781a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="bo"/>
<pp><spn>781</spn><epn>781</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315781a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Doing the rounds of the Solar System</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Carl D.</fnm><snm>Murray</snm><inits>C. D.</inits></au>
<aff>Lecturer in the Theoretical Astronomy Unit at Queen Mary College, University of London.</aff></aug>
<bookrev><bookttl>Rings: Discoveries from Galileo to Voyager</bookttl>. By <pubau><fnm>James</fnm><snm>Elliot</snm></pubau> and <pubau><fnm>Richard</fnm><snm>Kerr</snm></pubau>. <i>MIT Press: 1985. Pp.209. 17.50, 19.50</i>.</bookrev>
</fm>
<bdy>
OBSERVATIONS of the occultation of star SOA 158687 by the planet Uranus on 10 March, 1977, were intended to provide information on the shape and atmosphere of Uranus. An unexpected bonus for Jim Elliot and his team in the Kuiper Airborne Observatory was the first discovery of a ring system since the time of Galileo. After more occultations, the spectacular successes of the Pioneer and Voyager spacecraft and the increased use of charge coupled devices (CCDs), astronomers now have the luxury of studying planetary rings on a comparative basis.
Even to document the recent discoveries and theories is a difficult task after such an influx of ground-based and spacecraft results. But the authors of this book do not merely present the observations together with the latest well-polished theories, they also treat the reader to a revealing and honest portrayal of scientific discovery, complete with rejected grant applications, rivalry and occasional good luck.
In particular, the account of the spacecraft flybys captures the unique atmosphere of "instant science", when making discoveries "is just a matter of who's around". Explaining them can take a little longer. Theorists have had to turn their attention to such phenomena as narrow rings, eccentric rings, multiple rings and "spokes". The book relates how, during the Voyager 1 encounter with Saturn, some of the best theorists were unable to explain the "braided" appearance of Saturn's F-ring. Although there were doubts that gravitational forces alone could account for such a feature, one of the faithful remarked, "Don't worry about Newton's equations, most people don't realize how many solutions they have". Current theories of the F-ring have shown that his faith in gravity was not misplaced.
Accounting for some features can lead to more fundamental problems. Studies of satellite-ring interactions and the identification of spiral density waves have provided an explanation for most of the structure in Saturn's ?-ring. However, the same studies reveal the possibility that unless some locking mechanism can be found we may have to come to terms with the fact that the rings are relatively shortlived phenomena.
The combination of first-hand experience and good journalism has resulted in an immensely readable account of how ring studies have evolved over the past three centuries. Glimpses of the personalities involved and clear explanations of the various physical processes and ring theories help to convey the excitement of science. This golden age of discovery is not over. In January 1986 we can expect images of the Uranian rings from Voyager 2. Before the end of the decade we will have further information on the peculiar rings or arcs of material around Neptune and a look at Jupiter's ring from the Galileo spacecraft. There will be more discoveries, more puzzled astronomers, more theories and, we must hope, an equally fascinating sequel to this splendid book.</bdy>
</headerx>
