<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315777a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>777</spn><epn>778</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315777a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Phosphorylation of the glucose transporter <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i> by protein kinase C</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Lee A.</fnm><snm>Witters</snm><inits>L. A.</inits><super>&ast;</super><super>&Dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Carol A.</fnm><snm>Vater</snm><inits>C. A.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Gustav E.</fnm><snm>Lienhard</snm><inits>G. E.</inits><super>&dagger;</super></au>
<aff><super>&ast;</super>Medical Services and Diabetes Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital and Department of Medicine, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts 02114, USA</aff>
<aff><super>&dagger;</super>Department of Biochemistry, Dartmouth Medical School, Hanover, New Hampshire 03756, USA</aff>
<aff><super>&Dagger;</super>Present address: Endocrine-Metabolism Division, Department of Medicine, Dartmouth Medical School, Hanover, New Hampshire 03756, USA.</aff></aug>
<hst>
<re year="na" month="2" day="27"/>
<acc year="1985" month="4" day="15"/></hst>
<fp><p>The Ca<super>2&plus;</super>- and phospholipid-dependent protein kinase (protein kinase C) is present in many mammalian tissues<super>1</super>, and its important physiological protein substrates are only now beginning to be identified. A useful advance in identifying these i ntracellular substrates has been the recognition that the kinase is the receptor for phorbol esters, which stimulate phosphotransferase activity<super>2&ndash;4</super>. Phorbol ester-induced changes in protein phosphorylation in intact cells may thus be taken, in part, as a probable indication of protein kinase C activation. The many cellular effects of phorbol esters include the stimulation of glucose uptake<super>5&ndash;8</super>, although the response of glucose uptake to phorbol esters appears to be complex, apparently varying in response time and requirement for protein synthesis<super>6,7</super>. Such observations prompted us to explore one possible explanation for the alteration of glucose uptake, namely, phosphorylation of the glucose transporter by protein kinase C. We report here that incubation of purified human erythrocyte glucose transporter with rat brain protein kinase C results in the phosphorylation of a protein of relative molecular mass (<i>M</i><sub>r</sub>) 50,000&ndash;60,000 which has subsequently been identified as the glucose transporter by specific immunoprecipitation with a monoclonal antibody. Immunoprecipitation of membrane proteins from <super>32</super>P-labelled human erythrocytes revealed a phorbol ester-stimulated phosphorylation of the transporter. This covalent modification of the glucose transporter may thus, in part, underlie the ability of phorbol esters and certain hormones to stimulate glucose uptake.</p></fp>
</fm>
<bdy>
Incubation of a preparation of purified human erythrocyte glucose transporter with protein kinase C resulted in the phosphorylation of a protein that migrated on SDS-gel electro-phoresis as a broad band of apparent Mr 50,000-60,000 (50-60K), together with higher-Mr species, some of which did not enter the SDS gel (Fig. la). The phosphorylation was absolutely dependent on the addition of Ca2+; because the transporter preparation contained erythrocyte membrane phospholipids, added phosphatidylserine caused only a slight increase in phosphorylation. It has been shown previously that the transporter is a glycoprotein that migrates as a broad band of apparent Mr 50-60K on SDS gels, due to heterogeneity in its oligosac-charides9'10. In addition, on incubation with detergents, the protein has a tendency to form dimers and higher-Mr aggregates which is not prevented by reducing agents10'11. No phosphorylation of these bands was observed on incubation with casein kinase I, casein kinase II or the catalytic subunit of the cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase (not shown). Because the preparation of glucose transporter used in these experiments was only 70-80% pure11, the identity of the 32P-labelled protein as the transporter was established unequivocally by specific immunoprecipitation with a monoclonal antibody directed against the erythrocyte transporter (antibody G3)12 (Fig. 16). The bands at Mr -100,000 and at the top of the gel seen in Fig. l b (and in Fig. 3b) are due to the dimer and the higher-Mr aggregates of the transporter10'11.
Nearly 0.5 mol of 32P-phosphate per mol cytochalasin B binding was incorporated into the transporter on prolonged incubation with protein kinase C (Fig. 2a). Although the purified transporter is contained in largely unsealed membranes of erythrocyte lipids11'13, it is possible that not all of the potential phosphorylation sites are exposed to the kinase or that the preparation already contains phosphorylated amino acids. Limited acid hydrolysis of 32P-labelled transporter and subsequent thin-layer electrophoresis revealed only 32P-phospho-serine (not shown). HPLC separation of 32P-phosphopeptides, generated by prolonged tryptic digestion, yielded only one 32P-peptide (Fig. 20) which also contained only 32P-phosphoserine. These data support the conclusion that the phosphorylation is confined to a single protein in the transporter preparation and probably to a limited number of phosphorylation sites.
Fig. 1 In vitro phosphorylation of glucose transporter by protein kinas« C (a) and 32P-protein identification by immunoprecipitation (b). In a, human erythrocyte glucose transporter (55  mll ; lanes 1-4) or buffer (lanes 5-8) was incubated for 30 min with [ y-32P]ATP (100 ?), MgCl2 (10 mM) and protein kinase C (4,000 pmol units ml"1) in the presence of EGTA (1 mM; lanes 1,5), EGTA plus phosphatidylserine (PS) (40??G1; lanes 2,6), CaCl2 ( 1 mM ; lanes 3,7), and CaCl2 plus PS (lanes 4, 8). No phosphorylation of any protein was observed in the absence of added kinase. In 6, aliquots of the incubations of the transporter with added kinase were immunoprecipitated with monoclonal antibody to the transporter (lanes 1,2) or with control monoclonal antibody (lanes 3,4), and the immunoprecipitates separated by SDS-gel electro-phoresis before autoradiography. Lanes 1, 3, kinase reaction with CaCl2 and PS; lanes 2, 4, kinase reaction with CaCl2 alone. Afr markers are indicated on the left of a and b.
Methods. The glucose transporter from human erythrocytes was purified by the method of Baldwin et al.11. Protein kinase C was partially purified from rat brain through the gel filtration step by the method of Kikkawa et al.1 ; the kinase used in these experiments had a specific activity of 200 nmol per min per mg protein against histone III-S. Kinase assays were performed by the method of Parker et al.4. Immunoprecipitation was carried out by solubiliz-ation of the transporter (1 g) in 1.5% octyl glucoside, followed by incubation of the samples on ice with 1.5% octyl glucoside/protein A-Sepharose to which 10 g of the specific or control monoclonal IgG was complexed. The immune complexes were washed and then solubilized with 1.0% SDS in the absence of reducing agents and without heating. SDS gels were run according to Laemmli24.
To determine whether protein kinase C phosphorylates the glucose transporter in vivo, human erythrocytes were labelled with 32Pi and exposed for 20 min to phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA), 4a-phorbol didecanoate (inactive phorbol; 4aPDD) or dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO), the solvent used. We found that PMA, but not 4a PDD, stimulated the phosphorylation of two easily identifiable proteins in 32P-labelled membranes (Fig. 3a). These seem to correspond to band 4.1 (Mr80K), as reported previously in rabbit erythrocytes14, and a minor 32P-phosphoprotein of Mr 125K. 32P-labelled membrane protein was solubilized and immunoprecipitated with the monoclonal antibody. Specific immunoprecipitation of 32P-labelled transporter indicated that the transporter was phosphorylated in intact cells in the basal state and that the phosphorylation increased substantially in response to PMA (Fig. 36).
These data suggest that phorbol ester-stimulated glucose uptake may be, in part, a consequence of protein kinase C-mediated phosphorylation of the glucose transporter. We are now investigating whether the phosphorylation of the erythrocyte transporter in vivo in response to PMA alters, its activity and whether the stimulation of glucose uptake by PMA in other cell types is correlated with phosphorylation of the transporter in vivo. In addition to the possibility that such phosphorylation may directly affect the kinetic parameters of the transporter, in some cell types it may also lead to the redistribution of the transporter between the plasma membrane and intracellular membranes, such that a larger fraction of the transporter lies within the plasma membrane15.
Fig. 2 Time course and stoichiometry of glucose transporter phos-phorylation (a) and HPLC separation of tryptic 32P-phosphopep-tides (b). In a, the glucose transporter preparation was phosphory-lated with protein kinase C in the presence (·) and absence (O) of added CaCl2 and in the absence of added kinase ( x), as in Fig. 1, and 32P incorporation quantitated by trichloroacetic acid (TCA) precipitation in the presence of carrier bovine serum albumin. Control values for kinase autophosphorylation have been subtracted from total 32P incorporation. Results are expressed as mol 32P incorporated per mol cytochalasin B binding (taken as 1 binding site per mol functional transporter). Cytochalasin B is a high-affinity ligand for the transporter. Its binding provides a measure of the amount of functional transporter in a preparation, which is typically -60% of the protein weight11. In fe, phosphory-lated transporter was precipitated with TCA, washed and digested with 20% trypsin (w/w) at 37 C for 18 h. The solubilized 32P-peptides were separated by HPLC with C18 reverse-phase chromatography using an ascending gradient of acetonitrile in H2O/0.1% trifluoroacetic acid. When the same procedure was applied to a control reaction mixture containing only protein kinase C, no significant peak of 32P-peptide was found.
Evidence has been accumulating that epidermal growth factor and platelet-derived growth factor may lead to the activation of protein kinase C in intact cells16'20; this is often accompanied by an increase in phosphatidylinositol turnover, with the generation of diacylglycerol, an activator of the kinase21. Epidermal growth factor has also been shown to increase glucose uptake22, while phorbol esters mimic the insulin-stimulated phosphorylation of the insulin receptor /3-subunit on serine residues in IM-9 lymphocytes, suggesting that the kinase may be activated by insulin23. The present study suggests that the diverse effects of several hormones and phorbol esters on glucose transport may in part be linked through a common mechanism, phos^ phorylation of the glucose transporter by protein kinase C.
Fig. 3 Phorbol ester-stimulated protein phosphorylation of human erythrocyte membrane proteins (a) and glucose transporter, as determined by immunoprecipitation (²). In a, human erythro-cytes were labelled with 32Pi5 and membranes prepared by the method of Patel and Fairbanks25. Labelled cells were exposed for 20 min to phorbol 4a-didecanoate (1 ?, lane 1), DMSO (0.1%, lane 2) and phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (lane 3), before cell lysis. Membrane protein (20 g) from each sample was separated on SDS gels before autoradiography. In ², membrane protein from the same samples was solubilized with 2% octyl glucoside, cen-trifuged to remove insoluble cytoskeletal aggregates and the soluble 32P-proteins were immunoprecipitated with anti-transporter monoclonal antibody (lanes 1-3) or control monoclonal antibody (lanes 4-6). Lanes 1, 4, 4aPDD; lanes 2, 5, DMSO; lanes 3, 6, PMA. Preliminary experiments had established the presence of protein kinase C in human erythrocytes ; although not detectable as a Ca2+-and PS-stimulated kinase in red blood cell lysates, it was readily recognized following DEAE-cellulose separation of lysate proteins (not shown).
We thank Jeffrey Allard for the monoclonal antibodies ; Esther Freiberg, Julie Colliton and Matthew Fitzgibbon for technical assitance; and Drs Joseph Avruch and Grant Fairbanks for helpful advice. The manuscript was ably prepared by Martha Chambers. This work was supported in part by NIH grants AM19270 and AM25336.</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kikkawa</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>257</vid>, <ppf>13341</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>13348</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Castagna</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>257</vid>, <ppf>7847</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>7851</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Neidel</snm>, <fnm>J. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kuhn</snm>, <fnm>L. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Vandenbark</snm>, <fnm>G. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>36</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>40</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Parker</snm>, <fnm>P. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Stabel</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Waterfield</snm>, <fnm>M. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>953</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>959</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Driedger</snm>, <fnm>P. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Blumberg</snm>, <fnm>P. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl> <vid>37</vid>, <ppf>3257</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3265</ppl> (<cd year="1977">1977</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>L.-S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Weinstein</snm>, <fnm>I. B.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. cell. Physiol.</jtl> <vid>99</vid>, <ppf>451</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>460</ppl> (<cd year="1979">1979</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>O&apos;Brien</snm>, <fnm>T. G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. cell. Physiol.</jtl> <vid>110</vid>, <ppf>63</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>71</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Klip</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rothstein</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mack</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochem. biophys. Res. Commun.</jtl> <vid>124</vid>, <ppf>14</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>22</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gorga</snm>, <fnm>F. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Baldwin</snm>, <fnm>S. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lienhard</snm>, <fnm>G. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochem. biophys. Res. Commun.</jtl> <vid>91</vid>, <ppf>955</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>961</ppl> (<cd year="1979">1979</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lienhard</snm>, <fnm>G. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Crabb</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ransome</snm>, <fnm>K. J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochim. biophys. Acta</jtl> <vid>769</vid>, <ppf>404</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>410</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Baldwin</snm>, <fnm>S. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Baldwin</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lienhard</snm>, <fnm>G. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochemistry</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>3869</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3874</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Allard</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lienhard</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> (in the press).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gorga</snm>, <fnm>F. R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lienhard</snm>, <fnm>G. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochemistry</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>1905</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1908</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ling</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sapirstein</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochem. biophys. Res. Commun.</jtl> <vid>120</vid>, <ppf>291</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>298</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lienhard</snm>, <fnm>G. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Trends biochem. Sci.</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>125</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>127</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cochet</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>259</vid>, <ppf>2553</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2558</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Iwashita</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fox</snm>, <fnm>C. F.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>259</vid>, <ppf>2559</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2567</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sawyer</snm>, <fnm>S. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cohen</snm>, <fnm>S. T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochemistry</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>6280</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>6286</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Friedman</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>3034</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3038</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Habenicht</snm>, <fnm>A. J. R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>256</vid>, <ppf>12329</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>12335</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kishimoto</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>255</vid>, <ppf>2273</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2276</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Barnes</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Colowick</snm>, <fnm>S. P.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. cell. Physiol.</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>633</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>640</ppl> (<cd year="1976">1976</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jacobs</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>6211</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>6213</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Laemmli</snm>, <fnm>U. K.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>227</vid>, <ppf>680</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>685</ppl> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Patel</snm>, <fnm>V. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fairbanks</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>88</vid>, <ppf>430</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>444</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl>
</bm></headerx>