<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
    <ArticleIdList>
        <ArticleId>240115d0</ArticleId>
    </ArticleIdList>
    <pubfm>
        <jtl>Nature</jtl>
        <vol>240</vol>
        <iss>5376</iss>
        <idt>19721110</idt>
        <categ id="er"/>
        <pp>
            <spn>115</spn>
            <epn>115</epn>
        </pp>
        <issn>0028-0836</issn>
        <cpg>
            <cpy>1972</cpy>
            <cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn>
        </cpg>
        <doi>10.1038/240115d0</doi>
    </pubfm>
    <fm>
        <atl>Erratum</atl>
    </fm>
    <bdy> THE following corrections should be made to the article "How Bees Navigate" by Allan W.
        Snyder and Colin Pask (Nature, 239, 48; 1972): the footnote reference numbers at the end of
        paragraph 1 should be replaced by reference 6; footnote reference 7 should be inserted at
        the end of paragraph 4 and at the end of the legend to Fig. 3; footnote reference 7 in the
        legend to Fig. 5 should be replaced by reference 9; the first full paragraph on page 50
        should read: "It is relevant that bees respond most strongly to blue-ultraviolet
        electromagnetic waves1'15'16, which are not only the most important frequencies in polarized
        sky light10, but are also those which produce the most pronounced electromagnetic mode
        rejection effect. The structure of the drone bee eye13 is different from that of the worker.
        Furthermore, the drone also has a low resistance between retinular cells14 (unlike the
        worker). These differences may reduce the mode detection. Because the drone rarely leaves
        the hive, there is no reason for it to have evolved special navigational aids."; footnote
        reference 16 at the end of the penultimate paragraph should be replaced by 17; reference 6
        should read Snyder, A. W., and Pask, C, /. Comp. Physiol, 78, 346 (1972); reference 7 should
        read Snyder, A. W., and Pask, C., /. Opt. Soc. Amer., 12, 1389 (1972); reference 16 should
        be changed to reference 17, and a new reference 16 inserted as follows: Griba-kin, F. G.,
        Vision Res., 12, 1225 (1972).</bdy>
</headerx>
