<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315761a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>761</spn><epn>764</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315761a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Cloning, sequencing and expression of cDNA for a novel subunit of acetylcholine receptor from calf muscle</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Toshiyuki</fnm><snm>Takai</snm><inits>T.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Masaharu</fnm><snm>Noda</snm><inits>M.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Masayoshi</fnm><snm>Mishina</snm><inits>M.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Shin</fnm><snm>Shimizu</snm><inits>S.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Yasuji</fnm><snm>Furutani</snm><inits>Y.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Toshiaki</fnm><snm>Kayano</snm><inits>T.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Takayuki</fnm><snm>Ikeda</snm><inits>T.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Tai</fnm><snm>Kubo</snm><inits>T.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Hideo</fnm><snm>Takahashi</snm><inits>H.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Tomoyuki</fnm><snm>Takahashi</snm><inits>T.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Motoy</fnm><snm>Kuno</snm><inits>M.</inits><super>&ast;</super></au>
<au><fnm>Shosaku</fnm><snm>Numa</snm><inits>S.</inits></au>
<aff>Department of Medical Chemistry and <super>&ast;</super>Physiology, Kyoto University Faculty of Medicine, Kyoto 606, Japan</aff></aug>
<hst>
<re year="na" month="2" day="7"/>
<acc year="1985" month="4" day="24"/></hst>
<fp><p>The nicotinic acetylcholine receptor (AChR) from fish electric organ has a subunit structure of <i>&alpha;</i><sub>2</sub><i>&beta;&gamma;&delta;</i>, and this is thought to be also the case for the mammalian skeletal muscle AChR<super>1&ndash;3</super>. By cloning and sequencing the complementary or genomic DNAs, we have previously elucidated the primary structures of all four sub-units of the <i>Torpedo californica</i> electroplax<super>4&ndash;6</super> and calf muscle AChR<super>7&ndash;10</super> and of the <i>&alpha;</i>- and <i>&gamma;</i>-subunits of the human muscle AChR<super>7,11</super>; the primary structures of the <i>&gamma;</i>-subunit of the <i>T. californien</i> AChR<super>12</super> and the <i>&alpha;</i>-subunit of the <i>Torpedo marmorata</i> AChR<super>13,14</super> have also been deduced elsewhere. We have now cloned DNA complementary to the calf muscle messenger RNA encoding a novel polypeptide (the <i>&epsi;</i>-subunit) whose deduced amino-acid sequence has features characteristic of the AChR subunits and which shows higher sequence homology with the <i>&gamma;</i>-subunit than with the other subunits. cDNA expression studies indicate that the calf <i>&epsi;</i>-subunit, as well as the calf <i>&gamma;</i>-subunit, can replace the <i>Torpedo &gamma;</i>-subunit to form the functional receptor in combination with the <i>Torpedo &alpha;</i>-, <i>&beta;</i>- and <i>&delta;</i>-subunits.</p></fp></fm>
<bdy>The initial cDNA clone for the calf e-subunit was isolated by cross-hybridization with a calf y-subunit cDNA probe in an experiment aimed at cloning an upstream cDNA sequence for the calf y-subunit by primer extension (see Fig. 1 legend). Figure 1 shows the nucleotide sequence of the mRNA encoding the calf e-subunit precursor, deduced from the cDNA sequence, together with the predicted primary structure of the polypeptide.
We deduce that the e-subunit precursor consists of 491 amino acids including a hydrophobia prepeptide15 of 20 amino acids, and calculate the relative molecular masses of the e-subunit and its precursor to be 52,568 and 54,562, respectively.
Figure 2 shows the alignment of the amino-acid sequences of the calf e-subunit precursor and the calf, human and T. califor-nica y-subunit precursors. The mature calf e-subunit shows 53, 53 and 57% sequence homology with the mature calf, human and Torpedo y-subunits, respectively, whereas the degrees of its homology with other mature AChR subunits are as follows: calf, human and Torpedo a-subunit, 30% (refs 4, 7), calf -subunit, 37% (rf. 8), Torpedo /3-subunit, 39% (rf. 5), calf d-subunit, 45% (rf. 10) and Torpedo d-subunit, 44% (rf. 5). Homology among the mature y-subunits is 92%, 56% and 55%, respectively, for the calf/man, calf/Torpedo and man/Torpedo pairs. Because the calf e-subunit shows similar degrees of homology with the calf, human and Torpedo ^-subunits, the divergence of the e- and y-subunits may have occurred around the time of separation of mammals and fish. Thus, it is possible that fish have a second, undetected gene encoding a y/e-family subunit, which may or may not now be active.
The calf e-subunit shares structural features common to all four subunits of the fish and mammalian AChR4'12'14. It contains four strongly hydrophobic segments4"12'14 (M1-M4) and an amphipathic segment16"18 (MA). Our expression studies using site-directed mutagenesis of the a-subunit cDNA indicate that these five putative a-helical transmembrane segments are all required for the operation of the ionic channel18. The hydrophi-licity profile19 and the predicted secondary structures20 of the calf e-subunit are also similar to those of the other AChR subunits4'12'21. These findings suggest that the e-subunit is oriented across the membrane in the same manner as the four other subunits. Three cysteine residues (aligned at positions 128, 142 and 231) and one potential TV-glycosylation site22 (aligned at position 141) are conserved in all AChR subunits whose sequences are known4'14. The calf e-subunit contains two additional potential N-glycosylation sites (aligned at positions 66 and 307), one of which (position 66) is assigned to the extracellular side of the membrane4'12'14. Because our expression studies are consistent with the presence of a disulphide bridge between the conserved cysteine residues 128 and 142 of the a-subunit18, the corresponding cysteine residues of the e-subunit may also form a disulphide bond.
To examine whether the e-subunit can function as an AChR subunit, we synthesized the mRNA specific for this subunit (or the y-subunit) in vitro23'24 using the cDNA template and injected the mRNA, combined with the Torpedo a-, - and d-subunit-specific mRNAs synthesized similarly18, into Xenopus oocytes. The oocytes were then tested for response to acetylcholine (ACh) applied ionophoretically by recording the intracellular potentials. All of the 61 oocytes injected with the calf e-subunit and the three Torpedo mRNAs and 38 of the 56 oocytes injected with the calf y-subunit and the three Torpedo mRNAs responded to ACh (Fig. 3) with mean ACh sensitivities (for the responsive oocytes) of 510 and 8 mV G, respectively. None of 60 control oocytes injected only with the Torpedo a-, - and d-subunit-specific mRNAs was responsive (&lt;0.2 mX^C"1). The mean ACh sensitivity of 70 responsive oocytes out of 72 oocytes injected with the Torpedo a-, -, y- and d-subunit-specific mRNAs18 was 1,300 ????G1. The atropine-rsistant and (H-)tubocurarine-sensitive nature of the observed ACh responses (Fig. 3) indicates the formation of the nicotinic AChR. These results show that the calf e-subunit, as well as the calf y-subunit, can be functionally substituted for the Torpedo y-subunit.
Blot hybridization analysis using e-subunit cDNA probe of poly(A)+ RNA from the skeletal muscle of a 4-month-old fetal calf revealed a hybridization-positive species with an estimated size of 4,200 nucleotides (Fig. 4A, lane a). No hybridizable species was detected, however, in poly(A)"1" RNA from the skeletal muscle of a 7-month-old fetal calf (Fig. 4A, lane ²), a 9-month-old fetal calf or a newborn calf or from adult bovine diaphragm (data not shown).
Fig. 1 (opposite) Primary structure of the mRNA encoding the e-subunit precursor of the calf muscle AChR. The nucleotide sequence of the mRNA was deduced by sequence analysis^8 of the cDNA inserts in clones pcACRe64, pcACRel and pcACRe2. Nucleotide residues are numbered in the 5' to 3' direction, beginning with the first residue of the codon specifying the amino-terminal residue of the mature e-subunit, and the nucleotides on the 5' side of residue 1 are indicated by negative numbers. Because the 3'-untranslated sequence presented contains no polyadenylation signal29 and is not followed by a poly(A) tract, this sequence is incomplete, as is the 5'-untranslated sequence shown. The amino-acid sequence, deduced by using the reading frame of the mRNA corresponding to the known amino-acid sequences of the AChR subunit precursors4"14, is shown above the nucleotide sequence. Amino-acid residues are numbered beginning with the amino-terminal residue of the mature e-subunit, and the preceding residues are indicated by negative numbers. The possibility that the initiating methionine is located upstream of the 5' end of the cDNA sequence shown cannot be excluded. The nucleotide differences observed between the individual clones are as follows: G (pcACRe64) or A (pcACRe2) at position -46; A (pcACRe64) or C (???^e!) at position 235; the G at position 279 and the C at position 285 of pcACRel (instead of A and T, respectively, in pcACRe64), derived apparently from the synthetic primer, are not shown. Methods. Total RNA was extracted from newborn or fetal calf skeletal muscle, and poly(A)+ RNA was isolated by oligo(dT)-cellulose chromatography. The oligodeoxyribonucleotide 5'-GTTGTTCTCCAGCAC-3', complementary to residues 271-285 of the calf ?-subunit mRNA9, was synthesized by the triester method and used for specific priming of reverse transcription. Single-stranded cDNA was synthesized using 5 g of this primer and 100 g of newborn calf muscle poly(A)+ RNA as template and was converted to double-stranded cDNA, which was cloned in pBR322 plasmid by inserting it into the Pstl site using poly(dG)-poly(dC) homopolymeric extensions. Escherichia coli ?1116 or HB101 was used for transformation, and 3xl05 tetracycline-resistant transformants were screened by hybridization at 60 C with the Hincll(8&amp;)/Ava 11(202) fragment excised from clone pcACR-yS (rf. 9) to yield one positive clone (pcACRel carrying nucleotides 84-285); the restriction endonuclease sites are identified by numbers indicating the 5'-terminal nucleotide generated by cleavage; all hybridization probes were labelled by nick-translation with [&lt;-32P]dCTP. Another batch of cDNA clones prepared similarly (1.5 x IO5 transformants) was then screened by hybridization at 60 C with the M/?oII(152)/Fnw4HI(260) fragment from clone pcACRel to give one positive clone (pcACRe2 carrying nucleotides -46 to 203). The procedures used for the above experiments have been described previously30. A cDNA library was next constructed by the procedure of Gubler and Hoffman31, using 10 g of oligo(dT)12_18 primer and 13 p,g of a fraction of fetal (4-month-old) calf muscle poly(A)+ RNA (>4,000 nucleotides; see Fig. 4) obtained by centrifugation in a gradient of 5-25% (w/v) sucrose32. Screening of 8xl05 tetracycline-resistant transformants by hybridization at 60 C with the Hinfl(-46)/Hmfl(lll) fragment from clone pcACRe2 yielded one positive clone (pcACRe64 carrying nucleotides -82 to 1,539); the //mfI(-46) site was generated in pcACRe2 at the junction of the 5' end of the cDNA insert and the poly(dG) · poly(dC) tail.
The AChR is present predominantly at the neuromuscular junction in adult muscle, whereas in embryonic muscle and denervated adult muscle the AChR also occurs in the extrajunc-tional membrane1'2. Some reports suggest that the two types of AChR are structurally different, the junctional AChR being slightly more acidic than the extrajunctional AChR25. Our amino-acid sequence data reveal that the calf e-subunit contains more acidic residues and less basic residues than does the calf ?-subunit9; the numbers of charged residues contained in the mature e- and ?-subunits are 20/18 Asp, 33/28 Glu, 26/31 Arg, 12/14 Lys and 5/11 His, respectively. However, the content of both the ?- and e-subunit mRNAs in fetal calf muscle, like that of the /3-subunit mRNA8, decreases with increasing age of the calf (Fig. 4), although the relative contents of the e- and y-subunit mRNAs in other age groups were not studied systematically. Muscle contains much smaller amounts of e-subunit mRNA than of ?-subunit mRNA (Fig. 4), and the latter is present in similar amounts to the a-, - and d-subunit mRNAs7"10. It thus remains uncertain whether the differential presence of the ?- and e-subunits is responsible for the difference in the junctional and extrajunctional forms of the AChR. Alternatively, the e-subunit (or the ?-subunit) may be a component of a third type of AChR which appears at a particular stage of muscle development26. It is also possible that the e-subunit (or the ?-subunit) is a constituent of the nicotinic AChR present in neuronal synapses27.
Fig. 2 Alignment of the amino-acid sequences of the calf AChR e-subunit precursor (top) and the calf (second row), human (third row) and G. californica AChRy-subunit precursors (bottom). The one-letter amino-acid notation is used. The sequence data for the calf, human and T. californica ?-subunit precursors have been taken from refs 9, 11 and 6, respectively. Sets of four identical residues at one aligned position are enclosed by solid lines, and sets of four identical or conservative residues at one aligned position by dashed lines. Conservative amino-acid substitutions are defined as pairs of residues belonging to one of the following groups: S, T, P, A and G; N, D, E and Q; H, R and K; M, I, L and V; F, Y and W. Gaps (-) have been inserted to achieve maximum homology. The degrees of homology given in the text were calculated on the basis of the alignment of the amino-acid sequences of the 11 AChR subunits (calf, human and Torpedo a, calf and Torpedo , calf, human and Torpedo ?, calf and Torpedo d and calf e), gaps being counted as one substitution regardless of their length. The positions in the aligned sequences including gaps are numbered beginning with the amino-terminal residue of the mature subunits, and the preceding positions are indicated by negative numbers. The asparagine residues as potential glycosylation sites are marked with asterisks; only those preceding segment Ml are shown. The putative disulphide bridge (S-S) and the putative transmembrane segments (Ml, M2, M3, M4 and MA) are indicated; segment MA has been assigned by comparison with that of the Torpedo a-subunit defined by deletion mapping18.
Fig. 3 ACh potentials recorded from Xenopus oocytes injected with mRNA specific for the calf AChR e-subunit (?) or y-subunit (B) together with the T. californica AChR a-, - and d-subunit-specific mRNAs. The recordings were made at room temperature in Ringer's solution containing 1 ? atropine and 5 mM MgCl2 instead of CaCl2: upper traces, ACh potentials; lower traces, currents used for ionophoresis of ACh (backing current, 12 ? A). The membrane potential was held at -70 mV. Responses to ACh were recorded before (a) and 6-8 min after perfusion with 2 ? (-l-)tubocurarine (b) and 8-9 min after washing out the antagonist (c).
Methods. The 320-base-pair (bp) fragment extending from the Avail site generated at the 5' end of the cDNA insert to the At?aII(238) site and the At?aII(238)/coRI (1,444) fragment, derived from clone pcACR604, and the 520-bp fragment of clone pACR-yH (rf. 6) extending from the EcoRI(l,474) site to the Pvull site on the vector DNA were ligated. The resulting 2.0-kilobase-pair (kb) fragment was isolated, treated with E. coli DNA polymerase I (Klenow fragment) in the presence of dGTP, dCTP and dTTP and inserted into the Smal site of the plasmid pSP64 (rf. 24) in the same orientation as the SP6 promoter to yield the plasmid pSPce. The PsfI(-100)/XfioI(207) fragment from clone pcACRyll (rf. 9), the XJioI(207)/HmdIII(l,181) fragment, the HindIII(l,181)/ Accl( 1,560) fragment and the 180-bp fragment extending from the Ace I (1,560) site to the Pvull site on the vector DNA, derived from clone pcACRyS (rf. 9), and the 3.0-kb Smal/Pstl fragment from pSP64 were ligated. The resulting plasmid pSPcy, carrying the entire calf ?-subunit cDNA (except for a portion of the 5'-noncoding region) in the same orientation as the SP6 promoter, was identified by colony hybridization with both the above Xhol/ Hindlll and Hindlll/Accl fragments as probes and by restriction endonuclease analysis. The calf AChR e- and y-subunit-specific mRNAs were synthesized in vitro, using Sacl-cleaved pSPce and EcoRI-cleaved pSPcy, respectively, as templates and were then capped in vitro with vaccinia virus mRNA guanylyl transferase23. Each of these mRNAs, combined with the T. californica AChR a-, - and d-subunit-specificmRNAs18 (molar ratio of the a-, -, y/ e- and d-subunit-specific mRNAs, 2:1:2:1 ; total mRNA concentration, 120-340 ng G1), was injected into Xenopus laevis oocytes (average volume injected per oocyte, 20nl). The oocytes were incubated for 3 days in conditions described previously33 before being tested for response to ACh.
Conti-Tronconi et al.3 have determined the sequences of the amino-terminal 23-35 amino-acid residues of the four polypep-tides derived from fetal calf muscle AChR. Three of these sequences agree reasonably well with the amino-terminal sequences of the mature a- (rf. 7), /3- (rf. 8) and d-subunits10 deduced by us from the cDNA sequences, but the fourth sequence (designated x) matches neither the ?-subunit9 nor the e-subunit. This may imply the possible existence of still another subunit of the AChR.
We thank Dr Takashi Miyata for computer analysis and helpful discussions. This investigation was supported in part by research grants from the Ministry of Education, Science and Culture of Japan, the Mitsubishi Foundation and the Japanese Foundation of Metabolism and Diseases.
Fig. 4 Autoradiogram of blot hybridization analysis of calf muscle RNA with an AChR e-subunit (A) or ?-subunit (B) cDNA probe. Samples of skeletal muscle poly(A)+ RNA (40 g each in A or 30 g each in B) from a 4-month-old (lane a) or a 7-month-old (lane b} fetal calf were denatured with l M glyoxal and 50% dimethyl sulphoxide, electrophoresed on 1.5% agarose gels and transferred to a nitrocellulose filter34 (A) or diazophenylthioether paper35 (B). The hybridization probe used was the 1,535-bp fragment of clone pcACRe64 extending from the Pstl site flanking the 5' end of the cDNA insert to the EcoRI(l,444) site (A) or an equimolar mixture of the 1,004-bp fragment extending from the Pstl site flanking the 5' end of the cDNA insert to the Accl( 1,054) site and the Accl( 1,054)/Accl( 1,560) fragment, derived from clone pcACR?5 (rf. 9) (B) ; the two probes, labelled by nick-translation with [a-32P] dCTP, had nearly equal specific radioactivities (4 x IO8 c.p.m. per g), but the photograph in A is more exposed than that in , to intensify the hybridization signal. The size markers used were calf and E. coli ribosomal RNA. The positions of the e-subunit mRNA (-4,200 nucleotides) (A) and the ?-subunit mRNA (-2,000 nucleotides9) (B) are indicated by arrowheads; the larger RNA species (-3,700 nucleotides) hybridizable with the ?-subunit cDNA probe probably represents incompletely spliced RNA as described previously9.
</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Karlin</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> in <btl>Cell Surface Reviews</btl> Vol. <vid>6</vid> (eds Cotman, C. W., Poste, G. &amp; Nicolson, G. L.) <ppf>191</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>260</ppl> (North-Holland, Amsterdam, <cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Changeux</snm>, <fnm>J.-P.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Harvey Lect.</jtl> <vid>75</vid>, <ppf>85</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>254</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Conti-Tronconi</snm>, <fnm>B. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gotti</snm>, <fnm>C. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hunkapiller</snm>, <fnm>M. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Raftery</snm>, <fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>218</vid>, <ppf>1227</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1229</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Noda</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>299</vid>, <ppf>793</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>797</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Noda</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>301</vid>, <ppf>251</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>255</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Noda</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>302</vid>, <ppf>528</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>532</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Noda</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>305</vid>, <ppf>818</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>823</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Tanabe</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Eur. J. Biochem.</jtl> <vid>144</vid>, <ppf>11</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>17</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Takai</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Eur. J. Biochem.</jtl> <vid>143</vid>, <ppf>109</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>115</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kubo</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Eur. J. Biochem.</jtl> <vid>149</vid>, <ppf>5</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>13</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Shibahara</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Eur. J. Biochem.</jtl> <vid>146</vid>, <ppf>15</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>22</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Claudio</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ballivet</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Patrick</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Heinemann</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>1111</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1115</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sumikawa</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>5809</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>5822</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Devillers-Thiery</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Giraudat</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bentaboulet</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Changeux</snm>, <fnm>J.-P.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>2067</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2071</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Blobel</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Dobberstein</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>852</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>862</ppl> (<cd year="1975">1975</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Guy</snm>, <fnm>H. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biophys. J.</jtl> <vid>45</vid>, <ppf>249</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>261</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Finer-Moore</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Stroud</snm>, <fnm>R. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>155</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>159</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mishina</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>313</vid>, <ppf>364</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>369</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hopp</snm>, <fnm>T. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Woods</snm>, <fnm>K. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>78</vid>, <ppf>3824</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3828</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Chou</snm>, <fnm>P. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fasman</snm>, <fnm>G. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>A. Rev. Biochem.</jtl> <vid>47</vid>, <ppf>251</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>276</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Numa</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Cold Spring Harb. Symp. quant. Biol.</jtl> <vid>48</vid>, <ppf>57</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>69</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Marshall</snm>, <fnm>R. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochem. Soc. Symp.</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>17</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>26</ppl> (<cd year="1974">1974</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Green</snm>, <fnm>M. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Maniatis</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Melton</snm>, <fnm>D. A.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>32</vid>, <ppf>681</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>694</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Krainer</snm>, <fnm>A. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Maniatis</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ruskin</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Green</snm>, <fnm>M. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>36</vid>, <ppf>993</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1005</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Nathanson</snm>, <fnm>N. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hall</snm>, <fnm>Z. W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Biochemistry</jtl> <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>3392</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>3401</ppl> (<cd year="1979">1979</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hall</snm>, <fnm>Z. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Roisin</snm>, <fnm>M.-P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gu</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gorin</snm>, <fnm>P. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cold Spring Harb. Symp. quant. Biol.</jtl> <vid>48</vid>, <ppf>101</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>108</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Morley</snm>, <fnm>B. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kemp</snm>, <fnm>G. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Brain Res. Rev.</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>81</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>104</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Maxam</snm>, <fnm>A. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gilbert</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Meth. Enzym.</jtl> <vid>65</vid>, <ppf>499</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>560</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Nevins</snm>, <fnm>J. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>A. Rev. Biochem.</jtl> <vid>52</vid>, <ppf>441</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>466</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Noda</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>295</vid>, <ppf>202</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>206</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b31"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gubler</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hoffman</snm>, <fnm>B. J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Gene</jtl> <vid>25</vid>, <ppf>263</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>269</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b32"><reftxt><refau><snm>Houghton</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>1913</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1931</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b33"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mishina</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>307</vid>, <ppf>604</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>608</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b34"><reftxt><refau><snm>Thomas</snm>, <fnm>P. S.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>77</vid>, <ppf>5201</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>5205</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b35"><reftxt><refau><snm>Alwine</snm>, <fnm>J. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kemp</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Stark</snm>, <fnm>G. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>74</vid>, <ppf>5350</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>5354</ppl> (<cd year="1977">1977</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></headerx>