<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315715a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="nv"/>
<pp><spn>715</spn><epn>716</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315715a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Astrophysics: Optical bursts &ndash; where are they?</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>K.</fnm><snm>Hurley</snm><inits>K.</inits></au>
<aff>Ma&icirc;tre de Recherche in the CNRS at the Centre d&apos;Etude Spatiale des Rayonnements, Universit&eacute; Paul Sabatier, 31029 Toulouse, C&eacute;dex, France.</aff></aug></fm>
<bdy>DESPITE their brevity, and sometimes because of it, transient events are often the most spectacular in astrophysics. Gamma-ray bursters1, now widely believed to occur on or about neutron stars, are one example; typically they produce a blast of radiation lasting several seconds and with a peak luminosity of at least nine orders of magnitude over the quiescent state, in which they are quite undetectable. Transient phenomena in the optical waveband, apparently associated with some bursters23 have also been detected but, until recently, only on archival photographic plates. Therefore, they were not time-resolved. Now that continuous monitoring of optical bursts is being undertaken, the evidence indicates that they have light curves which strongly resemble their progenitor gamma bursts, and a clever argument has been advanced which uses this fact to constrain the still unknown distances to bursters.
Our present understanding of the gamma-burst phenomenon is still quite incomplete. It is much easier to list the objects with which gamma bursters are not associated, such as steady X-ray and ?-ray sources, than it is to identify convincingly any quiescent counterpart to them. This has proven to be perhaps the major obstacle to progress, as it leaves the distance to the source uncertain by four orders of magnitude. So, although a wealth of circumstantial evidence points to strongly magnetized neutron stars as burst sources in at least some cases, the question of the type of stellar system - if any - in which the neutron star resides has still not been answered.
Perhaps nowhere has the problem been so acute as with the fascinating burster of 5 March 19794: not only was its peak intensity (at Earth) the largest recorded for a gamma burst, but also its localization coincides with the N49 supernova remnant in the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC), at a distance of 55 kiloparsecs. A straightforward interpretation would be that the burst originated on the neutron star which produced the remnant. But a number of objections can be raised to this idea, not least that, if the source radiated isotropically from the LMC, then for a brief instant it outshone (in ?-rays alone) the entire luminous output of our Galaxy. A tantalizing new piece of evidence was announced last summer at a meeting at Stanford University and subsequently in Nature5. During a five-month period of optical monitoring of the 5 March source, three optical bursts were detected and clearly time-resolved. Their light curves generally resembled the time histories of gamma bursts, although no simultaneous ?-ray activity was noted at the times of the optical bursts (the instruments in orbit at the time were probably not sensitive enough to record it). Thus, the relation between the 5 March gamma bursts and the optical bursts remains tentative. However, as R. London of Lawrence Liver-more Laboratory was quick to point out, if the two bursts are associated, the distance to the source is strongly constrained, an idea later confirmed by J.-M. Hameury, J. P. Lasota and S. Bonnazola of Meudon Observatory.
The argument is that if the optical radiation is due to a thermal mechanism (for example, reprocessing of gamma radiation6 in an accretion disk or in the atmosphere of a stellar companion), the luminosity of the mechanism cannot exceed that of black-body radiation. Then, since the dimension of the optical source cannot exceed ct, where c is the speed of light and / is the rise time of the optical flash, a relation is obtained between the maximum distance to the source and its temperature. That temperature turns out to be at least several million electron volts for a source in the LMC. In general, it is difficult to construct thermal models with these temperatures and furthermore, the 5 March burster has never been observed to emit at these energies. The conclusion is that its source is much nearer than the LMC. In arriving at this conclusion, a number of special models for the optical radiation have to be excluded: coherent emission, sources in relativistic expansion, beaming and special geometries that appear to violate causality.
In addition to providing distance constraints, time-resolved optical flashes may do for ?-ray bursters what they did for X-ray bursters7, that is, allow an estimate of the dimension of the reprocessing region (via both the rise time and the duration of the flash). In the 5 March case, for example, a reprocessing region with a typical dimension of 30,000 km is indicated, ruling out reprocessing in the atmosphere of a non-degenerate stellar companion and suggesting the possibility of an accretion disk.
But what of the tentative nature of the association between optical flashes and gamma bursts? There has never been any simultaneous observation of the two, and since optical instruments tend to be many orders of magnitude more sensitive (as energy-flux detectors) than ?-ray burst instruments, for the time being only optical flashes associated with the largest (relatively infrequent) gamma bursts can be expected to give rise to coincident detections. Simultaneous direct imaging and photometry of an optical flash should soon be possible with a unique system now being deployed at the European Southern Observatory. The experiment, being conducted by H. Pedersen, consists of a battery of small automated telescopes each trained on the position of a particular ?-ray burst source.
Much of the uncertainty surrounding optical flashes comes from the possibility that they are generated rather closer to home, for example by meteors in the upper atmosphere. The use of two detection systems separated by even one kilometre eliminates these effects by parallax. Such a study was recently undertaken on an intercontinental baseline8 and another two-telescope proposal is under consideration by the European Southern Observatory. On top of this, a novel electronic camera array being installed at Kitt Peak National Observatory910, will eventually provide permanent night-time mon-itor-ing of much of the sky for optical transients down to magnitude 11, with source localization at the arc-second level. It is expected that some twenty optical flashes associated with gamma bursts will be I detected per year (not to mention a host of other short-timescale astronomical events), dramatically increasing the probability of a simultaneous optical and gamma-ray detection. This set up will also greatly increase accuracy of localization, in the wake of which may come both the long-awaited identification of the counterpart and the answer to the question of the distance scale.</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Klebesadel</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Strong</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Olson</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Astrophys. J. Lett.</jtl> <vid>182</vid>, <ppf>L85</ppf> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schaefer</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>294</vid>, <ppf>722</ppf> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schaefer</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Astrophys. J. Lett.</jtl> <vid>286</vid>, <ppf>L1</ppf> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cline</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Comments on Astrophysics</jtl> <vid>9</vid>(<iid>1</iid>), <ppf>13</ppf> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Pedersen</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>312</vid>, <ppf>46</ppf> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>London</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cominsky</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Astrophys. J. Lett.</jtl> <vid>275</vid>, <ppf>L59</ppf> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Pedersen</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Astrophys. J.</jtl> <vid>263</vid>, <ppf>325</ppf> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schaefer</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Vanderspek</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bradt</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ricker</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Astrophys. J.</jtl> <vid>283</vid>, <ppf>887</ppf> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ricker</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Doty</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Vallerga</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Vanderspek</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> in <i>Am. Instit. Phys. Conf. Proc</i>. No. 115 (ed. Woosley, S.) <ppf>669</ppf> (AIP, New York, <cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Teegarden</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>von Rosenvinge</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cline</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kaipa</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> in <i>Am. Instit. Phys. Conf. Proc.</i> No. 115 (ed Woosley, S.) <ppf>687</ppf> (AIP, New York, <cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></headerx>