<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315758a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>758</spn><epn>761</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315758a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Structural organization of the <i>bcr</i> gene and its role in the Ph&prime; translocation</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Nora</fnm><snm>Heisterkamp</snm><inits>N.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Kees</fnm><snm>Stam</snm><inits>K.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>John</fnm><snm>Groffen</snm><inits>J.</inits></au>
<aff>Oncogene Science, Inc., 222 Station Plaza North, Mineola, New York 11501, USA</aff>
<au><fnm>Annelies</fnm><snm>de Klein</snm><inits>A.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>Gerard</fnm><snm>Grosveld</snm><inits>G.</inits></au>
<aff>Department of Cell Biology and Genetics, Erasmus University, 3000 DR Rotterdam, The Netherlands</aff></aug>
<hst>
<re year="na" month="3" day="15"/>
<acc year="1985" month="5" day="14"/></hst>
<fp><p>The Philadelphia (Ph&prime;) chromosome, an abnormal chromosome 22 (ref. 1), is one of the best-known examples of a specific human chromosomal abnormality strongly associated with one form of human leukaemia, chronic myelocytic leukaemia (CML). The finding<super>2</super> that a small region of chromosome 9 which includes the c-<i>abl</i> oncogene is translocated to chromosome 22 prompted studies to elucidate the molecular mechanisms involved in this disease. We have demonstrated previously that the chromosome 9 of one patient with CML contains a breakpoint 14 kilobases (kb) 5&prime; of the most 5&prime; v-<i>abl</i>-homologous exon<super>3</super>. These data suggest a role for c-<i>abl</i> in CML, a theory supported by the presence of an abnormally sized <i>abl</i> messenger RNA<super>4,5</super> and protein<super>6</super> in the CML cell line K562. The region involved in the translocation on chromosome 22 has also been identified: all Ph&prime;-positive patients examined to date have a breakpoint within a 5.8-kb region, for which we have proposed the name &lsquo;breakpoint cluster region&rsquo; (<i>bcr</i>)<super>7</super>. To determine whether her contains protein-encoding regions, probes from <i>bcr</i> were tested for their ability to hybridize to complementary DNA sequences. A 0.6-kb <i>Hin</i>dIII/<i>Bam</i>Hl <i>bcr</i> restriction enzyme fragment proved suitable for isolating several cDNA clones from a human fibroblast cDNA library<super>8</super>. Using <i>bcr</i> cDNA sequences, we obtained data strongly suggesting the presence of a chimaeric <i>bcr/abl</i> mRNA in the leukaemic cells of Ph&prime;-positive CML patients. The recent isolation of cDNA clones containing <i>bcr</i> and <i>abl</i> sequences confirms this finding<super>12</super>. Because the <i>bcr</i> part of the chimaeric mRNA could be required to induce the transforming activity of the human c-<i>abl</i> oncogene, we have now initiated studies to characterize the normal &lsquo;<i>bcr</i> gene&rsquo; and to determine the effect of a translocation within its coding domain. We demonstrate that as a result of the Ph&prime; translocation, a variable number of <i>bcr</i> exons are included in the chimaeric <i>bcr/abl</i> mRNA. The <i>bcr</i> gene sequences in this mRNA could be responsible for the transition of the <i>abl</i> cellular proto-oncogene into an oncogene.</p></fp></fm>
<bdy>
The largest cDNA, VI-3, containing an insert of 2.2 kb, was characterized in detail by restriction enzyme mapping (Fig. la) and sequence analysis (Fig. lo). The cDNA contains one long open reading frame, starting at the poly(G) tail at the 5' end and continuing to nucleotide 1,770, where a stop codon is encountered. All other reading frames have many stop codons within the entire region. The long open reading frame has the coding capacity for 589 amino-acid residues, corresponding to a protein of relative molecular mass (Mr) -65,000; at the 3' end, a polyadenylation signal occurs at nucleotide 2,182 followed by a poly(A) tail beginning at base 2,208 indicating that the cDNA contains the complete 3' end of the gene. Although translational start sequences are encountered at the 5' end, it is unlikely that this cDNA contains a complete copy of the mRNA, as Northern blot hybridizations indicate the presence of bcr mRNAs of -4.0 and -6.5 kb. Computer searches of newly isolated protein sequences derived directly from proteins or deduced from cDNA nucleotide sequences frequently result in the identification of proteins with partial homology. Such information is valuable, frequently allowing the assignment of a preliminary function to an unknown protein. Therefore, the PIR FASTP program10 was used to search for bcr-homologous proteins ; no proteins with significant homology were found, indicating that the bcr protein exhibits an as yet unidentified cellular function.
To determine the orientation of the bcr gene on chromosome 22, 5' and 3' probes were prepared from the Vl-3 cDNA and hybridized to cosmids7 containing human chromosome 22 sequences. This established that the 5' end of the bcr gene is towards the centromere of chromosome 22 and is retained after the Ph' translocation; the 3' end of the bcr gene lies in the direction of the telomere and is translocated to chromosome 9 in the t(9 ; 22) translocation. The cDNA hybridizes to restriction enzyme fragments distributed over a region of up to 45 kb of chromosome 22 DNA (Fig. 2a). Within this region, a minimum of 13 exons are present. To determine the exact position and number of exons within the breakpoint cluster region, all hybridizing regions in bcr were sequenced and compared with the Vl-3 cDNA. Four relatively small exons, designated 1-4, were present within bcr, varying in size from 76 to 105 base pairs (bp) (Fig. 20); in the cDNA, these exons correspond to nucleotides 483-836 (Fig. lb). As bcr was defined as the area on chromosome 22 in which the Ph' breakpoints are found, we conclude that the breakpoints occur within a gene.
Having determined the position of the exons within bcr, we investigated whether the breakpoints occur in exon or intron regions. For CML DNA such as that of CML patient C481, this was readily determined. We had previously demonstrated7 a breakpoint within a 1.2-kb H/Bg bcr fragment in several CML DNA samples, including that of patient C481. As no coding sequences are located within this region (see Fig. 2), patients such as C481 must have a chromosomal breakpoint in the intron between the exons designated 3 and 4.
A less simple situation was encountered in the DNA of patients 0311068 and 7701C. Nonetheless, cloning of 9q+ breakpoint fragments from these DNAs (data not shown) and restriction enzyme analysis followed by Southern hybridization enabled us to locate the breakpoints between exons 2 and 3 (see Fig. 2). The breakpoints in the previously cloned3'7 9q+ breakpoint fragments of patients 0319129 and 02120185 were analysed by DNA sequencing. In addition, we cloned the 22q breakpoint fragments of patient 0319129 (unpublished results) and of the cell line K562. DNA sequence analysis of the breakpoint regions of these fragments and that of the sequence of the corresponding chromosome 22 regions enabled us to define the point of translocation for these DNAs (see Fig. 2). None of the breakpoints analysed here could be located within an exon, indicating that in the Ph' translocation, breakpoints occur within intron regions of bcr. For four of the six DNA samples analysed, the translocation would result in the transcription of a mRNA that includes bcr exons 1 and 2 (see Fig. 2); in two CML DNAs the third exon would be additionally incorporated in the chimaeric bcr/c-abl mRNA. Exon 3 encodes only 25 amino acids, not substantially increasing the size of the chimaeric protein.
Fig. l    bcr cDNA Vl-3. a, Restriction enzyme map of Vl-3. The black bar indicates the open reading frame sequences, the thin line non-translated sequences. The 3' end of the cDNA containing the poly(A) tail is depicted as An. Restriction enzymes include:   A,   Avail   Ap,  Apali   B, g/II; Bs, BstElli H, Hindlll; Hf, Hinfli P, Pstli PH, PuwII; S, Saw3A. ², DNA sequence and translation of Vl-3 sequence. Amino-acid residues are indicated with a one-letter symbol below the sequence. The exact position of exons designated 1-6 (see Fig. 2a) within Vl-3 bcr cDNA is shown by the numbers above the sequence. DNA sequencing was performed   using   the   dideoxy-chain termination method14 on restriction enzyme fragments of the cDNA sub-cloned into M13 phage15. All regions were sequenced on both strands.
A knowledge of the DNA sequence of the translocation junction point may provide additional information about the mechanism of chromosomal translocation. Figure 3 a shows the sequence of the region containing the crossover point for translocation in the DNA of patient 031929 and compares this with normal chromosome 22 and 9 DNA sequences. In 0319129 DNA, the chromosomal break has occurred in a rather 'precise' manner, leading to the generation of a 22q and 9q+ sequence exactly reflecting the sequence of the normal chromosome 22 and 9 DNA sequences. However, at the breakpoint, a C nucleo-tide is found in both the 9q+ and 22q sequences, whereas the chromosome 22 sequence contains a G at that position. Note that both chromosomes 9 and 22 contain limited stretches of homology near the break (Fig. 3a underlined); a DNA search revealed homology of this region to human Alu repetitive sequences.
No such similar stretches of homologous sequences between chromosomes 9 and 22 occur at the breakpoint in the DNA of patient 0212015 (Fig. 30) or in that of K562 DNA (data not shown). In the 9q+ DNA of patient 0212015, sequences are found between the breakpoints on chromosomes 9 and 22 (Fig. 36) which are not present in the sequenced region of the normal chromosomes 9 and 22. This suggests that in the 9q+ chromosome a secondary event has taken place; it is possible that after translocation of chromosome 22 sequences to chromosome 9, a deletion affecting chromosome 9 sequences occurred. The arrow indicating the breakpoint on chromosome 9 (see Fig. 30) would then represent the point of deletion. In addition, compared with the normal chromosome 9 sequences, the chromosome 9 sequences of the 9q+ fragment contain 13 nucleo-tide changes within an 81-bp stretch. These changes may reflect differences between individuals (the control chromosome 9 sequences were isolated from a human lung carcinoma cosmid library) ; however, the number of nucleotide substitutions would be very high in such an event. Moreover, the chromosome 22 part of the 9q+ fragment contains no nucleotide changes in either intron or exon sequences, favouring the explanation of inefficient DNA repair on deletion of chromosome 9 sequences.
These results indicate that bcr is part of a gene oriented with its 5' end towards the centromere of chromosome 22. In the Philadelphia translocation, a break occurs within bcr, and sequences from chromosome 9 which contain the human c-abl oncogene in all Ph'-positive cases examined7'9 are translocated to the 3' of the truncated bcr gene. The joining of bcr and c-abl sequences is highly specific for CML, as this configuration has been found in complex translocations9 and even in the leukaemic cells of one CML patient cytogenetically lacking the Ph' chromosome11. Because the orientation of c-abl on chromosome 9 is also centromere-5'-3'-telomere, bcr and c-abl are joined in a head-to-tail fashion on the Ph' chromosome. Although the distance between the most 5' v-abl homologous to v-abl and the physical breakpoint may vary from 14kb (patient 0319129) to > 100 kb (K562), the effect of the translocation on the expression of the bcr gene and c-abl seems to be very similar in different patients: in K562 and in Ph'-positive CML patients, abnormal RNA transcripts of 8.5 kb are detected, which hybridize to both c-abl and 5' bcr exon probes. The molecular cloning of a chimaeric cDNA from K562 cells has provided definitive proof for the existence of chimaeric mRNA12. The chimaeric mRNAs must be the result of transcription initiating at the promoter of the bcr gene; depending on the exact location of the breakpoint, the transcript will include all 5' exons in addition to either exons 1 and 2 or exons 1, 2 and 3 of bcr. Recent sequence analysis of K562 bcr/abl cDNA confirms the variable presence of the third exon. In K562 we found that, as predicted, the third exon is present in the cDNA, immediately preceding c-abl sequences. In contrast, Southern blot analysis of the molecularly cloned 22q genomic DNA fragment of, for example, patient 0319129 unambiguously demonstrates that in this patient exon 3 has been removed from the Ph' chromosome and will not be included in a chimaeric bcr/abl transcript. Transcription continues into the c-abl oncogene, including, as a minimum, the most 5' v-abl-homologous exon and all exons 3' of it, including the phos-photyrosine acceptor site13. We do not know whether the inclusion of exon 3 in the chimaeric mRNA has an effect on the progression of the disease.
Fig. 2 Genomic organization of the her gene, a, Restriction enzyme map of chromosome 22 sequences encompassing bcr. Exons are indicated by black boxes below the restriction enzyme map. The position of the numbered exons has been determined by sequencing; all other exons were located by hybridization to the Vl-3 cDNA. The asterisk indicates a polymorphic Bglll restriction enzyme site. 6, Restriction enzyme map of the breakpoint cluster region, with the exons as indicated in a. Below the map, the approximate positions of the breakpoints in different CML DNAs are indicated by horizontal or vertical arrows. Restriction enzymes include: A, Ava\\ B, BamHI; Bg, g/II; E, Eco RI, H, H­ndIII; P, Ps­l; S, Smal\ Ss, Sstl; X, Xhol. The breakpoint of the 22q chromosome from DNA 0319129 was cloned as a 9.5-kb Bglll fragment in Charon 30 according to previously described methods16.9q+ fragments were isolated by cloning a 7.2-kb Bam HI fragment and a 7.7-kb c0RI fragment into Charon 30 and Agtwes, respectively.
Chromosomal aberrations may be generated by specific events involving recombination-prone DNA sequences. Alternatively, such recombination events could occur almost at random. In either case, a very limited number of translocations will result in gene alterations leading to the disruption of normal growth and differentiation. In the Ph' translocation, we have found that breakpoints on chromosome 9 are spread over a region of up to 100 kb. The breakpoints on chomosome 22 occur within a smaller region of around 5.0kb. Nonetheless, no sequence homology can be found between breakpoint regions of different CML patients or coding regions of c-abl and bcr genes. Therefore, we may conclude that the processes underlying the Ph' translocation are random recombination events. Once such recombinations result in a genomic configuration that allows the transcription of chimaeric bcr/abl mRNA, malignant proliferation of specific cell types may occur. It seems highly likely that this chimaeric mRNA is translated into protein because an abnormally sized 210,000-Mr c-abl protein was detected in K562 cells. In contrast to the normal c-abl protein, the P210 has tyrosine kinase activity6.
Fig. 3 Breakpoint sequences of the DNAs of two CML patients, a, Sequence of 0319129 DNA; the sequences are in a 5'-3' orientation. Normal chromosome 9 sequences (first line) are from non-CML DNA; the 9q and 22q sequences (second and third lines) are from DNA of patient 0319129. Normal chromosome 22 sequences (fourth line) are from non-CML DNA. An arrow indicates the breakpoint on chromosomes 9 and 22; the nucleotide C found in both the 9q" and 22q sequences at the breakpoint is boxed. Limited regions of homology between the normal chromosome 9 and 22 sequences are underlined. 6, Breakpoint sequence of 02120185 DNA; normal chromosome 9 and 22 sequences (first and third lines in each set) were from non-CML DNA. The 9q+ sequence on the second line contains an area boxed to indicate that it does not originate from the normal chromosomes 9 or 22 sequenced in the present experiments. Dots above the chromosome 9 sequences indicate nucleotide differences at those positions from the 9q+ chromosome. The beginning of exon 3 (see Fig. 26) in the 9q+ and 22 sequence is indicated in the figure. Small restriction enzyme fragments containing the breakpoints were chosen for sequence analysis, based on restriction enzyme mapping data and comparison with normal chromosome 9 and 22 maps.
It is tempting to speculate that the bcr moiety of the fusion protein is responsible for this effect. However, although the consequences of the Ph' translocation on a molecular level are becoming evident, it remains to be established whether this phenomenon is actually the cause or merely one of the steps that eventually result in CML.
We thank Pamela Hansen and Gail Blennerhassett for technical assistance, John Stephenson for critical reading of the manuscript, H. Okayama for the generous gift of the cDNA library and Rosanne Beyer for typing the manuscript. This work was supported by Oncogene Science, Inc.</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rowley</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>243</vid>, <ppf>290</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>293</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>de Klein</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>300</vid>, <ppf>765</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>767</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Heisterkamp</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>306</vid>, <ppf>239</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>242</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Collins</snm>, <fnm>S. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kubonishi</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Miyoshi</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Groudine</snm>, <fnm>M. T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>225</vid>, <ppf>72</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>74</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gale</snm>, <fnm>R. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Canaani</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>5648</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>5652</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Konopka</snm>, <fnm>J. B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Watanabe</snm>, <fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Witte</snm>, <fnm>O. N.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>317</vid>, <ppf>1035</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1042</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Groffen</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>36</vid>, <ppf>93</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>99</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Okayama</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Berg</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Molec. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>280</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>289</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bartram</snm>, <fnm>C. R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>306</vid>, <ppf>277</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>280</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lipman</snm>, <fnm>D. F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pearson</snm>, <fnm>W. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>227</vid>, <ppf>1435</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1441</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bartram</snm>, <fnm>C. R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>4</vid>, <ppf>683</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>686</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Canaani</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>315</vid>, <ppf>550</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>554</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Groffen</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Heisterkamp</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Reynolds</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm> <suff>Jr</suff></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Stephenson</snm>, <fnm>J. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>304</vid>, <ppf>167</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>169</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sanger</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nicklen</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Coulson</snm>, <fnm>A. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl> <vid>74</vid>, <ppf>5463</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>5467</ppl> (<cd year="1977">1977</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Messing</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Vieira</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Gene</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>269</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>276</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Groffen</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Heisterkamp</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Blennerhassett</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Stephenson</snm>, <fnm>J. R.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Virology</jtl> <vid>126</vid>, <ppf>213</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>227</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></headerx>