<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE headerx PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD headerx//EN" "headerx.dtd">
<headerx>
<ArticleIdList>
<ArticleId>315736a0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList>
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature</jtl>
<vol>315</vol>
<iss>6022</iss>
<idt>19850627</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>736</spn><epn>739</epn></pp>
<issn>0028-0836</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1985</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/315736a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Radial distribution studies of non-framework aluminium species formed during dehydroxylation of zeolite HY</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>R. D.</fnm><snm>Shannon</snm><inits>R. D.</inits></au>
<aff>Central Research &amp; Development Department, Experimental Station, E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, Wilmington, Delaware 19898, USA</aff>
<au><fnm>G.</fnm><snm>Bergeret</snm><inits>G.</inits></au>
<au><fnm>P.</fnm><snm>Gallezot</snm><inits>P.</inits></au>
<aff>Institut de Recherches sur la Catalyse, CNRS, 2, Ave Albert Einstein, 69626 Villeurbanne Cedex, France</aff></aug>
<hst>
<re year="1984" month="12" day="27"/>
<acc year="1985" month="4" day="24"/></hst>
<fp><p>The use of stabilized zeolite Y as a cracking catalyst for converting petroleum into gasoline, fuel oil and petrochemical feeds is widespread<super>1</super>. During the stabilization process, when the ammonium-exchanged form of zeolite Y is heated to high temperatures, aluminium is extracted from the zeolite framework<super>1&ndash;3</super>. The nature of this non-framework aluminium has been of considerable interest because of its possible influence on the zeolite acidity and thermal stability. Indirect information on the nature of the non-framework Al (NFA) has been obtained from infrared spectroscopy, X-ray diffraction, absorption and nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) studies. To obtain further knowledge of the NFA species, we have now performed radial electron distribution studies of H&ndash;Y and H&ndash;Y dehydroxylated in vacuum and steam. These studies suggest that the non-framework Al species probably contain edge-shared octahedral Al<sub><i>m</i></sub>(O,OH)<sub><i>n</i></sub> chains similar to those found in NaAlSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>6</sub> (jadeite), CaAl<sub>2</sub>(OH)<sub>4</sub>SiO<sub>4</sub> (chantalite) and Al<sub>2</sub>(OH)<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>.</p></fp></fm>
<bdy>The loss of Al from the framework and the development of octahedral Al is evidenced by (1) infrared spectroscopy from shifts in the infrared (Si, Al)-oxygen (T-O) stretching frequencies4'9; (2) X-ray fluorescence spectroscopy from shifts of the SiKjS and A1K/3 lines10'13; (3) X-ray diffraction from the decrease in cell dimensions5'7'8'14; (4) X-ray structure analyses of dehydroxylated Y14; (5) 29Si-NMR from increases in the Si/Al ratios15'17; and (6) 27A1-NMR from observation of spectra arising from octahedral Al species (refs 18-20 and P. A. Jacobs et a?, in preparation). Infrared spectra in the OH region frequently show weak bands which appear after dehydroxyla-tion. These bands are generally believed to result from OH groups associated with either the NFA species21 or vacancies created during the removal of Al5'22'23. There has been no unequivocal identification of these bands, but the species A1(OH)2+, Al(OH) J, A10+, [?12?2??G, [?12?]4+ and A1(OH)3 (refs 11, 14, 21, 24-29) have been proposed. Recently, 27A1-NMR studies have indicated that the NFA species in zeolite Y contain octahedrally coordinated Al and are located in large cavities after deammoniation at 300 C and are distributed in both the large cavities and the sodalite cages after treatment at 500 C20. A distinction between low-condensed mobile NFA species formed at 300-500 C under shallow-bed conditions and higher-condensed, immobile species formed at 500 C under deep bed or moist conditions was made by Freude et al.19 and Raatz et a/.13.
Fig. 1    Experimental RDFs for HY (a) and HY-DH (²). Both in vacuum; temperatures 300C (a) and 650C (fe).
One sample of Na-Y for use in vacuum dehydroxylation was exchanged eight times with l M NH4C1 to yield NH4-Y-containing 0.99% Na (dry basis). Activation was carried out in a U-shaped quartz cell containing two 5-cm2 frits. NH4-Y (5 g) was heated in flowing O2 (5 C min"1) from 25 to 300 C to eliminate all hydrocarbons. The sample was then evacuated and held for 15 h at 300 C to obtain H-Y. The quartz cell was opened in a glove box where l g of zeolite was transferred to a controlled atmosphere cell used to collect X-ray intensity data. The zeolite powder was pressed into a rectangular cavity in the inside of the back of the X-ray cell which was filled with Ar before removal from the glove box. Vacuum-dehydroxylated Y (HY-DHV) was prepared by transferring the H-Y used for data collection back to the U-tube, heating the sample to 650 C for 6 h in a 10 5 torr vacuum. To minimize possible de-alumination by escaping NH3 and H2O, care was taken to heat the sample in a shallow-bed (1 mm thick) configuration and to increase the temperature slowly from 25 to 650 C under vacuum. The sample was then retransferred to the X-ray sample holder in the glove box. A further sample of NH4-Y containing 2.2% Na was prepared for steam dehydroxylation. NH4-Y was heated under 100% H2O at 600 C, re-exchanged with NH4C1 and reheated in 100% H2O at 890 C to give steam-dehydroxylated Y (Hy-DHSt)
Table 1    RDF spectra for non-framework Al species in HY-DH
HY-DHV	HY-DHSt	Assignment
-	1.86	Al-Ot
-	2.10	Al-0br
2.87	2.91	AI-AI, O-O
3.39	3.35	Al-0
4.12	4.17	Al-O
4.82	4.84	AI-AI, O-O, Al-O
5.79	-	Al-O, O-O
The X-ray diffraction patterns were recorded with a stabilized Philips diffractometer usine a 2,400-W tube with molybdenum anode (?(???a) = 0.710 A) using a technique described earlier31. The radial distribution functions (RDFs) were calculated by Fourier transformation of the scaled intensities as described previously32.
The calculations of the RDFs of the A13O14 clusters were made using the computer program RADMOR developed by D'Antonio and Konnert33 after modification to run on a VAXS 11/780 computer. The program is described in detail in rf. 33 but we include above a brief description of the quantities calculated and parameters used in our calculations.
RADMOR calculates the following expression:
where 4?rp(r) is the probability, weighted by the scattering power of the atomic pair ij, (/j/j), of finding atoms j in a shell of thickness ? r and radius r^ from origin atoms i. w{ is the occupancy of atom i,/i=/i(s = 0)/[/2(s = 0)]1/2 where - 5 = 4p sin ?/ ? - is the reduced, scattering angle independent, scattering factor for atom i, r·^ is the distance between atoms i and j "and oYj(r) includes both the r.m.s. displacement along raj and positional disorder. The first sum is carried out over the n atoms in the asymmetric unit for a crystalline material. The second sum is carried out over the m atoms in the structure that are separated from an atom in the asymmetric unit by less than the maximum distance selected for the calculation. For crystalline materials, space group transformations and unit cell translations are used to generate the atom positions in the second sum.
The pair correlation function, G(r), for a spherical region of radius t is defined as:
where for spherical particles e(r, R) is given by:
When the input model is an infinite crystal, e(r, R) = l and e(r, f) corrects for the fall-off in scattering near the diameter of a finite spherical particle. R is radius of model fragment.
The disorder parameters s? = 0.05 at 1.5 ƒ and 0.19 at 10 ƒ were based on experimental values for SiO2 glass obtained by Konnert and Karle34 and Konnert et al.35. The RDFs of the A13O14 clusters were obtained using the published atomic coordinates of Jadeite36, chantalite37 and Al2(OH)2TeO3SO438.
Fig. 2    RDFs for non-framework Al species in HY-DHV (a) and HY-DHSt (b).
Figure la shows a plot of 4ttt2?( r) against r for ?-? prepared at 300 C in vacuum. The peaks were identified by comparison with calculated distances from the structure refinement of H53 g Na2 2-Y by Gallezot and Imelik39. The T-O value of 1.653 ‚ agrees well with the mean T-O distance of 1.648 ‚ calculated for T = Al0.29Si0.7i from ionic radii40.
The RDF of HY-DHV (Fig. 16) shows significant changes in peak position and poorer resolution of the T-T and O-O peaks at 3.13 and 2.69 ƒ and 4.39 and 3.86 A, respectively.
More useful information is obtained, however, from subtraction of the HY RDF from the HY-DHV RDF. Figure 2a shows that this difference spectrum is characterized by peaks at 2.87, 3.39, 4.12, 4.82 and 5.79 A. Because NMR studies of Freude et al19'20 show that extensive framework de-alumination occurs on dehydroxylation of H-Y at 650 C in vacuum, we attribute the difference spectrum to the non-framework aluminium species.
To confirm that the difference spectrum of Fig. 2a is not an artefact, a further difference spectrum was obtained from the sample of Y dehydroxylated in steam at 890 C (HY-DHSt) (Fig. 2o) using the same H-Y as a reference30. The same prominent peaks as in Fig. 2 a are present, but two additional peaks occur at 1.86 and 2.10 A. It is apparent that a similar residual species is present in both HY-DHV and HY-DHSt.
The Al-O peak at 1.9 A is only barely visible in HY-DHV. Although visible in HY-DHSt, its intensity is less than predicted from the calculated RDF. The increased intensity of the 1.9-‚ peak and the generally narrower peaks for HY-DHSt probably reflect the increased degree of condensation and crystallinity of the NFA species in ultra-stable Y.
Table 1 summarizes the RDF peak positions from the NFA species in the two de-aluminated HY samples. The distances present in the NFA produced at 650 C clearly correspond to a larger Al-OH cluster than the sample species listed earlier, that is, A1(OH)2+, ?1(??)? or [A12O]4+.
Fig. 3    Calculated RDFs for A13O14 clusters.
To help identify the NFA species, we have calculated the RDFs of A13(O,OH)14 groups extracted from the edge-shared octahedral chains in Jadeite, chantalite and A^iOH^TeOsSCV From the RDFs shown in Fig. 3, it can be seen that edge-shared octahedral clusters result in RDF peaks at positions similar to those shown in Table 1. The most prominent peaks occur at 1.9 A (Al-O), 2.8 ‚ (0-O,A1-A1), 3.5 ‚ (Al-O), 3.8 ‚ (O-O), 4.4 ‚ (Al-O), 4.8 A (O-O), 5.5 ‚ (O-O) and 5.9 ‚ (Al-O), where the values in parentheses indicate atom pair interactions calculated separately. This similarity suggests that the NFA species in HY-DHV and HY-DHSt contain edge-shared octahedral AlmOn(OH)p chains.
Two significant differences exist between the NFA peaks and those of the A13(O,OH)14 clusters. First, the NFA peak at 1.9 ‚ is considerably broader and less intense than the 1.9-‚ peak in the chains. The breadth could result from the considerable disorder caused by a large number of terminal OH groups expected in 10-‚ clusters located in the supercages of Y zeolite. The peak at 1.86 ‚ probably corresponds to terminal OH groups whereas the peak at 2.1 ‚ would correspond to bridging OH or O atoms. Second, the NFA peak at 4.1 A is shifted considerably from the typical value of 4.5 A for the A13(O,OH)14 clusters and its intensity is greatly increased. This suggests a different arrangement of the chains from the simple isolated species used for the calculations. Further calculations of RDF spectra for other AlmO"(OH)p(OH2)q clusters and the known crystalline forms of Al oxides and hydroxides are in progress with the hope that one of these will correspond to the difference RDFs of Fig. 2.
It should be emphasized that the NFA species formed in this study corresponds to an advanced stage of de-alumination under shallow-bed conditions. Dehydroxylation of H-Y occurs at 450 C in shallow bed conditions and 300 C in deep-bed conditions19'20. The de-alumination carried out in this study is in the region of substantial dehydroxylation and therefore de-alumination. No attempt has yet been made to look at the de-alumination species obtained at lower temperatures. The species formed at 300-550 C may well be different and could correspond to some of the species proposed to form before condensation as emphasized by Freude et al.19.
Table 2    Peak positions in calculated partial RDFs for AlmO"(OH)p
A\mOn(OH)p	Compound	Al-O	0-0	AI-AI	Al-O	0-0	Al-O	O-O	0-0	Al-O	0-0
A13014	Jadeite	2.00	2.80	3.05	3.70	3.85	4.55	5.00			6.20
A13010(OH)4	Al2(OH)2Te03S04	1.90	2.80	3.00	3.60	3.80	4.40	4.85		6.00	
A1306(OH)8	Chantalite	1.90	2.80	3.00	3.55	3.80	4.45	4.85	5.50	6.00	6.10
We thank P. D. Antonio and J. H. Konnert for making the program RADMOR available and K. H. Gardner for assistance in the RDF calculations.</bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>McDaniel</snm>, <fnm>C. V.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Maher</snm>, <fnm>P. K.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Am. chem. Soc. Monogr.</jtl> <vid>171</vid>, <ppf>285</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>331</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kerr</snm>, <fnm>G. T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Am. chem. Soc. adv. Chem. Ser.</jtl> <vid>121</vid>, <ppf>219</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>229</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>von Ballmoos</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <btl>The <super>19</super>O Exchange Method in Zeolite Chemistry</btl> (Salle-Sauerlander,Frankfurt, <cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Flanigan</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Amer. chem. Soc. Monogr.</jtl> <vid>171</vid>, <ppf>80</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>117</ppl> (<cd year="1976">1976</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Scherzer</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bass</snm>, <fnm>J. L.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Catal.</jtl> <vid>28</vid>, <ppf>101</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>115</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Pichat</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Beaumont</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Barthomeuf</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>JCS Faraday Trans. I</jtl> <vid>70</vid>, <ppf>1402</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1407</ppl> (<cd year="1974">1974</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Eberly</snm>, <fnm>P. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Laurent</snm>, <fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Robson</snm>, <fnm>H. F.</fnm></refau> <i>US Patent</i> 3,506,400 (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lohse</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Alsdorf</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Stach</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Z. Anorg. Allgem. Chem.</jtl> <vid>447</vid>, <ppf>64</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>74</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Weeks</snm>, <fnm>T. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Angell</snm>, <fnm>C. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bolton</snm>, <fnm>A. P. J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Crystalysis</jtl> <vid>38</vid>, <ppf>461</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>468</ppl> (<cd year="1975">1975</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kuhl</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Proc. 3rd int. Conf. Molecular Sieves</jtl>, Zurich, <ppl>277</ppl>&ndash;<ppf>229</ppf> (Leuven University Press, <cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kuhl</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. phys. Chem. Solids</jtl> <vid>38</vid>, <ppf>1259</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1263</ppl> (<cd year="1977">1977</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Patton</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Flanigan</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dowell</snm>, <fnm>L. G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Passoja</snm>, <fnm>D. E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Am. chem. Soc. Symp. Ser.</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>64</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>75</ppl> (<cd year="1977">1977</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Raatz</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Freund</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Marcilly</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <jtl>JCS Faraday Trans. I</jtl> <vid>79</vid>, <ppf>2299</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>2309</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Maher</snm>, <fnm>P. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hunter</snm>, <fnm>F. D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Scherzer</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Am. chem. Soc. edv. Chem. Ser.</jtl> <vid>101</vid>, <ppf>266</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>278</ppl> (<cd year="1971">1971</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Klinowski</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Thomas</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fyfe</snm>, <fnm>C. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gobbi</snm>, <fnm>G. C.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>296</vid>, <ppf>533</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>536</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Engelhardt</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Zeolites</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>59</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>62</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Engelhardt</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lohse</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Patzelova</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Magi</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lippmaa</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Zeolites</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>233</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>238</ppl>; <ppf>239</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>245</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bosacek</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Freude</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Frohlich</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pfeifer</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schmiedel</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Colloid Interf. Sci.</jtl> <vid>85</vid>, <ppf>502</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>507</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Freude</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Frohlich</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pfeifer</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Scheler</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Zeolites</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>171</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>177</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Freude</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Frohlich</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hunger</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pfeifer</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Scheler</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Chem. Phys. Lett.</jtl> <vid>98</vid>, <ppf>263</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>266</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ward</snm>, <fnm>J. W.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Catal.</jtl> <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>348</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>351</ppl> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jacobs</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Uytterhoeven</snm>, <fnm>J. B.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Catal.</jtl> <vid>22</vid>, <ppf>193</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>203</ppl> (<cd year="1971">1971</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jacobs</snm>, <fnm>P. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Uytterhoeven</snm>, <fnm>J. B.</fnm></refau> <jtl>JCS Faraday Trans. I</jtl> <vid>69</vid>, <ppf>373</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>386</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Peri</snm>, <fnm>J. B.</fnm></refau> <i>Proc. 5th intern. Congr. Catalysis</i> (ed. Hightower, J.) <ppf>329</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>341</ppl> (Elsevier, New York, <cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kerr</snm>, <fnm>G. T.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Catal.</jtl> <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>200</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>204</ppl> (<cd year="1969">1969</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Breck</snm>, <fnm>D. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Skeels</snm>, <fnm>G. W.</fnm></refau> <i>Proc. 6th int. Congr. Catalysis</i> Vol. <vid>2</vid> (eds Bond, G. C., Wells, P. B. and Tompkins, F. C.) <ppf>645</ppf> (Chemical Society, London, <cd year="1976">1976</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kuhl</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Am. chem. Soc. Symp. Set.</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>96</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>107</ppl> (<cd year="1977">1977</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Breck</snm>, <fnm>D. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Skeels</snm>, <fnm>G. W.</fnm></refau> <i>Proc. 5th int. Conf. Zeolites</i> (ed. Rees, L. V. C., 335) (Heyden, London, <cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Beran</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jiru</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wichterlova</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. phys. Chem.</jtl> <vid>85</vid>, <ppf>1951</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>1958</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mauge</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> <i>et al.</i> in <btl>Catalysis by Acids and Bases</btl> (ed. Imelik, B.) <ppf>91</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>99</ppl> (Elsevier, Amsterdam, <cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b31"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gallezot</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bergeret</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Catal.</jtl> <vid>72</vid>, <ppf>294</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>302</ppl> (<cd year="1981">1981</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b32"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gallezot</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bienenstock</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Boudart</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Nouv. J. Chim.</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>263</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>266</ppl> (<cd year="1978">1978</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b33"><reftxt><refau><snm>D&apos;Antonio</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Konnert</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. appl. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>459</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>461</ppl> (<cd year="1980">1980</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b34"><reftxt><refau><snm>Konnert</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Karle</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Acta crystallogr.</jtl> A<vid>29</vid>, <ppf>702</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>709</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b35"><reftxt><refau><snm>Konnert</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>D&apos;Antonio</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Karle</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. Non-cryst. Solids</jtl> <vid>53</vid>, <ppf>135</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>141</ppl> (<cd year="1982">1982</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b36"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cameron</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sueno</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Prewitt</snm>, <fnm>C. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Papike</snm>, <fnm>J. J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Am. Miner</jtl> <vid>58</vid>, <ppf>594</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>618</ppl> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b37"><reftxt><refau><snm>Liebich</snm>, <fnm>B. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sarp</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Parthe</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Z. Kristallogr.</jtl> <vid>150</vid>, <ppf>53</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>63</ppl> (<cd year="1979">1979</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b38"><reftxt><refau><snm>Johansson</snm>, <fnm>G. B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lindqvist</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Acta cryst.</jtl> B<vid>32</vid>, <ppf>407</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>411</ppl> (<cd year="1976">1976</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b39"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gallezot</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Imelik</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <jtl>J. chim. Phys.</jtl> <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>816</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>821</ppl> (<cd year="1971">1971</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b40"><reftxt><refau><snm>Shannon</snm>, <fnm>R. D.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Acta crystallogr.</jtl> A<vid>32</vid>, <ppf>751</ppf>&ndash;<ppl>767</ppl> (<cd year="1976">1976</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></headerx>
