<?xml version="1.0"?>

<article id="nrd3810" language="eng" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
    <entity-declarations>
        <entity id="figf1" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-f1.jpg"/>
        <entity id="figf2" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-f2.jpg"/>
        <entity id="figf3" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-f3.jpg"/>
        <entity id="figf4" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-f4.jpg"/>
        <entity id="figf5" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-f5.jpg"/>
        <entity id="figf6" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-f6.jpg"/>
        <entity id="tbl1" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-t1.jpg"/>
        <entity id="tbl2" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-t2.jpg"/>
        <entity id="illus1" url="/nrd/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrd3810-i1.jpg"/>
    </entity-declarations>
    <!--nrd3810-->
    <pubfm>
        <jtl>Nature Reviews Drug Discovery</jtl>
        <vol>11</vol>
        <iss>10</iss>
        <idt>201210</idt>
        <categ id="rv"/>
        <pp>
            <spn>790</spn>
            <epn>811</epn>
            <cnt>22</cnt>
        </pp>
        <issn type="print">1474-1776</issn>
        <issn type="electronic">1474-1784</issn>
        <cpg>
            <cpy>2012</cpy>
            <cpn>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</cpn>
        </cpg>
<chghst>
<chg chgtype="correctn">
<chgperson><fnm>Judith</fnm><snm>Shadwill</snm></chgperson>
<chgdate year="2012" month="10" day="19"/><chgloc><?xm-replace_text {chgloc}?></chgloc>
<chgmade>On page 7 of the main text, LY2382770 was incorrectly referred to as a pan-TGFbeta; ligand-specific blocking antibody; it is a TGFbeta;1 ligand-selective blocking antibody. This has now been corrected online.</chgmade>
<chgreason></chgreason></chg></chghst>	
        <subject code="67" id="67" path="/67" version="1.0" type="npg.subjects"/>
        <subject code="256" id="256" path="/256" version="1.0" type="npg.subjects"/>
        <subject code="109" id="109" path="/109" version="1.0" type="npg.subjects"/>
        <doi>10.1038/nrd3810</doi>
    </pubfm>
    <fm>
        <atl>Targeting the TGFbeta; signalling pathway in disease</atl>
        <aug>
            <cau>
                <fnm>Rosemary J.</fnm>
                <snm>Akhurst</snm>
                <inits>R J</inits>
                <orf rid="a1"/>
                <corf rid="c1"/>
                <bio>
                    <p>Rosemary J. Akhurst is a professor within the Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center at the University of California at San Francisco (UCSF), USA, where she studies the <i>in vivo</i> regulation of transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) action in cancer and angiogenesis. She obtained her Ph.D. at the Beatson Institute for Cancer Research, Glasgow, UK, and was a visiting EMBO research fellow at the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, USA until 1984. She held faculty positions at the University of London, UK, and the University of Glasgow, UK, and a position as senior scientist at Onyx Pharmaceuticals, USA, before joining UCSF in 1999.</p>
                </bio>
            </cau>
            <au>
                <fnm>Akiko</fnm>
                <snm>Hata</snm>
                <inits>A</inits>
                <orf rid="a2"/>
                <bio>
                    <p>Akiko Hata is a professor within the Cardiovascular Research Institute at UCSF, where she studies basic mechanisms of gene regulatory action of the TGFbeta; signalling pathway: in particular, the regulation of microRNA biogenesis. She received her Ph.D. from the Rockefeller University, New York, USA, where she studied the tyrosine kinase pathway in B cells in the laboratory of Hidesaburo Hanafusa. She subsequently completed postdoctoral training at the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, New York, USA, in the laboratory of Joan Massague. During her postdoctoral training, she characterized a role of SMAD proteins as signal transducers of the TGFbeta; superfamily of growth factors. She was an assistant and associate professor of biochemistry at the Tufts University School of Medicine and Molecular Cardiology Research Institute at Tufts Medical Center, Boston, Massachusetts, USA, where she studied the role of the bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) signalling pathway in vascular cells. In June 2011, she moved to her current institution.</p>
                </bio>
            </au>
            <aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center, University of California at San Francisco</org>, <cty>San Francisco</cty>, <st>California</st>
                <zip>94158</zip>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
            <aff><oid id="a2"/><org>Cardiovascular Research Institute, University of California at San Francisco</org>, <cty>San Francisco</cty>, <st>California</st>
                <zip>94158</zip>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
            <caff>
                <coid id="c1"/>
                <email>RAkhurst@cc.ucsf.edu</email>
            </caff>
        </aug>
        <hst>
            <pubdate type="aop" year="2012" month="09" day="24"/>
        </hst>
        <execsumm>
            <p>
                <list id="l1" type="bullet">
                    <li>Transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) has pleiotropic effects on many cell types <i>in vivo</i>, mediated via multiple signalling pathways mdash; canonical and non-canonical</li>
                    <li>TGFbeta; signalling is modulated by other signalling pathways (for example, Notch and RAS).</li>
                    <li>TGFbeta; effects are context-dependent: they are influenced by cell type, growth or differentiation status, and innate genetic variation.</li>
                    <li>TGFbeta; is potently immune-modulatory and signalling is upregulated in, and can exacerbate, many disease states, especially cancer and fibrosis.</li>
                    <li>Drugs for TGFbeta; signalling blockade have been developed that target biosynthesis, activation, ligand and receptor binding as well as downstream responses to TGFbeta;.</li>
                    <li>Drug classes include antisense oligonucleotides (ASOs), ligand traps, antibodies, small-molecule chemical inhibitors, antisense genes, pyrrole-imidazole polyamide DNA binders and gene therapy.</li>
                    <li>In cancer therapy, TGFbeta; blockade may suppress metastasis by targeting tumour-initiating cells, enhancing immune surveillance and cytotoxic T cell activity, modulating the tumour stroma and suppressing angiogenesis.</li>
                    <li>In fibrosis, TGFbeta; blockade suppresses epithelialndash;mesenchymal transition, inhibits myofibroblast differentiation and proliferation, and prevents excessive elaboration of the extracellular matrix.</li>
                    <li>Clinical trials are ongoing for applications in oncology and fibrosis.</li>
                    <li>In oncology, clinical trials show promise with ASOs for malignant glioblastoma and pancreatic cancer, antibodies for metastatic melanoma and renal cell carcinoma, and chemical inhibition for glioblastoma, as well as augmentation of tumour vaccines for non-small-cell lung cancer.</li>
                    <li>In fibrosis, clinical trials show promise for focal segmental glomerulosclerosis and diabetic kidney disease using anti-ligand antibodies, for scleroderma/skin fibrosis using a topical betaglycan mimetic peptide, and for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, glomerulosclerosis and diabetic kidney disease with pirfenidone.</li>
                    <li>Combination therapies of chemotherapy or radiation with TGFbeta; blockade show great promise for oncology.</li>
                    <li>Patient selection will be critical to obtain therapeutic efficacy and minimize side effects.</li>
                </list>
            </p>
        </execsumm>
        <websumm>The transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) signalling pathway is implicated in a variety of disorders, including cancer, fibrosis and inflammation, and has become an attractive target for drug development. Here, Akhurst and Hata present therapeutic strategies for intervening in this pathway and discuss agents currently under investigation while addressing the associated challenges in their development and application.</websumm>
        <abs>
            <p>Many drugs that target transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) signalling have been developed, some of which have reached Phase III clinical trials for a number of disease applications. Preclinical and clinical studies indicate the utility of these agents in fibrosis and oncology, particularly in augmentation of existing cancer therapies, such as radiation and chemotherapy, as well as in tumour vaccines. There are also reports of specialized applications, such as the reduction of vascular symptoms of Marfan syndrome. Here, we consider why the TGFbeta; signalling pathway is a drug target, the potential clinical applications of TGFbeta; inhibition, the issues arising with anti-TGFbeta; therapy and how these might be tackled using personalized approaches to dosing, monitoring of biomarkers as well as brief and/or localized drug-dosing regimens.</p>
        </abs>
    </fm>
    <bdy>
        <p>The transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) superfamily of cytokines, which consists of TGFbeta;s, activins, inhibins, Nodal, bone morphogenetic proteins (BMPs), anti-Muuml;llerian hormone (AMH; also known as Muuml;llerian-inhibiting factor) as well as growth and differentiation factors (GDFs), is conserved through evolution and found in all multicellular organisms<bibr rid="b1"/>. The TGFbeta;s <i>per se</i> are involved in many cellular processes, including growth inhibition, cell migration, invasion, <deflistr rid="df1">epithelialndash;mesenchymal transition</deflistr> (EMT), <deflistr rid="df2">extracellular matrix</deflistr> (ECM) remodelling and immune-suppression<bibr rid="b2"/>. However, although normally dynamically regulated and involved in maintenance of tissue homeostasis, TGFbeta;s are often chronically overexpressed in disease states, including cancer, <deflistr rid="df3">fibrosis</deflistr> and inflammation, and this excessive production of TGFbeta; drives disease progression by modulating cell growth, migration or phenotype. The TGFbeta; signalling pathway has therefore become a popular target for drug development.</p>
        <p>Knowledge about cellular activities gleaned from studying one disease is often applicable to others. For example, inhibition of TGFbeta;-induced EMT mdash; a process that contributes to cancer progression mdash; is a goal not only of oncologists but also of cardiovascular surgeons to prevent neointimal hyperplasia, and of nephrologists and pneumologists in the treatment of fibrosis<bibr rid="b3"/>. In addition, the immune-modulatory activities of TGFbeta; have implications in many diseases, including cancer, cardiovascular disease, asthma, rheumatoid arthritis and multiple sclerosis<bibr rid="b4"/>.</p>
        <p>TGFbeta; action is highly context-dependent and influenced by cell type, culture conditions, interaction with other signalling pathways, developmental or disease stage <i>in vivo</i> and innate genetic variation among individuals<bibr rid="b5 b6 b7 b8 b9"/>. This makes the pathway a particular challenge for drug development. Nevertheless, over the past decade several drugs targeting the TGFbeta; signalling pathway have been developed by pharmaceutical companies and biotechnology firms alike. Drug design strategies have been numerous and include the development of small-molecule inhibitors (SMIs) and monoclonal antibodies, as well as the inhibition of gene expression; some drugs have reached Phase III clinical trials for a number of disease applications, particularly fibrosis and oncology. There is an increasing number of preclinical examples of TGFbeta; inhibitors that are capable of reducing cancer progression and <deflistr rid="df4">metastasis</deflistr>, and that augment existing cancer therapies (such as radiation therapy in breast cancer) while simultaneously guarding against radiation-induced fibrosis<bibr rid="b10"/>. Additionally, there are novel reports of targeting TGFbeta; signalling in less prevalent indications, such as reduction of vascular symptoms of Marfan syndrome (MFS)<bibr rid="b11 b12"/>. Although there have been many reviews on the pleiotropic action of TGFbeta; during tumorigenesis, which is characterized by tumour-suppressing activity of TGFbeta; at an early stage of cancer and tumour-promoting activity at later stages<bibr rid="b13 b14 b15 b16"/>, few focus specifically on drug targets, drug classes and possible therapeutic applications beyond the oncology arena. The translation of anti-TGFbeta; therapies has been pursued most intensively for oncology; however, this Review also discusses the potential of the TGFbeta; signalling pathway as a target for non-neoplastic disease therapies and addresses the associated challenges in the development and application of these strategies.</p>
        <crosshd>The TGFbeta; family</crosshd>
        <p>The vertebrate genome contains more than 30 pleiotropic ligands that belong to the TGFbeta; superfamily, including TGFbeta;s, BMPs, GDFs, activins, inhibins, Nodal and AMH<bibr rid="b1"/>. TGFbeta; has a conserved motif of nine cysteine residues, eight of which form a tight cysteine knot, with the ninth being crucial for homodimerization<bibr rid="b2"/>. Aberrant expression and activity of many of the ligands of the TGFbeta; superfamily are associated with developmental defects and human diseases<bibr rid="b17"/>. Here we focus on TGFbeta;s as there are currently several clinical trials underway involving therapies targeting TGFbeta; signalling, whereas other members of the TGFbeta; superfamily are under-represented in current trials.</p>
        <p>Three highly homologous isoforms of TGFbeta; exist in humans: TGFbeta;1, TGFbeta;2 and TGFbeta;3. They share a receptor complex and signal in similar ways but their expression levels vary depending on the tissue<bibr rid="b18"/>, and their functions are distinct as demonstrated by the phenotypes of knockout mice<bibr rid="b19 b20 b21 b22 b23"/>. Each TGFbeta; ligand is synthesized as a precursor, which forms a homodimer that interacts with its latency-associated peptide (LAP) and a latent TGFbeta;-binding protein (LTBP), forming a larger complex called the large latent complex (LLC). The TGFbeta; activation process involves the release of the LLC from the ECM, followed by further proteolysis of LAP to release active TGFbeta; to its receptors<bibr rid="b2"/>. Matrix metalloproteinase 2 (MMP2) and MMP9 are known to cleave latent TGFbeta;. In addition to MMPs, thrombospondin 1 (THBS1) is known to activate latent TGFbeta;<bibr rid="b24"/>. Alternatively, upon mechanical stretch, alpha;Vbeta;6 integrin can activate TGFbeta; by binding to the RGD motif present in LAP and inducing the release of mature TGFbeta; from its latent complex<bibr rid="b25 b26"/>.</p>
        <crosshd>TGFbeta; signalling</crosshd>
        <p>Proteolytic cleavage, interaction with integrins or pH changes in the local environment are known to activate latent TGFbeta; and free active TGFbeta; for binding to its receptors at the cell membrane. TGFbeta; superfamily members signal via heteromeric complexes of two related transmembrane type I and type II serine/threonine kinase receptors. Five type II receptors and seven type I receptors (also termed activin receptor-like kinases (ALKs)) have been identified. Auxilliary co-receptors (also known as type III receptors) that regulate the access of TGFbeta; superfamily members to signalling receptors also exist. Each subfamily of the TGFbeta; superfamily of ligands binds to type I and type II receptors (<bxr rid="bx1">Box 1</bxr>). BMPs can bind to type I receptors alone and, in their absence, can weakly bind to type II receptors, but they show highest affinity when both receptors act together. TGFbeta; and activin display high affinity only for type II receptors and do not normally interact with isolated type I receptors. Binding to the extracellular domains of type I and type II receptors by the dimeric ligand induces close proximity and a productive conformation for the intracellular serine/threonine kinase domains of the receptors, facilitating the phosphorylation and subsequent activation of the type I receptor. The activation of the type I receptor leads to the propagation of signalling by at least two seemingly independent routes: the <deflistr rid="df5">SMAD</deflistr>-dependent canonical pathway (<bxr rid="bx1">Box 1</bxr>; <figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>) and the SMAD-independent or non-canonical pathways (<bxr rid="bx2">Box 2</bxr>; <figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>).</p>
        <p>In the SMAD-dependent pathway, activation of TGFbeta; receptor type I (Tbeta;RI; also known as TGFBR1 and ALK5) leads to phosphorylation of receptor-specific SMAD (R-SMAD) proteins. SMAD2 and SMAD3 are substrates of Tbeta;RI, whereas type I receptors for BMPs utilize SMAD1, SMAD5 and SMAD8 (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>). Upon phosphorylation by the receptor, R-SMADs together with the common mediator SMAD4 (co-SMAD) translocate to the nucleus, where they interact with other transcription factors (cofactors) to regulate transcriptional responses<bibr rid="b27"/> (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>). In addition to the canonical role of SMADs as transcription factors, a novel role for R-SMADs in the post-transcriptional regulation of <deflistr rid="df6">microRNA</deflistr> (miRNA) biogenesis has been identified<bibr rid="b28"/> (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>). Therefore, the canonical TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD pathway modulates gene expression both transcriptionally and post-transcriptionally to propagate the physiological and pathological activities of TGFbeta;. In the non-canonical pathway, the activated TGFbeta; receptor complex transmits a signal through other factors, such as tumour necrosis factor (TNF) receptor-associated factor 4 (TRAF4), TRAF6, TGFbeta;-activated kinase 1 (TAK1; also known as MAP3K7), p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (p38 MAPK), RHO, phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K), AKT (also known as protein kinase B), extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK), JUN N-terminal kinase (JNK) or nuclear factor-kappa;B (NF-kappa;B) (<bxr rid="bx2">Box 2</bxr>; <figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). Thus, cellular responses to TGFbeta; signalling result from the dynamic combination of canonical and non-canonical signalling cascades. In addition to the complexity generated by the canonical and non-canonical TGFbeta; signalling pathway, TGFbeta; signalling can be influenced by different signalling pathways, including the PI3Kndash;AKT, WNT, Hedgehog (HH), Notch, interferon (IFN), TNF and RAS pathways (<bxr rid="bx2">Box 2</bxr>; <figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). Interactions with several of these pathways can change the output of TGFbeta; signalling from suppressing growth to inducing cellular plasticity<bibr rid="b29"/>. Nuclear accumulation and transcriptional activity of R-SMADs can also be negatively regulated through phosphorylation of multiple Ser-Pro and Thr-Pro residues (in the linker region connecting the MH1 and MH2 domains) by ERK, MAPKs, calcium/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase II and cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs)<bibr rid="b30"/>. The mode and outcome of the crosstalk between TGFbeta; and other signalling pathways vary considerably but are essential to define the activities of TGFbeta; in propagating spatially and temporally specific outputs<bibr rid="b6 b31 b32"/>.</p>
        <crosshd>Biological actions of TGFbeta;</crosshd>
        <p>TGFbeta; is involved in a range of biological processes both during embryogenesis and in adult tissue homeostasis. Although the physiological roles of TGFbeta; have been extensively reviewed elsewhere<bibr rid="b16 b33 b34 b35 b36"/>, the major functions of TGFbeta; that are relevant to the topic of this Review are briefly outlined below.</p>
        <p><bi>Inhibition of cell proliferation.</bi> TGFbeta; strongly inhibits the growth of many cell types, including epithelial, endothelial, haematopoietic and immune cells<bibr rid="b37 b38"/>. TGFbeta; also has pro-apoptotic and differentiation-inducing actions on epithelial cells; together, these actions result in tumour suppression in the context of cancer<bibr rid="b34"/>. TGFbeta; in epithelial cells activates transcription of cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1A (<i>CDKN1A</i>) and <i>CDKN2A</i> (which encode p21<super>CIP1</super> and p15<super>INK4B</super>, respectively) to mediate cell cycle arrest at the G1 phase<bibr rid="b39"/>. Conversely, TGFbeta; represses the transcription of <i>MYC</i>, which encodes a potent transcriptional activator of genes that is required for cell proliferation and growth, and inhibitor of DNA binding (ID) family genes, which encode transcription factors that promote cell differentiation and determination<bibr rid="b40"/>. In oncology, many tumours attenuate TGFbeta; growth-inhibitory effects but respond to this ligand in a pro-tumorigenic manner. Thus, depending on the tumour type and the stage of tumour progression, TGFbeta; may provide potent tumour-suppressive or tumour-promoting functions directly on the tumour cell, presumably by mediating differential gene expression programmes (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3</figr>).</p>
        <p>Unlike the role of TGFbeta; signalling during tumorigenesis, the contribution of TGFbeta; to vascular disease is more complex and confusing. Studies on clinical samples from vascular disorders, such as atherosclerosis, hypertension and pulmonary hypertension, often find signatures of both upregulation and downregulation of TGFbeta; signalling, as well as complex interactions between this pathway and other ligands of the TGFbeta; family, such as BMPs (<bxr rid="bx3">Box 3</bxr>). This has been confirmed by <i>in vitro</i> studies, demonstrating the contradictory effects of TGFbeta; in the regulation of vascular cells<bibr rid="b36 b41"/>. Furthermore, the TGFbeta; pathway often exhibits contrasting effects in different vascular cell types, such as endothelial versus vascular smooth muscle cells<bibr rid="b36"/>. The promiscuous and cell type-specific action of the TGFbeta; pathway on vascular cells makes the application of targeted TGFbeta; signalling therapies for cardiovascular disease a particular challenge.</p>
        <p><bi>Induction of epithelialndash;mesenchymal transition and the myofibroblast phenotype.</bi> TGFbeta; can induce an EMT of both epithelial and endothelial cells. This has consequences for disease progression in both cancer and fibrosis<bibr rid="b3"/>. EMT enhances cellular migration and invasive properties, as cell migration requires loss of cellndash;cell contacts and acquisition of fibroblastic characteristics. E-cadherin is commonly downregulated in many cancers, and its overexpression can suppress invasion by tumour cells. The TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD pathway mediates the expression of high mobility group AT-hook 2 (HMGA2), which is important for the induction of SNAIL (also known as SNAI1) and SLUG (also known as SNAI2): two zinc-finger transcription factors that are known to repress the E-cadherin gene<bibr rid="b33"/>. In breast and skin cancer, tumour cell EMT contributes to cancer progression as cells consequently become more migratory and invasive, and they can ultimately transition to a myofibroblastic phenotype<bibr rid="b3"/>. The <deflistr rid="df7">myofibroblast</deflistr> further modulates the basic biology of the tumour by increasing ECM elaboration and eliciting a tissue contraction process, which results in increased interstitial fluid pressure (IFP). This has consequences for the efficiency of drug delivery to the tumour<bibr rid="b42"/>, as drugs cannot penetrate tissue under positive IFP. EMT can also polarize carcinoma cells towards 'stem cell-like' properties, such as increased tumour-initiating capacity and tumour cell drug resistance<bibr rid="b43"/>. Blocking the TGFbeta; pathway can thus have a threefold benefit: the reduction of tumour invasion and metastasis; the suppression of cancer stem cell-like properties; and the restoration of negative IFP to enhance chemotherapeutic drug delivery<bibr rid="b44"/>.</p>
        <p>In fibrotic conditions, excessive TGFbeta; production induced in the diseased state contributes to EMT elaboration, which can further exacerbate fibrosis, as seen in pulmonary<bibr rid="b45 b46"/>, cardiac<bibr rid="b47"/> and renal<bibr rid="b48 b49"/> fibrosis, and in arterial restenosis following surgical trauma<bibr rid="b50"/>. TGFbeta; can also promote a proliferative and/or migratory phenotype on smooth muscle cells that can aggravate some vascular diseases, including neointimal formation following vascular surgery<bibr rid="b51 b52 b53"/>.</p>
        <p><bi>Extracellular matrix regulation.</bi> The ECM is a complex structure that surrounds mammalian cells. It is the major component of connective tissue and is composed of multiple proteins, such as collagen, elastin, fibrillin, fibronectin, lamin and proteoglycans. Fibrosis is characterized by the accumulation of fibroblasts, which secrete excessive amounts of ECM. As TGFbeta; is widely documented to increase collagen synthesis and deposition by fibroblasts, TGFbeta; has become a central therapeutic target for different types of fibrosis. TGFbeta; activity and the synthesis of ECM proteins are mutually regulated. Several genes encoding ECM proteins that are known to be important in driving fibrosis are directly regulated by TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD signalling pathways. There is a reciprocal regulation of TGFbeta; by the ECM: latent TGFbeta; bound to ECM components, such as fibronectin and fibrillin, is inactive until physiological or pathological processes initiate its release. This is seen in MFS, in which the mutation of a fibrillin-encoding gene results in reduced fibrillin levels and a consequent increase in levels of unbound TGFbeta;; this, in turn, leads to the activation of TGFbeta; signalling, which is possibly responsible for the aetiology of many Marfanoid features<bibr rid="b11 b12"/>.</p>
        <p><bi>Immune-suppression and inflammation.</bi> The lethal postnatal inflammatory phenotype of <i>Tgfb1-</i>knockout mice<bibr rid="b19 b20 b54"/> demonstrates the important immune-suppressor function of this ligand. The widespread expression profile of TGFbeta; receptors on all immune cell types suggests that they have broad activities, including responses in cytotoxic CD8<super>+</super> effector T cells, CD4<super>+</super> effector T helper 1 (T<sub>H</sub>1) and T<sub>H</sub>2 cells, suppressive regulatory T (T<sub>Reg</sub>) cells, natural killer (NK) cells, monocytes, macrophages, neutrophils and eosinophils (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). Cell type-specific mouse gene knockout studies with <i>Tgfbr2</i> demonstrate both direct and indirect actions of TGFbeta; on effector T cells<bibr rid="b4"/>.</p>
        <p>TGFbeta; has potent growth-suppressing activity on most precursor cells of the immune system, particularly T and B cells of the adaptive arm. TGFbeta; is a potent suppressor of T cell proliferation<bibr rid="b55"/> and an inducer of B cell apoptosis<bibr rid="b56"/>. Additionally, the ligand can alter the course of immune cell differentiation. Suppressive T<sub>Reg</sub> cells that are driven by the expression of the transcription factor forkhead box protein P3 (FOXP3) are crucial for maintenance of peripheral immune tolerance as well as regulation of tumour immunity and infection. In CD4<super>+</super> T cells, <i>Foxp3</i> expression is positively but indirectly regulated by TGFbeta;1 through enhanced binding of the SMAD2-induced transcription factor E2A to the <i>Foxp3</i> gene promoter, and by relief from GATA3-mediated transcriptional inhibition of the <i>Foxp3</i> promoter by competition with TGFbeta;-induced <i>Id3</i> (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b57">57</bibrinl>). TGFbeta; suppresses inflammatory T<sub>H</sub>1 and T<sub>H</sub>2 cell differentiation while stimulating suppressor T<sub>Reg</sub> cells. Overall, TGFbeta;-mediated suppression of effector CD8<super>+</super> cytolytic cells and T<sub>H</sub> cells, together with TGFbeta; dependence for suppressive T<sub>Reg</sub> cell differentiation, results in the hyper-inflammatory phenotype seen in <i>Tgfb1</i><super>minus;/minus;</super> mice.</p>
        <p>During tumour progression, excess TGFbeta; suppresses immune surveillance by attenuating the antitumour functions of CD8<super>+</super> T cells, CD4<super>+</super> T cells and dendritic cells. CD4<super>+</super> T cell-specific ablation of TGFbeta; signalling in transgenic mice expressing dominant negative Tbeta;RII (DNRII; also known as CD4-Delta;Tbeta;RII and CD4-Delta;TGFBR2) led to the development of autoimmunity<bibr rid="b58"/> and enhanced the differentiation of CD8<super>+</super> cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs). When challenged with tumour cells, these transgenic mice raised a greater tumour-specific CTL response than wild-type littermates<bibr rid="b58"/>. Tumour-derived TGFbeta; also blocks the differentiation of antigen-presenting dendritic cells<bibr rid="b59"/> and modifies chemokine receptor expression to blunt dendritic cell chemotaxis<bibr rid="b60"/>, further suppressing immune surveillance.</p>
        <p>In addition to having a predominant immune-suppressive function, TGFbeta; counterintuitively may have a pro-inflammatory role through its effects on T<sub>H</sub>17 cells and cells of the innate immune system. TGFbeta;, together with interleukin-6 (IL-6), was reported to be an essential player in driving pro-inflammatory T<sub>H</sub>17 lineage differentiation<bibr rid="b61 b62 b63"/>. However, there is considerable controversy surrounding this topic. First, different laboratories cannot agree on the specific functions of various T<sub>H</sub>1, T<sub>H</sub>2 and T<sub>H</sub>17 cell types in disease progression. T<sub>H</sub>17 cells were implicated as major agonists in inflammatory diseases, including inflammatory cancer, asthma and autoimmune disorders<bibr rid="b55"/>. However, recent studies suggest that the active player in disease progression is in fact a T<sub>H</sub>17-derived T<sub>H</sub>1 cell, or a 'T<sub>H</sub>1-T<sub>H</sub>17' cell<bibr rid="b64"/>. Second, the role of TGFbeta; in regulating the balance between T<sub>H</sub>1 and T<sub>H</sub>17 differentiation is in dispute. Despite the widespread acceptance of a role for TGFbeta; in T<sub>H</sub>17 differentiation<bibr rid="b61 b62 b63"/>, more recent studies have suggested that TGFbeta; is totally dispensable for the generation of these cells<bibr rid="b65 b66"/>.</p>
        <p>With respect to cells of the innate immune system, TGFbeta; directly suppresses NK cell-mediated production of IFNgamma; (which is required for the tumour killing activity of NK cells) through transcriptional effects of SMAD3 on the IFNgamma; promoter<bibr rid="b67"/>. It also 'polarizes' macrophages<bibr rid="b68"/> and neutrophils<bibr rid="b69"/> from a type I, productive phenotype (that evolved to attack and devour foreign agents such as cancer cells) towards a type II phenotype (that has reduced effector function but produces large quantities of inflammatory molecules, such as IL-6, IL-11 and TGFbeta;). These molecules can exacerbate the local diseased state, resulting in solid tumour progression or inflammation associated with fibrosis or atherosclerosis<bibr rid="b4"/>.</p>
        <p>In summary, the regulation of the immune system by TGFbeta; is highly complex and context-dependent. It delicately regulates the tolerogenic versus immunogenic arms of the immune system to balance adequate host defence while limiting collateral inflammatory tissue damage. The molecular details of this regulation have been recently reviewed in depth<bibr rid="b4 b55 b64"/>.</p>
        <crosshd>Targeting TGFbeta; signalling</crosshd>
        <p>Virtually every component of the TGFbeta; pathway has been targeted for drug development (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5</figr>) through numerous design strategies (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6</figr>). Several have been developed through preclinical to clinical trials (<tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr>)and many more have been tested only in preclinical systems (<tablr rid="t2">Table 2</tablr>). The drugs that have progressed furthest in clinical development include anti-ligand <deflistr rid="df8">antisense oligonucleotides</deflistr> (ASOs) from Antisense Pharma<bibr rid="b70 b71 b72 b73 b74"/>, ligand-competitive peptides from Digna Biotech<bibr rid="b75 b76 b77 b78"/>, antibodies that target ligands, receptors or associated proteins spearheaded by Genzyme<bibr rid="b79 b80 b81"/>, and SMIs against TGFbeta; receptor kinases developed by many companies, with Eli Lilly having an active clinical programme in Phase II development<bibr rid="b82"/>. The various approaches currently being investigated are discussed in more detail below.</p>
        <p><bi>Antisense oligonucleotides and antisense RNA.</bi> Antisense Pharma uses the strategy of targeting mRNA translation using ASOs to downregulate ligand synthesis<bibr rid="b70 b83"/>. Its focus has been on targeting TGFbeta;2, which is produced in excessive quantities by glioblastoma and pancreatic carcinoma cells. Trabedersen (AP12009), a synthetic 18-mer phosphorothioate ASO, binds specifically to human <i>TGFBgr;2</i> mRNA, and this drug has progressed to a Phase III clinical trial for oncology applications (<bxr rid="bx4">Box 4</bxr>). One of the challenges of this drug is delivering it directly to the tumour to avoid the off-target toxicity associated with systemic delivery of first-generation ASOs. In the case of glioblastoma, this was achieved using intrathecal catheter delivery directly into the tumour<bibr rid="b74"/>. More recently, the company has started developing intravenous delivery approaches for pancreatic cancer, which appear to be effective in mouse models<bibr rid="b73"/> and were recently shown to be safe in humans<bibr rid="b84"/>.</p>
        <p>An anti-<i>TGFB2</i> antisense strategy has also been used to generate augmented tumour vaccines. Belagenpumatucel-L (Lucanix; NovaRx) is such a drug, in which an sim;900-nucleotide <i>TGFB2</i> antisense construct is transfected into allogeneic non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) cells, which are then used as a tumour vaccine. Here, drug delivery is not an issue as the 'drug' is in fact genetically engineered NSCLC tumour cell lines. This tumour vaccine has superior activity compared to conventional tumour vaccination approaches<bibr rid="b85 b86"/>. A significant dose-related survival difference was seen in patients who received 2.5 times; 10<super>7</super> cells per injection, allowing progression to a Phase III clinical trial<bibr rid="b87"/>.</p>
        <p><bi>Monoclonal antibodies.</bi> The advantages of monoclonal antibodies are their specificity and extracellular mechanism of action mdash; an advantage when trying to mop up excess extracellular ligand. This is tempered by the less convenient intravenous mode of delivery. However, prolonged pharmacokinetic stability permits infrequent drug administration. Cambridge Antibody Technologies and Genzyme developed humanized (or murinized for preclinical studies) monoclonal antibodies specific to individual ligands, such as lerdelimumab (CAT-152)<bibr rid="b88 b89"/> and metelimumab (CAT-192)<bibr rid="b90"/>, or with pan-ligand specificity, such as fresolimumab (GC-1008)<bibr rid="b91 b92 b93"/>. These antibodies have proceeded through various stages of preclinical and clinical development. Of these three humanized antibodies, fresolimumab has progressed furthest in the clinic for both neoplastic and non-neoplastic applications. This drug was found to be well tolerated and safe at 15 mg per ml in Phase I trials for metastatic melanoma (MetM) plus renal cell carcinoma<bibr rid="b93"/> and at 1 mg per ml for the fibrotic disorder focal segmental glomerulosclerosis<bibr rid="b92"/>. Lerdelimumab<bibr rid="b88 b89"/> and metelimumab<bibr rid="b90"/>, despite passing safety tests, failed to show efficacy in fibrotic models of corneal scarring and systemic sclerosis, respectively, and were therefore discontinued<bibr rid="b90"/>. Despite a promising Phase I oncology trial of fresolimumab, after Genzyme was acquired by Sanofi the company made the decision to focus on fibrotic applications of this drug.</p>
        <p>Eli Lilly entered the monoclonal antibody arena with a TGFbeta;1 ligand-selective blocking antibody, LY2382770, which has progressed to Phase II trials for kidney fibrosis (<tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr>). Since merging with ImClone, Eli Lilly has also developed a Tbeta;RII-blocking antibody, IMC-TR1 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b94">94</bibrinl>), which has just entered clinical trials for breast and colon cancer (<weblink url="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov/
">ClinicalTrials.gov</weblink> identifier: NCT01646203). In addition, Biogen Idec and Stromedix have developed an anti-integrin beta;6 antibody that prevents the activation of TGFbeta; and has been used efficaciously in preclinical studies of fibrosis and cancer<bibr rid="b95"/>; it is in a Phase II trial for fibrosis (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT01371305).</p>
        <p><bi>Ligand traps and peptides.</bi> Genzyme developed a ligand trap by fusing Fcgamma; to the extracellular domain of Tbeta;RII, but this construct never reached clinical trials<bibr rid="b96"/>. However, an alternative ligand trap approach, pursued by Digna Biotech, using peptide mimetics of Tbeta;RIII (also known as betaglycan and TGFBR3), completed a Phase IIa clinical trial for scleroderma and skin fibrosis, showing safety and efficacy when topically applied to skin (<tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr>; <bxr rid="bx4">Box 4</bxr>). This company has plans to extend to Phase IIb/III trials in 2013 (J. Dotor, personal communication). A peptide antagonist of TGFbeta; activation, LSKL (Leu-Ser-Lys-Leu), binds to a conserved sequence in the LAP region of the latent complex and has demonstrated efficacy in reducing TGFbeta; signalling <i>in vitro</i><bibr rid="b97"/>. This antagonist is based on thrombospondin and specifically blocks TGFbeta; activation. The issue of peptide drug delivery is not a problem for topical application; however, to progress to systemic delivery, Digna Biotech has partnered with Flamel Technologies to investigate proprietary peptide delivery systems.</p>
        <p><bi>Small-molecule inhibitors.</bi> There are a plethora of SMIs that specifically target the type I receptor of TGFbeta; to inhibit the phosphorylation of SMAD2 and SMAD3 while keeping at least some non-canonical responses, such as TAK1 activation, intact. These drugs are generally ATP mimetics that bind competitively within the hydrophobic ATP binding pocket of the receptor kinase. The chemistry of these compounds has been extensively reviewed<bibr rid="b98 b99"/> and some molecular structures are shown in <figr rid="f6">Fig. 6</figr>. The obvious advantages of these molecules over most others are their economical production, stability and ease of oral administration, set against a possible disadvantage of cross-inhibition of other kinases. The short half-life of these drugs provides the possibility of rapid drug withdrawal should adverse events arise. Many successful preclinical studies for metastatic cancer have been undertaken with these SMIs, as reviewed previously<bibr rid="b100 b101"/>. However, the only company to continue pursuit of a Tbeta;RI-targeted SMI into clinical trials for oncology is Eli Lilly with LY2157299 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b82">82</bibrinl>) (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT01373164).</p>
        <p><bi>Other approaches.</bi> A novel approach to the suppression of ligand production has been the preclinical development of pyrrole-imidazole polyamides that bind with sequence specificity to the <i>TGFB1</i> gene promoter to attenuate gene expression<bibr rid="b50 b102 b103"/>. These large sim;17 kDa polymeric molecules (<figr rid="f5">Figs 5</figr>,<figr rid="f6">6</figr>) bind within the minor groove of DNA to prevent transcription factor binding. Challenges associated with these drugs include the specificity of promoter binding, along with drug delivery issues owing to their large molecular size and the high local concentration required for activity. However, preclinical studies suggest that these molecules might be used in drug-eluting stents for the purpose of reducing restenosis after coronary or carotid artery surgery<bibr rid="b50"/>.</p>
        <p>An alternative approach to suppress TGFbeta; signalling is gene transfer of antagonizing signalling molecules, such as the inhibitory SMAD7. This approach has been applied in model systems to treat or prevent various pathological conditions, including colonic and hepatic fibrosis, vascular remodelling and diabetic kidney disease<bibr rid="b104 b105"/>. Such an application has the potential to be applied to many other systemic diseases to attenuate the activity of the TGFbeta; pathway, with the caveat that gene therapy is still far from being widely accepted as a therapeutic approach<bibr rid="b106"/>.</p>
        <p>As an approach to stimulate immune destruction of cancer cells by tumour-infiltrating T cells, human tumour antigen-specific CTLs have been engineered to express DNRII using a clinical grade retrovirus vector. TGFbeta;-resistant CTLs were found to have a functional advantage over unmodified CTLs in clearing TGFbeta;- secreting Epsteinndash;Barr virus (EBV)-positive lymphoma <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i><bibr rid="b107"/>, and this approach to therapy has progressed to a Phase I clinical trial for EBV-positive lymphoma. A further modification of the CTLs, by engineering in an HER2 (also known as ERBB2) chimeric receptor as well as a DNRII, allows the CTLs to target HER2-positive tumour cells<bibr rid="b108 b109 b110 b111"/>. This approach is in a Phase I clinical trial for advanced HER2-positive lung malignancy, labelled the HERCREEM trial (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT00889954).</p>
        <p>Finally, Renova has developed a recombinant TGFbeta;3 ligand as an anti-scarring agent on the basis of the hypothesis that this ligand has activity that is independent of and antagonistic to TGFbeta;1 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b112">112</bibrinl>). The drug, administered by injection around a surgical wound site, progressed to a Phase III clinical trial, but unfortunately it did not reach its primary or secondary efficacy end points.</p>
        <p><bi>Pre-existing drugs that inhibit TGFbeta;.</bi> Pre-existing drugs that have been extensively used for other applications may act, in part, by inhibiting TGFbeta;. Examples are losartan and candesartan, which are angiotensin type II receptor inhibitors that were originally developed for the treatment of hypertension. Both appear to reduce TGFbeta; signalling, although the precise molecular mechanisms of this action are still unclear<bibr rid="b12 b113 b114 b115"/>. Pirfenidone acts in part by reducing the fibrotic effects of TGFbeta;<bibr rid="b116"/> via unknown targets. It is the first approved drug in Europe for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF), and is in a Phase III trial in the United States<bibr rid="b117 b118"/>. On the other side of the coin, some common drugs, including aspirin, elevate circulating TGFbeta; levels, which mdash; in certain cases such as arteriosclerosis mdash; correlates with disease suppression<bibr rid="b119"/>.</p>
        <crosshd>Therapeutic uses of TGFbeta; signalling inhibition</crosshd>
        <p><bi>Cancer.</bi> TGFbeta; has a biphasic action during tumorigenesis, suppressing tumorigenesis at early stages but promoting tumour progression later on (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3</figr>). This is a paradigm for the action of TGFbeta; during disease progression in general, including that of fibrosis, inflammation and cardiovascular disease, and it is rooted in the fact that the normal function of this ligand is in the regulation of homeostasis. During disease progression, TGFbeta; signalling can go into override and, once unharnessed, results in more damage than good. The main goal in cancer therapy is therefore to downmodulate excessive levels of TGFbeta; ligands.</p>
        <p>A major challenge in developing TGFbeta; inhibitors for cancer therapy has been the fact that these compounds are not cytotoxic or cytostatic to most tumour cells <i>in vitro</i>. They were developed to target properties of the tumour that are required for cancer progression, including migration, invasion and metastasis, as well as effects on the tumour microenvironment (<figr rid="f3">Figs 3</figr>,<figr rid="f4">4</figr>). Standard cytotoxic screens used by the pharmaceutical industry to identify anticancer drugs were therefore not relevant, and therapeutic utility could only be determined by <i>in vivo</i> efficacy in animal models and ultimately in the clinic.</p>
        <p>Two major concerns in TGFbeta; drug development have been the inadvertent inhibition of the tumour-suppressing arm of TGFbeta; signalling in cancer<bibr rid="b120 b121 b122"/> and the development of adverse side effects unrelated to cancer, such as widespread inflammation, autoimmunity or cardiovascular defects that have been revealed by mouse gene knockout studies<bibr rid="b19 b20 b21 b123"/>. Preclinical studies suggested that attenuation of TGFbeta;-mediated growth inhibition would not be a major issue<bibr rid="b96 b124 b125"/>. However, clinical trials to date<bibr rid="b82"/> have not revealed the cardiac valvulopathy<bibr rid="b126"/> or hyperostosis and chondrocyte hypertrophy and hyperplasia<bibr rid="b127"/> observed in rat preclinical toxicology studies. Moreover, there has been no widespread evidence of inflammatory complications in clinical trials reported to date<bibr rid="b54 b82"/>. These reassuring safety findings are supported by evidence from patients with the rare disease multiple self-healing squamous epithelioma (MSSE), who have germline-null mutations in the gene encoding Tbeta;RI but develop only self-limiting and mostly non-malignant skin lesions<bibr rid="b128"/>. Intriguingly, in a Phase I clinical trial of GC-1008 for the treatment of MetM, patients developed skin lesions, keratoacanthoma or squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) that were similar to the skin abnormalities reported in MSSE, with the appearance of keratoacanthoma and SCC seemingly influenced by the extent of exposure to GC-1008. These lesions, which appeared on sun-damaged skin, were manifested in approximately 25% of patients who received higher dose levels of GC-1008 and/or longer exposure to the drug, and the lesions resolved on drug withdrawal<bibr rid="b91 b93"/>. To put this toxicity into context, non-melanoma skin cancers, such as SCC and keratoacanthoma, develop in approximately 15ndash;30% of patients with MetM who are treated with BRAF inhibitors such as vemurafenib and dabrafenib<bibr rid="b129"/>, and therapy with sorafenib and TNF antagonists produced similar findings<bibr rid="b130 b131"/>. Recent data from studies with vemurafenib for MetM therapy suggest that these lesions arise from pre-existent mutant RAS-containing cells within sun-damaged skin<bibr rid="b132"/>. Intriguingly, one study of keratoacanthoma that appeared in sorafenib-treated patients showed somatic <i>TGFBR1</i> missense mutations<bibr rid="b133"/>, one of which was also identified as a causative germline mutation for MSSE<bibr rid="b128"/>.</p>
        <p>Cancer 'stem cells', or <deflistr rid="df9">tumour-initiating cells</deflistr> (TICs), are defined by their capacity to self-renew and to initiate and persistently propagate the entire tumour. Targeting the cancer stem cell for destruction or irreversible quiescence is therefore the Holy Grail of oncology, especially as these cells are exceedingly resistant to both chemotherapy and radiotherapy, and are responsible for tumour metastasis and recurrence after therapy<bibr rid="b134"/>. Several groups have now reported the phenomenon that TGFbeta;-induced EMT can drive tumour cells towards a more 'stem cell-like' phenotype characterized by increased expression of stem cell markers and enhanced tumour-initiating activity <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i><bibr rid="b43 b135"/>. In breast cancer<bibr rid="b135"/>, the TGFbeta; and WNT signalling pathways were shown to be the most commonly activated signalling pathways in cancer stem cells that had been fractionated from the bulk tumour on the basis of expression of stem cell markers such as CD44<super>hi</super> and CD24<super>low</super>. In preclinical studies, TGFbeta; inhibitors have been shown to deplete the stem cell compartment in various cancers mdash; including breast cancer<bibr rid="b135"/>, glioblastoma<bibr rid="b136 b137 b138"/> and chronic myeloid leukaemia<bibr rid="b139"/> mdash; which leads to increased lifespan in several mouse models of metastatic cancer. Anido <i>et al</i>.<bibr rid="b137"/> showed that glioblastoma-initiating cells (GICs, which express the stem cell markers CD44, ID1, ID3, SOX2 and SOX4) responded to LY2109761 by downregulating the expression of 'stem cell' genes. Moreover, patient-derived glioblastoma neurospheres transplanted orthotopically into non-obese diabetic/severe combined immunodeficient mice (NOD/SCID mice, which do not have T cells or B cells) responded to LY2109761 by decreasing in size and reducing their expression of stem cell markers<bibr rid="b137"/>. The same research team is currently undertaking a Phase I/II clinical trial for glioblastoma using the closely related drug LY2157299 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b137">137</bibrinl>). Importantly, they showed a reduction of CD44 and ID1 RNA levels after 2 months of LY2157299 treatment in tumour biopsy material from one patient with glioblastoma for whom a salvage surgical resection was performed both before and after 2 months on the trial<bibr rid="b137"/>. The ability to reduce the number of stem cells in an aggressive tumour such as glioblastoma is a major coup.</p>
        <p>It has been argued that TGFbeta; inhibitors might, however, release isolated and disseminated tumour (stem) cells from dormancy by initiating proliferation and/or disrupting the stem cell niche. A couple of recent studies may give credence to this notion, as systemic TGFbeta; inhibition resulted in increased numbers of circulating tumours as well as micro- and macro-metastases in mouse models of head and neck SCC and mammary cancer <i>in vivo</i><bibr rid="b140 b141"/>. It might therefore be wise to use TGFbeta; inhibitors in combination with cytotoxic drugs to coax tumour cells out of their quiescent niche while simultaneously targeting those that respond proliferatively to TGFbeta; inhibition using chemotherapy. This strategy may be highly beneficial for 'flushing out' dormant disseminated tumour cells, as alluded to by Carlos Arteaga many years ago<bibr rid="b142"/>. A further cautionary note is warranted, however, on the basis of two reports indicating that TGFbeta; may decrease the cancer-initiating cell population of diffuse type gastric carcinoma<bibr rid="b143"/> and breast carcinoma<bibr rid="b144"/> despite having little or no effect on cellular proliferation. Finally, TGFbeta; inhibitors might act on the stem cell niche by recruiting bone marrow mesenchymal stem cell-derived myofibroblasts that home in on the primary tumour, contribute to the tumour microenvironment as cancer-associated fibroblasts and consequently promote tumour progression<bibr rid="b145"/>. Clearly there are tissue- and cell type-specific effects of TGFbeta; inhibition that can influence the action of TGFbeta; on the cancer stem cell and its niche<bibr rid="b146"/>. Understanding the differential molecular mechanisms that elicit these variable responses will be critical to a judicious choice of treatment with TGFbeta; inhibitors or their derivatives. As TGFbeta; inhibitors are not directly cytotoxic, the use of these inhibitors in combination with cytotoxic chemotherapeutics may be particularly efficacious. The activation of TGFbeta; signalling in response to chemotherapeutics may drive the generation of cancer stem cells (via EMT), resulting in their chemoresistance<bibr rid="b134"/>. This event may be targeted with TGFbeta; inhibitors, as demonstrated by the synergistic activity of doxorubicin and TGFbeta; inhibitor combination therapy on breast cancer growth and metastasis<bibr rid="b147"/>. Studies in multiple myeloma also suggest that TGFbeta; inhibitors could potentiate the cytotoxic effects of melphalan and dexamethasone<bibr rid="b148"/>. <i>In vitro</i>, the exposure of multiple myeloma cells to differentiated versus immature MC3T3-E1 pro-osteoblastic cells potentiated chemotherapy-induced multiple myeloma cell death. As TGFbeta; inhibition acts within the bone microenvironment to elicit osteoblastic differentiation<bibr rid="b148 b149"/>, this combinatorial approach holds great promise for the treatment of multiple myeloma and other bone metastatic cancers. Likewise, in a mouse model of serous gastric cell carcinoma, Ki26894 had an additive effect with a fluorouracil analogue in reducing tumour growth<bibr rid="b150"/>. Finally, another mechanism whereby TGFbeta; inhibition can augment conventional therapies is in enhancing drug delivery to the tumour. There are reports that TGFbeta; inhibition can reduce interstitial tumour pressure<bibr rid="b44"/>, which enhances the delivery of SMIs, and regulates vascular leakiness, which enhances the delivery of nanoparticle-encapsulated drugs, particularly in highly fibrotic and drug-refractile tumour types such as pancreatic cancer<bibr rid="b151"/>.</p>
        <p>Adoptive T cell therapy involves the harvesting and <i>ex vivo</i> expansion of autologous tumour-specific CTLs followed by their reintroduction into the patient to stimulate tumour killing<bibr rid="b152"/>. Used most extensively in the treatment of MetM and lung cancer, this therapy often fails owing to the apoptosis of re-grafted CTLs. Preclinical studies suggest that failure may be due to the direct effects of TGFbeta; on CTLs<bibr rid="b153"/>, and strategies to prevent such failure include the use of genetically modified CTLs with reduced TGFbeta; responsiveness. Transduction of CTLs with a virus encoding a DNRII<bibr rid="b154"/> has reached Phase I clinical trials, and recent preclinical data indicate that combining CTL therapy with Tbeta;RI-targeting SMIs may also significantly improve T cell survival and antitumour T cell cytotoxicity<bibr rid="b155"/>. Augmenting adoptive T cell therapy with SMIs may be a particularly attractive application of Tbeta;RI SMIs as patients need not be exposed to genetically engineered T cells. Moreover, patients might only require short-term exposure to the drug for efficacy in this application, thus avoiding the side effects of long-term SMI drug exposure, such as inflammation<bibr rid="b19"/>, cardiovascular complications<bibr rid="b126"/>, bone and/or cartilage problems<bibr rid="b127"/>, subphyseal hyperostosis as well as chondrocyte hypertrophy and/or hyperplasia, and reducing the risk of developing SMI drug resistance<bibr rid="b156"/>.</p>
        <p>Another clinical application with great promise is augmenting radiotherapy by inhibiting the TGFbeta; pathway<bibr rid="b10 b81 b157"/>. Radiation not only physically activates latent TGFbeta;
            <i>in vitro</i> but also induces the biological release of this growth factor as part of a stress response<bibr rid="b158"/>. Several groups have reported the positive role of TGFbeta; in supporting the DNA damage repair pathway, particularly through activation of p53 and phosphorylation of ataxia telangiectasia mutated (ATM) after radiation therapy<bibr rid="b159"/>. Barcellos-Hoff's group demonstrated that LY2109761 and ID11 both attenuate radiation-induced activation of p53 and ATM in breast cancer cells <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i>, thus preventing DNA repair and accentuating the cytotoxic effect of radiation<bibr rid="b81"/>. Even short-term dosing with Tbeta;RI inhibitors might provide a considerable therapeutic advantage in potentiating radiotherapy, with the added benefit that the local activation of pro-tumorigenic stroma and tissue fibrosis mdash; a major complication of radiation therapy<bibr rid="b10"/> mdash; may also be suppressed by these drugs. In partnership with Genzyme, this group is currently undertaking a Phase I trial of fresolimumab in combination with radiotherapy for metastatic breast cancer. Eli Lilly is also undertaking a Phase I/IIa trial to test the safety and efficacy of LY2157299 in combination with temozolomide-based radiochemotherapy in patients with newly diagnosed malignant glioma<bibr rid="b157"/>.</p>
        <p><bi>Myelodysplastic syndrome.</bi> Myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) is characterized by abnormal myeloid and/or erythroid differentiation of bone marrow cells that results in various anaemias and cytopaenias. In one-third of MDS cases, a high-risk group of patients can progress to leukaemia. However, refractory cytopaenias are the major cause of morbidity and mortality in sufferers. It was recently shown that reduced expression of SMAD7, an inhibitor of Tbeta;RI, was a common and significant event observed in CD34<super>+</super> myeloid progenitor cells in the bone marrow of patients with MDS<bibr rid="b160"/>. Indeed, low levels of myeloid SMAD7 expression were seen in most patients with MDS, regardless of the risk for progression to leukaemia. Downregulation of SMAD7 expression sensitized myeloid precursors to TGFbeta; such that even very low levels of the ligand elicited an increase in TGFbeta; responsiveness, as defined by P-SMAD2 levels and enhanced immune-suppressive effect, thus providing another opportunity to utilize TGFbeta; inhibitors for therapeutic utility in human disease.</p>
        <p>Treatment of primary CD34<super>+</super> haematopoietic stem cells with LY2157299 suppressed the activation of Tbeta;RI by its ligand. Moreover, in a liver-specific TGFbeta;1-overexpressing transgenic mouse model of MDS that exhibits severe anaemia, LY2157299 decreased P-SMAD2 levels in the bone marrow and significantly increased the haematocrit of these mice. Importantly, in ten out of ten primary bone marrow cultures from patients with MDS, administration of LY2157299 significantly increased erythroid (burst-forming unit (BFU-E)) and myeloid (colony-forming unit (CFU); granulocytic monocytic) colony numbers <i>in vitro</i>, harbouring great promise for the treatment of patients with MDS<bibr rid="b160"/>.</p>
        <p><bi>Fibrosis.</bi> IPF is a progressive, chronic and irreversible lung disease occurring in older adults, and has an unknown cause<bibr rid="b161"/>. The main histological features of IPF are heterogeneous parenchyma, with areas of fibrosis and honeycombing alternating with areas of less-affected or normal parenchyma. IPF is characterized by a progressive reduction in lung function, with an estimated 20% survival prospect after 5 years, making it more lethal than many cancers. The progressive fibrotic reaction in IPF is associated with an epithelium-dependent fibroblast activation, in which TGFbeta; plays a major part<bibr rid="b16"/>. TGFbeta;1, which is secreted by alveolar epithelial cells in patients with IPF, drives the process by promoting the migration, proliferation and differentiation of resident mesenchymal cells. alpha;Vbeta;6 integrin, which binds and activates latent TGFbeta;1 and TGFbeta;3, is highly induced following lung injury or fibrosis<bibr rid="b162"/>. TGFbeta; activity<bibr rid="b163"/> then promotes activation and differentiation of fibroblasts into myofibroblasts, which are specialized contractile cells that cause aberrant ECM deposition, leading to the destruction of lung architecture, scarring<bibr rid="b162"/> and reduced lung function. TGFbeta; also promotes pulmonary EMT that additionally contributes to the expansion of fibroblasts and myofibroblasts<bibr rid="b164"/>.</p>
        <p>Pirfenidone, a novel compound that inhibits TGFbeta; activity <i>in vitro</i>, decreased the rate of decline in vital lung capacity and marginally increased progression-free survival in patients with IPF. Pooled data from two concurrent Phase III clinical trials in IPF indicated improvement in pulmonary function in the pirfenidone-treated group<bibr rid="b165"/>. Currently, there are no US Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved drugs for IPF, and pirfenidone is the first such drug to be approved for IPF in Europe. Other approaches to develop TGFbeta;-based therapies for IPF include gene transfer of a soluble Tbeta;RII construct (as a ligand decoy), which attenuated injury and fibrosis in bleomycin-induced IPF in mice<bibr rid="b166"/>. P144 (disitertide; Digna Biotech), a synthetic peptide that attenuates TGFbeta; activity and is derived from the extracellular domain of betaglycan, was also shown to reduce carbon tetrachloride-induced liver injury in mice<bibr rid="b78"/>. P17, another Digna Biotech anti-TGFbeta; peptide, has been shown to be efficacious in attenuation of injury and fibrosis in bleomycin-induced IPF in mice<bibr rid="b167"/>. Although P144 has been used clinically for skin fibrosis, drug delivery is an issue for the clinical development of P144 for IPF. However, Digna Biotech has recently partnered with Flamel Technologies to investigate the use of a proprietary drug delivery platform for this application (see the <weblink url="http://www.dignabiotech.com/comun/fichero.asp?id=105
">press release</weblink>: 'Flamel Technologies and Digna Biotech Announce Multiple Product Development Agreement'). Other anti-TGFbeta; therapies in clinical trials for IPF include the pan TGFbeta;-neutralizing antibody GC-1008 (Genzyme) and the alpha;Vbeta;6 integrin-blocking antibody STX-100 (Stromedix)<bibr rid="b168 b169"/>.</p>
        <p>Renal fibrosis has long been thought to be driven by excess TGFbeta;, which results in renal scarring and, ultimately, kidney failure<bibr rid="b170"/>. With the increasing incidence of diabetes and associated kidney damage in affluent countries, this is a clinical application of growing importance. Mice overexpressing an active form of TGFbeta;1 (from the liver) develop progressive liver and renal fibrosis<bibr rid="b170"/>. Interestingly, although mice overexpressing active TGFbeta;1 develop progressive renal injury, latent TGFbeta;1 also has a protective role in renal fibrosis through negative effects on inflammation<bibr rid="b49"/>. TGFbeta;1 mediates progressive renal fibrosis by stimulating the synthesis of ECM production while inhibiting its degradation<bibr rid="b49"/>. TGFbeta;1 also mediates renal fibrosis by inducing the transformation of tubular epithelial cells into myofibroblasts through EMT in a similar way to the process seen in IPF<bibr rid="b171"/>. Blockade of TGFbeta;1 with neutralizing TGFbeta; antibodies prevents or ameliorates renal fibrosis <i>in vivo</i> and <i>in vitro</i>, demonstrating the functional role of TGFbeta;1 in EMT and renal fibrosis. A number of therapeutic interventions that block the action of TGFbeta; have resulted in various degrees of improvement in kidney structure and function in preclinical studies; such interventions include TGFbeta; ASOs, a neutralizing anti-TGFbeta; antibody, a soluble TGFbeta; receptor, blockade of TGFbeta; activation by decorin<bibr rid="b172"/>, an SMI of TGFbeta; receptors, delivery of the inhibitor protein SMAD7 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b173">173</bibrinl>) and a THBS1-blocking peptide that interferes with TGFbeta; activation<bibr rid="b97"/>. A Phase I/II trial with GC-1008, a pan-TGFbeta;-neutralizing antibody, exhibited encouraging efficacy in patients with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis<bibr rid="b92"/>, and Eli Lilly is undertaking trials of its own anti-TGFbeta;1 monoclonal antibody, LY2382770, in diabetic kidney disease.</p>
        <p>Cardiac fibrosis is a pathological feature that is common to a number of forms of heart disease, including myocardial infarction, ischaemic, dilated and hypertrophic cardiomyopathies and congestive heart failure<bibr rid="b36"/>. The cellular basis of cardiac fibrosis is the aberrant accumulation of collagens and other ECM proteins, which impair ventricular function and predispose to cardiac arrhythmias. Because TGFbeta; has pleiotropic effects in the cardiovascular system and as cardiac fibrosis is a multifactorial disease, the development of an effective therapy will require a detailed understanding of the role of the TGFbeta; signalling pathway in this pathogenesis. TGFbeta;, a potent stimulator of collagen production by cardiac fibroblasts, is induced in response to cardiovascular injury. The TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD pathway activates the transcription of several key fibrotic genes, such as those encoding connective tissue growth factor (CTGF), fibronectin, collagens and plasminogen activator inhibitor 1 (PAI1)<bibr rid="b36"/>. TGFbeta; reduces collagenase production and stimulates the expression of tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases (TIMPs), resulting in an overall inhibition of ECM degradation and leading to excessive ECM accumulation. P144 has been investigated in a preclinical model of cardiac fibrosis<bibr rid="b77"/>, and losartan can reverse fibrosis in a mouse model of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy<bibr rid="b174"/>; however, no drug targeting the TGFbeta; pathway has yet reached clinical trials for this application. A recent study demonstrated that miR-21, which is regulated by SMADs upon TGFbeta; activation, is consistently induced by cardiac stress. As miR-21 plays a part in tumorigenesis by promoting cell proliferation, increased expression of miR-21 might contribute to the progression of fibrotic lesions<bibr rid="b175"/>. ASOs against miR-21 might therefore become a novel therapeutic approach for treating cardiac fibrosis.</p>
        <p><bi>Scleroderma.</bi> Scleroderma (progressive systemic sclerosis) is a systemic autoimmune disorder characterized by skin sclerosis, calcinosis and changes in microvasculature. Increased expression of Tbeta;RI and Tbeta;RII in sclerodermal fibroblasts suggests that increased production of type I collagen by autocrine TGFbeta; signalling leads to aberrant ECM deposition and scarring<bibr rid="b36"/>. Therapeutic approaches to scleroderma have included inhibition of TGFbeta; activity in sclerotic tissue. Unfortunately, CAT-192, a TGFbeta;1-neutralizing antibody, did not show evidence of efficacy in a study on the treatment of patients with early-stage systemic scleroderma<bibr rid="b90"/>; however, GC-1008 is now in a Phase I clinical trial for patients with diffuse systemic sclerosis. Furthermore, topical application of Digna Biotech's P144 peptide inhibitor of TGFbeta;1 has shown some efficacy in reducing skin fibrosis in a Phase II clinical trial for systemic sclerosis (see the press release: 'Flamel Technologies and Digna Biotech Announce Multiple Product Development Agreement'), with the caveat that clinical end points for quantifying skin fibrosis have not yet been standardized<bibr rid="b176"/>.</p>
        <p><bi>Restenosis following coronary artery bypass and angioplasty.</bi> The development of fibromuscular intimal hyperplasia following angioplasty and coronary artery bypass surgery is a major clinical problem and can lead to coronary artery graft failure. The success of coronary artery reconstructive procedures is limited by the high incidence of restenosis secondary to intimal hyperplasia. TGFbeta;1 is a major player in the early development of intimal hyperplasia in arteries and peripheral vein grafts. The exact mechanism of action of TGFbeta; signalling in intimal hyperplasia and subsequent graft failure is unclear, but it is speculated that TGFbeta;1 contributes at multiple steps, including EMT, promotion of fibroblast, endothelial and vascular smooth muscle cell proliferation, increased collagen synthesis and deposition, and induction of fibrosis<bibr rid="b177"/>. Soluble forms of the small, leucine-rich proteoglycans decorin and fibromodulin, which possess TGFbeta;-antagonist activity, exhibit potent intimal hyperplasia-suppressing effects in cultured human saphenous vein, offering the potential for therapeutic benefit after coronary artery bypass surgery<bibr rid="b178 b179 b180"/>. The novel pyrrole-imidazole polyamide drug class, targeted to suppress <i>TGFB1</i> gene transcription, showed efficacy in reducing neointimal hyperplasia and stimulating re-endothelialization of carotid arteries in a preclinical model of arterial injury<bibr rid="b50"/>.</p>
        <p><bi>Marfan syndrome.</bi> MFS is a connective tissue disorder that affects the musculoskeletal, ocular and cardiovascular systems. It is caused by mutations in the gene encoding an ECM protein, fibrillin 1 (<i>FBN1</i>)<bibr rid="b181"/>. Growing evidence suggests that <i>FBN1</i> mutations perturb not only the general integrity and elasticity of tissues but also mdash; probably more crucially mdash; local TGFbeta; signalling<bibr rid="b11"/>. Normal fibrillin 1-containing microfibrils interact with the large latent TGFbeta; complex (LLC) to control the release of mature, active TGFbeta;<bibr rid="b181"/>. Mutated fibrillin 1 fails to sequester latent TGFbeta;, leading to the promiscuous activation of TGFbeta;<bibr rid="b11"/>. Thus, MFS highlights the critical role of microfibrils in regulating local concentrations of TGFbeta; and in maintaining the homeostasis, morphogenesis and function of various organs<bibr rid="b181"/>. Dilation of the aortic root, which leads to aortic rupture and sudden death, is a major clinical issue for patients with MFS and patients of the Loeysndash;Dietz spectrum who carry mutations in <i>TGFBR1, TGFBR2</i> and <i>SMAD3</i>. A mouse model of MFS carrying a heterozygous <i>Fbn1</i> mutation developed an aortic aneurism similar to that of patients with MFS. Administration of TGFbeta; antagonists, including a TGFbeta;-neutralizing antibody or the angiotensin II type 1 receptor (AT1) blocker losartan, successfully rescued both cardiovascular and non-cardiovascular manifestations of MFS<bibr rid="b12 b182"/>. As losartan is already in widespread clinical use for hypertension and has shown no adverse effects, this drug is currently being tested in Phase I/II clinical trials for MFS (ClinicalTrials.gov identifiers: NCT00429364, NCT00593710, NCT00683124, NCT00723801, NCT00763893, NCT00782327 and NCT01145612) and may plausibly reduce this life-threatening manifestation of MFS.</p>
        <p><bi>Postoperative scarring in ocular conditions.</bi> Trabeculectomy is a surgical procedure designed to reduce intraocular fluid pressure in patients with glaucoma. However, postoperative scarring and fibrotic blockage of the 'filtering bleb' that drains excess ocular fluid are serious complications of this procedure. In preclinical experiments, administration of neutralizing antibodies against human TGFbeta;2 (CAT-152) exhibited promising inhibition of scarring after glaucoma surgery in rabbits without having any adverse effects. Initial clinical trials with CAT-152 ameliorated scarring in patients who received trabeculectomy for intractable glaucoma<bibr rid="b88 b183"/>; however, Phase III clinical trials were unable to validate such beneficial effects<bibr rid="b184"/>. Tranilast, another incidental TGFbeta; inhibitor, has also been used successfully to reduce re-occurrence of corneal fibrosis, or primary pterygium, following corneal surgery<bibr rid="b185"/>. It is possible that topical application of more-specific TGFbeta; inhibitors might also be used in treating corneal haze and conjunctival scarring (<tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr>).</p>
        <crosshd>Challenges and considerations for TGFbeta; blockade</crosshd>
        <p><bi>Individualized responses to TGFbeta; blockade.</bi> Many diseases being tackled with TGFbeta; inhibitors, including fibrosis, inflammation, autoimmunity and cancer, are complex in nature and show strong genetic predisposition owing to innate genetic variation between individuals. It is well established that there is considerable phenotypic diversity in the range of responses to reduced TGFbeta; signalling <i>in vivo</i>, which are dictated by differential inheritance of germline genetic variants. This is illustrated by the large spectrum of clinical severity and disease manifestations in individuals with mutations in TGFbeta; signalling pathway genes<bibr rid="b8 b41 b186"/>. Moreover, in mouse models of cancer, asthma and vascular development, outcomes of reduced TGFbeta;1 levels are strongly influenced by interacting genetic modifier loci<bibr rid="b5 b9 b186 b187"/>. It is therefore most rational, economical and safe to preselect patient populations before initiating anti-TGFbeta; drug treatment on the basis of surrogate markers of TGFbeta; involvement in the disease process (such as increased TGFbeta; ligand and P-SMAD levels, and specific disease characteristics) and contra-indications of possible adverse side effects (such as susceptibility to inflammation or certain vascular conditions). Peripheral blood may provide non-invasive markers that might be useful in this respect, including the ability to quantitatively screen patient responses to TGFbeta; inhibition on the basis of measuring P-SMAD2 levels in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PMNCs)<bibr rid="b188"/>. Similarly, potential adverse inflammatory effects could be predicted by examining specific immunological responses of PMNCs<bibr rid="b189 b190 b191 b192"/> to TGFbeta; inhibition <i>ex vivo</i>.</p>
        <p><bi>Patient selection for TGFbeta; inhibitors in oncology.</bi> The simplest biomarker for patient selection for TGFbeta; inhibitors in oncology is probably high circulating levels of TGFbeta;, as one major goal of this therapy is to reduce, but not totally ablate, TGFbeta; signalling<bibr rid="b193"/>. As indicated above, non-invasive biomarkers for predicting patient responsiveness and efficacy of TGFbeta; inhibitors have been developed on the basis of measuring P-SMAD2 levels in PMNCs. Indeed, PMNCs can be treated with drugs <i>ex vivo</i> to determine, and thus predict, individual patient responses to SMIs<bibr rid="b188 b193"/>. As TGFbeta; inhibitors certainly act to reduce tumour metastasis, the assay of circulating tumour cell number may also be a useful indicator for therapeutic response. Moreover, as many of the pro-tumorigenic effects of TGFbeta; are mediated by immune system modulation, it might be possible to monitor blood cell or plasma protein profiles for patient selection and for surrogate monitoring of patient responses.</p>
        <p>In cancer (as well as non-malignant diseases), the outcome of reduced TGFbeta; signalling may be highly dependent on the innate genetic background of the individual, especially when considering tumour microenvironment effects, such as immune surveillance. Elucidating specifically which genetic variants influence signalling output will not only be useful for dissecting the intricacies of this signalling pathway <i>in vivo</i>, but may also provide predictive markers for the outcome (desired or undesired) of TGFbeta; signal inhibition. However, for cancer therapeutics, patient selection may be more complex, as the response of both the tumour cell and host (tumour microenvironment and normal patient tissue) to TGFbeta; blockade needs to be considered. Tumour biopsy and genetic analysis (for example, loss of <i>TGFBR2, SMAD2</i> or <i>SMAD4</i>)<bibr rid="b194 b195"/> might predict whether the tumour retains growth sensitivity to TGFbeta;. Molecular and histological analyses may also contribute to the prediction of tumour responses to TGFbeta; inhibition. The activation of alternative intracellular signalling pathways and transcription factor profiles has been associated with the switch from tumour suppression mdash; by TGFbeta; mdash; to tumour progression. These include an increased ratio of liver-enriched inhibitory protein (LIP) to liver-enriched activating protein (LAP), which are isoforms of CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein-beta; (C/EBPbeta;), a central transcription factor that binds within the SMAD transcription factor complex to elicit TGFbeta;-mediated cytostatic responses<bibr rid="b196"/>. Upregulation of SIX1 in breast cancer has also been shown to be pivotal in the growth-suppressive to tumour-progressive switch<bibr rid="b197"/>, as has downregulation of DAB2 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b198">198</bibrinl>). Any of these tumour markers, possibly in combination, may be used in the future to predict tumour responses to TGFbeta; inhibition.</p>
        <p>Finally, the effects of interactions with other anticancer drugs will need to be considered, as some drugs may resurrect the growth-inhibitory arm of the TGFbeta; signalling pathway, which would then counter-indicate their combinatorial use with TGFbeta; inhibitors<bibr rid="b199"/>. Indeed, the ability to specifically target the pro-tumorigenic versus the tumour-suppressive effects of TGFbeta; on the tumour cell <i>per se</i> will require the development of next-generation drugs focusing on these downstream pathways. In the meantime, much research still remains to be undertaken to make inroads into the area of informed patient selection for oncology applications of TGFbeta; inhibitors.</p>
        <p><bi>Drug resistance.</bi> In oncology, the development of tumour drug resistance is inevitable<bibr rid="b134 b200 b201"/>. It has been documented for standard chemotherapy, pathway-targeted therapies and is even common with anti-angiogenesis inhibitors<bibr rid="b200 b201"/>. Acquired biochemical resistance of tumour cells to LY2109761 has been observed in a preclinical model of SCC and may have adverse consequences in driving a more stem cell-like phenotype<bibr rid="b156"/>, although this remains to be tested. Carefully restricting TGFbeta; inhibitors to short-term or intermittent usage should avoid these complications<bibr rid="b82"/>. Combinatorial and/or sequential treatment with complementary drugs will also be important. It is clear that oncologists will need an arsenal of different anticancer drugs to tackle cancer, in much the same way that antibiotics have been developed to combat infectious diseases.</p>
        <crosshd>Conclusion and future directions</crosshd>
        <p>In conclusion, TGFbeta; signalling inhibitors are generally safe and may be efficacious in several clinical applications, especially in desperate cases such as end-stage cancer or IPF. The development of these drugs may offer further therapeutic opportunities. Counterintuitively, there have been reports suggesting that inhibition of the TGFbeta; signalling pathway may be beneficial in autoimmune disorders, such as multiple sclerosis, through downregulation of the T<sub>H</sub>17 pathway<bibr rid="b202 b203"/>. Recent studies have also suggested that TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD3 signalling regulates glucose tolerance and energy homeostasis, and that blockade of the pathway may be used for regulation of diabetes and obesity<bibr rid="b204"/>. The outlook for anti-TGFbeta; signalling therapy for numerous diseases appears bright. At least four companies are well on their way in clinical drug development, and further scientific and mechanistic studies are warranted in order to optimize patient selection and drug-dosing regimens for each disease application.</p>
    </bdy>
    <bm>
        <objects>
            <deflist id="df1">
                <term>Epithelialndash;mesenchymal transition</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>(EMT). The transformation of a keratin-expressing epithelial cell into one with fibroblastic properties that express mesenchymal markers.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df2">
                <term>Extracellular matrix</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>(ECM). Matrix that supports connective tissue and is composed of proteoglycans, hyaluronic acid and fibrillar proteins secreted from the cell and rich in bound growth factors.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df3">
                <term>Fibrosis</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>The excess accumulation of fibroblasts and associated extracellular matrix.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df4">
                <term>Metastasis</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>The dissemination of tumour cells and re-establishment of tumours at a secondary site.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df5">
                <term>SMAD</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>Signal transduction component of the canonical transforming growth factor-beta; signalling pathway.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df6">
                <term>microRNA</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>(miRNA). Small (20ndash;23 nucleotides long) non-coding RNA involved in post- translational regulation of gene expression. miRNAs bind to the partially complementary sequence in the 3prime;-untranslated region (3prime;-UTR) of mRNAs and negatively regulate their expression either through translational inhibition or promotion of mRNA degradation.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df7">
                <term>Myofibroblast</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>A contractile fibroblast that expresses smooth muscle actin and myosin, and contributes to disease progression in cancer and fibrosis.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df8">
                <term>Antisense oligonucleotides</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>(ASOs). Short chemically modified oligonucleotides complementary to a specific mRNA that can be used to cause specific knockdown of targeted gene expression.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <deflist id="df9">
                <term>Tumour-initiating cells</term>
                <defn>
                    <p>(TICs). The putative cancer stem cells that have the ability to maintain tumour growth, differentiate into all cell types of a heterogenous tumour, and to re-establish secondary tumours with exceedingly high efficiency.</p>
                </defn>
            </deflist>
            <linkgrp>
                <linkset name="FURTHER INFORMATION">
                    <weblink url="http://cancer.ucsf.edu/research/akhurst-lab">Rosemary J. Akhurst's homepage</weblink>
                    <weblink url="http://www.cvri.ucsf.edu/Scientist/Hata.shtml">Akiko Hata's homepage</weblink>
                    <weblink url="http://www.clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov website</weblink>
                    <weblink url="http://www.dignabiotech.com/comun/fichero.asp?id=105">Flamel Technologies and Digna Biotech Announce Multiple Product Development Agreement (27 June 2011 press release)</weblink>
                </linkset>
            </linkgrp>
            <fig id="f1" type="bmp" entref="figf1">
                <!--nrd3810-f1-->
                <figtl>Schematic overview of the canonical, SMAD-dependent TGFbeta; signalling pathway.</figtl>
                <caption>
                    <p>The transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) ligands are synthesized as a large latent TGFbeta; complex consisting of mature dimeric TGFbeta; associated with its latency-associated peptide (LAP) and a latent TGFbeta;-binding protein (LTBP) (not shown). Upon activation, TGFbeta; dimers induce heteromeric complex formation between specific type II and type I receptors (such as TGFbeta; receptor type II (Tbeta;RII) and Tbeta;RI, respectively). Type II receptors then transphosphorylate the type I receptors, which propagate the signal into the cell by phosphorylating TGFbeta; receptor-specific SMADs (R-SMADs: SMAD2 and SMAD3). They form heteromeric complexes with the common mediator SMAD (co-SMAD: SMAD4) and translocate to the nucleus. Once in the nucleus, the R-SMADndash;co-SMAD complex preferentially associates with the genomic SMAD-binding element (SBE) in a sequence-specific manner. However, high-affinity binding of the R-SMADndash;co-SMAD complex with the SBE generally occurs in concert with other DNA-binding transcription factors that bind to distinct sequences adjacent to the SBE<bibr rid="b27"/>. The nuclear proteins SKI and SNO (also known as SKIL) antagonize the transcriptional regulation by SMADs. An inhibitory SMAD (I-SMAD), SMAD7, inhibits the TGFbeta; pathway through multiple mechanisms, including by mediating the degradation of the type I receptor, inhibiting phosphorylation of R-SMADs by the type I receptor kinase or inhibiting the formation of the R-SMADndash;co-SMAD complex. In addition to regulating transcription, R-SMADs can modulate microRNA (miRNA) biogenesis by facilitating the processing of primary miRNA into precursor miRNA in the nucleus. The co-SMAD is not required for the regulation of miRNA biosynthesis by R-SMADs. 'mG' and 'AAAAA' represent 5prime; capping and 3prime; polyadenylation of mRNAs, respectively.</p>
                </caption>
            </fig>
            <fig id="f2" type="bmp" entref="figf2">
                <!--nrd3810-f2-->
                <figtl>Schematic representation of non-canonical TGFbeta; signalling and crosstalk with other signalling pathways.</figtl>
                <caption>
                    <p>In the non-canonical pathways, the activated transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) receptor complex transmits a signal through other factors, such as TNF receptor associated factor 4 (TRAF4) or TRAF6, TGFbeta;-activated kinase 1 (TAK1), p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (p38 MAPK), RHO, phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)ndash;AKT, extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK), JUN N-terminal kinase (JNK) or nuclear factor-kappa;B (NF-kappa;B). TGFbeta; signalling can be influenced by pathways other than the canonical and non-canonical TGFbeta; signalling pathways, such as the WNT, Hedgehog, Notch, interferon (IFN), tumour necrosis factor (TNF) and RAS pathways. The crosstalk between TGFbeta; and other pathways defines the activities of TGFbeta; to propagate spatial- and temporal-specific signals. miRNA, microRNA; ROCK, RHO-associated protein kinase; R-SMAD, receptor-specific SMAD; Tbeta;R, TGFbeta; receptor. 'mG' and 'AAAAA' represent 5prime; capping and 3prime; polyadenylation of mRNAs, respectively.</p>
                </caption>
            </fig>
            <fig id="f3" type="bmp" entref="figf3">
                <!--nrd3810-f3-->
                <figtl>Biphasic activities of the TGFbeta; signalling pathway during tumorigenesis: from the tumour suppressor to the tumour promoter.</figtl>
                <caption>
                    <p>Transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) has biphasic actions during tumorigenesis, suppressing tumorigenesis at early stages but promoting tumour progression later on, which is the underlying paradigm for the action of TGFbeta; during disease progression in general and thus complicates the development of therapies targeting TGFbeta; signalling. The light grey arrows indicate a positive feedforward loop resulting in higher levels of TGFbeta;, which is a feature of non-neoplastic as well as neoplastic diseases. The current goal in cancer therapy is to downmodulate excessive levels of TGFbeta; ligands and to target the tumour-progressing versus the tumour-suppressing arm of TGFbeta; action; the latter goal will almost certainly require more-specific second-generation drugs. CTGF, connective tissue growth factor; EMT, epithelialndash;mesenchymal transition; IL, interleukin; PTHRP, parathyroid hormone-related protein; TAMs, tumour-associated macrophages; TANs, tumour-associated neutrophils; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor.</p>
                </caption>
            </fig>
            <fig id="f4" type="bmp" entref="figf4">
                <!--nrd3810-f4-->
                <figtl>TGFbeta; effects on immune cells.</figtl>
                <caption>
                    <p>Transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) has effects on most immune cell types. The figure depicts the activity of TGFbeta; on immune cell subsets that is relevant to human diseases. M1rarr;M2 and N1rarr;N2 indicate polarization of macrophages and neutrophils, respectively, from type I to type II. IgA, immunoglobulin A; T<sub>H</sub>, T helper; T<sub>Reg</sub>, regulatory T.</p>
                </caption>
            </fig>
            <fig id="f5" type="bmp" entref="figf5">
                <!--nrd3810-f5-->
                <figtl>Schematic representation of therapeutic approaches for blocking TGFbeta; signalling.</figtl>
                <caption>
                    <p>Transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) signalling can be inhibited by: sequestering ligands using soluble receptor ectodomain constructs (ligand traps) derived from TGFbeta; receptor type II (Tbeta;RII) or Tbeta;RIII; using TGFbeta;-neutralizing antibodies; or with Tbeta;RII or Tbeta;RI kinase inhibitors. Furthermore, translation of TGFbeta; mRNA can be blocked by targeting TGFbeta; mRNA with antisense oligonucleotides, thus preventing the production of the ligand. Different small-molecule kinase inhibitors against Tbeta;RI have been developed to block its kinase activity. Peptide inhibitors against specific TGFbeta; ligands are also used. Other approaches block the transformation of TGFbeta; from the latent to the active form. Three molecules are shown that either affect TGFbeta; signalling indirectly (losartan) or that have an as-yet-unidentified target (tranilast and pirfenidone). All of these approaches decrease the initiation of intracellular receptor signalling pathways, such as phosphorylation of downstream receptor-specific SMADs (R-SMADs), and thereby blunt the transcriptional regulation of target genes. AT1, angiotensin II type 1 receptor; co-TFs, co-transcription factors; FOXH1B, forkhead box protein H1B; LEF, lymphoid enhancer-binding factor; LSKL, Leu-Ser-Lys-Leu peptide; TRX, thioredoxin.</p>
                </caption>
            </fig>
            <fig id="f6" type="bmp" entref="figf6">
                <!--nrd3810-f6-->
                <figtl>Structures of representative small-molecule inhibitors of TGFbeta; signalling.</figtl>
                <caption>
                    <p>Depicted are the molecular structures of a selection of small-molecule inhibitors identified to target the transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) signalling pathway. SB-431542, LY2157299, SD208 and SM16 are all ATP mimetics that inhibit TGFbeta; receptor type I (Tbeta;RI; also known as TGFBR1) kinase activity. Pyrrole-imidazole polyamide blocks transcription of the <i>TGFB1</i> gene. Pirfenidone and tranilast have unknown molecular mechanisms of action. Dashed lines denote putative hydrogen bonding with bases in DNA; asterisks indicate positions where hydrogen bonds form with nucleotide residues of DNA within the <i>TGFB1</i> gene promoter.</p>
                </caption>
            </fig>
            <table id="t1" tocentry="0" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0" orient="port" pgwide="0" tabcols="8">
                <title>Summary of clinical trials for TGFbeta; inhibitory drugs</title>
                <tgroup cols="8" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="left"><colspec colnum="1" colname="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="3" colname="3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="4" colname="4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="5" colname="5" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="6" colname="6" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="7" colname="7" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="8" colname="8" align="right" colwidth="1*"/><spanspec namest="1" nameend="8" spanname="1"/><thead valign="top">
                        <row rowsep="1">
                            <entry>Drug; company</entry>
                            <entry>Type</entry>
                            <entry>Targets</entry>
                            <entry>Disease applications</entry>
                            <entry>Stage</entry>
                            <entry>Clinical trial identifiers</entry>
                            <entry>Summary of results</entry>
                            <entry>Refs</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead><tbody valign="top">
                        <row rowsep="1">
                            <entry morerows="2">Trabedersen (AP12009); Antisense Pharma</entry>
                            <entry morerows="2">Antisense oligo</entry>
                            <entry morerows="2">TGFbeta;2 ligand</entry>
                            <entry>Glioblastoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I/IIb</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00431561</entry>
                            <entry>Safe</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b70">70</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b73">73</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b74">74</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Pancreatic cancer, MetM, colon cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00844064</entry>
                            <entry>Pancreatic cancer trials continue</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b84">84</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Glioblastoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase III</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00761280</entry>
                            <entry>Glioblastoma trials stopped in March 2012 owing to advances in standard of care and neurosurgery (<bxr rid="bx4">BOX 4</bxr>)</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Belagenpumatucel-L (Lucanix); NovaRx</entry>
                            <entry>Antisense gene-modified allogeneic tumour cell vaccine</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;2</entry>
                            <entry>NSCLC</entry>
                            <entry>Phase III</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00676507</entry>
                            <entry>Well tolerated in 75 patients; survival advantage justifies further Phase III evaluation</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b85">85</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b86">86</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b87">87</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Disitertide (P144); Digna Biotech</entry>
                            <entry>Peptide</entry>
                            <entry>Peptide based on Tbeta;RIII that blocks ligand binding to receptors</entry>
                            <entry>Skin fibrosis in systemic sclerosis</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00574613, NCT00781053</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical efficacy in peritoneal fibrosis associated with peritoneal dialysis, renal and cardiac fibrosis, corneal haze and retinal AMD; safety and efficacy in Phase IIa clinical trial for scleroderma/skin fibrosis</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b75">75</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b76">76</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b77">77</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b78">78</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Lerdelimumab (CAT-152); Cambridge Antibody Technology</entry>
                            <entry>Humanized antibody</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;2 ligand</entry>
                            <entry>Reduction of scarring after glaucoma surgery</entry>
                            <entry>Phase III (complete)</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>Safe; ineffective in reducing scarring in Phase III trial</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b88">88</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b89">89</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Metelimumab (CAT-192); Cambridge Antibody Technology</entry>
                            <entry>Humanized Antibody</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;1 ligand</entry>
                            <entry>Diffuse systemic sclerosis</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I/II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00043706</entry>
                            <entry>Ineffective when systemically administered in doses up to 10 mg per kg</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b90">90</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry morerows="9">Fresolimumab (GC-1008); Cambridge Antibody Technology/Genzyme/Sanofi</entry>
                            <entry morerows="9">Humanized antibody</entry>
                            <entry morerows="9">TGFbeta;1, TGFbeta;2 and TGFbeta;3 ligands</entry>
                            <entry>Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00464321</entry>
                            <entry>Completed and safe; plans to progress</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b92">92</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry morerows="2">Systemic sclerosis</entry>
                            <entry morerows="2">Phase I</entry>
                            <entry morerows="2">NCT01284322</entry>
                            <entry>Still recruiting</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Study ongoing</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Completed, no results</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Myelofibrosis</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01291784</entry>
                            <entry>See <bxr rid="bx4">BOX 4</bxr></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b93">93</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>IPF</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00125385</entry>
                            <entry>See <bxr rid="bx4">BOX 4</bxr></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b93">93</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Renal cell carcinoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00356460</entry>
                            <entry>See <bxr rid="bx4">BOX 4</bxr></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b93">93</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Malignant melanoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00356460</entry>
                            <entry>See <bxr rid="bx4">BOX 4</bxr></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b81">81</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Metastatic breast cancer (with radiotherapy)</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01401062</entry>
                            <entry>Active and recruiting patients</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Relapsed malignant pleural, mesothelioma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01112293</entry>
                            <entry>Ongoing but not recruiting participants</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LY2382770; Eli Lilly</entry>
                            <entry>Humanized Antibody</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;1</entry>
                            <entry>Diabetic kidney disease (fibrosis)</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01113801</entry>
                            <entry>Safety and efficacy in protecting kidney function in patients with diabetic kidney disease; still recruiting</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>STX-100; Stromedix</entry>
                            <entry>Antibody</entry>
                            <entry>alpha;Vbeta;6 integrin</entry>
                            <entry>Fibrosis</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01371305</entry>
                            <entry>Significant antifibrotic activity in preclinical models of lung, kidney and liver disease</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b168">168</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry morerows="4">LY2157299; Eli Lilly</entry>
                            <entry morerows="4">Small molecule</entry>
                            <entry morerows="4">Tbeta;RI kinase</entry>
                            <entry>Advanced-stage melanoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT10038320</entry>
                            <entry>See <bxr rid="bx4">BOX 4</bxr></entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b82">82</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Recurrent glioblastoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01582269</entry>
                            <entry>Recruiting; LY2157299 alone or with lomustine therapy versus lomustine alone in recurrent glioblastoma</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b213">213</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Glioblastoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01220271</entry>
                            <entry>Recruiting; LY2157299 with temozolomide-based radiochemotherapy in newly diagnosed malignant glioma</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b212">212</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Hepatocellular carcinoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01246986</entry>
                            <entry>Recruiting</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Advanced pancreatic carcinoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01373164</entry>
                            <entry>Recruiting; comparison of gemcitabine with gemcitabine plus LY2157299</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Dominant negative <i>TGFBR2</i>-modified CTLs</entry>
                            <entry>Recombinant T cells</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RII</entry>
                            <entry>Adoptive transfer of T cells expressing HER2 and Delta;N<i>TGFBR2</i> for lung cancer (HERCREEM)</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00889954</entry>
                            <entry>No update on clinical trials</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Dominant negative <i>TGFBR2-</i> modified CTLs</entry>
                            <entry>Recombinant T cells (a clinical grade retrovirus vector encoding dominant negative Tbeta;RII)</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RII</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;-resistant LMP2A-specific CTLs for EBV-positive lymphoma</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00368082</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical efficacy in tumour killing of TGFbeta;-secreting EBV-positive lymphoma; no update on clinical trials</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b107">107</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Avotermin (Juvista); Renova</entry>
                            <entry>Recombinant protein</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;3</entry>
                            <entry>Scarring</entry>
                            <entry>Phase II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT004322111, NCT00656227</entry>
                            <entry>The Juvista Phase II trial had not reached its primary or secondary efficacy end points as of February 2011</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b214">214</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Pirfenidone; InterMune</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule, not TGFbeta;-specific</entry>
                            <entry/>
                            <entry>IPF, glomerulosclerosis and diabetic kidney disease, pathological skin scarring</entry>
                            <entry>Phase III</entry>
                            <entry>Multiple trials</entry>
                            <entry>First drug approved for IPF in Europe</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b162">162</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Losartan; Merck and Co.</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule, not TGFbeta;-specific</entry>
                            <entry>AT1</entry>
                            <entry>Marfan syndrome (MFS)</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I/II</entry>
                            <entry>NCT00723801, NCT00763893, NCT00782327</entry>
                            <entry>Reduction of aortic aneurysm in mouse model of MFS; clinical trials in progress to reduce aortic root dilation and cardiac muscle stiffness in patients with MFS</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b12">12</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b182">182</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Tranilast; Kissei Pharmaceuticals</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule, not TGFbeta;-specific</entry>
                            <entry>Unknown</entry>
                            <entry>Corneal primary pterygium</entry>
                            <entry>Phase III</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01003613</entry>
                            <entry>Tranilast reduces myofibroblast proliferation of corneal myofibroblasts <i>in vitro</i> and may be a novel adjuvant therapy for corneal keloid</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b185">185</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b215">215</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b216">216</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>IMC-TR1; ImClone Systems/Eli Lilly</entry>
                            <entry>Humanized antibody</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RII</entry>
                            <entry>Mammary and colon cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Phase I</entry>
                            <entry>NCT01646203</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical efficacy against primary tumour growth and metastasis through multiple effects on tumour, stroma and immune cells</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b94">94</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry spanname="1"> AMD, age-related macular degeneration; AT1, angiotensin II type 1 receptor; CTL, cytotoxic T lymphocyte; EBV, Epsteinndash;Barr virus; IPF, idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis; LMP2A, an EBV-specific antigen; MetM, metastatic melanoma; NSCLC, non-small-cell lung cancer; oligo, oligonucleotide; Tbeta;R, TGFbeta; receptor; TGFbeta;, transforming growth factor-beta;; <i>TGFBR2</i>, gene encoding Tbeta;RII. </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody></tgroup>
                <!--nrd3810-t1-->
            </table>
            <table id="t2" tocentry="0" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0" orient="port" pgwide="0" tabcols="7">
                <title>Summary of TGFbeta; inhibitory drugs in preclinical development</title>
                <tgroup cols="7" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="left"><colspec colnum="1" colname="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="3" colname="3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="4" colname="4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="5" colname="5" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="6" colname="6" align="left" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colnum="7" colname="7" align="right" colwidth="1*"/><spanspec namest="1" nameend="7" spanname="1"/><thead valign="top">
                        <row rowsep="1">
                            <entry>Drugs; company</entry>
                            <entry>Type</entry>
                            <entry>Targets</entry>
                            <entry>Disease applications</entry>
                            <entry>Stage</entry>
                            <entry>Summary of results</entry>
                            <entry>Refs</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead><tbody valign="top">
                        <row rowsep="1">
                            <entry>AP11014; Antisense Pharma</entry>
                            <entry>Antisense oligo</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;1 ligand</entry>
                            <entry>Prostate cancer, NSCLC, colorectal cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>AP11014 significantly reduced TGFbeta;1 secretion by 43ndash;100% in different NSCLC, colon and prostate cancer cell lines</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b217">217</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>P17; Digna Biotech</entry>
                            <entry>Peptide</entry>
                            <entry>Peptide derived from Phage Display Technology that targets TGFbeta;1 binding to receptor</entry>
                            <entry>Liver and pulmonary fibrosis, metastatic lung cancer, angiogenesis, melanoma, immunosuppression, wet AMD</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical efficacy in peritoneal fibrosis associated with peritoneal dialysis, lung fibrosis, corneal haze and retinal AMD</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b76">76</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LSKL (academic only)</entry>
                            <entry>Peptide</entry>
                            <entry>Thrombospondin</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical efficacy in reducing renal injury and proteinuria in a murine model of diabetic nephropathy</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b97">97</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>1D11; Ramp;D Systems</entry>
                            <entry>Mouse antibody</entry>
                            <entry>Mouse TGFbeta;1, TGFbeta;2 and TGFbeta;3 ligands</entry>
                            <entry>Breast cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Safe and efficacious in tumour metastasis in mice</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b79">79</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b80">80</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b218">218</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>SR2F (academic only)</entry>
                            <entry>Ligand trap</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;1, TGFbeta;3</entry>
                            <entry>Breast cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Very safe after lifetime exposure in mice; not progressing to clinical trial</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b125">125</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Soluble Tbeta;R2-Fc; Genzyme</entry>
                            <entry>Ligand trap</entry>
                            <entry>TGFbeta;1, TGFbeta;3</entry>
                            <entry>Breast cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Safe and efficacious in suppressing metastasis in preclinical model of breast carcinoma; not progressing to clinical trial</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <bibrinl rid="b96">96</bibrinl>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>LY580276, LY550410, LY364947, LY2109761<super>ast;</super>; Eli Lilly</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RI kinase</entry>
                            <entry>Cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>LY2109761 is safe in long-term dosing of tumour-bearing mice, and efficacious in reducing metastasis and TICs in mouse cancer models</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b80">80</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b156">156</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b219">219</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b220">220</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b221">221</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b222">222</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>SB-505124, SB-431542; GlaxoSmithKline</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RI kinase</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Extensively used <i>in vitro</i>; pharmacokinetically unstable <i>in vivo</i></entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b223">223</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b224">224</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b225">225</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>SD208, SD093; Scios</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RI kinase</entry>
                            <entry>Cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Efficacious in suppressing tumour metastasis in rodent models; programme discontinued after merger with Johnson amp; Johnson</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b146">146</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b226">226</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b227">227</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Ki26894; Kirin Pharmaceuticals</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RI kinase</entry>
                            <entry>Breast cancer</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Not progressing to clinical trial</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b148">148</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b150">150</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>SM16; Biogen Idec</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RI kinase</entry>
                            <entry>Mesothelioma</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Not progressing to clinical trial</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b10">10</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b155">155</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b228">228</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b229">229</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>GW788388; GlaxoSmithKline</entry>
                            <entry>Small molecule</entry>
                            <entry>Tbeta;RI kinase</entry>
                            <entry>Fibrosis</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Not progressing to clinical trial</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b230">230</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b231">231</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b232">232</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>GB1201, GB1203 (academic)</entry>
                            <entry>Pyrrole- imidazole polyamide</entry>
                            <entry><i>TGFB1</i> gene promoter</entry>
                            <entry>Cutaneous and corneal scarring, arterial restenosis, kidney fibrosis</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical</entry>
                            <entry>Preclinical efficacy in inhibition of <i>TGFB1</i> gene expression, which reduced corneal scarring and carotid artery restenosis</entry>
                            <entry><bibrinl rid="b50">50</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b102">102</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b103">103</bibrinl></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry spanname="1">
                                <super>ast;</super>Contrary to earlier reports<bibr rid="b4 b16"/>, LY573636 is not a TGFbeta;-specific inhibitor. NSCLC, non-small-cell lung cancer; oligo, oligonucleotide; Tbeta;R, TGFbeta; receptor; TGFbeta;, transforming growth factor-beta;; TICs, tumour-initiating cells. </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody></tgroup>
                <!--nrd3810-t2-->
            </table>
            <bx id="bx1" placement="external" type="reg">
                <bxtitle>Box 1 verbar; Canonical signal transduction pathway of the TGFbeta; superfamily of growth factors</bxtitle>
                <p>The basic framework of the canonical signal transduction pathways of three subfamilies of the transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) superfamily mdash; TGFbeta;s, activins/inhibins/Nodal and bone morphogenetic proteins (BMPs) mdash; is highly conserved. The ligand binds to a specific set of type I and type II receptors, which are both serine/threonine kinases, followed by signal transduction by SMAD proteins<bibr rid="b31 b205"/>. Although each subfamily transmits the signal through a specific signalling pathway, the interaction among the TGFbeta;, activins/inhibins/Nodal and BMP subfamilies is well recognized during development and in postnatal homeostasis of various organs (<bxr rid="bx3">Box 3</bxr>). Upon ligand binding and resultant heterotetrameric receptor complex formation, the constitutively active type II receptor phosphorylates the type I receptor, which in turn propagates a signal by phosphorylating the receptor-specific SMADs (R-SMADs)<bibr rid="b31 b205"/>. Unlike type I and type II receptors, type III receptors do not possess kinase activity and are not required for signal transduction; however, they bind to specific ligands and modulate the signalling pathway either positively or negatively<bibr rid="b31 b205"/>. Phosphorylation of R-SMADs at two serine residues within the extreme carboxyl terminus by type I receptor kinase activity promotes association with the common mediator SMAD (co-SMAD), SMAD4, resulting in nuclear accumulation and sequence-specific binding to DNA in concert with other DNA-binding transcription factors that bind distinct sequences adjacent to the SMAD-binding element (SBE)<bibr rid="b27"/>, and together these complexes modulate transcription. The inhibitory SMADs (I-SMADs), SMAD6 and SMAD7, antagonize R-SMAD activation by competing with R-SMADs for type I receptor interaction and/or by recruiting specific ubiquitin ligases or phosphatases to the activated receptor complex, thereby targeting it for proteasomal degradation or dephosphorylation, respectively. SMAD7 inhibits signalling from all branches of the TGFbeta; superfamily, whereas SMAD6 is a specific inhibitor of the BMP signalling pathway. The table indicates the basic molecules in the signal transduction pathway, including three types of receptors and SMADs, for three subfamilies of the TGFbeta; superfamily of ligands: TGFbeta;s, activins/inhibins/Nodal and BMPs.<illusr rid="i1"/></p>
            </bx>
            <bx id="bx2" placement="external" type="reg">
                <bxtitle>Box 2 verbar; Non-canonical TGFbeta; signalling and crosstalk with other pathways</bxtitle>
                <p>In addition to activating SMAD proteins, transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) signalling can regulate the activity of a number of signalling molecules, such as TNF receptor-associated factor 4 (TRAF4), TRAF6, TGFbeta;-activated kinase 1 (TAK1), p38 mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPKs), extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK), JUN N-terminal kinase (JNK), RHO GTPases, phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)ndash;AKT and nuclear factor-kappa;B (NF-kappa;B), to transmit a signal<bibr rid="b6"/>. In addition, these non-canonical signals can crosstalk with the SMAD pathways and mutually modulate each other. Both canonical and non-canonical TGFbeta; signalling can also be influenced by other signalling pathways, such as the RAS, WNT, Hedgehog, Notch, tumour necrosis factor (TNF) and interferon pathways<bibr rid="b6"/>. The exact nature of the crosstalk with other pathways and biological outcomes is complex and highly context-dependent<bibr rid="b6"/>. However, some of the crosstalk has been found to modulate the function and stability of SMAD proteins through post-translational modifications, and to define cell type- and context-specific outcomes by inducing other factors that modulate TGFbeta; activity.</p>
            </bx>
            <bx id="bx3" placement="external" type="reg">
                <bxtitle>Box 3 verbar; BMPndash;TGFbeta;ndash;activin crosstalk in endothelial cells</bxtitle>
                <p>Within the transforming growth factor-beta; (TGFbeta;) superfamily, the crosstalk between three subfamilies mdash; activins/inhibins/Nodal, TGFbeta;s and bone morphogenetic proteins (BMPs) mdash; is well established during development and postnatal homeostasis of various organs<bibr rid="b206 b207"/>. In vertebrates, the BMPndash;SMAD1/SMAD5/SMAD8 and activinndash;Nodalndash;TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD2/SMAD3 signalling pathways execute antagonistic actions in different developmental contexts by inducing the expression of antagonistic factors, such as inhibitory SMADs (I-SMADs: SMAD6 and SMAD7). Some studies have shown that the common mediator SMAD (co-SMAD), SMAD4, is rate-limiting; therefore, when one of the two pathways is activated, it can negatively influence the other pathway by sequestering SMAD4. In endothelial cells, TGFbeta; can signal not only via canonical TGFbeta; receptor type I (Tbeta;RI)ndash;SMAD2/SMAD3 but also via activin receptor-like kinase 1 (ALK1)ndash;SMAD1/SMAD5/SMAD8 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b36">36</bibrinl>). In contrast to TGFbeta;ndash;Tbeta;RI signalling-mediated activation of SMAD2 or SMAD3, which leads to endothelium quiescence, TGFbeta;ndash;ALK1 signalling induces SMAD1/SMAD5/SMAD8 activation and has been shown to stimulate endothelial cell migration, proliferation and tube formation, thus promoting angiogenesis<bibr rid="b208"/>. BMP9 was shown to induce SMAD2/SMAD3 and SMAD1/SMAD5/SMAD8 phosphorylation via signalling mediated by BMP receptor 2 (BMPR2), activin receptor type II (ACTRII) and ALK1 or ALK2. Cross-activation of TGFbeta;-specific and BMP-specific receptor-specific SMADs (R-SMADs) by a single ligand is believed to provide a mechanism for the ligand to fine-tune endothelial cell behaviour and function<bibr rid="b36"/>. In summary, the crosstalk among signalling pathways mediated by different TGFbeta; family ligands exists in every tissue. However, the mechanism and the biological outcome of this crosstalk are highly species-, tissue- and context-dependent.</p>
            </bx>
            <bx id="bx4" placement="external" type="reg">
                <bxtitle>Box 4 verbar; Oncology trials to date</bxtitle>
                <p>A two-part clinical trial of GC-1008 for the treatment of advanced metastatic melanoma (MetM) and renal cell carcinoma (22 patients) found the drug to be safe and well tolerated with no dose-limiting toxicities (DTLs). Five patients achieved at least stable disease as assessed by RECIST (response evaluation criteria in solid tumours) criteria, and therefore received extended treatment. One patient achieved a partial response with a greater than 75% reduction in the target lesion. The only adverse effect was keratoacanthoma-like lesions in sun-damaged skin of two of the patients with MetM. However, these resolved on cessation of drug treatment and were not malignant<bibr rid="b93"/>. Despite these promising results, the pursuit of GC-1008 for oncology was terminated after Genzyme was acquired by Sanofi in late 2011.</p>
                <p>Antisense Pharma has had success with trabedersen (AP12009) in glioblastoma, pancreatic cancer and colon cancer. Preclinical and clinical studies<bibr rid="b70 b71 b73"/> indicate that neutralization of transforming growth factor-beta;2 (TGFbeta;2)-mediated immunosuppression, leading to activation of tumour-infiltrating natural killer cells, is the major mode of action. Intra-tumoural administration of trabedersen to glioblastoma led to shrinkage of the targeted tumour as well as tumours elsewhere in the brain. Three Phase I/II studies of trabedersen for recurrent or refractory high-grade glioma (glioblastoma) and anaplastic astrocytoma showed survival benefit compared with conventional chemotherapy<bibr rid="b209"/>. A randomized, controlled Phase IIb study evaluating the efficacy and safety of two doses (10 and 80 mM) of trabedersen in comparison with standard therapy concluded that patients with glioblastoma on trabedersen had a threefold enhancement in cognitive function 2 and 3 years after therapy compared to standard chemotherapy<bibr rid="b74"/>. However, questions have been raised about this most recent study<bibr rid="b210 b211"/>. Wick and Weller<bibr rid="b211"/> conceded that although trabedersen was clinically safe and that TGFbeta; inhibitors, in general, show promise for cancer therapy, the conclusions drawn by Bogdahn <i>et al</i>.<bibr rid="b74"/> were premature. Because of other advances in both neurosurgical procedures and first-line standard of care for patients with glioblastoma<bibr rid="b212"/>, the SAPPHIRE Phase III trial of trabedersen was recently halted owing to patient recruitment issues (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT00761280). Nevertheless, the drug has undergone a Phase I/II trial for patients with advanced pancreatic cancer, MetM or metastatic colorectal carcinoma, and showed excellent safety and encouraging survival results (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT00844064)<bibr rid="b84"/>.</p>
                <p>Eli Lilly's clinical small-molecule inhibitor LY2157299 was found to be safe and well tolerated in a Phase I glioblastoma trial<bibr rid="b82"/>. Of 28 patients treated in a dose escalation study (14 days on/14 days off treatment), at least three patients showed antitumour effects with durable responses beyond 1 year. As a result, the Eli Lilly anti-TGFbeta; signalling programme for oncology continues to be pursued with an ongoing Phase II trial of LY2157299, with or without gemcitabine, for hepatocellular carcinoma, glioblastoma and advanced pancreatic cancer, and with lomustine in patients with treatment-refractory malignant glioma<bibr rid="b213"/>, plus a new Phase I trial of IMC-TM1, an anti-TGFbeta; receptor type II (Tbeta;RII) antibody.</p>
                <p>NovaRx's belagenpumatucel-L (Lucanix) has completed an open-label clinical trial of 75 patients with non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) with a median follow-up of 14.5 months (44 months for patients with stable disease). One-year, two-year and five-year survivals were 55%, 35% and 20%, respectively. Individuals who demonstrated an increase in both cellular and humoral immune reactivity had a significant survival advantage over individuals who showed an increase in only one measure of immunity (32.5 months versus 11.6 months; <i>p</i> = 0.015). On the basis of these findings, an international, randomized Phase III trial to evaluate the efficacy of belagenpumatucel-L in a maintenance setting has been initiated for patients with stage III/IV NSCLC who have stable disease following frontline chemotherapy<bibr rid="b87"/>.</p>
            </bx>
            <illus id="i1" type="bmp" entref="illus1" embed="yes" display="print-online">
                <!--nrd3810-i1-->
            </illus>
        </objects>
        <ack>
            <p>The authors give thanks to J. Dotor, J. McPherson and J. Yingling for useful discussions. Work in the authors' laboratories is funded by grants from the US National Cancer Institute, the US National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (NHLBI), the US National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, the US National Institute of General Medical Sciences, the Bouque Foundation and the Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center to R.J.A., and from the NHLBI, the American Heart Association and the LeDucq Foundation to A.H. We apologize to all colleagues whose work could not be cited owing to space restrictions.</p>
        </ack>
        <audecl conflct="no"/>
        <bibl>
            <bib id="b1">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Schmierer</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Hill</snm>, <fnm>C. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD signal transduction: molecular specificity and functional flexibility</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>970</ppf>ndash;<ppl>982</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b2">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Derynck</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Miyazono</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> (eds) <btl>The TGF-beta; Family</btl> (Cold Spring Harbor Press, <cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b3">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Derynck</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Differentiation plasticity regulated by TGF-beta; family proteins in development and disease</atl>. <jtl>Nature Cell Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>1000</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1004</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b4">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Flavell</snm>, <fnm>R. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sanjabi</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wrzesinski</snm>, <fnm>S. H.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Licona-Limon</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>The polarization of immune cells in the tumour environment by TGFbeta;</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Immunol.</jtl>
                    <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>554</ppf>ndash;<ppl>567</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b5">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Mao</snm>, <fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Genetic variants of <i>Tgfb1</i> act as context-dependent modifiers of mouse skin tumor susceptibility</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>103</vid>, <ppf>8125</ppf>ndash;<ppl>8130</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b6">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Guo</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>X. F.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Signaling cross-talk between TGF-beta;/BMP and other pathways</atl>. <jtl>Cell Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>71</ppf>ndash;<ppl>88</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b7">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Conidi</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Few Smad proteins and many Smad-interacting proteins yield multiple functions and action modes in TGFbeta;/BMP signaling <i>in vivo</i></atl>. <jtl>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev.</jtl>
                    <vid>22</vid>, <ppf>287</ppf>ndash;<ppl>300</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b8">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGFbeta; signaling in health and disease</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl>
                    <vid>36</vid>, <ppf>790</ppf>ndash;<ppl>792</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b9">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Freimuth</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Epistatic interactions between <i>Tgfb1</i> and genetic loci, <i>Tgfbm2</i> and <i>Tgfbm3</i>, determine susceptibility to an asthmatic stimulus</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> (in the press).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b10">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Anscher</snm>, <fnm>M. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Small molecular inhibitor of transforming growth factor-beta; protects against development of radiation-induced lung injury</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Radiat. Oncol. Biol. Phys.</jtl>
                    <vid>71</vid>, <ppf>829</ppf>ndash;<ppl>837</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b11">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Neptune</snm>, <fnm>E. R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Dysregulation of TGF-beta; activation contributes to pathogenesis in Marfan syndrome</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl>
                    <vid>33</vid>, <ppf>407</ppf>ndash;<ppl>411</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b12">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Habashi</snm>, <fnm>J. P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Losartan, an AT1 antagonist, prevents aortic aneurysm in a mouse model of Marfan syndrome</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl>
                    <vid>312</vid>, <ppf>117</ppf>ndash;<ppl>121</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b13">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Roberts</snm>, <fnm>A. B.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Wakefield</snm>, <fnm>L. M.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>The two faces of transforming growth factor beta; in carcinogenesis</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>100</vid>, <ppf>8621</ppf>ndash;<ppl>8623</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b14">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGFbeta; in cancer</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>134</vid>, <ppf>215</ppf>ndash;<ppl>230</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b15">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Levy</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Hill</snm>, <fnm>C. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Alterations in components of the TGF-beta; superfamily signaling pathways in human cancer</atl>. <jtl>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev.</jtl>
                    <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>41</ppf>ndash;<ppl>58</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b16">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Hawinkels</snm>, <fnm>L. J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Ten Dijke</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Exploring anti-TGF-beta; therapies in cancer and fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Growth Factors</jtl>
                    <vid>29</vid>, <ppf>140</ppf>ndash;<ppl>152</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b17">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Harradine</snm>, <fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Mutations of TGFbeta; signaling molecules in human disease</atl>. <jtl>Ann. Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>38</vid>, <ppf>403</ppf>ndash;<ppl>414</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b18">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Millan</snm>, <fnm>F. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Denhez</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kondaiah</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Embryonic gene expression patterns of TGF beta;1, beta;2 and beta;3 suggest different developmental functions <i>in vivo</i></atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl>
                    <vid>111</vid>, <ppf>131</ppf>ndash;<ppl>143</ppl> (<cd year="1991">1991</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b19">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Kulkarni</snm>, <fnm>A. B.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor beta;1 null mutation in mice causes excessive inflammatory response and early death</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>90</vid>, <ppf>770</ppf>ndash;<ppl>774</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b20">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Shull</snm>, <fnm>M. M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Targeted disruption of the mouse transforming growth factor-beta;1 gene results in multifocal inflammatory disease</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl>
                    <vid>359</vid>, <ppf>693</ppf>ndash;<ppl>699</ppl> (<cd year="1992">1992</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b21">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Dickson</snm>, <fnm>M. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Defective haematopoiesis and vasculogenesis in transforming growth factor-beta;1 knock out mice</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl>
                    <vid>121</vid>, <ppf>1845</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1854</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b22">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Sanford</snm>, <fnm>L. P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGFbeta;2 knockout mice have multiple developmental defects that are non-overlapping with other TGFbeta; knockout phenotypes</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl>
                    <vid>124</vid>, <ppf>2659</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2670</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b23">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Proetzel</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta;3 is required for secondary palate fusion</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl>
                    <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>409</ppf>ndash;<ppl>414</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b24">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Schultz-Cherry</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ribeiro</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gentry</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Murphy-Ullrich</snm>, <fnm>J. E.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Thrombospondin binds and activates the small and large forms of latent transforming growth factor-beta; in a chemically defined system</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl>
                    <vid>269</vid>, <ppf>26775</ppf>ndash;<ppl>26782</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b25">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Munger</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The integrin alpha;vbeta;6 binds and activates latent TGF beta;1: a mechanism for regulating pulmonary inflammation and fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>96</vid>, <ppf>319</ppf>ndash;<ppl>328</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b26">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Shi</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Latent TGF-beta; structure and activation</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl>
                    <vid>474</vid>, <ppf>343</ppf>ndash;<ppl>349</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b27">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Shi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Mechanisms of TGF-beta; signaling from cell membrane to the nucleus</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>113</vid>, <ppf>685</ppf>ndash;<ppl>700</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b28">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Davis-Dusenbery</snm>, <fnm>B. N.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Hata</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Smad-mediated miRNA processing: a critical role for a conserved RNA sequence</atl>. <jtl>RNA Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>71</ppf>ndash;<ppl>76</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b29">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Oft</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta;1 and Ha-Ras collaborate in modulating the phenotypic plasticity and invasiveness of epithelial tumor cells</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl>
                    <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>2462</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2477</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b30">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Gomis</snm>, <fnm>R. R.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>The logic of TGFbeta; signaling</atl>. <jtl>FEBS Lett.</jtl>
                    <vid>580</vid>, <ppf>2811</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2820</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b31">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>How cells read TGF-beta; signals</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>169</ppf>ndash;<ppl>178</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b32">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Mehra</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Wrana</snm>, <fnm>J. L.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGF-beta; and the Smad signal transduction pathway</atl>. <jtl>Biochem. Cell Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>605</ppf>ndash;<ppl>622</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b33">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Padua</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Roles of TGFbeta; in metastasis</atl>. <jtl>Cell Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>89</ppf>ndash;<ppl>102</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b34">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Heldin</snm>, <fnm>C. H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Landstrom</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Moustakas</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Mechanism of TGF-beta; signaling to growth arrest, apoptosis, and epithelialndash;mesenchymal transition</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>166</ppf>ndash;<ppl>176</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b35">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Dooley</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>ten Dijke</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGF-beta; in progression of liver disease</atl>. <jtl>Cell Tissue Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>347</vid>, <ppf>245</ppf>ndash;<ppl>256</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b36">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Pardali</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Ten Dijke</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGFbeta; signaling and cardiovascular diseases</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Biol. Sci.</jtl>
                    <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>195</ppf>ndash;<ppl>213</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b37">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Derynck</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Balmain</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGF-beta; signaling in tumor suppression and cancer progression</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl>
                    <vid>29</vid>, <ppf>117</ppf>ndash;<ppl>129</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b38">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Coffey</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm>
                        <suff>Jr.</suff></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Growth modulation of mouse keratinocytes by transforming growth factors</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>48</vid>, <ppf>1596</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1602</ppl> (<cd year="1988">1988</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b39">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Gomis</snm>, <fnm>R. R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>A FoxO-Smad synexpression group in human keratinocytes</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>103</vid>, <ppf>12747</ppf>ndash;<ppl>12752</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b40">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Siegel</snm>, <fnm>P. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shu</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Mad upregulation and Id2 repression accompany transforming growth factor (TGF)-beta;-mediated epithelial cell growth suppression</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl>
                    <vid>278</vid>, <ppf>35444</ppf>ndash;<ppl>35450</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b41">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>The paradoxical TGF-beta; vasculopathies</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl>
                    <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>838</ppf>ndash;<ppl>839</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b42">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Heldin</snm>, <fnm>C. H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rubin</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pietras</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Ostman</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>High interstitial fluid pressure mdash; an obstacle in cancer therapy</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Cancer</jtl>
                    <vid>4</vid>, <ppf>806</ppf>ndash;<ppl>813</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b43">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Mani</snm>, <fnm>S. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The epithelial-mesenchymal transition generates cells with properties of stem cells</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>133</vid>, <ppf>704</ppf>ndash;<ppl>715</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b44">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Salnikov</snm>, <fnm>A. V.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibition of TGF-beta; modulates macrophages and vessel maturation in parallel to a lowering of interstitial fluid pressure in experimental carcinoma</atl>. <jtl>Lab. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>85</vid>, <ppf>512</ppf>ndash;<ppl>521</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b45">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Willis</snm>, <fnm>B. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Induction of epithelial-mesenchymal transition in alveolar epithelial cells by transforming growth factor-beta;1: potential role in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Am. J. Pathol.</jtl>
                    <vid>166</vid>, <ppf>1321</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1332</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b46">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>K. K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Alveolar epithelial cell mesenchymal transition develops <i>in vivo</i> during pulmonary fibrosis and is regulated by the extracellular matrix</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>103</vid>, <ppf>13180</ppf>ndash;<ppl>13185</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b47">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Goumans</snm>, <fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>van Zonneveld</snm>, <fnm>A. J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>ten Dijke</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Transforming growth factor beta;-induced endothelial-to-mesenchymal transition: a switch to cardiac fibrosis?</atl>
                    <jtl>Trends Cardiovasc. Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>293</ppf>ndash;<ppl>298</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b48">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Sato</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Muragaki</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Saika</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Roberts</snm>, <fnm>A. B.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Ooshima</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Targeted disruption of TGF-beta;1/Smad3 signaling protects against renal tubulointerstitial fibrosis induced by unilateral ureteral obstruction</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>112</vid>, <ppf>1486</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1494</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b49">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Lan</snm>, <fnm>H. Y.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Diverse roles of TGF-beta;/Smads in renal fibrosis and inflammation</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Biol. Sci.</jtl>
                    <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>1056</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1067</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b50">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Yao</snm>, <fnm>E. H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>A pyrrole-imidazole polyamide targeting transforming growth factor-beta;1 inhibits restenosis and preserves endothelialization in the injured artery</atl>. <jtl>Cardiovasc. Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>797</ppf>ndash;<ppl>804</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>). <newline/><b>This study evaluates the potential use of a pyrrole-imidazole polyamide that targets <i>TGFB1</i> expression for preventing restenosis after the use of drug-eluting stents</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b51">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Tsai</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta; through Smad3 signaling stimulates vascular smooth muscle cell proliferation and neointimal formation</atl>. <jtl>Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol.</jtl>
                    <vid>297</vid>, <ppf>H540</ppf>ndash;<ppl>H549</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>). <newline/><b>This study demonstrates the role of the TGFbeta;ndash;SMAD3 pathway in the development of intimal hyperplasia in response to endothelial injury</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b52">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Fu</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>SM16, an orally active TGFbeta; type I receptor inhibitor prevents myofibroblast induction and vascular fibrosis in the rat carotid injury model</atl>. <jtl>Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>28</vid>, <ppf>665</ppf>ndash;<ppl>671</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b53">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Nishimura</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>delta;EF1 mediates TGF-beta; signaling in vascular smooth muscle cell differentiation</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>93</ppf>ndash;<ppl>104</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b54">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Diebold</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Early-onset multifocal inflammation in the transforming growth factor beta;1-null mouse is lymphocyte mediated</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>92</vid>, <ppf>12215</ppf>ndash;<ppl>12219</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b55">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Rubtsov</snm>, <fnm>Y. P.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Rudensky</snm>, <fnm>A. Y.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGFbeta; signalling in control of T-cell-mediated self-reactivity</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Immunol.</jtl>
                    <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>443</ppf>ndash;<ppl>453</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b56">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ramesh</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wildey</snm>, <fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Howe</snm>, <fnm>P. H.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Transforming growth factor beta; (TGFbeta;)-induced apoptosis: the rise and fall of Bim</atl>. <jtl>Cell Cycle</jtl>
                    <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>11</ppf>ndash;<ppl>17</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b57">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Maruyama</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Control of the differentiation of regulatory T cells and T<sub>H</sub>17 cells by the DNA-binding inhibitor Id3</atl>. <jtl>Nature Immunol.</jtl>
                    <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>86</ppf>ndash;<ppl>95</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b58">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Gorelik</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Flavell</snm>, <fnm>R. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Immune-mediated eradication of tumors through the blockade of transforming growth factor-beta; signaling in T cells</atl>. <jtl>Nature Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>1118</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1122</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>). <newline/><b>This study shows that T cell-specific blockade of TGFbeta; signalling using a dominant negative type II receptor potentiates immune eradication of tumours in mice challenged with live tumour cells</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b59">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Yamaguchi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tsumura</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Miwa</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Inaba</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Contrasting effects of TGF-beta;1 and TNF-alpha; on the development of dendritic cells from progenitors in mouse bone marrow</atl>. <jtl>Stem Cells</jtl>
                    <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>144</ppf>ndash;<ppl>153</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b60">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Sato</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta;1 reciprocally controls chemotaxis of human peripheral blood monocyte-derived dendritic cells via chemokine receptors</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl>
                    <vid>164</vid>, <ppf>2285</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2295</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b61">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bettelli</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Reciprocal developmental pathways for the generation of pathogenic effector T<sub>H</sub>17 and regulatory T cells</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl>
                    <vid>441</vid>, <ppf>235</ppf>ndash;<ppl>238</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b62">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Mangan</snm>, <fnm>P. R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta; induces development of the T<sub>H</sub>17 lineage</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl>
                    <vid>441</vid>, <ppf>231</ppf>ndash;<ppl>234</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b63">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Gutcher</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Autocrine transforming growth factor-beta;1 promotes <i>in vivo</i> T<sub>H</sub>17 cell differentiation</atl>. <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
                    <vid>34</vid>, <ppf>396</ppf>ndash;<ppl>408</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b64">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Annunziato</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Romagnani</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Mouse T helper 17 phenotype: not so different than in man after all</atl>. <jtl>Cytokine</jtl>
                    <vid>56</vid>, <ppf>112</ppf>ndash;<ppl>115</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b65">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Das</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor beta; is dispensable for the molecular orchestration of T<sub>H</sub>17 cell differentiation</atl>. <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>206</vid>, <ppf>2407</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2416</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b66">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ghoreschi</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Generation of pathogenic T<sub>H</sub>17 cells in the absence of TGF-beta; signalling</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl>
                    <vid>467</vid>, <ppf>967</ppf>ndash;<ppl>971</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b67">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Laouar</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sutterwala</snm>, <fnm>F. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gorelik</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Flavell</snm>, <fnm>R. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta; controls T helper type 1 cell development through regulation of natural killer cell interferon-gamma;</atl>. <jtl>Nature Immunol.</jtl>
                    <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>600</ppf>ndash;<ppl>607</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b68">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Mantovani</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sozzani</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Locati</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Allavena</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Sica</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Macrophage polarization: tumor-associated macrophages as a paradigm for polarized M2 mononuclear phagocytes</atl>. <jtl>Trends Immunol.</jtl>
                    <vid>23</vid>, <ppf>549</ppf>ndash;<ppl>555</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b69">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Fridlender</snm>, <fnm>Z. G.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Polarization of tumor-associated neutrophil phenotype by TGF-beta;: ldquo;N1rdquo; versus ldquo;N2rdquo; TAN</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>183</ppf>ndash;<ppl>194</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>). <newline/><b>This study shows that TGFbeta; blockade increases neutrophil-attracting chemokines, and 'depolarizes' the invading tumour-associated neutrophils to become more cytotoxic to tumour cells and to express higher levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b70">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Schlingensiepen</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Intracerebral and intrathecal infusion of the TGF-beta;2-specific antisense phosphorothioate oligonucleotide AP 12009 in rabbits and primates: toxicology and safety</atl>. <jtl>Oligonucleotides</jtl>
                    <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>94</ppf>ndash;<ppl>104</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b71">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Schlingensiepen</snm>, <fnm>K. H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Targeted tumor therapy with the TGF-beta;2 antisense compound AP 12009</atl>. <jtl>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev.</jtl>
                    <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>129</ppf>ndash;<ppl>139</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b72">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Jachimczak</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The effect of transforming growth factor-beta;2-specific phosphorothioate-anti-sense oligodeoxynucleotides in reversing cellular immunosuppression in malignant glioma</atl>. <jtl>J. Neurosurg.</jtl>
                    <vid>78</vid>, <ppf>944</ppf>ndash;<ppl>951</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b73">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Schlingensiepen</snm>, <fnm>K. H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta;2 gene silencing with trabedersen (AP 12009) in pancreatic cancer</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Sci.</jtl>
                    <vid>102</vid>, <ppf>1193</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1200</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b74">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bogdahn</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Targeted therapy for high-grade glioma with the TGF-beta;2 inhibitor trabedersen: results of a randomized and controlled phase IIb study</atl>. <jtl>Neuro Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>132</ppf>ndash;<ppl>142</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>). <newline/><b>This is the full report of a randomized, open-label, active-controlled, dose-finding Phase IIb study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of trabedersen (AP12009) administered intra-tumourally by convection-enhanced delivery in patients with recurrent or refractory high-grade glioma</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b75">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Santiago</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Topical application of a peptide inhibitor of transforming growth factor-beta;1 ameliorates bleomycin-induced skin fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>J. Invest. Dermatol.</jtl>
                    <vid>125</vid>, <ppf>450</ppf>ndash;<ppl>455</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>). <newline/><b>This is the first evidence that the peptide inhibitor P144 may be efficacious in the treatment of skin fibrosis after topical application</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b76">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Llopiz</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Peptide inhibitors of transforming growth factor-beta; enhance the efficacy of antitumor immunotherapy</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Cancer</jtl>
                    <vid>125</vid>, <ppf>2614</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2623</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b77">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Hermida</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>A synthetic peptide from transforming growth factor-beta;1 type III receptor prevents myocardial fibrosis in spontaneously hypertensive rats</atl>. <jtl>Cardiovascular Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>601</ppf>ndash;<ppl>609</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>). <newline/><b>This study shows that P144 inhibits the TGFbeta;1-dependent signalling pathway and prevents myocardial fibrosis</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b78">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ezquerro</snm>, <fnm>I. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>A synthetic peptide from transforming growth factor beta; type III receptor inhibits liver fibrogenesis in rats with carbon tetrachloride liver injury</atl>. <jtl>Cytokine</jtl>
                    <vid>22</vid>, <ppf>12</ppf>ndash;<ppl>20</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b79">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Nam</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>An anti-transforming growth factor beta; antibody suppresses metastasis via cooperative effects on multiple cell compartments</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>3835</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3843</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b80">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ganapathy</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Targeting the transforming growth factor-beta; pathway inhibits human basal-like breast cancer metastasis</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cancer</jtl>
                    <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>122</ppf> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b81">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bouquet</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGFbeta;1 inhibition increases the radiosensitivity of breast cancer cells <i>in vitro</i> and promotes tumor control by radiation <i>in vivo</i></atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>6754</ppf>ndash;<ppl>6765</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b82">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Rodon Ahnert</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>First human dose (FHD) study of the oral transforming growth factor-beta; receptor I kinase inhibitor LY2157299 in patients with treatment-refractory malignant glioma</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>29</vid>, Abstract <ppf>3011</ppf> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b83">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Schlingensiepen</snm>, <fnm>K. H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fischer-Blass</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Schmaus</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Ludwig</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Antisense therapeutics for tumor treatment: the TGF-beta;2 inhibitor AP 12009 in clinical development against malignant tumors</atl>. <jtl>Recent Results Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>177</vid>, <ppf>137</ppf>ndash;<ppl>150</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b84">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Oettle</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Final results of a phase I/II study in patients with pancreatic cancer, malignant melanoma, and colorectal carcinoma with trabedersen</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>30</vid>, Abstract <ppf>4034</ppf> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b85">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Nemunaitis</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Phase II study of belagenpumatucel-L, a transforming growth factor beta;-2 antisense gene-modified allogeneic tumor cell vaccine in non-small-cell lung cancer</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>24</vid>, <ppf>4721</ppf>ndash;<ppl>4730</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>). <newline/><b>This paper reports the first Phase II trial of the non-viral, gene-based, allogeneic tumour cell vaccine of antisense TGFbeta;2-transfected NSCLC cells. This vaccine shows great promise in increasing survival rates for NSCLC</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b86">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Nemunaitis</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Phase II trial of Belagenpumatucel-L, a TGF-beta;2 antisense gene modified allogeneic tumor vaccine in advanced non small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Gene Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>620</ppf>ndash;<ppl>624</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b87">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bazhenova</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Carrier</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shawler</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Fakhrai</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Long-term survival in a phase II study of belagenpumatucel-L (antisense TGFbeta; vaccine) in non small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC)</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>72</vid>, Abstract <ppf>5367</ppf> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b88">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Mead</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wong</snm>, <fnm>T. T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cordeiro</snm>, <fnm>M. F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>I. K.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Khaw</snm>, <fnm>P. T.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Evaluation of anti-TGF-beta;2 antibody as a new postoperative anti-scarring agent in glaucoma surgery</atl>. <jtl>Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</jtl>
                    <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>3394</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3401</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b89">
                <reftxt>CAT-152 0201 Trabeculectomy Study Group. <atl>CAT-152 trabeculectomy study</atl>. <jtl>Ophthalmology</jtl>
                    <vid>114</vid>, <ppf>1950</ppf> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b90">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Denton</snm>, <fnm>C. P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Recombinant human anti-transforming growth factor beta;1 antibody therapy in systemic sclerosis: a multicenter, randomized, placebo-controlled phase I/II trial of CAT-192</atl>. <jtl>Arthritis Rheum.</jtl>
                    <vid>56</vid>, <ppf>323</ppf>ndash;<ppl>333</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>). <newline/><b>This report evaluates CAT-192, a recombinant human antibody that neutralizes TGFbeta;1, in the treatment of early-stage diffuse cutaneous systemic sclerosis and concludes that there is no evidence of efficacy</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b91">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Lonning</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mannick</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>McPherson</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Antibody targeting of TGF-beta; in cancer patients</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Pharm. Biotechnol.</jtl>
                    <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>2176</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2189</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b92">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Trachtman</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>A phase 1, single-dose study of fresolimumab, an anti-TGF-beta; antibody, in treatment-resistant primary focal segmental glomerulosclerosis</atl>. <jtl>Kidney Int.</jtl>
                    <vid>79</vid>, <ppf>1236</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1243</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b93">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Morris</snm>, <fnm>J. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Phase I/II study of GC1008: a human anti-transforming growth factor-beta (TGFbeta;) monoclonal antibody (MAb) in patients with advanced malignant melanoma (MM) or renal cell carcinoma (RCC)</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>26</vid>, Abstract <ppf>9028</ppf> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b94">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhong</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Anti-transforming growth factor beta; receptor II antibody has therapeutic efficacy against primary tumor growth and metastasis through multieffects on cancer, stroma, and immune cells</atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>1191</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1205</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b95">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Van Aarsen</snm>, <fnm>L. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Antibody-mediated blockade of integrin alpha;vbeta;6 inhibits tumor progression <i>in vivo</i> by a transforming growth factor-beta;-regulated mechanism</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>561</ppf>ndash;<ppl>570</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b96">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Muraoka</snm>, <fnm>R. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Blockade of TGF-beta; inhibits mammary tumor cell viability, migration, and metastases</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>109</vid>, <ppf>1551</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1559</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b97">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Lu</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Miao</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Schoeb</snm>, <fnm>T. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Agarwal</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Murphy-Ullrich</snm>, <fnm>J. E.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Blockade of TSP1-dependent TGF-beta; activity reduces renal injury and proteinuria in a murine model of diabetic nephropathy</atl>. <jtl>Am. J. Pathol.</jtl>
                    <vid>178</vid>, <ppf>2573</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2586</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b98">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Yingling</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Blanchard</snm>, <fnm>K. L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Sawyer</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Development of TGF-beta; signalling inhibitors for cancer therapy</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Drug Discov.</jtl>
                    <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>1011</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1022</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b99">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bonafoux</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>W. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Strategies for TGF-beta; modulation: a review of recent patents</atl>. <jtl>Expert Opin. Ther. Pat.</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>1759</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1769</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b100">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Saunier</snm>, <fnm>E. F.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGFbeta; inhibition for cancer therapy</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Cancer Drug Targets</jtl>
                    <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>519</ppf>ndash;<ppl>532</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b101">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Large- and small-molecule inhibitors of transforming growth factor-beta signaling</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Investig. Drugs</jtl>
                    <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>513</ppf>ndash;<ppl>521</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b102">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Washio</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transcriptional inhibition of hypertrophic scars by a gene silencer, pyrrole-imidazole polyamide, targeting the TGF-beta;1 promoter</atl>. <jtl>J. Invest. Dermatol.</jtl>
                    <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>1987</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1995</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b103">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Pretranscriptional regulation of Tgf-beta;1 by PI polyamide prevents scarring and accelerates wound healing of the cornea after exposure to alkali</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>519</ppf>ndash;<ppl>527</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b104">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>H. Y.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The protective role of Smad7 in diabetic kidney disease: mechanism and therapeutic potential</atl>. <jtl>Diabetes</jtl>
                    <vid>60</vid>, <ppf>590</ppf>ndash;<ppl>601</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b105">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Kapoor</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Smad7 gene transfer therapy: therapeutic applications beyond colonic fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Eur. J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>38</vid>, <ppf>876</ppf>ndash;<ppl>877</ppl>; author reply <ppf>878</ppf>ndash;<ppl>880</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b106">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Sheridan</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Gene therapy finds its niche</atl>. <jtl>Nature Biotech.</jtl>
                    <vid>29</vid>, <ppf>121</ppf>ndash;<ppl>128</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b107">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Foster</snm>, <fnm>A. E.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Antitumor activity of EBV-specific T lymphocytes transduced with a dominant negative TGF-beta; receptor</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunother.</jtl>
                    <vid>31</vid>, <ppf>500</ppf>ndash;<ppl>505</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b108">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Rainusso</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Immunotherapy targeting HER2 with genetically modified T cells eliminates tumor-initiating cells in osteosarcoma</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Gene Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>212</ppf>ndash;<ppl>217</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b109">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Nakazawa</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>PiggyBac-mediated cancer immunotherapy using EBV-specific cytotoxic T-cells expressing HER2-specific chimeric antigen receptor</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>2133</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2143</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b110">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ahmed</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>HER2-specific T cells target primary glioblastoma stem cells and induce regression of autologous experimental tumors</atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>474</ppf>ndash;<ppl>485</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b111">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ahmed</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Regression of experimental medulloblastoma following transfer of HER2-specific T cells</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>5957</ppf>ndash;<ppl>5964</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b112">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Laverty</snm>, <fnm>H. G.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Effects of avotermin (transforming growth factor beta;3) in a clinically relevant pig model of long, full-thickness incisional wounds</atl>. <jtl>J. Cutan. Med. Surg.</jtl>
                    <vid>14</vid>, <ppf>223</ppf>ndash;<ppl>232</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b113">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Cohn</snm>, <fnm>R. D.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Angiotensin II type 1 receptor blockade attenuates TGF-beta;-induced failure of muscle regeneration in multiple myopathic states</atl>. <jtl>Nature Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>204</ppf>ndash;<ppl>210</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b114">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Podowski</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Angiotensin receptor blockade attenuates cigarette smoke-induced lung injury and rescues lung architecture in mice</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>122</vid>, <ppf>229</ppf>ndash;<ppl>240</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b115">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Lanz</snm>, <fnm>T. V.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Angiotensin II sustains brain inflammation in mice via TGF-beta;</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>120</vid>, <ppf>2782</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2794</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b116">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhou</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Latham</snm>, <fnm>C. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zander</snm>, <fnm>D. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Margolin</snm>, <fnm>S. B.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Visner</snm>, <fnm>G. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Pirfenidone inhibits obliterative airway disease in mouse tracheal allografts</atl>. <jtl>J. Heart Lung Transplant.</jtl>
                    <vid>24</vid>, <ppf>1577</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1585</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b117">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Taniguchi</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The clinical significance of 5% change in vital capacity in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: extended analysis of the pirfenidone trial</atl>. <jtl>Respir. Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>93</ppf> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b118">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Noble</snm>, <fnm>P. W.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Pirfenidone in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (CAPACITY): two randomised trials</atl>. <jtl>Lancet</jtl>
                    <vid>377</vid>, <ppf>1760</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1769</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b119">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Grainger</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The serum concentration of active transforming growth factor-beta; is severely depressed in advanced atherosclerosis</atl>. <jtl>Nature Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>74</ppf>ndash;<ppl>79</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b120">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Cui</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGFbeta;1 inhibits the formation of benign skin tumors, but enhances progression to invasive spindle carcinomas in transgenic mice</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>86</vid>, <ppf>531</ppf>ndash;<ppl>542</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b121">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bierie</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Moses</snm>, <fnm>H. L.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Gain or loss of TGFbeta; signaling in mammary carcinoma cells can promote metastasis</atl>. <jtl>Cell Cycle</jtl>
                    <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>3319</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3327</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b122">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bierie</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Abrogation of TGF-beta; signaling enhances chemokine production and correlates with prognosis in human breast cancer</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>119</vid>, <ppf>1571</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1582</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b123">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Larsson</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Abnormal angiogenesis but intact hematopoietic potential in TGF-beta; type I receptor-deficient mice</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl>
                    <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>1663</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1673</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b124">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGF-beta; antagonists: why suppress a tumor suppressor?</atl>
                    <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>109</vid>, <ppf>1533</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1536</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b125">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Yang</snm>, <fnm>Y. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Lifetime exposure to a soluble TGF-beta; antagonist protects mice against metastasis without adverse side effects</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>109</vid>, <ppf>1607</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1615</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>). <newline/><b>This is the first demonstration that long-term exposure to a TGFbeta; antagonist in mice does not manifest any major adverse effects</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b126">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Anderton</snm>, <fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Induction of heart valve lesions by small-molecule ALK5 inhibitors</atl>. <jtl>Toxicol. Pathol.</jtl>
                    <vid>39</vid>, <ppf>916</ppf>ndash;<ppl>924</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b127">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Frazier</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibition of ALK5 signaling induces physeal dysplasia in rats</atl>. <jtl>Toxicol. Pathol.</jtl>
                    <vid>35</vid>, <ppf>284</ppf>ndash;<ppl>295</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b128">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Goudie</snm>, <fnm>D. R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Multiple self-healing squamous epithelioma is caused by a disease-specific spectrum of mutations in <i>TGFBR1</i></atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl>
                    <vid>43</vid>, <ppf>365</ppf>ndash;<ppl>369</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b129">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Chapman</snm>, <fnm>P. B.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Improved survival with vemurafenib in melanoma with BRAF V600E mutation</atl>. <jtl>N. Engl. J. Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>364</vid>, <ppf>2507</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2516</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b130">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Arnault</snm>, <fnm>J. P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Keratoacanthomas and squamous cell carcinomas in patients receiving sorafenib</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>27</vid>, <ppf>e59</ppf>ndash;<ppl>e61</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b131">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Esser</snm>, <fnm>A. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Abril</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fayne</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Doyle</snm>, <fnm>J. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Acute development of multiple keratoacanthomas and squamous cell carcinomas after treatment with infliximab</atl>. <jtl>J. Am. Acad. Dermatol.</jtl>
                    <vid>50</vid>, <ppf>S75</ppf>ndash;<ppl>S77</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b132">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Su</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>RAS mutations in cutaneous squamous-cell carcinomas in patients treated with BRAF inhibitors</atl>. <jtl>N. Engl. J. Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>366</vid>, <ppf>207</ppf>ndash;<ppl>215</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b133">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Arnault</snm>, <fnm>J. P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Skin tumors induced by sorafenib; paradoxic RAS-RAF pathway activation and oncogenic mutations of <i>HRAS, TP53</i>, and <i>TGFBR1</i></atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>263</ppf>ndash;<ppl>272</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b134">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Singh</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Settleman</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>EMT, cancer stem cells and drug resistance: an emerging axis of evil in the war on cancer</atl>. <jtl>Oncogene</jtl>
                    <vid>29</vid>, <ppf>4741</ppf>ndash;<ppl>4751</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b135">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Shipitsin</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Molecular definition of breast tumor heterogeneity</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>259</ppf>ndash;<ppl>273</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b136">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ikushima</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Autocrine TGF-beta; signaling maintains tumorigenicity of glioma-initiating cells through Sry-related HMG-box factors</atl>. <jtl>Cell Stem Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>504</ppf>ndash;<ppl>514</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b137">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Anido</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta; receptor inhibitors target the CD44<super>high</super>/Id1<super>high</super> glioma-initiating cell population in human glioblastoma</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>655</ppf>ndash;<ppl>668</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>). <newline/><b>This is a demonstration of the targeting of tumour-initiating cells by TGFbeta; blockade in a mouse model of glioblastoma</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b138">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Penuelas</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta; increases glioma-initiating cell self-renewal through the induction of LIF in human glioblastoma</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>315</ppf>ndash;<ppl>327</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b139">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Naka</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta;ndash;FOXO signalling maintains leukaemia-initiating cells in chronic myeloid leukaemia</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl>
                    <vid>463</vid>, <ppf>676</ppf>ndash;<ppl>680</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>). <newline/><b>This is a demonstration of the targeting of leukaemia-initiating cells by TGFbeta; blockade in a mouse model of chronic myeloid leukaemia</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b140">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bragado</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Microenvironmental signals dictate disseminated tumor cells (DTCs) fate through regulation of TGFbeta;II and p38alpha;</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>72</vid> (<iid>Suppl. 1</iid>), Abstract <ppf>5234</ppf> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b141">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Biswas</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yang</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zhao</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Sun</snm>, <fnm>L. Z.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Development of murine models of breast cancer metastasis for the evaluation of the efficacy of TGF-beta; inhibitors as therapeutic agents</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>72</vid> (<iid>Suppl. 1</iid>), Abstract <ppf>1366</ppf> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b142">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ohmori</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yang</snm>, <fnm>J. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Price</snm>, <fnm>J. O.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Arteaga</snm>, <fnm>C. L.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Blockade of tumor cell transforming growth factor-beta;s enhances cell cycle progression and sensitizes human breast carcinoma cells to cytotoxic chemotherapy</atl>. <jtl>Exp. Cell Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>245</vid>, <ppf>350</ppf>ndash;<ppl>359</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b143">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ehata</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta; decreases the cancer-initiating cell population within diffuse-type gastric carcinoma cells</atl>. <jtl>Oncogene</jtl>
                    <vid>30</vid>, <ppf>1693</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1705</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b144">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Tang</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta; can suppress tumorigenesis through effects on the putative cancer stem or early progenitor cell and committed progeny in a breast cancer xenograft model</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>8643</ppf>ndash;<ppl>8652</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b145">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Quante</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Bone marrow-derived myofibroblasts contribute to the mesenchymal stem cell niche and promote tumor growth</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>257</ppf>ndash;<ppl>272</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b146">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Hayashi</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor beta; receptor I kinase inhibitor down-regulates cytokine secretion and multiple myeloma cell growth in the bone marrow microenvironment</atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>7540</ppf>ndash;<ppl>7546</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>). <newline/><b>This is the first report of a chemical inhibitor of Tbeta;RI showing antitumour effects via activity on the tumour microenvironment in a mouse model of multiple myeloma</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b147">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bandyopadhyay</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Doxorubicin in combination with a small TGFbeta; inhibitor: a potential novel therapy for metastatic breast cancer in mouse models</atl>. <jtl>PLoS ONE</jtl>
                    <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>e10365</ppf> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b148">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Takeuchi</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta; inhibition restores terminal osteoblast differentiation to suppress myeloma growth</atl>. <jtl>PLoS ONE</jtl>
                    <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>e9870</ppf> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b149">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Yin</snm>, <fnm>J. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta; signaling blockade inhibits PTHrP secretion by breast cancer cells and bone metastases development</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>103</vid>, <ppf>197</ppf>ndash;<ppl>206</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b150">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Shinto</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Combination effect of a TGF-beta; receptor kinase inhibitor with 5-FU analog S1 on lymph node metastasis of scirrhous gastric cancer in mice</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Sci.</jtl>
                    <vid>101</vid>, <ppf>1846</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1852</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b151">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Kano</snm>, <fnm>M. R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Improvement of cancer-targeting therapy, using nanocarriers for intractable solid tumors by inhibition of TGF-beta; signaling</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>104</vid>, <ppf>3460</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3465</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b152">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Zeng</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Cancer and innate immune system interactions: translational potentials for cancer immunotherapy</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunother.</jtl>
                    <vid>35</vid>, <ppf>299</ppf>ndash;<ppl>308</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b153">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Immunotherapy for human renal cell carcinoma by adoptive transfer of autologous transforming growth factor beta;-insensitive CD8<super>+</super> T cells</atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>164</ppf>ndash;<ppl>173</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b154">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhang</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Blockade of transforming growth factor-beta; signaling in tumor-reactive CD8<super>+</super> T cells activates the antitumor immune response cycle</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cancer Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>1733</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1743</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b155">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Wallace</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta; receptor blockade augments the effectiveness of adoptive T-cell therapy of established solid cancers</atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>14</vid>, <ppf>3966</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3974</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>). <newline/><b>This is the first demonstration of the use of a chemical TGFbeta; receptor inhibitor augmenting adoptive T cell therapy via its immunomodulatory effects</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b156">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Connolly</snm>, <fnm>E. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Outgrowth of drug-resistant carcinomas expressing markers of tumor aggression after long term Tbeta;RI/II kinase inhibition with LY2109761</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>71</vid>, <ppf>1</ppf>ndash;<ppl>11</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b157">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhang</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Blockade of TGF-beta; signaling by the TGFbeta;R-I kinase inhibitor LY2109761 enhances radiation response and prolongs survival in glioblastoma</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>71</vid>, <ppf>7155</ppf>ndash;<ppl>7167</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b158">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Barcellos-Hoff</snm>, <fnm>M. H.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Akhurst</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Transforming growth factor-beta; in breast cancer: too much, too late</atl>. <jtl>Breast Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>202</ppf> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b159">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Kirshner</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibition of transforming growth factor-beta;1 signaling attenuates ataxia telangiectasia mutated activity in response to genotoxic stress</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>66</vid>, <ppf>10861</ppf>ndash;<ppl>10869</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b160">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhou</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Reduced SMAD7 leads to overactivation of TGF-beta; signaling in MDS that can be reversed by a specific inhibitor of TGF-beta; receptor I kinase</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>71</vid>, <ppf>955</ppf>ndash;<ppl>963</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b161">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Cerri</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Spagnolo</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Luppi</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Richeldi</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Management of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Clin. Chest Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>33</vid>, <ppf>85</ppf>ndash;<ppl>94</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b162">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Sheppard</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Transforming growth factor beta;: a central modulator of pulmonary and airway inflammation and fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Am. Thorac. Soc.</jtl>
                    <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>413</ppf>ndash;<ppl>417</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b163">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Katsumoto</snm>, <fnm>T. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Violette</snm>, <fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Sheppard</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Blocking TGFbeta; via inhibition of the alpha;vbeta;6 integrin: a possible therapy for systemic sclerosis interstitial lung disease</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Rheumatol.</jtl>
                    <vid>2011</vid>, <ppf>208219</ppf> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>). <newline/><b>This report summarizes the inhibition of alpha;Vbeta;6 integrin as an attractive therapeutic option for systemic sclerosis and interstitial lung disease mediated by TGFbeta;</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b164">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Chapman</snm>, <fnm>H. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Epithelial-mesenchymal interactions in pulmonary fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Annu. Rev. Physiol.</jtl>
                    <vid>73</vid>, <ppf>413</ppf>ndash;<ppl>435</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b165">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Azuma</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Pirfenidone treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Ther. Adv. Respir. Dis.</jtl>
                    <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>107</ppf>ndash;<ppl>114</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>). <newline/><b>This report summarizes the outcome of a number of clinical trials of pirfenidone, which is the first antifibrotic agent to be approved for the treatment of IPF</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b166">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Yamada</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Gene transfer of soluble transforming growth factor type II receptor by <i>in vivo</i> electroporation attenuates lung injury and fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Pathol.</jtl>
                    <vid>60</vid>, <ppf>916</ppf>ndash;<ppl>920</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b167">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Arribillaga</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Therapeutic effect of a peptide inhibitor of TGF-beta; on pulmonary fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Cytokine</jtl>
                    <vid>53</vid>, <ppf>327</ppf>ndash;<ppl>333</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b168">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Crunkhorn</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Deal watch: Biogen acquires Stromedix to pursue novel fibrosis therapy</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Drug Discov.</jtl>
                    <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>260</ppf> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b169">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Allison</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Stromedix acquisition signals growing interest in fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Nature Biotech.</jtl>
                    <vid>30</vid>, <ppf>375</ppf>ndash;<ppl>376</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b170">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Renal fibrosis: new insights into the pathogenesis and therapeutics</atl>. <jtl>Kidney Int.</jtl>
                    <vid>69</vid>, <ppf>213</ppf>ndash;<ppl>217</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b171">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Fragiadaki</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Mason</snm>, <fnm>R. M.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Epithelial-mesenchymal transition in renal fibrosis mdash; evidence for and against</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Exp. Pathol.</jtl>
                    <vid>92</vid>, <ppf>143</ppf>ndash;<ppl>150</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b172">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Alan</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kocoglu</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Altintas</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Alici</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Resit Ersay</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Protective effect of decorin on acute ischaemia-reperfusion injury in the rat kidney</atl>. <jtl>Arch. Med. Sci.</jtl>
                    <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>211</ppf>ndash;<ppl>216</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b173">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Terada</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Gene transfer of Smad7 using electroporation of adenovirus prevents renal fibrosis in post-obstructed kidney</atl>. <jtl>Kidney Int.</jtl>
                    <vid>61</vid>, <ppf>S94</ppf>ndash;<ppl>S98</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>). <newline/><b>This report indicates that genetic transfer of <i>Smad7</i> prevents unilateral ureteral obstruction-induced renal fibrosis, suggesting that SMAD7 may be applicable for the treatment of renal fibrosis</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b174">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Lim</snm>, <fnm>D. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Angiotensin II blockade reverses myocardial fibrosis in a transgenic mouse model of human hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</atl>. <jtl>Circulation</jtl>
                    <vid>103</vid>, <ppf>789</ppf>ndash;<ppl>791</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b175">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>van Rooij</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Olson</snm>, <fnm>E. N.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Searching for miR-acles in cardiac fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Circ. Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>104</vid>, <ppf>138</ppf>ndash;<ppl>140</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b176">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Merkel</snm>, <fnm>P. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Validity, reliability, and feasibility of durometer measurements of scleroderma skin disease in a multicenter treatment trial</atl>. <jtl>Arthritis Rheum.</jtl>
                    <vid>59</vid>, <ppf>699</ppf>ndash;<ppl>705</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b177">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>McCaffrey</snm>, <fnm>T. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>TGF-beta; signaling in atherosclerosis and restenosis</atl>. <jtl>Front. Biosci. (Schol. Ed.)</jtl>
                    <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>236</ppf>ndash;<ppl>245</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b178">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Friedl</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Intimal hyperplasia and expression of transforming growth factor-beta;1 in saphenous veins and internal mammary arteries before coronary artery surgery</atl>. <jtl>Ann. Thorac. Surg.</jtl>
                    <vid>78</vid>, <ppf>1312</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1318</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b179">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ranjzad</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Salem</snm>, <fnm>H. K.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Kingston</snm>, <fnm>P. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Adenovirus-mediated gene transfer of fibromodulin inhibits neointimal hyperplasia in an organ culture model of human saphenous vein graft disease</atl>. <jtl>Gene Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>1154</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1162</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b180">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Kapur</snm>, <fnm>N. K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibition of transforming growth factor-beta; restores endothelial thromboresistance in vein grafts</atl>. <jtl>J. Vasc. Surg.</jtl>
                    <vid>54</vid>, <ppf>1117</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1123.e1</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b181">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ramirez</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Dietz</snm>, <fnm>H. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Marfan syndrome: from molecular pathogenesis to clinical treatment</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</jtl>
                    <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>252</ppf>ndash;<ppl>258</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b182">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Holm</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Noncanonical TGFbeta; signaling contributes to aortic aneurysm progression in Marfan syndrome mice</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl>
                    <vid>332</vid>, <ppf>358</ppf>ndash;<ppl>361</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>). <newline/><b>This report demonstrates a significant contribution of the non-canonical TGFbeta; signalling pathway to aortic aneurysm progression in MFS</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b183">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Siriwardena</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Human antitransforming growth factor beta;<sub>2</sub> monoclonal antibody mdash; a new modulator of wound healing in trabeculectomy: a randomized placebo controlled clinical study</atl>. <jtl>Ophthalmology</jtl>
                    <vid>109</vid>, <ppf>427</ppf>ndash;<ppl>431</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b184">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Khaw</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>A phase III study of subconjunctival human anti-transforming growth factor beta;<sub>2</sub> monoclonal antibody (CAT-152) to prevent scarring after first-time trabeculectomy</atl>. <jtl>Ophthalmology</jtl>
                    <vid>114</vid>, <ppf>1822</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1830</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>). <newline/><b>This study reports the results from a Phase III study examining the efficacy of CAT-152, a monoclonal antibody to TGFbeta;2, in preventing the progression of fibrosis in patients undergoing first-time trabeculectomy. The study found no difference between CAT-152 and placebo in preventing the failure of trabeculectomy</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b185">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Fukuda</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chikama</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Takahashi</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Nishida</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Long-term follow-up after lamellar keratoplasty in a patient with bilateral idiopathic corneal keloid</atl>. <jtl>Cornea</jtl>
                    <vid>30</vid>, <ppf>1491</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1494</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b186">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Benzinou</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Mouse and human strategies identify PTPN14 as a modifier of angiogenesis and hereditary haemorrhagic telangiectasia</atl>. <jtl>Nature Commun.</jtl>
                    <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>616</ppf> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b187">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bonyadi</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Mapping of a major genetic modifier of embryonic lethality in TGFbeta;1 knockout mice</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl>
                    <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>207</ppf>ndash;<ppl>211</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b188">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Farrington</snm>, <fnm>D. L.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Development and validation of a phosphorylated SMAD <i>ex vivo</i> stimulation assay</atl>. <jtl>Biomarkers</jtl>
                    <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>313</ppf>ndash;<ppl>330</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b189">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>CD127 expression inversely correlates with FoxP3 and suppressive function of human CD4<super>+</super> T reg cells</atl>. <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
                    <vid>203</vid>, <ppf>1701</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1711</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b190">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>McClymont</snm>, <fnm>S. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Plasticity of human regulatory T cells in healthy subjects and patients with type 1 diabetes</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl>
                    <vid>186</vid>, <ppf>3918</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3926</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b191">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>You</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Adaptive TGF-beta;-dependent regulatory T cells control autoimmune diabetes and are a privileged target of anti-CD3 antibody treatment</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl>
                    <vid>104</vid>, <ppf>6335</ppf>ndash;<ppl>6340</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b192">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Clay</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hobeika</snm>, <fnm>A. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mosca</snm>, <fnm>P. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lyerly</snm>, <fnm>H. K.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Morse</snm>, <fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Assays for monitoring cellular immune responses to active immunotherapy of cancer</atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>1127</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1135</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b193">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Baselga</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>TGF-beta; signalling-related markers in cancer patients with bone metastasis</atl>. <jtl>Biomarkers</jtl>
                    <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>217</ppf>ndash;<ppl>236</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b194">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Bornstein</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Smad4 loss in mice causes spontaneous head and neck cancer with increased genomic instability and inflammation</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>119</vid>, <ppf>3408</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3419</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b195">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Lu</snm>, <fnm>S. L.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Loss of transforming growth factor-beta; type II receptor promotes metastatic head-and-neck squamous cell carcinoma</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl>
                    <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>1331</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1342</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b196">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Gomis</snm>, <fnm>R. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Alarcon</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nadal</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Van Poznak</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>C/EBPbeta; at the core of the TGFbeta; cytostatic response and its evasion in metastatic breast cancer cells</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>203</ppf>ndash;<ppl>214</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b197">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Micalizzi</snm>, <fnm>D. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The Six1 homeoprotein induces human mammary carcinoma cells to undergo epithelial-mesenchymal transition and metastasis in mice through increasing TGF-beta; signaling</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>119</vid>, <ppf>2678</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2690</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b198">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Hannigan</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Epigenetic downregulation of human disabled homolog 2 switches TGF-beta; from a tumor suppressor to a tumor promoter</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>120</vid>, <ppf>2842</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2857</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b199">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Law</snm>, <fnm>B. K.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Rapamycin potentiates transforming growth factor beta;-induced growth arrest in nontransformed, oncogene-transformed, and human cancer cells</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell. Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>22</vid>, <ppf>8184</ppf>ndash;<ppl>8198</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b200">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Engelman</snm>, <fnm>J. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Settleman</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Acquired resistance to tyrosine kinase inhibitors during cancer therapy</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</jtl>
                    <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>73</ppf>ndash;<ppl>79</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b201">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Corcoran</snm>, <fnm>R. B.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl><i>BRAF</i> gene amplification can promote acquired resistance to MEK inhibitors in cancer cells harboring the BRAF V600E mutation</atl>. <jtl>Sci. Signal.</jtl>
                    <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>ra84</ppf> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b202">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Acharya</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>alpha;v Integrin expression by DCs is required for T<sub>H</sub>17 cell differentiation and development of experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis in mice</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>120</vid>, <ppf>4445</ppf>ndash;<ppl>4452</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b203">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Melton</snm>, <fnm>A. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Expression of alpha;vbeta;8 integrin on dendritic cells regulates T<sub>H</sub>17 cell development and experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis in mice</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Invest.</jtl>
                    <vid>120</vid>, <ppf>4436</ppf>ndash;<ppl>4444</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b204">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Yadav</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Protection from obesity and diabetes by blockade of TGF-beta;/Smad3 signaling</atl>. <jtl>Cell Metab.</jtl>
                    <vid>14</vid>, <ppf>67</ppf>ndash;<ppl>79</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b205">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Massague</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Seoane</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Wotton</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Smad transcription factors</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>2783</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2810</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b206">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Keller</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Interaction of TGFbeta; and BMP signaling pathways during chondrogenesis</atl>. <jtl>PLoS ONE</jtl>
                    <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>e16421</ppf> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b207">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Montero</snm>, <fnm>J. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lorda-Diez</snm>, <fnm>C. I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ganan</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Macias</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Hurle</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Activin/TGFbeta; and BMP crosstalk determines digit chondrogenesis</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl>
                    <vid>321</vid>, <ppf>343</ppf>ndash;<ppl>356</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b208">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Goumans</snm>, <fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Activin receptor-like kinase (ALK)1 is an antagonistic mediator of lateral TGFbeta;/ALK5 signaling</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl>
                    <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>817</ppf>ndash;<ppl>828</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>). <newline/><b>This study demonstrates that TGFbeta; regulates the activation state of the endothelium via two opposing type I receptors, ALK1 and Tbeta;RI (also known as ALK5)</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b209">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Hau</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibition of TGF-beta;2 with AP 12009 in recurrent malignant gliomas: from preclinical to phase I/II studies</atl>. <jtl>Oligonucleotides</jtl>
                    <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>201</ppf>ndash;<ppl>212</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b210">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Chamberlain</snm>, <fnm>M. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Convection-enhanced delivery of a transforming growth factor-beta;2 inhibitor trabedersen for recurrent high-grade gliomas: efficacy real or imagined?</atl>, in reference to Bogdahn et al. (Neuro-Oncology <cd year="2011">2011</cd>;<vid>13</vid>:<ppf>132</ppf>ndash;<ppl>142</ppl>). <jtl>Neuro Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>558</ppf>ndash;<ppl>559</ppl>; author reply <ppf>561</ppf>ndash;<ppl>552</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b211">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Wick</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Weller</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Trabedersen to target transforming growth factor-beta;: when the journey is not the reward</atl>, in reference to Bogdahn et al. (Neuro-Oncology <cd year="2011">2011</cd>;<vid>13</vid>:<ppf>132</ppf>ndash;<ppl>142</ppl>). <jtl>Neuro Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>559</ppf>ndash;<ppl>560</ppl>; author reply <ppf>561</ppf>ndash;<ppl>552</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b212">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Roldan Urgoiti</snm>, <fnm>G. B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Singh</snm>, <fnm>A. D.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Easaw</snm>, <fnm>J. C.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Extended adjuvant temozolomide for treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma multiforme</atl>. <jtl>J. Neurooncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>108</vid>, <ppf>173</ppf>ndash;<ppl>177</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b213">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Azaro</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The oral transforming growth factor-beta; (TGF-beta;) receptor I kinase inhibitor LY2157299 plus lomustine in patients with treatment-refractory malignant glioma: the first human dose study</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>30</vid>, Abstract <ppf>2042</ppf> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b214">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Occleston</snm>, <fnm>N. L.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Discovery and development of avotermin (recombinant human transforming growth factor beta;3): a new class of prophylactic therapeutic for the improvement of scarring</atl>. <jtl>Wound Repair Regen.</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid> (<iid>Suppl. 1</iid>), <ppf>S38</ppf>ndash;<ppl>S48</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b215">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Platten</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl><i>N</i>minus;[3,4-dimethoxycinnamoyl]-anthranilic acid (tranilast) inhibits transforming growth factor-beta; relesase and reduces migration and invasiveness of human malignant glioma cells</atl>. <jtl>Int. J. Cancer</jtl>
                    <vid>93</vid>, <ppf>53</ppf>ndash;<ppl>61</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b216">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Isaji</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibitory effects of tranilast on the proliferation and functions of human pterygium-derived fibroblasts</atl>. <jtl>Cornea</jtl>
                    <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>364</ppf>ndash;<ppl>368</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b217">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Schlingensiepen</snm>, <fnm>K. H.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>The TGF-beta;1 antisense oligonucleotide AP 11014 for the treatment of non-small cell lung, colorectal and prostate cancer: preclinical studies</atl>. <jtl>J. Clin. Oncol.</jtl>
                    <vid>22</vid>, Abstract <ppf>3132</ppf> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b218">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Nam</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Bone sialoprotein mediates the tumor cell-targeted prometastatic activity of transforming growth factor beta; in a mouse model of breast cancer</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>66</vid>, <ppf>6327</ppf>ndash;<ppl>6335</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b219">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Melisi</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>LY2109761, a novel transforming growth factor beta; receptor type I and type II dual inhibitor, as a therapeutic approach to suppressing pancreatic cancer metastasis</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cancer Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>829</ppf>ndash;<ppl>840</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b220">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Fransvea</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Angelotti</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Antonaci</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Giannelli</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Blocking transforming growth factor-beta; up-regulates E-cadherin and reduces migration and invasion of hepatocellular carcinoma cells</atl>. <jtl>Hepatology</jtl>
                    <vid>47</vid>, <ppf>1557</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1566</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b221">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Mazzocca</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fransvea</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lavezzari</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Antonaci</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Giannelli</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Inhibition of transforming growth factor beta; receptor I kinase blocks hepatocellular carcinoma growth through neo-angiogenesis regulation</atl>. <jtl>Hepatology</jtl>
                    <vid>50</vid>, <ppf>1140</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1151</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b222">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhang</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Halder</snm>, <fnm>S. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zhang</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Datta</snm>, <fnm>P. K.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Targeting transforming growth factor-beta; signaling in liver metastasis of colon cancer</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Lett.</jtl>
                    <vid>277</vid>, <ppf>114</ppf>ndash;<ppl>120</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b223">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Inman</snm>, <fnm>G. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>SB-431542 is a potent and specific inhibitor of transforming growth factor-beta; superfamily type I activin receptor-like kinase (ALK) receptors ALK4, ALK5, and ALK7</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Pharmacol.</jtl>
                    <vid>62</vid>, <ppf>65</ppf>ndash;<ppl>74</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b224">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Hjelmeland</snm>, <fnm>M. D.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>SB-431542, a small molecule transforming growth factor-beta;-receptor antagonist, inhibits human glioma cell line proliferation and motility</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cancer Ther.</jtl>
                    <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>737</ppf>ndash;<ppl>745</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b225">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>DaCosta Byfield</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Major</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Laping</snm>, <fnm>N. J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Roberts</snm>, <fnm>A. B.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>SB-505124 is a selective inhibitor of transforming growth factor-beta; type I receptors ALK4, ALK5, and ALK7</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Pharmacol.</jtl>
                    <vid>65</vid>, <ppf>744</ppf>ndash;<ppl>752</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b226">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Uhl</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>SD-208, a novel transforming growth factor beta; receptor I kinase inhibitor, inhibits growth and invasiveness and enhances immunogenicity of murine and human glioma cells <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo.</i></atl>
                    <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>64</vid>, <ppf>7954</ppf>ndash;<ppl>7961</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>). <newline/><b>This is the first report of the use of a chemical inhibitor of Tbeta;RI showing efficacy in reduced tumour growth and invasion as well as increased immunogenicity in a mouse model of glioblastoma</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b227">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Ge</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibition of growth and metastasis of mouse mammary carcinoma by selective inhibitor of transforming growth factor-beta; type I receptor kinase <i>in vivo</i></atl>. <jtl>Clin. Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>4315</ppf>ndash;<ppl>4330</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b228">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Suzuki</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>A novel small-molecule inhibitor of transforming growth factor beta; type I receptor kinase (SM16) inhibits murine mesothelioma tumor growth <i>in vivo</i> and prevents tumor recurrence after surgical resection</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>2351</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2359</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b229">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Systemic blockade of transforming growth factor-beta; signaling augments the efficacy of immunogene therapy</atl>. <jtl>Cancer Res.</jtl>
                    <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>10247</ppf>ndash;<ppl>10256</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>). <newline/><b>This is the first demonstration of the use of a chemical TGFbeta; receptor inhibitor, acting via its immunomodulatory effects, to enhance the efficacy of an adenovirus expressing IFNbeta;-based immunotherapy</b>.</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b230">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Gellibert</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Discovery of 4-{4-[3-(pyridin-2-yl)-1<i>H</i>-pyrazol-4-yl]pyridin-2-yl}-<i>N</i>-(tetrahydro-2<i>H</i>- pyran-4-yl)benzamide (GW788388): a potent, selective, and orally active transforming growth factor-beta; type I receptor inhibitor</atl>. <jtl>J. Med. Chem.</jtl>
                    <vid>49</vid>, <ppf>2210</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2221</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b231">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Petersen</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
                    <i>et al</i>. <atl>Oral administration of GW788388, an inhibitor of TGF-beta; type I and II receptor kinases, decreases renal fibrosis</atl>. <jtl>Kidney Int.</jtl>
                    <vid>73</vid>, <ppf>705</ppf>ndash;<ppl>715</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
            <bib id="b232">
                <reftxt><refau><snm>Tan</snm>, <fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zhang</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Connelly</snm>, <fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gilbert</snm>, <fnm>R. E.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Kelly</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau>
                    <atl>Targeted inhibition of activin receptor-like kinase 5 signaling attenuates cardiac dysfunction following myocardial infarction</atl>. <jtl>Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol.</jtl>
                    <vid>298</vid>, <ppf>H1415</ppf>ndash;<ppl>H1425</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt>
            </bib>
        </bibl>
    </bm>
</article>
