<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "../../DTDs/NPG_XML_Article/NPG_XML_Article.dtd" [
<!ENTITY figf1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2380-F1//EN" "nsmb.2380-F1" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf2 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2380-F2//EN" "nsmb.2380-F2" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf3 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2380-F3//EN" "nsmb.2380-F3" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf4 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2380-F4//EN" "nsmb.2380-F4" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf5 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2380-F5//EN" "nsmb.2380-F5" NDATA ITEM>
]>
<article id="nsmb.2380" language="eng" relation="no">
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</jtl>
<vol>19</vol>
<iss>10</iss>
<idt>201210</idt>
<categ id="af"/>
<pp><spn>983</spn><epn>990</epn><cnt>8</cnt></pp>
<issn type="print">1545-9993</issn>
<issn type="electronic">1545-9985</issn>
<cpg><cpy>2012</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</cpn></cpg>
<suppinfo id="S1">
<suppobj extrefid="nsmb.2380-S1" format="pdf" filesize="6M"><title>Supplementary Text and Figures</title>
<descrip><p>Supplementary Figures 1&#x2013;5, Supplementary Tables 1 and 2, and Supplementary Note</p></descrip></suppobj>
</suppinfo>
<subject code="npg_subject_502"/>
<doi>10.1038/nsmb.2380</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Human <named-entity id="named-entity-1">CWC22</named-entity> escorts the helicase <named-entity id="named-entity-2">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to spliceosomes and promotes exon junction complex assembly</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Isabelle</fnm><snm>Barbosa</snm><inits>I</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Nazmul</fnm><snm>Haque</snm><inits>N</inits><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<au><fnm>Francesca</fnm><snm>Fiorini</snm><inits>F</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Charlotte</fnm><snm>Barrandon</snm><inits>C</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Catherine</fnm><snm>Tomasetto</snm><inits>C</inits><orf rid="a4"/></au>
<au><fnm>Marco</fnm><snm>Blanchette</snm><inits>M</inits><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<cau><fnm>Herv&#xE9;</fnm><snm>Le Hir</snm><inits>H</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a2"/><corf rid="c1"/></cau>
<aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Institut de Biologie de l'Ecole Normale Sup&#xE9;rieure, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique UMR8197</org>, <cty>Paris</cty>, <cny>France</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a2"/><org>Institut de Biologie de l'Ecole Normale Sup&#xE9;rieure, Institut National de la Sant&#xE9; et de la Recherche M&#xE9;dicale U1024</org>, <cty>Paris</cty>, <cny>France</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a3"/><org>Stowers Institute for Medical Research</org>, <cty>Kansas City</cty>, <st>Missouri</st>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a4"/><org>Institut de G&#xE9;n&#xE9;tique et de Biologie Mol&#xE9;culaire et Cellulaire, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique UMR7104</org>, <cty>Illkirch</cty>, <cny>France</cny>.</aff>
<caff><coid id="c1"/><email>lehir@ens.fr</email></caff>
</aug>
<hst>
<re year="2012" month="04" day="15"/>
<acc year="2012" month="08" day="08"/>
<pubdate type="aop" year="2012" month="09" day="09"/></hst>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="aop">
<title/>
<p>The exon junction complex (EJC) links splicing to downstream events including mRNA localization, translation and stability. A combination of <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i> approaches were used to identify the splicing factor CWC22 as a direct partner of EJC component eIF4AIII in flies and humans and to demonstrate its functions in preventing eIF4AIII binding to RNA and in escorting eIF4AIII to active spliceosomes before EJC assembly.</p></edsumm>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="issue">
<title/>
<p>The exon junction complex (EJC) links splicing to downstream events including mRNA localization, translation and stability. A combination of <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i> approaches were used to identify the splicing factor CWC22 as a direct partner of EJC component eIF4AIII in flies and humans and to demonstrate its functions in preventing eIF4AIII binding to RNA and in escorting eIF4AIII to active spliceosomes before EJC assembly.</p></edsumm>
<abs><p>The exon-junction complex (EJC) functionally links splicing to subsequent mRNA localization, translation and stability. Sequence-independent binding of the EJC core to RNA is ensured by the DEAD-box helicase <named-entity id="named-entity-3">eIF4AIII</named-entity>. Here, we identified the splicing factor <named-entity id="named-entity-4">CWC22</named-entity> as a new <named-entity id="named-entity-5">eIF4AIII</named-entity> partner in flies and humans. <named-entity id="named-entity-6">CWC22</named-entity> coexists with <named-entity id="named-entity-7">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in large protein complexes distinct from EJCs. Recombinant <named-entity id="named-entity-8">CWC22</named-entity> directly contacts <named-entity id="named-entity-9">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and prevents it from binding RNA. <i>In vitro</i> splicing assays revealed that <named-entity id="named-entity-10">CWC22</named-entity> introduces <named-entity id="named-entity-11">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to spliceosomes before remodeling to facilitate <named-entity id="named-entity-12">eIF4AIII</named-entity> incorporation into the EJC. Finally, using knockdowns <i>in vivo</i>, we showed that <named-entity id="named-entity-13">CWC22</named-entity> is essential for EJC assembly. We elucidated the initial step of EJC assembly and the duality of <named-entity id="named-entity-14">CWC22</named-entity> function that hinders <named-entity id="named-entity-15">eIF4AIII</named-entity> from nonspecifically binding RNA and escorts it to the splicing machinery to promote EJC assembly on mature mRNAs.</p></abs></fm>
<bdy>
<p>The EJC exemplifies the dynamic aspect of messenger ribonucleoprotein (mRNP) particles and its importance in eukaryotic gene expression<bibr rid="b1"/>. As a consequence of splicing, assembly of the EJC occurs approximately 24 nucleotides (nt) upstream of mRNA exon junctions<bibr rid="b2 b3"/>. The spliceosome loads a core complex, which stably binds RNA, around which the full EJC is organized to constitute a molecular signature of splicing events. Four proteins compose the EJC core: the RNA helicase <named-entity id="named-entity-16">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-17">eukaryotic initiation factor 4AIII</named-entity>), the heterodimer of <named-entity id="named-entity-18">MAGOH</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-19">Y14</named-entity>, and <named-entity id="named-entity-20">MLN51</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-21">metastatic lymph node 51</named-entity>, also known as <named-entity id="named-entity-22">Barentsz</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-23">CASC3</named-entity>)<bibr rid="b3 b4"/>. The reconstitution and the crystal structures of the EJC core revealed the singular mechanism used by this complex to tightly bind RNA in a sequence-nonspecific manner<bibr rid="b4 b5 b6 b7"/>. At the center of the EJC core is <named-entity id="named-entity-24">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, one of the smallest DEAD-box RNA helicases<bibr rid="b8"/>. In the presence of <named-entity id="named-entity-25">ATP</named-entity>, the <named-entity id="named-entity-26">eIF4AIII</named-entity> RecA-like domains (RecA-1 and RecA-2) together with <named-entity id="named-entity-27">MLN51</named-entity> form a large interaction surface with RNA. The association of the <named-entity id="named-entity-28">MAGOH</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-29">Y14</named-entity> heterodimer with the EJC prevents conformational changes coupled to <named-entity id="named-entity-30">ATP</named-entity> hydrolysis and thus maintains stable binding of <named-entity id="named-entity-31">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to RNA<bibr rid="b9"/>. Once locked, the EJC core escorts spliced mRNAs as they proceed through different cellular locations before EJC disassembly by translating ribosomes in the cytoplasm<bibr rid="b10 b11 b12 b13"/>.</p>
<p>During this journey, several factors associate with and dissociate from the EJC core to affect its dynamics and functional versatility. The EJC is involved in pre-mRNA splicing<bibr rid="b14 b15 b16"/>, mRNA transport<bibr rid="b12 b17"/>, translation<bibr rid="b18"/> and nonsense-mediated mRNA decay (NMD), which subjects aberrant mRNAs containing a premature termination codon to rapid degradation to prevent synthesis of truncated proteins. Among the different pathways that trigger NMD<bibr rid="b19"/>, the one involving the EJC most clearly illustrates the EJC's dynamics. NMD requires the assembly of the conserved core complex made of the essential RNA helicase <named-entity id="named-entity-32">Upf1</named-entity> and its partners <named-entity id="named-entity-33">Upf2</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-34">Upf3b</named-entity><bibr rid="b20 b21"/>. Once deposited on nuclear spliced mRNAs, the EJC core recruits <named-entity id="named-entity-35">Upf3b</named-entity> in the nucleus and then <named-entity id="named-entity-36">Upf2</named-entity> in the cytoplasm. Upon premature translation termination upstream of the last exon junction, <named-entity id="named-entity-37">Upf1</named-entity> joins the downstream EJC to form the NMD surveillance complex that represses mRNA translation and triggers mRNA degradation<bibr rid="b20"/>. Through the NMD process, the EJC also contributes to the regulation of natural NMD targets such as ARC mRNAs expressed in neuronal cells<bibr rid="b22"/>.</p>
<p>Until recently, the EJC had been considered a constitutive mark of splicing. However, the study of its assembly <i>in vivo</i> in cultured <i>Drosophila</i> cells revealed that EJCs are not bound to every spliced junction of every spliced mRNA<bibr rid="b23"/>. Given its multiple functions, a variation in EJC deposition and/or stability may offer an additional way to modulate the fate of spliced mRNAs at many different steps. In this regard, the differential loading of the EJC may well explain the implication of its components in peculiar phenomena including <i><named-entity id="named-entity-38">oskar</named-entity></i> mRNA transport in <i>Drosophila</i> embryos<bibr rid="b17"/>, the splicing of MAPK pre-mRNAs in <i>Drosophila</i><bibr rid="b14 b16"/> or neural-stem-cell maintenance and mitosis in mice<bibr rid="b24"/>. However, the extent to which the EJC participates in the regulation of the expression of specific genes remains unclear.</p>
<p>The precise mechanism by which the EJC is deposited onto spliced junctions is not fully understood. The EJC is not a preassembled complex, and its formation is tightly coupled to the splicing reaction. Spliceosome assembly follows a stepwise pathway marked by successive complexes named E, A, B, B* and C, defined by the presence of the spliceosomal small nuclear RNPs (snRNPs) and associated factors<bibr rid="b25"/>. The B complex contains all snRNPs (U1, U2, U4, U5 and U6), but it is inactive. Spliceosome activation releases U1 and U4 to sequentially form the B* and C complexes, in which the first and the second transesterifications of the splicing reaction take place. Biochemical analyses of the protein contents of splicing complexes assembled <i>in vitro</i> revealed that <named-entity id="named-entity-39">MAGOH</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-40">Y14</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-41">eIF4AIII</named-entity> are already present in the B complex and become more stably associated in the C complex before exon ligation<bibr rid="b26 b27 b28 b29 b30 b31"/>. Interestingly, the presence of <named-entity id="named-entity-42">MAGOH</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-43">Y14</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-44">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in the C complex does not require the EJC binding platform located 24 nt upstream of the 5&#x2032; exon, which suggests that the assembly of a pre-EJC core on RNA occurs after exon ligation<bibr rid="b29 b31"/>. Finally, <named-entity id="named-entity-45">MLN51</named-entity> joins its partners to form the stable tetrameric EJC core after the second step of splicing<bibr rid="b32 b33 b34"/>. To date, the mode of recruitment of the EJC core proteins and the factors involved in their ordered assembly at the conserved position upstream of the 5&#x2032; exon are not known.</p>
<p>To determine the initial steps of EJC assembly, we searched for proteins interacting with <named-entity id="named-entity-46">eIF4AIII</named-entity>. We identified the splicing factor <named-entity id="named-entity-47">CWC22</named-entity> as a direct partner of <named-entity id="named-entity-48">eIF4AIII</named-entity>. We employed a combination of <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i> approaches to determine the interaction mode of the two proteins and its impact on <named-entity id="named-entity-49">eIF4AIII</named-entity> association with RNA, spliceosomes and EJC assembly.</p>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Results</sectitle>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Identification of <named-entity id="named-entity-50">CWC22</named-entity> as a new binding partner of <named-entity id="named-entity-51">eIF4AIII</named-entity></sectitle>
<p>In our efforts to elucidate the molecular steps in EJC assembly, we sought to identify new nuclear proteins interacting with <named-entity id="named-entity-52">eIF4AIII</named-entity> by proteomic analysis. We affinity purified hemagglutinin (HA)- and <named-entity id="named-entity-53">Flag</named-entity>-tagged <i>Drosophila melanogaster</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-54">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (HF-<named-entity id="named-entity-55">eIF4AIII</named-entity>) from S2 cells stably expressing <named-entity id="named-entity-56">eIF4AIII</named-entity> at levels similar to those of the endogenous protein (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1a</figr>). The proteins isolated after double affinity purification were first visualized on SDS-PAGE. A 130-kDa protein was present in the HF-<named-entity id="named-entity-57">eIF4AIII</named-entity> pulldown and absent in cells not expressing the tagged protein (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr>). In addition, this protein remained associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-58">eIF4AIII</named-entity> after RNase treatment, which indicated that it represents a direct binding partner of <named-entity id="named-entity-59">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr>). Analysis by mass spectrometry of proteins that copurified with HF-<named-entity id="named-entity-60">eIF4AIII</named-entity> identified most of the EJC proteins as well as peptides corresponding to the <i>Drosophila</i> protein <named-entity id="named-entity-61">nucampholin</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-62">ncm</named-entity> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Table 1</sir>). <i>Drosophila</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-63">ncm</named-entity>, conserved in all eukaryotes, is named <named-entity id="named-entity-64">CWC22</named-entity> (complexed with Cef1 22)<bibr rid="b35"/> in other species, and it is often referred as <named-entity id="named-entity-65">KIAA1604</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-66">fSAPb</named-entity> in humans. <named-entity id="named-entity-67">CWC22</named-entity> orthologs contain two defined domains, MIF4G (middle of eIF4G) and MA3, conserved in eukaryotes from <i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i> to humans (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>). The size of CWC22 proteins varies greatly between species, owing to less conserved variable N- and C-terminal regions (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1c</figr>). First isolated in a screen for embryonic lethal mutations in <i>Caenorhabditis elegans</i><bibr rid="b36"/>, <named-entity id="named-entity-68">CWC22</named-entity> was subsequently identified in yeast <i>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</i> and <i>S. cerevisiae</i>, where it is associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-69">CDC5</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-70">Cef1</named-entity> in endogenous spliceosomal complexes<bibr rid="b35"/>. <named-entity id="named-entity-71">CWC22</named-entity> is not part of the Prp19 complex, but its recruitment to the spliceosome prior to the catalytic steps depends on Prp19 in <i>S. cerevisiae</i><bibr rid="b37"/>. In yeast, <named-entity id="named-entity-72">CWC22</named-entity> is required for splicing and notably for the activation of the first catalytic step by <named-entity id="named-entity-73">Prp2</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b37">37</bibrinl>). In humans, <named-entity id="named-entity-74">CWC22</named-entity> is also present in the splicing complexes B and C before splicing catalysis<bibr rid="b25 b26 b27"/>, but its exact function remains unknown.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-75">CWC22</named-entity> associates with <named-entity id="named-entity-76">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-77">hPrp19</named-entity></sectitle>
<p>Because <named-entity id="named-entity-78">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-79">CWC22</named-entity> are highly conserved in metazoans, we asked whether the two proteins also interact in humans. To study the binding partners of endogenous human <named-entity id="named-entity-80">CWC22</named-entity>, we used affinity-purified polyclonal antibodies specific to <named-entity id="named-entity-81">CWC22</named-entity> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</sir>) and to <named-entity id="named-entity-82">eIF4AIII</named-entity><bibr rid="b38"/>. We performed immunoprecipitations of HEK293 cell lysates treated with RNase, and the contents of input, supernatant and precipitate were analyzed by western blotting (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1d</figr>). We controlled the specificity of the immunoprecipitations by performing the experiment in parallel in the absence of antibody or with antibodies against an unrelated protein, Rab5, a regulator of endocytosis. Immunoprecipitation of <named-entity id="named-entity-83">eIF4AIII</named-entity> resulted in nearly complete depletion, concurrent depletion of <named-entity id="named-entity-84">CWC22</named-entity> from the supernatant and detection of <named-entity id="named-entity-85">CWC22</named-entity> in the precipitate (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1d</figr>, lanes 4 and 8). Therefore, a proportion of <named-entity id="named-entity-86">CWC22</named-entity> is associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-87">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in HEK293 cells. In contrast, whereas anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-88">CWC22</named-entity> antibodies efficiently coprecipitated <named-entity id="named-entity-89">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, they only modestly depleted <named-entity id="named-entity-90">eIF4AIII</named-entity> from the supernatant (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1d</figr>, lanes 5 and 9). So if <named-entity id="named-entity-91">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-92">eIF4AIII</named-entity> are associated <i>in vivo</i>, a large proportion of <named-entity id="named-entity-93">eIF4AIII</named-entity> remains free or is engaged with other partners. The splicing factor <named-entity id="named-entity-94">hPrp19</named-entity> was also precipitated comparably with anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-95">CWC22</named-entity> and anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-96">eIF4AIII</named-entity> antibodies (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1d</figr>, lanes 8 and 9), which showed that both proteins were associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-97">hPrp19</named-entity> in RNase-resistant complexes. In contrast, <named-entity id="named-entity-98">MAGOH</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-99">Y14</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-100">MLN51</named-entity> were associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-101">eIF4AIII</named-entity> as expected, but none was present in comparable amounts in <named-entity id="named-entity-102">CWC22</named-entity> precipitate (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1d</figr>). To clarify these differential immunoprecipitations, we subjected the RNase-treated cell lysate to size fractionation on a 5%&#x2013;45% glycerol gradient, and we analyzed the fractions by western blotting (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1e</figr>). Notably, <named-entity id="named-entity-103">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-104">hPrp19</named-entity> cofractionated with <named-entity id="named-entity-105">eIF4AIII</named-entity> but not with the EJC core. In contrast, <named-entity id="named-entity-106">eIF4AIII</named-entity> cofractionated with the two groups of proteins. Taken together with immunoprecipitations, these data revealed that <named-entity id="named-entity-107">CWC22</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-108">hPrp19</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-109">eIF4AIII</named-entity> coexist in an RNase-resistant complex distinct from the EJC. Because EJCs have an estimated size of 335 kDa after RNase treatment<bibr rid="b2"/>, these complexes larger than EJCs most likely contain additional proteins.</p>
<p>We next studied the localization of <named-entity id="named-entity-110">CWC22</named-entity> to determine whether the two complexes exist in different cellular locations. Immunofluorescence staining of EJC core factors showed their enrichment in and around nuclear speckles<bibr rid="b32 b38 b39 b40 b41"/>. These punctate structures, containing splicing factors such as <named-entity id="named-entity-111">SC35</named-entity>, correspond to assembly and storage compartments supplying processing factors to active transcription sites<bibr rid="b42"/>. Transient expression of green fluorescent protein (GFP)&#x2013;tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-112">CWC22</named-entity> (GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-113">CWC22</named-entity>) and immunofluorescence staining of endogenous <named-entity id="named-entity-114">CWC22</named-entity> revealed that it is almost exclusively nuclear and that it concentrates around speckles (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 3a,b</sir> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Note</sir>). We observed that GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-115">CWC22</named-entity> colocalized with endogenous <named-entity id="named-entity-116">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 3a</sir>) as well as with coexpressed Cherry-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-117">MAGOH</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-118">Y14</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-119">MLN51</named-entity> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 3c</sir>). In agreement with their respective links to splicing, <named-entity id="named-entity-120">CWC22</named-entity> and EJC core proteins concentrate in the same nuclear regions, which coincide with sites of pre-mRNA synthesis and processing<bibr rid="b38"/>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-121">CWC22</named-entity> directly interacts with the <named-entity id="named-entity-122">eIF4AIII</named-entity> RecA-2 domain</sectitle>
<p>To better characterize the association mode of <named-entity id="named-entity-123">CWC22</named-entity> with <named-entity id="named-entity-124">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, we used <i>in vitro</i> reconstitution experiments with recombinant proteins purified from <i>Escherichia coli</i>. We produced full-length <named-entity id="named-entity-125">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2a</figr>) and a truncated version of <named-entity id="named-entity-126">CWC22</named-entity>, named <named-entity id="named-entity-127">CWC22</named-entity>-S ('S' for short, residues 100&#x2013;665). <named-entity id="named-entity-128">CWC22</named-entity>-S, which includes the MIF4G and MA3 domains, was fused to a N-terminal calmodulin-binding peptide (CBP) and a C-terminal His<sub>6</sub> tag to create CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-129">CWC22</named-entity>-S. Double affinity purification yielded highly purified recombinant <named-entity id="named-entity-130">CWC22</named-entity>-S protein (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 4a</sir>). Interaction between proteins was monitored by precipitation on calmodulin resin, and after extensive washes, eluted protein(s) were fractionated by SDS-PAGE and visualized by Coomassie staining. <named-entity id="named-entity-131">EIF4AIII</named-entity> interacts directly with <named-entity id="named-entity-132">CWC22</named-entity> because it is efficiently precipitated by CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-133">CWC22</named-entity>-S (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr>, lane 1). This interaction is specific to <named-entity id="named-entity-134">eIF4AIII</named-entity> because CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-135">CWC22</named-entity>-S did not precipitate the related protein <named-entity id="named-entity-136">eIF4AI</named-entity> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr>, lane 3), which has high sequence identity (65%) with <named-entity id="named-entity-137">eIF4AIII</named-entity> but is functionally distinct<bibr rid="b6 b43"/>. To determine more precisely the regions of <named-entity id="named-entity-138">eIF4AIII</named-entity> interacting with <named-entity id="named-entity-139">CWC22</named-entity>-S, we used recombinant chimeric forms of <named-entity id="named-entity-140">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-141">eIF4AI</named-entity> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2a</figr>) as previously described<bibr rid="b6"/>. For eIF4A13 and eIF4A31, we swapped the RecA-1 and RecA-2 domains of each protein. For eIF4A1333, 3133, 3313 and 3331, <named-entity id="named-entity-142">eIF4AIII</named-entity> was divided into four portions, and each portion was replaced by the corresponding portion of <named-entity id="named-entity-143">eIF4AI</named-entity>. Among these chimeric versions, CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-144">CWC22</named-entity>-S precipitated only eIF4A13, eIF4A1333 and eIF4A3133 (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b,c</figr>), which shows that <named-entity id="named-entity-145">CWC22</named-entity> interacts preferentially with the RecA-2 domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-146">eIF4AIII</named-entity>.</p>
<p>The <named-entity id="named-entity-147">eIF4AIII</named-entity> orthologs from various species contain eight conserved motifs (named patches A&#x2013;H) that distinguish them from their paralogs <named-entity id="named-entity-148">eIF4AI</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-149">eIF4AII</named-entity><bibr rid="b44"/>. Most of them are involved in intermolecular contacts within the EJC core that are formed with <named-entity id="named-entity-150">eIF4AIII</named-entity> but not <named-entity id="named-entity-151">eIF4AI</named-entity><bibr rid="b5 b6"/>. Among the three patches located in the <named-entity id="named-entity-152">eIF4AIII</named-entity> RecA-2 domain, the G patch has no known binding partner. It is localized on an exposed surface of <named-entity id="named-entity-153">eIF4AIII</named-entity> even when the protein is buried inside the EJC (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2d</figr>). We reasoned that this motif might be involved in a specific interaction and replaced its sequence (Arg298-Glu299-Ala300-Asn301) with the corresponding sequence of <named-entity id="named-entity-154">eIF4AI</named-entity> (His286-Ala287-Arg288-Asp299). This mutation did not completely prevent but drastically reduced the proportion of <named-entity id="named-entity-155">eIF4AIII</named-entity> precipitated by CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-156">CWC22</named-entity>-S (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2e</figr>). Altogether, these interaction assays revealed that <named-entity id="named-entity-157">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-158">eIF4AIII</named-entity> directly interact, potentially via several sites. The principal site of contact corresponds to the G patch characteristic of eukaryotic <named-entity id="named-entity-159">eIF4AIII</named-entity> homologs and localized on the RecA-2 domain.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-160">CWC22</named-entity> prevents <named-entity id="named-entity-161">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding to RNA</sectitle>
<p>As an archetypal DEAD-box helicase, <named-entity id="named-entity-162">eIF4AIII</named-entity> adopts different conformations. In the absence of RNA and <named-entity id="named-entity-163">ATP</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-164">eIF4AIII</named-entity> assumes an open shape, whereas <named-entity id="named-entity-165">eIF4AIII</named-entity> adopts a closed conformation inside the EJC to simultaneously bind <named-entity id="named-entity-166">ATP</named-entity> and RNA in addition to <named-entity id="named-entity-167">MAGOH</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-168">Y14</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-169">MLN51</named-entity> (refs. <bibrinl rid="b5">5</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b7">7</bibrinl>). <named-entity id="named-entity-170">CWC22</named-entity> binds the G patch, which is accessible in both <named-entity id="named-entity-171">eIF4AIII</named-entity> conformations, but it may also contact other sites buried in the EJC. To test this, we mixed CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-172">CWC22</named-entity>-S with the tetrameric EJC core reconstituted and purified to homogeneity. Notably, CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-173">CWC22</named-entity>-S was not able to efficiently precipitate the preformed EJC core (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3a</figr>, lane 1). CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-174">CWC22</named-entity>-S precipitated some <named-entity id="named-entity-175">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, which could be due to partial disassembly of the EJC core during the incubation period. As a positive control, CBP-UPF3b was able to pull down the preformed EJC under the same conditions (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3a</figr>, lane 2), as previously shown<bibr rid="b45"/>. This result strongly suggested that full interaction between <named-entity id="named-entity-176">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-177">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is impossible when the latter is part of the EJC.</p>
<p>However, we also observed that <named-entity id="named-entity-178">CWC22</named-entity> is able to bind <named-entity id="named-entity-179">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in a closed conformation but that some binding sites are masked by <named-entity id="named-entity-180">MAGOH</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-181">Y14</named-entity> and/or <named-entity id="named-entity-182">MLN51</named-entity>. To clarify this point, we purified the preassembled heterodimer CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-183">eIF4AIII</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-184">CWC22</named-entity>-S (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 4b</sir>). This heterodimer allowed us to compare the effect of <named-entity id="named-entity-185">CWC22</named-entity> on the ability of <named-entity id="named-entity-186">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to bind a 3&#x2032;-end&#x2013;biotinylated single-stranded RNA (ssRNA) in the presence of <named-entity id="named-entity-187">ADPNP</named-entity>, a nonhydrolyzable <named-entity id="named-entity-188">ATP</named-entity> analog. The RNA&#x2013;protein complexes were isolated with streptavidin beads, and eluted protein(s) were fractionated by SDS-PAGE and visualized by Coomassie staining (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b</figr>). We monitored <named-entity id="named-entity-189">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding to RNA in the presence or absence of <named-entity id="named-entity-190">CWC22</named-entity>-S. As previously observed<bibr rid="b6"/>, <named-entity id="named-entity-191">eIF4AIII</named-entity> was coprecipitated with or without <named-entity id="named-entity-192">ADPNP</named-entity> (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b</figr>, lanes 4 and 5). In contrast, <named-entity id="named-entity-193">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in complex with <named-entity id="named-entity-194">CWC22</named-entity>-S was not coprecipitated (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b</figr>, lanes 1 and 2), which showed that the <named-entity id="named-entity-195">CWC22</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-196">eIF4AIII</named-entity> interaction is incompatible with <named-entity id="named-entity-197">eIF4AIII</named-entity> RNA-binding activity. We next asked whether <named-entity id="named-entity-198">CWC22</named-entity> interferes with the formation of the EJC core. To do so, CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-199">eIF4AIII</named-entity> alone or associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-200">CWC22</named-entity>-S was mixed with <named-entity id="named-entity-201">MAGOH</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-202">Y14</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-203">MLN51</named-entity>-S, <named-entity id="named-entity-204">ADPNP</named-entity> and biotinylated ssRNA. When CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-205">eIF4AIII</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-206">CWC22</named-entity>-S was the only source of <named-entity id="named-entity-207">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, the EJC core was assembled almost as efficiently as CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-208">eIF4AIII</named-entity> alone, and <named-entity id="named-entity-209">CWC22</named-entity>-S was poorly coprecipitated (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b</figr>, lanes 3 and 6). In this experiment, the formation of the EJC was favored, and <named-entity id="named-entity-210">CWC22</named-entity> was most likely displaced from <named-entity id="named-entity-211">eIF4AIII</named-entity>.</p>
<p>DEAD-box helicases have various levels of ATPase activity that increase in an RNA-dependent manner by promoting a more favorable conformation for <named-entity id="named-entity-212">ATP</named-entity> hydrolysis<bibr rid="b46"/>. If <named-entity id="named-entity-213">CWC22</named-entity> prevents RNA binding, it is also expected to decrease <named-entity id="named-entity-214">eIF4AIII</named-entity> ATPase activity. We measured <named-entity id="named-entity-215">ATP</named-entity> hydrolysis by <named-entity id="named-entity-216">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and showed that its very weak activity was activated (~4 fold) in the presence of RNA (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3c</figr>). In agreement with our hypothesis, when <named-entity id="named-entity-217">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-218">CWC22</named-entity>, its ATPase activity was reduced to the level observed in the absence of RNA (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3c</figr>).</p>
<p>In conclusion, these observations suggest that <named-entity id="named-entity-219">CWC22</named-entity> fully interacts with <named-entity id="named-entity-220">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in an open conformation. This interaction is not compatible with the closed conformation adopted by <named-entity id="named-entity-221">eIF4AIII</named-entity> inside the EJC core, which is required for optimal <named-entity id="named-entity-222">ATP</named-entity> hydrolysis. A possible function of <named-entity id="named-entity-223">CWC22</named-entity> is to shield <named-entity id="named-entity-224">eIF4AIII</named-entity> from binding of RNA molecules before its incorporation into the EJC.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-225">CWC22</named-entity> ensures <named-entity id="named-entity-226">eIF4AIII</named-entity> recruitment to active spliceosomes</sectitle>
<p>Both <named-entity id="named-entity-227">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-228">eIF4AIII</named-entity> have been detected by mass spectrometry in spliceosomes assembled <i>in vitro</i><bibr rid="b26 b27"/>. In addition, this study showed that the two proteins coexist in large protein complexes (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1e</figr>). To confirm that both proteins are present in the same splicing complexes, we carried out immunoprecipitations from <i>in vitro</i> splicing reactions performed in HeLa cell nuclear extracts. Splicing reactions were performed with two uniformly labeled pre-mRNAs, AdML-AG and AdML-GG. The latter contains a mutation (AG to GG) in the 3&#x2032; splice site that blocks splicing before the second catalytic step. This mutation leads to the accumulation of C complexes containing the products of the first step, the lariat-exon 2 and exon 1 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b47">47</bibrinl>). Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-229">CWC22</named-entity> and anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-230">eIF4AIII</named-entity> antibodies immunoprecipitated AdML splicing intermediates, which indicated that both <named-entity id="named-entity-231">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-232">eIF4AIII</named-entity> are associated with the C complex (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4a,b</figr>). As expected, anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-233">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-234">Y14</named-entity> efficiently immunoprecipitated spliced mRNAs (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4a,b</figr>, lanes 7 and 8). The low proportion of splicing intermediates immunoprecipitated by <named-entity id="named-entity-235">Y14</named-entity>, known to be present in the C complex<bibr rid="b26 b27 b28 b30"/>, either reflects its less-stable association with the spliceosome<bibr rid="b10 b31"/> or could be attributed to <named-entity id="named-entity-236">Y14</named-entity> epitopes being less accessible in the C complex than in the spliced mRNP. In contrast to anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-237">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-238">CWC22</named-entity> antibodies predominantly coprecipitated splicing intermediates. The lack of mRNA pulldown is unlikely to be due to inaccessible epitopes because similar results were observed with the two anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-239">CWC22</named-entity> antibodies directed against the N- or the C-terminal extremities of the protein (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4a,b</figr>, lanes 5 and 6). We can conclude that <named-entity id="named-entity-240">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-241">eIF4AIII</named-entity> are present in the C complex but that <named-entity id="named-entity-242">CWC22</named-entity> does not remain associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-243">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in mRNPs. Because <named-entity id="named-entity-244">CWC22</named-entity> prevents <named-entity id="named-entity-245">eIF4AIII</named-entity> from binding to RNA, this result suggested that, concomitantly with the second step of splicing, the heterodimer <named-entity id="named-entity-246">CWC22</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-247">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is remodeled to release <named-entity id="named-entity-248">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, allowing the assembly of the EJC core.</p>
<p>Immunoprecipitations of endogenous proteins present in nuclear extracts revealed the presence of <named-entity id="named-entity-249">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-250">CWC22</named-entity> in different splicing complexes. However, we could not determine whether <named-entity id="named-entity-251">CWC22</named-entity> is required for the recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-252">eIF4AIII</named-entity> into spliceosomes and/or its subsequent incorporation into EJCs. To answer this crucial question, we supplemented splicing reactions with the tandem affinity purification (TAP)-tagged recombinant proteins TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-253">CWC22</named-entity>-S, TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-254">eIF4AIII</named-entity> or the heterodimer TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-255">eIF4AIII</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-256">CWC22</named-entity>-S and tested their ability to be incorporated into the splicing complexes by measuring the proportion of coprecipitated RNA. When added separately, both TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-257">CWC22</named-entity>-S and TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-258">eIF4AIII</named-entity> very inefficiently coprecipitated splicing intermediates and spliced mRNAs (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4c,d</figr>, lanes 5&#x2013;8). In contrast, when complemented as a heterodimer with <named-entity id="named-entity-259">CWC22</named-entity>-S, TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-260">eIF4AIII</named-entity> was more efficiently incorporated into C complexes, as shown by the larger proportion of splicing intermediates precipitated by TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-261">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (4-fold increase). The difference was even more striking when we compared the proportion of TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-262">eIF4AIII</named-entity> associated with spliced mRNPs (8-fold increase; <figr rid="f4">Fig. 4d</figr>, lanes 9 and 10 compared to lanes 5 and 6). The more efficient coprecipitation by TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-263">eIF4AIII</named-entity> of spliced mRNAs compared to splicing intermediates could be explained by a less accessible tag in C complexes or by a less stable association of the protein with spliceosomes than with spliced mRNPs<bibr rid="b10 b31"/>. Our results revealed an additional aspect of <named-entity id="named-entity-264">CWC22</named-entity> function, which consists of facilitating the recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-265">eIF4AIII</named-entity> by the splicing machinery.</p>
<p>We also wanted to differentiate the recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-266">eIF4AIII</named-entity> from its ability to assemble an EJC core. We produced a TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-267">eIF4AIII</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-268">CWC22</named-entity>-S heterodimer carrying a mutation of <named-entity id="named-entity-269">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (D401K and E402R, denoted <named-entity id="named-entity-270">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>KR</super>) that is known to prevent its incorporation into EJCs <i>in vivo</i> by affecting <named-entity id="named-entity-271">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding to <named-entity id="named-entity-272">MAGOH</named-entity><bibr rid="b5 b7 b33"/>. Notably, when splicing reactions were supplemented with TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-273">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>KR</super>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-274">CWC22</named-entity>-S, TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-275">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>KR</super> pulled down splicing intermediates as efficiently as did TAP-tagged wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-276">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (TAP-eIF4AIII<super>WT</super>) from the TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-277">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>WT</super>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-278">CWC22</named-entity>-S (<figr rid="f4">Figs. 4c,d</figr>, lanes 11 and 12). However, in contrast to the wild-type protein, TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-279">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>KR</super> failed to pull down spliced mRNAs. So entrance of <named-entity id="named-entity-280">eIF4AIII</named-entity> into spliceosomes, promoted by <named-entity id="named-entity-281">CWC22</named-entity>, is independent of the ability of <named-entity id="named-entity-282">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to form an EJC core.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-283">CWC22</named-entity> is required for <named-entity id="named-entity-284">eIF4AIII</named-entity> association with spliced mRNAs</sectitle>
<p>Finally, we performed <i>in vivo</i> experiments to determine the role of <named-entity id="named-entity-285">CWC22</named-entity> in EJC association with cellular spliced mRNAs. The expression levels of <named-entity id="named-entity-286">Y14</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-287">CWC22</named-entity> were knocked down in HEK293 cells by RNA interference, and the level of EJCs assembled on specific mRNA was assayed by immunoprecipitation of <named-entity id="named-entity-288">eIF4AIII</named-entity>. The expression levels of <named-entity id="named-entity-289">Y14</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-290">CWC22</named-entity> were efficiently reduced compared to those in cells transfected with nonspecific short interfering RNA (siRNA) directed against GFP (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5a</figr>). The ability of anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-291">eIF4AIII</named-entity> antibodies to coprecipitate three endogenous spliced mRNAs, <named-entity id="named-entity-292">MAT2A</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-293">GAPDH</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-294">FUSIP</named-entity>, was then assayed by real-time quantitative PCR (RT-qPCR) and compared to the nonspecific siRNA treatment. As expected, the levels of the three mRNAs tested were similarly reduced when <named-entity id="named-entity-295">Y14</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-296">CWC22</named-entity> was knocked down (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5b</figr>). This was not caused by a reduction in splicing efficiency, as amplification of three spliced junctions by RT-PCR indicated that their splicing was not significantly affected (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Fig. 5</sir>). Therefore, <named-entity id="named-entity-297">CWC22</named-entity>, like <named-entity id="named-entity-298">Y14</named-entity>, is required for <named-entity id="named-entity-299">eIF4AIII</named-entity> association with cellular spliced mRNAs, and <named-entity id="named-entity-300">CWC22</named-entity> is required for EJC assembly <i>in vivo</i>. Taken together, our data uncovered the initial steps of EJC assembly orchestrated by the conserved splicing factor <named-entity id="named-entity-301">CWC22</named-entity>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Discussion</sectitle>
<p>All dynamic cellular processes dealing with RNA employ the mechanical properties of specific RNA helicases as molecular motors. Eukaryotic RNA helicases have central functions in processes including ribosome biogenesis, pre-mRNA processing and mRNA transport, translation, decay and surveillance<bibr rid="b48"/>. For example, the highly dynamic splicing machinery employs eight conserved DExD&#x2013;H-box RNA helicases<bibr rid="b25"/>. Paradoxically, biochemical and structural studies revealed that RNA-helicase cores exhibit no apparent sequence specificity. Therefore, RNA helicases must follow specific pathways to be localized and activated at the right time on the appropriate substrate. To date, much remains to be learned about the molecular roads used by eukaryotic RNA helicases to reach their cellular targets. An additional level of complexity must exist for the numerous RNA helicases that participate in different processes<bibr rid="b48"/>. This is notably the case for <named-entity id="named-entity-302">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, which clamps the EJC onto spliced mRNAs but also participates in ribosomal RNA processing<bibr rid="b49"/> and the regulation of selenoprotein synthesis<bibr rid="b50"/>. Here, we discovered that the splicing factor <named-entity id="named-entity-303">CWC22</named-entity> escorts <named-entity id="named-entity-304">eIF4AIII</named-entity> into active spliceosomes to promote subsequent EJC assembly.</p>
<p>The purification of proteins associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-305">eIF4AIII</named-entity> showed that <named-entity id="named-entity-306">CWC22</named-entity> is a major partner of <named-entity id="named-entity-307">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in human cells in which <named-entity id="named-entity-308">CWC22</named-entity> was co-depleted with <named-entity id="named-entity-309">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1d</figr>). In contrast, the immunodepletion of <named-entity id="named-entity-310">CWC22</named-entity> led to a detectable but partial depletion of <named-entity id="named-entity-311">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, suggesting that a certain amount of <named-entity id="named-entity-312">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is separate from <named-entity id="named-entity-313">CWC22</named-entity>. In agreement with this, size fractionation of human cell lysates showed that <named-entity id="named-entity-314">CWC22</named-entity> did not cofractionate with EJC components but with <named-entity id="named-entity-315">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-316">hPrp19</named-entity> in larger complexes (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1e</figr>). Therefore, at least two distinct <named-entity id="named-entity-317">eIF4AIII</named-entity>-containing complexes exist that correspond to EJCs and complexes with <named-entity id="named-entity-318">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-319">hPrp19</named-entity>. The latter is resistant to RNase, and its apparent size is clearly larger than EJCs. So the three proteins are most likely assembled with additional factors, and their identification will certainly illuminate the pathway by which they join spliceosomes. As <named-entity id="named-entity-320">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is involved in processes unrelated to splicing<bibr rid="b49 b50"/>, we can suppose that it is also part of other kinds of complexes.</p>
<p>Our biochemical approaches brought to light the role of <named-entity id="named-entity-321">CWC22</named-entity> in preventing <named-entity id="named-entity-322">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding to RNA. The central region of <named-entity id="named-entity-323">CWC22</named-entity>, containing the MIF4G and MA3 domains, is sufficient to bind <named-entity id="named-entity-324">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>), which suggests that the less-conserved N- and C-terminal regions of <named-entity id="named-entity-325">CWC22</named-entity> do not directly contribute to <named-entity id="named-entity-326">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding. In contrast to a majority of DExD-H-box proteins, <named-entity id="named-entity-327">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is simply made of the archetypal helicase core and does not possess extra domains. Despite the elevated percentage of identity (65%) between <named-entity id="named-entity-328">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and the bona fide translation initiation factors <named-entity id="named-entity-329">eIF4AI</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-330">eIF4AII</named-entity><bibr rid="b43"/>, <named-entity id="named-entity-331">eIF4AI</named-entity> is not interchangeable with <named-entity id="named-entity-332">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to assemble the EJC core<bibr rid="b6"/>. This specificity is conferred by conserved motifs on the surface <named-entity id="named-entity-333">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (patches A&#x2013;H) that are absent in <named-entity id="named-entity-334">eIF4AI</named-entity>-II<bibr rid="b5 b7 b44"/>. Chimeric and mutant <named-entity id="named-entity-335">eIF4AIII</named-entity> proteins showed that <named-entity id="named-entity-336">CWC22</named-entity> specifically binds <named-entity id="named-entity-337">eIF4AIII</named-entity> but not <named-entity id="named-entity-338">eIF4AI</named-entity> by contacting the G motif located in the RecA-2 domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-339">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). Notably, we also showed that by interacting with <named-entity id="named-entity-340">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-341">CWC22</named-entity> prevents <named-entity id="named-entity-342">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding to RNA (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3</figr>). The G patch that sustains a majority but not all of the binding on the RecA-2 surface is far away from the regions involved in RNA binding<bibr rid="b5"/>. Therefore, <named-entity id="named-entity-343">CWC22</named-entity> may fully interact with <named-entity id="named-entity-344">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in the open conformation but cannot interact with it in the closed conformation adopted to stably contact RNA and to hydrolyze <named-entity id="named-entity-345">ATP</named-entity><bibr rid="b4 b51"/>. An initial phase during which <named-entity id="named-entity-346">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-347">CWC22</named-entity> and does not hydrolyze <named-entity id="named-entity-348">ATP</named-entity> is in agreement with the observation that mutants preventing RNA-dependent <named-entity id="named-entity-349">ATP</named-entity> hydrolysis are not detrimental to <named-entity id="named-entity-350">eIF4AIII</named-entity> incorporation into spliceosomes<bibr rid="b44"/>. RNA binding of <named-entity id="named-entity-351">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is hindered either by directly blocking one or several conserved motifs involved in RNA contacts or, more indirectly, by blocking the closing of the protein<bibr rid="b4 b6 b51"/>. This scenario is supported by its similarity to the mode of action of other essential RNA-helicase regulators. The closest example is eIF4G, known to modulate eIF4A activities during translation initiation. With a domain organization similar to <named-entity id="named-entity-352">CWC22</named-entity> (one MIF4G and one MA3 domain), eIF4G has multiple interfaces with eIF4A. The MIF4G domain ensures the primary interface by contacting eIF4A RecA-2, whereas the MA3 domain competes with RNA for binding to eIF4A<bibr rid="b52 b53"/>. By a structurally similar mechanism, <named-entity id="named-entity-353">Gle1</named-entity> and its cofactor InsP6 regulate the DEAD-box protein <named-entity id="named-entity-354">Dbp5</named-entity>, involved in mRNP remodeling, during their export to the cytoplasm<bibr rid="b54"/>. Although the ultimate mechanical functions of <named-entity id="named-entity-355">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, eIF4A and <named-entity id="named-entity-356">Dbp5</named-entity> are clearly distinct, these three helicases require their cofactors to be momentarily dissociated from RNA. In addition, it is interesting to note that the role of <named-entity id="named-entity-357">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in ribosomal RNA processing requires the protein <named-entity id="named-entity-358">NOM1</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b49">49</bibrinl>), whose domain organization is identical to the one of <named-entity id="named-entity-359">CWC22</named-entity>. Whether <named-entity id="named-entity-360">NOM1</named-entity> connects <named-entity id="named-entity-361">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in rRNA processing as <named-entity id="named-entity-362">CWC22</named-entity> does in splicing remains an open question. For the EJC, the first <named-entity id="named-entity-363">CWC22</named-entity> function might be to prevent <named-entity id="named-entity-364">eIF4AIII</named-entity> from interacting nonspecifically with RNAs that could divert it on its way to spliceosome.</p>
<p>The second function of <named-entity id="named-entity-365">CWC22</named-entity> is to escort <named-entity id="named-entity-366">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to spliceosomes. By complementing <i>in vitro</i> splicing reactions with recombinant proteins, we showed that <named-entity id="named-entity-367">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is efficiently incorporated into the C complex only in the presence of <named-entity id="named-entity-368">CWC22</named-entity> (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). Immunoprecipitations of endogenous proteins revealed that both <named-entity id="named-entity-369">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-370">eIF4AIII</named-entity> are associated in an RNA-independent manner with <named-entity id="named-entity-371">hPrp19</named-entity> and, most likely, additional factors (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>). The three proteins indeed join the spliceosome with a large set of factors prior to activation<bibr rid="b25"/>. We can imagine that the heterodimer <named-entity id="named-entity-372">CWC22</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-373">eIF4AIII</named-entity> offers a composite interface necessary to make contacts with splicing factors, in order to guide them toward splicing complexes. The helicase-like <named-entity id="named-entity-374">intron-binding protein 160</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-375">IBP160</named-entity>) may be an important mediator in the recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-376">CWC22</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-377">eIF4AIII</named-entity>. <named-entity id="named-entity-378">IBP160</named-entity> contacts pre-mRNAs at a conserved position upstream of the intron branch point and associates with EJC proteins, a step necessary for the formation of functional EJCs<bibr rid="b55"/>. Whether <named-entity id="named-entity-379">IBP160</named-entity> directly interacts with <named-entity id="named-entity-380">CWC22</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-381">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is unknown, but an initial association by means of the intron would be in agreement with the presence of <named-entity id="named-entity-382">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in spliceosomes even in the absence of its future mRNA binding site<bibr rid="b29"/>. Our observation that <named-entity id="named-entity-383">eIF4AIII</named-entity> is recruited to spliceosomes by <named-entity id="named-entity-384">CWC22</named-entity> independently from its ability to form a stable EJC core (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>) confirms that <named-entity id="named-entity-385">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-386">MAGOH</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-387">Y14</named-entity> join the spliceosome independently<bibr rid="b33 b44"/>. The EJC becomes stably positioned onto RNA concomitantly with substantial RNP remodeling orchestrated upon exon ligation<bibr rid="b29 b30 b31 b33 b44"/>. <named-entity id="named-entity-388">Prp22</named-entity>, a conserved RNA helicase, remodels the RNP around the exon junction to facilitate mRNA release and EJC binding to RNA<bibr rid="b31 b56"/>. During this step, <named-entity id="named-entity-389">eIF4AIII</named-entity> must be released from <named-entity id="named-entity-390">CWC22</named-entity> to bind mRNA and to be rapidly locked onto it by <named-entity id="named-entity-391">MAGOH</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-392">Y14</named-entity>.</p>
<p>In this study, we open a new chapter in the fascinating history of the EJC by elucidating the recruitment pathway of <named-entity id="named-entity-393">eIF4AIII</named-entity> by the splicing machinery. Future investigations will be necessary to answer several questions that persist: which splicing factor remodels the interaction between <named-entity id="named-entity-394">CWC22</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-395">eIF4AIII</named-entity> before EJC core assembly? Is the recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-396">MAGOH</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-397">Y14</named-entity> also promoted by particular splicing factors? What are the factors that guide <named-entity id="named-entity-398">eIF4AIII</named-entity> toward its splicing-independent functions? The answers will illuminate the essential part played by RNA helicase regulators in RNP functions.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Methods</sectitle>
<online-methods>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><i>Drosophila</i> stable cell lines and mass spectrometry.</sectitle>
<p><i>Drosophila</i> S2 cells stably expressing 2&#xD7; HA- and 2&#xD7; <named-entity id="named-entity-399">Flag</named-entity>-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-400">eIF4AIII</named-entity><bibr rid="b23"/> were used to grow 2&#x2013;4 l to a density of 2 &#xD7; 10<super>6</super>&#x2013;4 &#xD7; 10<super>6</super> cells/ml. Nuclear extracts were prepared as previously described<bibr rid="b57"/>. Protein (200 mg) was mixed with 100 &#x3BC;l of anti-Flag M2 agarose beads (M8823, Sigma) prewashed three times with 0.5 ml of IPB1 buffer (10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-401">Tris</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-402">NaCl</named-entity>, 2.5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-403">MgCl<sub>2</sub></named-entity> 0.05% Triton X-100, 0.5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-404">PMSF</named-entity>, 1&#xD7; complete protease inhibitor (Roche)) and rotated for 4 h at 4 &#xB0;C. The slurry was filtered on a spin column (Bio-Rad) and washed three times with 300 &#x3BC;l of IPB2 (10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-405">Tris</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-406">NaCl</named-entity>, 2.5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-407">MgCl<sub>2</sub></named-entity> 0.02% Triton X-100). The complexes were eluted with 0.5 mg/ml of 3&#xD7; <named-entity id="named-entity-408">Flag</named-entity> peptide (DYKDDDDKGDYKDDDDKGDYKDDDDK) in IPB1 and mixed with 100 &#x3BC;l of anti-HA beads (A2095, Sigma) prewashed with IPB1. Benzonase (3U) was added and incubated with samples at 4 &#xB0;C for 16 h. The beads were filtered on a spin column (Bio-Rad) and washed three times with 300 &#x3BC;l of IPB2. The purified complexes were eluted with 100 &#x3BC;l of 0.2 mg/ml 3&#xD7; HA peptide (YPYDVPDYAGYPYDVPDYAGYPYDVPDYA) in IPB2 for 30 min at 4 &#xB0;C. The affinity-purified complexes were <named-entity id="named-entity-409">TCA</named-entity> precipitated, and 10% were resolved in SDS-PAGE and visualized by silver staining. The remaining samples were subjected to MudPIT analysis as previously described<bibr rid="b58"/>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Antibodies, immunoprecipitation, immunoblotting and glycerol gradient.</sectitle>
<p>To generate anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-410">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-411">CWC22</named-entity>n (N-terminal) and anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-412">CWC22</named-entity>c (C-terminal) rabbit polyclonal antibodies, the synthetic peptides (Bio Basic Inc. or IGBMC peptide synthesis facility), MKSSVAQIKPSSGHDRRENLN-C (<named-entity id="named-entity-413">hCWC22</named-entity>, residues 1&#x2013;23) and C-EQSRESKKNQDRRREKSPAKQK (<named-entity id="named-entity-414">hCWC22</named-entity>, residues 887&#x2013;908) were coupled to ovalbumin through an additional <named-entity id="named-entity-415">cysteine</named-entity> residue and injected into New Zealand rabbits. Immunoreactive sera were affinity purified against the synthetic peptide coupled to Sulfolink coupling gel (Pierce) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-416">eIF4AIII</named-entity> antibody was previously described<bibr rid="b38"/>. Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-417">Y14</named-entity> (NB100-55326, RBM8A, Novus), Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-418">MAGOH</named-entity> 58 sera (E. Izaurralde, Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology, Tuebingen, Germany), anti-GAPDH (14C10, Ozyme), anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-419">hPrp19</named-entity> (NBP1-66538, Novus) and anti-Rab5 (prepared by C.T.) were also used.</p>
<p>For coimmunoprecipitation, 15-cm plates of confluent HEK293 cells were collected and washed in 1 ml PBS. Cell were lysed for 15 min at 4 &#xB0;C in 600 &#x3BC;l of lysis buffer (20 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-420">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-421">NaCl</named-entity>, 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-422">Na<sub>2</sub>EDTA</named-entity>, 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-423">EGTA</named-entity>, 1% NP-40, 1% <named-entity id="named-entity-424">sodium deoxycholate</named-entity>, 1% protease-inhibitor mixture), with 10 U RNase T1 (Fermentas) and 12 U RQ1 DNase (Promega). Cellular debris was removed by centrifugation at 13,000 r.p.m. for 10 min. The lysates were split in half and were incubated with 40 &#x3BC;l protein A&#x2013;coupled Dynabeads (Life Technologies) with or without antibody for 2 h at 4 &#xB0;C. The beads were washed extensively with IP buffer 150 (10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-425">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-426">NaCl</named-entity>, 2.5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-427">MgCl<sub>2</sub></named-entity>, 1% NP-40, 1% protease-inhibitor mixture), and the bound proteins were eluted with loading buffer (50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-428">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 6.8, 2% <named-entity id="named-entity-429">SDS</named-entity>, 10% <named-entity id="named-entity-430">glycerol</named-entity>, 1.4 M <named-entity id="named-entity-431">&#x3B2;-mercaptoethanol</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-432">bromophenol blue</named-entity>). Total proteins, input proteins or eluted proteins were resolved by 12% SDS-PAGE and electrotransferred to nitrocellulose membrane (Schleicher &amp; Schuell). The membrane was blocked in PBS containing 5% nonfat dry milk and 0.05% Tween 20. Rabbit polyclonal anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-433">CWC22</named-entity>, anti-GAPDH, anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-434">Y14</named-entity>, anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-435">MAGOH</named-entity> and mouse monoclonal anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-436">eIF4AIII</named-entity> were used as primary antibodies at 1:1,000 dilution. After washing, the membrane was incubated with secondary antibodies: goat anti-rabbit-HRP or goat anti-mouse at 1:10,000 dilution (Thermo Scientific). Protein-antibody complexes were visualized by an enhanced chemiluminescence detection system (SuperSignal West Femto, Thermo Scientific).</p>
<p>For glycerol gradients, cellular lysates from HEK293 were then loaded onto a 12-ml 5&#x2013;45% glycerol gradient in 20 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-437">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-438">NaCl</named-entity>, 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-439">EDTA</named-entity>, 1mM <named-entity id="named-entity-440">EGTA</named-entity> before centrifugation at 40,000 r.p.m. in a Beckman SW-41 rotor for 16 h at 4 &#xB0;C. Ten fractions of 1.2 ml were collected from the top of the gradient. Four-hundred microliters of the eight first fractions were precipitated by <named-entity id="named-entity-441">trichloroacetate</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-442">TCA</named-entity>) and analyzed by western blotting.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>cDNA cloning and protein purification.</sectitle>
<p>Coding sequences of human <named-entity id="named-entity-443">CWC22</named-entity> (Uniprot accession code <weblink url="http://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/Q9HCG8">Q9HCG8</weblink>) were cloned between NdeI and XhoI in variants of pET28a (Novagen) allowing for the fusion of an N-terminal tag (TAP or CBP) and a C-terminal His<sub>6</sub> Tag as described before<bibr rid="b45"/>. Fragments of <named-entity id="named-entity-444">CWC22</named-entity> (Full length (FL), residues 1&#x2013;908; S, residues 100&#x2013;665) were amplified by PCR with the appropriate restriction sites. Mutants of <named-entity id="named-entity-445">eIF4AIII</named-entity> were constructed with the QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis kit (Stratagene) using CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-446">eIF4AIII</named-entity> or TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-447">eIF4AIII</named-entity> as a vector template. All proteins were expressed and purified as described before<bibr rid="b6 b45"/>. mCherry-fused <named-entity id="named-entity-448">MLN51</named-entity>/137-283 (SELOR), <named-entity id="named-entity-449">MAGOH</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-450">Y14</named-entity> were obtained as described before<bibr rid="b38"/>, except that MunI-digested cDNA fragments were inserted in frame into the EcoRI site of the pmCherry-C1 expression vector (Clontech).</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Recombinant protein binding, RNA binding and ATPase assays.</sectitle>
<p>Interaction between recombinant proteins and between recombinant proteins and biotinylated ssRNA were performed as previously described<bibr rid="b45"/>. ATPase assays were performed as previously described<bibr rid="b59"/>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><i>In vitro</i> splicing and coprecipitation.</sectitle>
<p>DNA templates for radiolabeled RNA synthesis, <i>in vitro</i> splicing and coprecipitation were performed as previously described<bibr rid="b6 b32"/>, except that RNAs were coprecipitated with protein A&#x2013;coupled magnetic beads.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>siRNA, RNA extraction and RT-qPCR.</sectitle>
<p>HEK293 cells were grown in complete growth medium without antibiotics and transfected in 10-cm dishes with Lipofectamine RNAiMax (Life Techologies) by the standard method, using 12 &#x3BC;l of Lipofectamine RNAi MAX and 1 &#x3BC;l of 100 &#x3BC;M of siRNA (Eurogentec) duplexes for 48 h. The sequences of the siRNAs are the following: GFP, UGAAUUAGAUGGCGAUGUUdTdT; <named-entity id="named-entity-451">Y14</named-entity>, CGCUCUGUUGAAGGCUGGAdTdT; <named-entity id="named-entity-452">CWC22</named-entity> siRNA 1, GGUCAUGACAGAAGGGAAAdTdT; and siRNA 2, GGACAUGGGAAGACCAGAAdTdT. For RNA extraction, cells were collected, washed with PBS and lysed in 300 &#x3BC;l of PXL Buffer (PBS1X, 0.1% <named-entity id="named-entity-453">SDS</named-entity>, 0.5% NP-40, 0.5% <named-entity id="named-entity-454">sodium deoxycholate</named-entity> and a mixture of protease inhibitors (Calbiochem)) with 3 &#x3BC;l Turbo DNase (Fermentas) and 1 &#x3BC;l RNAsin (Promega) for 3 min at 37 &#xB0;C. The lysate was clarified by centrifugation at 13,000 r.p.m. for 10 min and incubated for 2 h at 4 &#xB0;C with magnetic beads bound to anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-455">eIF4AIII</named-entity> antibodies. The beads were washed three times in high-salt buffer (50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-456">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 7.4, 1 M <named-entity id="named-entity-457">NaCl</named-entity>, 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-458">EDTA</named-entity>, 1% NP-40, 0.1% <named-entity id="named-entity-459">SDS</named-entity> and 0.5% <named-entity id="named-entity-460">sodium deoxycholate</named-entity>) and eluted in 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-461">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH7.4, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-462">NaCl</named-entity>, 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-463">EDTA</named-entity>, 1% <named-entity id="named-entity-464">SDS</named-entity> and 300 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-465">AcNa</named-entity>, pH 5.2 before phenol extraction. The precipitated RNAs were treated with 2 U of DNase RQ1 (Promega) for 30 min at 37 &#xB0;C before additional precipitation and reverse transcription with RT revertaid (Thermo Scientific) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Real-time PCR (Roche, LightCycler 480) was performed by using Master Mix Maxima SYBR Green qPCR (Thermo Scientific) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Primers are listed in <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Table 2</sir> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2380-S1">Supplementary Note</sir>.</p>
</sec>
</online-methods>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Author contributions</sectitle>
<p>N.H. established <i>Drosophila</i> cell lines, purified and identified <i>Drosophila</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-466">CWC22</named-entity> and performed all experiments with <i>Drosophila</i> cells. I.B. and F.F. cloned reporter constructs for human protein expression. I.B. performed cellular imagery, produced recombinant proteins and performed the interaction assays. F.F. performed ATPase assays. C.T. produced anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-467">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-468">CWC22</named-entity> rabbit polyclonal antibodies. H.L.H. performed <i>in vitro</i> splicing reactions and coprecipitations. I.B. and C.B. performed immunoprecipitations and knockdowns. M.B. and H.L.H. provided resources, conceived and directed the project. H.L.H. wrote the paper.</p></sec>
</bdy>
<bm>
<objects>
<fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-469">CWC22</named-entity> is associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-470">eIF4AIII</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Expression and purification of HF-<named-entity id="named-entity-471">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in <i>Drosophila</i> S2 stable cell lines, as detected with anti-<i>D. melanogaster</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-472">eIF4AIII</named-entity> antibodies. Input, supernatant (S) and precipitate (P) of successive affinity purification of HF-<named-entity id="named-entity-473">eIF4AIII</named-entity> on anti-Flag and anti-HA resins with (+) or without (&#x2212;) RNase treatment are shown. (<b>b</b>) Silver staining of eluted proteins purified by anti-HA and anti-Flag resins in HF-<named-entity id="named-entity-474">eIF4AIII</named-entity>-expressing and control cell lines with (+) or without (&#x2212;) RNase treatment. The protein migrating with an apparent molecular weight of 130 kDa was identified by mass spectrometry as <named-entity id="named-entity-475">CWC22</named-entity>. M, protein molecular weight standards (kDa). (<b>c</b>) Schematic representation of <named-entity id="named-entity-476">CWC22</named-entity> with its conserved MIF4G and MA3 domains in different species. Coordinates of the two domains are indicated for human <named-entity id="named-entity-477">CWC22</named-entity>. The size in amino acids of each protein is indicated. (<b>d</b>) Western blots of coimmunoprecipitated proteins associated with <named-entity id="named-entity-478">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and with <named-entity id="named-entity-479">CWC22</named-entity>. Protein extracts from HEK293 cells treated with RNase and immunoprecipitated without antibody (&#x2212;) or with the purified antibodies anti-Rab5, anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-480">eIF4AIII</named-entity> and anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-481">CWC22</named-entity> (N terminus) are shown. Western blot antibodies are indicated at left. Asterisk, nonspecific detection of IgG. (<b>e</b>) Western blots of size-fractionated HEK293 cell extracts. Antibodies are indicated at left. Fractions containing EJCs are indicated at bottom.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
<figtl>Recombinant <named-entity id="named-entity-482">CWC22</named-entity> directly interacts with <named-entity id="named-entity-483">eIF4AIII</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Schematic representation of human <named-entity id="named-entity-484">eIF4AIII</named-entity> (green) with its conserved motifs characteristic of DEAD-box proteins (F to VI, light green) and its G patch (orange). The boundary between <named-entity id="named-entity-485">eIF4AIII</named-entity> RecA-1 and RecA-2 domains is indicated. Below, representation of <named-entity id="named-entity-486">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-487">eIF4AI</named-entity> (gray) and chimeric proteins. Residue numbers at fragment boundaries are indicated. (<b>b</b>) Interaction of <named-entity id="named-entity-488">eIF4A3</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-489">eIF4A1</named-entity> or chimeric proteins with <named-entity id="named-entity-490">CWC22</named-entity>. SDS-PAGE (13.5% <named-entity id="named-entity-491">acrylamide</named-entity>) of the indicated eIF4A proteins (labels, left) coprecipitated with CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-492">CWC22</named-entity>-S (lanes 1, 3, 5 and 7) or not (lanes 2, 4, 6 and 8). Protein mixtures before (input: 35% of total) or after precipitation (precipitate) are shown. (<b>c</b>) Same as <b>b</b> except that the chimeric proteins eIF4A1333, eIF4A3133, eIF4A3313 and eIF4A3331 were used. (<b>d</b>) 3D structure of the EJC core<bibr rid="b5"/>. The surface of <named-entity id="named-entity-493">eIF4AIII</named-entity> RecA-1 and RecA-2 are colored in blue and green, respectively. The G patch is in orange. <named-entity id="named-entity-494">MAGOH</named-entity> (red), <named-entity id="named-entity-495">Y14</named-entity> (yellow) and <named-entity id="named-entity-496">MLN51</named-entity> (pink) are shown as skeletons and RNA as sticks. (<b>e</b>) Same as <b>b</b> except that wild-type (WT; lanes 1 and 2) and G-patch mutant (<named-entity id="named-entity-497">eIF4AIII</named-entity>mutG; lanes 3 and 4) <named-entity id="named-entity-498">eIF4AIII</named-entity> were mixed with CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-499">CWC22</named-entity>-S (lanes 2 and 4) or not (lanes 1 and 3).</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-500">CWC22</named-entity> does not bind EJC core and inhibits <named-entity id="named-entity-501">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding to RNA and ATPase activity.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Coprecipitations with CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-502">CWC22</named-entity>-S or CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-503">Upf3b</named-entity>-Ct (C-terminal, residues 262&#x2013;470) mixed with purified EJC core. Proteins before (input) and after precipitation (precipitate) are shown. (<b>b</b>) Protein coprecipitation with 3&#x2032;-end&#x2013;biotinylated 30-mer ssRNA, analyzed as in <b>a</b>. The heterodimer CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-504">eIF4AIII</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-505">CWC22</named-entity>-S or CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-506">eIF4AIII</named-entity>, with or without the EJC core proteins <named-entity id="named-entity-507">MLN51</named-entity>-S and <named-entity id="named-entity-508">MAGOH</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-509">Y14</named-entity>, mixed with ssRNA in the presence or in the absence of <named-entity id="named-entity-510">ADPNP</named-entity> are as indicated. (<b>c</b>) ATPase activities of CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-511">CWC22</named-entity> (as a control) and of CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-512">eIF4AIII</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-513">CWC22</named-entity>-S and CBP-<named-entity id="named-entity-514">eIF4AIII</named-entity> in the absence or in the presence of RNA as indicated. Fractions of hydrolyzed <named-entity id="named-entity-515">ATP</named-entity> were measured at 0, 1, 2 and 3 h. Data represent mean values and s.d. measured from three independent experiments.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-516">CWC22</named-entity> recruits <named-entity id="named-entity-517">eIF4AIII</named-entity> to active spliceosomes.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Splicing reactions with uniformly <super>32</super>P-labeled AdML-AG pre-mRNA. Denaturing PAGE gel (15% <named-entity id="named-entity-518">acrylamide</named-entity>) shows RNA extracts from splicing reactions either before (input, 10% of total) or after coprecipitation with the antibodies indicated or without (&#x2212;). Splicing substrate and intermediates are indicated on the left. (<b>b</b>) Same as <b>a</b> except that AdML-GG (allowing only the first step of splicing) was used as pre-mRNA. Splicing substrate and intermediates are indicated at left. (<b>c</b>) Coprecipitation of splicing products with TAP-tagged recombinant proteins. Gel shows RNA extracts before (I, 10% of total) or after precipitation with IgG beads (P, 90% total) as in <b>a</b>, following splicing reactions with AdML-AG pre-mRNA supplemented with TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-519">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>WT</super>, TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-520">CWC22</named-entity>-S, TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-521">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>WT</super>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-522">CWC22</named-entity> or TAP-<named-entity id="named-entity-523">eIF4AIII</named-entity><super>KR</super>. Precipitation (IP) efficiency of mRNA corresponding to the amount of RNA coprecipitated compared to input (considered as 100%) is indicated. (<b>d</b>) Same as <b>c</b>, except that AdML-GG was used as pre-mRNA. Precipitation efficiency of exon 1 is indicated.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f5" type="bmp" entname="figf5">
<figtl>Knockdown of <named-entity id="named-entity-524">CWC22</named-entity> prevents <named-entity id="named-entity-525">eIF4AIII</named-entity> binding to cellular mRNAs.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Western blot showing HEK293 cells treated with the siRNAs indicated on top. For <named-entity id="named-entity-526">CWC22</named-entity>, two different siRNAs were used. Antibodies used for detection are indicated at left. (<b>b</b>) RT-qPCR of endogenous mRNAs immunoprecipitated by anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-527">eIF4AIII</named-entity> antibodies in extracts from HEK293 cells treated with the siRNAs indicated. For each mRNA, the amount detected in cells treated with the control siRNA against GFP was considered as 100%. Data represent mean values and s.d. measured from three independent experiments.</p></caption></fig>
</objects>
<ack><p>We thank E. Izaurralde (Max Planck Institute for Developmental Biology, Tuebingen, Germany) for anti-MAGOH antibodies and E. Conti (Max Planck Institute for Biochemistry, Martinsried, Germany) for purified EJC core. We thank the Institut de G&#xE9;n&#xE9;tique et de Biologie Mol&#xE9;culaire et Cellulaire peptide-synthesis and antibody facilities. We thank M. Noizet and X. Darzacq for technical assistance for cellular imagery. We are grateful to the members of the lab for technical assistance, helpful advice and discussions. This work was supported in part by the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (ATIP programme blanc 2008, to H.L.H.), the Agence Nationale de la Recherche (2008-BLAN-0323, 2011-BLAN-01801, to H.L.H.), the Fondation pour la Recherche M&#xE9;dicale (H.L.H.) and the Stowers Institute for Medical Research (M.B.).</p></ack>
<audecl conflct="no"/>
<bibl><bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Proudfoot</snm>, <fnm>N.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Pre-mRNA processing reaches back to transcription and ahead to translation</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>136</vid>, <ppf>688</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>700</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Le Hir</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Izaurralde</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Maquat</snm>, <fnm>L.E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The spliceosome deposits multiple proteins 20&#x2013;24 nucleotides upstream of mRNA exon-exon junctions</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>6860</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>6869</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Tange</snm>, <fnm>T.&#xD8;.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nott</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The ever-increasing complexities of the exon junction complex</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>279</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>284</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Le Hir</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Andersen</snm>, <fnm>G.R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structural insights into the exon junction complex</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</jtl> <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>112</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>119</ppl> (<cd year="2008a">2008a</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Andersen</snm>, <fnm>C.B.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Structure of the exon junction core complex with a trapped DEAD-box ATPase bound to RNA</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>313</vid>, <ppf>1968</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1972</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ballut</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The exon junction core complex is locked onto RNA by inhibition of eIF4AIII ATPase activity</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>861</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>869</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bono</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ebert</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lorentzen</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Conti</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl>The crystal structure of the exon junction complex reveals how it maintains a stable grip on mRNA</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>126</vid>, <ppf>713</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>725</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Fairman-Williams</snm>, <fnm>M.E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Guenther</snm>, <fnm>U.P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jankowsky</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl>SF1 and SF2 helicases: family matters</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>313</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>324</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Nielsen</snm>, <fnm>K.H.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Mechanism of ATP turnover inhibition in the EJC</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>67</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>75</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gehring</snm>, <fnm>N.H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lamprinaki</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kulozik</snm>, <fnm>A.E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hentze</snm>, <fnm>M.W.</fnm></refau> <atl>Disassembly of exon junction complexes by PYM</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>137</vid>, <ppf>536</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>548</ppl> (<cd year="2009a">2009a</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>V.N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The Y14 protein communicates to the cytoplasm the position of exon-exon junctions</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>2062</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2068</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Le Hir</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gatfield</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Izaurralde</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The exon-exon junction complex provides a binding platform for factors involved in mRNA export and nonsense-mediated mRNA decay</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>4987</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>4997</ppl> (<cd year="2001a">2001a</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lejeune</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ishigaki</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Maquat</snm>, <fnm>L.E.</fnm></refau> <atl>The exon junction complex is detected on CBP80-bound but not eIF4E-bound mRNA in mammalian cells: dynamics of mRNP remodeling</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>3536</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3545</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ashton-Beaucage</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The exon junction complex controls the splicing of MAPK and other long intron-containing transcripts in <i>Drosophila</i></atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>143</vid>, <ppf>251</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>262</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Michelle</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Proteins associated with the exon junction complex also control the alternative splicing of apoptotic regulators</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell. Biol.</jtl> <vid>32</vid>, <ppf>954</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>967</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Roignant</snm>, <fnm>J.Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Treisman</snm>, <fnm>J.E.</fnm></refau> <atl>Exon junction complex subunits are required to splice <i>Drosophila</i> MAP kinase, a large heterochromatic gene</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>143</vid>, <ppf>238</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>250</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hachet</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ephrussi</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Splicing of oskar RNA in the nucleus is coupled to its cytoplasmic localization</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>428</vid>, <ppf>959</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>963</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Le Hir</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Seraphin</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <atl>EJCs at the heart of translational control</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>133</vid>, <ppf>213</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>216</ppl> (<cd year="2008b">2008b</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rebbapragada</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lykke-Andersen</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Execution of nonsense-mediated mRNA decay: what defines a substrate?</atl> <jtl>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>394</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>402</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hwang</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Maquat</snm>, <fnm>L.E.</fnm></refau> <atl>Nonsense-mediated mRNA decay (NMD) in animal embryogenesis: to die or not to die, that is the question</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>422</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>430</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>M&#xFC;hlemann</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lykke-Andersen</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>How and where are nonsense mRNAs degraded in mammalian cells?</atl> <jtl>RNA Biol.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>28</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>32</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Giorgi</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The EJC factor eIF4AIII modulates synaptic strength and neuronal protein expression</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>130</vid>, <ppf>179</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>191</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sauli&#xE8;re</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The exon junction complex differentially marks spliced junctions</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>1269</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1271</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Silver</snm>, <fnm>D.L.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The exon junction complex component Magoh controls brain size by regulating neural stem cell division</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>551</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>558</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wahl</snm>, <fnm>M.C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Will</snm>, <fnm>C.L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Luhrmann</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl>The spliceosome: design principles of a dynamic RNP machine</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>136</vid>, <ppf>701</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>718</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bessonov</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Anokhina</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Will</snm>, <fnm>C.L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Urlaub</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Luhrmann</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Isolation of an active step I spliceosome and composition of its RNP core</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>452</vid>, <ppf>846</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>850</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jurica</snm>, <fnm>M.S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Licklider</snm>, <fnm>L.J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gygi</snm>, <fnm>S.R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Grigorieff</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Purification and characterization of native spliceosomes suitable for three-dimensional structural analysis</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>426</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>439</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Makarov</snm>, <fnm>E.M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Small nuclear ribonucleoprotein remodeling during catalytic activation of the spliceosome</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>298</vid>, <ppf>2205</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2208</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Merz</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Urlaub</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Will</snm>, <fnm>C.L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Luhrmann</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Protein composition of human mRNPs spliced in vitro and differential requirements for mRNP protein recruitment</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>116</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>128</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Reichert</snm>, <fnm>V.L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Le Hir</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jurica</snm>, <fnm>M.S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>5&#x2032; exon interactions within the human spliceosome establish a framework for exon junction complex structure and assembly</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>2778</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2791</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b31"><reftxt><refau><snm>Zhang</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Krainer</snm>, <fnm>A.R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Splicing remodels messenger ribonucleoprotein architecture via eIF4A3-dependent and -independent recruitment of exon junction complex components</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>104</vid>, <ppf>11574</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>11579</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b32"><reftxt><refau><snm>Degot</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Association of the breast cancer protein MLN51 with the exon junction complex via its speckle localizer and RNA binding module</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>279</vid>, <ppf>33702</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>33715</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b33"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gehring</snm>, <fnm>N.H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lamprinaki</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hentze</snm>, <fnm>M.W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kulozik</snm>, <fnm>A.E.</fnm></refau> <atl>The hierarchy of exon-junction complex assembly by the spliceosome explains key features of mammalian nonsense-mediated mRNA decay</atl>. <jtl>PLoS Biol.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>e1000120</ppf> (<cd year="2009b">2009b</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b34"><reftxt><refau><snm>Tange</snm>, <fnm>T.&#xD8;.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shibuya</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jurica</snm>, <fnm>M.S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Biochemical analysis of the EJC reveals two new factors and a stable tetrameric protein core</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>1869</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1883</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b35"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ohi</snm>, <fnm>M.D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gould</snm>, <fnm>K.L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Characterization of interactions among the Cef1p-Prp19p-associated splicing complex</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>798</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>815</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b36"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kelly</snm>, <fnm>W.G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xu</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Montgomery</snm>, <fnm>M.K.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fire</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Distinct requirements for somatic and germline expression of a generally expressed <i>Caernorhabditis elegans</i> gene</atl>. <jtl>Genetics</jtl> <vid>146</vid>, <ppf>227</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>238</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b37"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yeh</snm>, <fnm>T.C.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Splicing factor Cwc22 is required for the function of Prp2 and for the spliceosome to escape from a futile pathway</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell. Biol.</jtl> <vid>31</vid>, <ppf>43</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>53</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b38"><reftxt><refau><snm>Daguenet</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Perispeckles are major assembly sites for the exon junction core complex</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Biol. Cell</jtl> <vid>23</vid>, <ppf>1765</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1782</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b39"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cust&#xF3;dio</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl><i>In vivo</i> recruitment of exon junction complex proteins to transcription sites in mammalian cell nuclei</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>622</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>633</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b40"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kataoka</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Diem</snm>, <fnm>M.D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>V.N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yong</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Dreyfuss</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Magoh, a human homolog of <i>Drosophila</i> mago nashi protein, is a component of the splicing-dependent exon-exon junction complex</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>6424</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>6433</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b41"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schmidt</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Richter</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Berger</snm>, <fnm>A.B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lichter</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl>In vivo BiFC analysis of Y14 and NXF1 mRNA export complexes: preferential localization within and around SC35 domains</atl>. <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>172</vid>, <ppf>373</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>381</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b42"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hall</snm>, <fnm>L.L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Smith</snm>, <fnm>K.P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Byron</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lawrence</snm>, <fnm>J.B.</fnm></refau> <atl>Molecular anatomy of a speckle</atl>. <jtl>Anat. Rec. A Discov. Mol. Cell. Evol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>288</vid>, <ppf>664</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>675</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b43"><reftxt><refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Eukaryotic translation initiation factor 4AIII (eIF4AIII) is functionally distinct from eIF4AI and eIF4AII</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell. Biol.</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>7336</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>7346</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b44"><reftxt><refau><snm>Shibuya</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tange</snm>, <fnm>T.O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Stroupe</snm>, <fnm>M.E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Moore</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Mutational analysis of human eIF4AIII identifies regions necessary for exon junction complex formation and nonsense-mediated mRNA decay</atl>. <jtl>RNA</jtl> <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>360</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>374</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b45"><reftxt><refau><snm>Chamieh</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ballut</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bonneau</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Le Hir</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <atl>NMD factors UPF2 and UPF3 bridge UPF1 to the exon junction complex and stimulate its RNA helicase activity</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>85</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>93</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b46"><reftxt><refau><snm>Henn</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bradley</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>De La Cruz</snm>, <fnm>E.M.</fnm></refau> <atl>ATP utilization and RNA conformational rearrangement by DEAD-box proteins</atl>. <jtl>Annu Rev Biophys</jtl> <vid>41</vid>, <ppf>247</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>267</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b47"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gozani</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Patton</snm>, <fnm>J.G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Reed</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl>A novel set of spliceosome-associated proteins and the essential splicing factor PSF bind stably to pre-mRNA prior to catalytic step II of the splicing reaction</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>3356</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3367</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b48"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jankowsky</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl>RNA helicases at work: binding and rearranging</atl>. <jtl>Trends Biochem. Sci.</jtl> <vid>36</vid>, <ppf>19</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>29</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b49"><reftxt><refau><snm>Alexandrov</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Colognori</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Steitz</snm>, <fnm>J.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Human eIF4AIII interacts with an eIF4G-like partner, NOM1, revealing an evolutionarily conserved function outside the exon junction complex</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>25</vid>, <ppf>1078</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1090</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b50"><reftxt><refau><snm>Budiman</snm>, <fnm>M.E.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Eukaryotic initiation factor 4a3 is a selenium-regulated RNA-binding protein that selectively inhibits selenocysteine incorporation</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>35</vid>, <ppf>479</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>489</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b51"><reftxt><refau><snm>Linder</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jankowsky</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl>From unwinding to clamping&#x2014;the DEAD box RNA helicase family</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>505</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>516</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b52"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hilbert</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kebbel</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gubaev</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klostermeier</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <atl>eIF4G stimulates the activity of the DEAD box protein eIF4A by a conformational guidance mechanism</atl>. <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>39</vid>, <ppf>2260</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2270</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b53"><reftxt><refau><snm>Marintchev</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Topology and regulation of the human eIF4A/4G/4H helicase complex in translation initiation</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>136</vid>, <ppf>447</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>460</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b54"><reftxt><refau><snm>Montpetit</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>A conserved mechanism of DEAD-box ATPase activation by nucleoporins and InsP6 in mRNA export</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>472</vid>, <ppf>238</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>242</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b55"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ideue</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sasaki</snm>, <fnm>Y.T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hagiwara</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hirose</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl>Introns play an essential role in splicing-dependent formation of the exon junction complex</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>1993</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1998</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b56"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schwer</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <atl>A conformational rearrangement in the spliceosome sets the stage for Prp22-dependent mRNA release</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>30</vid>, <ppf>743</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>754</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b57"><reftxt><refau><snm>Dignam</snm>, <fnm>J.D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lebovitz</snm>, <fnm>R.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Roeder</snm>, <fnm>R.G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Accurate transcription initiation by RNA polymerase II in a soluble extract from isolated mammalian nuclei</atl>. <jtl>Nucleic Acids Res.</jtl> <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>1475</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1489</ppl> (<cd year="1983">1983</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b58"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>K.K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Florens</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Swanson</snm>, <fnm>S.K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Washburn</snm>, <fnm>M.P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Workman</snm>, <fnm>J.L.</fnm></refau> <atl>The deubiquitylation activity of Ubp8 is dependent upon Sgf11 and its association with the SAGA complex</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell. Biol.</jtl> <vid>25</vid>, <ppf>1173</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1182</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b59"><reftxt><refau><snm>Chakrabarti</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Molecular mechanisms for the RNA-dependent ATPase activity of Upf1 and its regulation by Upf2</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>41</vid>, <ppf>693</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>703</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
</bibl></bm></article>
