<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "../../DTDs/NPG_XML_Article/NPG_XML_Article.dtd" [
<!ENTITY figf1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F1//EN" "nsmb.2395-F1" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf2 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F2//EN" "nsmb.2395-F2" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf3 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F3//EN" "nsmb.2395-F3" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf4 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F4//EN" "nsmb.2395-F4" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf5 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F5//EN" "nsmb.2395-F5" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf6 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F6//EN" "nsmb.2395-F6" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf7 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F7//EN" "nsmb.2395-F7" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf8 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2395-F8//EN" "nsmb.2395-F8" NDATA ITEM>
]>
<article id="nsmb.2395" language="eng" relation="no">
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</jtl>
<vol>19</vol>
<iss>11</iss>
<idt>201211</idt>
<categ id="af"/>
<pp><spn>1084</spn><epn>1092</epn><cnt>9</cnt></pp>
<issn type="print">1545-9993</issn>
<issn type="electronic">1545-9985</issn>
<cpg><cpy>2012</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</cpn></cpg>
<suppinfo id="S1">
<suppobj extrefid="nsmb.2395-S1" format="pdf" filesize="3M"><title>Supplementary Text and Figures</title>
<descrip><p>Supplementary Figures 1&#x2013;7 and Supplementary Table 1</p></descrip></suppobj>
</suppinfo>
<subject code="npg_subject_150"/>
<subject code="npg_subject_151"/>
<subject code="npg_subject_582"/>
<subject code="npg_subject_516"/>
<doi>10.1038/nsmb.2395</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl><named-entity id="named-entity-1">DVC1</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-2">C1orf124</named-entity>) is a DNA damage&#x2013;targeting <named-entity id="named-entity-3">p97</named-entity> adaptor that promotes ubiquitin-dependent responses to replication blocks</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Anna</fnm><snm>Mosbech</snm><inits>A</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a7"/></au>
<au><fnm>Ian</fnm><snm>Gibbs-Seymour</snm><inits>I</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a7"/></au>
<au><fnm>Konstantinos</fnm><snm>Kagias</snm><inits>K</inits><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Tina</fnm><snm>Thorslund</snm><inits>T</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Petra</fnm><snm>Beli</snm><inits>P</inits><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<au><fnm>Lou</fnm><snm>Povlsen</snm><inits>L</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Sofie Vincents</fnm><snm>Nielsen</snm><inits>S V</inits><orf rid="a4"/></au>
<au><fnm>Stine</fnm><snm>Smedegaard</snm><inits>S</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Garry</fnm><snm>Sedgwick</snm><inits>G</inits><orf rid="a5"/></au>
<au><fnm>Claudia</fnm><snm>Lukas</snm><inits>C</inits><orf rid="a6"/></au>
<au><fnm>Rasmus</fnm><snm>Hartmann-Petersen</snm><inits>R</inits><orf rid="a4"/></au>
<au><fnm>Jiri</fnm><snm>Lukas</snm><inits>J</inits><orf rid="a6"/></au>
<au><fnm>Chunaram</fnm><snm>Choudhary</snm><inits>C</inits><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<au><fnm>Roger</fnm><snm>Pocock</snm><inits>R</inits><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Simon</fnm><snm>Bekker-Jensen</snm><inits>S</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<cau><fnm>Niels</fnm><snm>Mailand</snm><inits>N</inits><orf rid="a1"/><corf rid="c1"/></cau>
<aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Ubiquitin Signaling Group, Department of Disease Biology, Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for Protein Research, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Copenhagen</org>, <cty>Copenhagen</cty>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a2"/><org>Biotech Research and Innovation Center, University of Copenhagen</org>, <cty>Copenhagen</cty>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a3"/><org>Department of Proteomics, Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for Protein Research, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Copenhagen</org>, <cty>Copenhagen</cty>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a4"/><org>Department of Biology, University of Copenhagen</org>, <cty>Copenhagen</cty>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a5"/><org>Mitotic Mechanisms and Regulation, Department of Disease Biology, Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for Protein Research, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Copenhagen</org>, <cty>Copenhagen</cty>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a6"/><org>Centre for Genotoxic Stress Research and Chromosome Biology Unit, Danish Cancer Society Research Center</org>, <cty>Copenhagen</cty>, <cny>Denmark</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a7"/>These authors contributed equally to this work.</aff>
<caff><coid id="c1"/><email>niels.mailand@cpr.ku.dk</email></caff>
</aug>
<hst>
<re year="2012" month="04" day="30"/>
<acc year="2012" month="08" day="30"/>
<pubdate type="aop" year="2012" month="10" day="07"/></hst>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="aop">
<title/>
<p>The AAA ATPase p97 (VCP) is thought to remove specific proteins from chromatin at sites of DNA damage, to allow proper repair or processing, but how p97 targets those sites was unclear. The protein DVC1 is now shown to localize to sites of replication stress and UV-light damage, and to be required for p97 recruitment. DVC1's localization to DNA damage sites requires its UBZ domain and PCNA-interacting motif but not PCNA ubiquitination. DVC1 deficiency caused retention of error-prone translesion polymerase &eta; at foci after UV-light damage and increased mutagenesis levels.</p></edsumm>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="issue">
<title/>
<p>The AAA ATPase p97 (VCP) is thought to remove specific proteins from chromatin at sites of DNA damage, to allow proper repair or processing, but how p97 targets those sites was unclear. The protein DVC1 is now shown to localize to sites of replication stress and UV-light damage, and to be required for p97 recruitment. DVC1's localization to DNA damage sites requires its UBZ domain and PCNA-interacting motif but not PCNA ubiquitination. DVC1 deficiency caused retention of error-prone translesion polymerase &eta; at foci after UV-light damage and increased mutagenesis levels.</p></edsumm>
<abs><p>Ubiquitin-mediated processes orchestrate critical DNA-damage signaling and repair pathways. We identify human <named-entity id="named-entity-4">DVC1</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-5">C1orf124</named-entity>; <named-entity id="named-entity-6">Spartan</named-entity>) as a cell cycle&#x2013;regulated anaphase-promoting complex (APC) substrate that accumulates at stalled replication forks. <named-entity id="named-entity-7">DVC1</named-entity> recruitment to sites of replication stress requires its ubiquitin-binding UBZ domain and PCNA-binding PIP box motif but is independent of <named-entity id="named-entity-8">RAD18</named-entity>-mediated <named-entity id="named-entity-9">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation. Via a conserved SHP box, <named-entity id="named-entity-10">DVC1</named-entity> recruits the ubiquitin-selective chaperone <named-entity id="named-entity-11">p97</named-entity> to blocked replication forks, which may facilitate <named-entity id="named-entity-12">p97</named-entity>-dependent removal of translesion synthesis (TLS) <named-entity id="named-entity-13">DNA polymerase &#x3B7;</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-14">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>) from monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-15">PCNA</named-entity>. <named-entity id="named-entity-16">DVC1</named-entity> knockdown enhances UV light&#x2013;induced mutagenesis, and depletion of human <named-entity id="named-entity-17">DVC1</named-entity> or the <i>Caenorhabditis elegans</i> ortholog <named-entity id="named-entity-18">DVC-1</named-entity> causes hypersensitivity to replication stress&#x2013;inducing agents. Our findings establish <named-entity id="named-entity-19">DVC1</named-entity> as a DNA damage&#x2013;targeting <named-entity id="named-entity-20">p97</named-entity> adaptor that protects cells from deleterious consequences of replication blocks and suggest an important role of <named-entity id="named-entity-21">p97</named-entity> in ubiquitin-dependent regulation of TLS.</p></abs></fm>
<bdy>
<p>All cells are continuously exposed to a multitude of DNA-damaging insults, which, if not properly sensed and repaired, represent a serious challenge to the maintenance of genomic stability and overall cell survival and fitness<bibr rid="b1 b2 b3"/>. Genetic material is particularly vulnerable to DNA damage encountered during DNA replication, which normally proceeds in a highly processive and largely error-free manner owing to the extremely high fidelity and proofreading activity of replicative DNA polymerases<bibr rid="b4 b5"/>. Because these polymerases cannot accommodate damaged or modified nucleotides in their active sites, however, the presence of unrepaired DNA lesions during DNA replication poses a major threat to genome stability, as the advancing replication machinery may stall at the lesion and potentially collapse, giving rise to highly cytotoxic DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs)<bibr rid="b3 b5 b6"/>. To mitigate such danger, cells have evolved damage-avoidance strategies to bypass replication-blocking lesions. One strategy involves specialized TLS DNA polymerases, which, unlike replicative DNA polymerases can incorporate nucleotides opposite bulky lesions and thus replicate DNA across a damaged site<bibr rid="b7 b8"/>. However, because the fidelity of TLS polymerases is generally much lower than that of replicative DNA polymerases, TLS is potentially an error-prone and thus mutagenic process.</p>
<p>TLS is primarily controlled at the level of TLS polymerase interactions with <named-entity id="named-entity-22">PCNA</named-entity>, and, given the low fidelity of these polymerases, their access to <named-entity id="named-entity-23">PCNA</named-entity> must be stringently controlled. Replication stress&#x2013;induced <named-entity id="named-entity-24">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation by the <named-entity id="named-entity-25">RAD18</named-entity>&#x2013;RAD6 ubiquitin ligase complex facilitates an exchange of the replicative polymerase with a TLS polymerase, which contains both PCNA-binding PIP box and ubiquitin-binding motifs that enables it to preferentially interact with monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-26">PCNA</named-entity><bibr rid="b9 b10 b11 b12"/>. Ubiquitin-dependent regulation of the TLS <named-entity id="named-entity-27">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> also contributes to the control of TLS activity. <named-entity id="named-entity-28">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> is modified by coupled monoubiquitylation dependent on its ubiquitin-binding UBZ domain, and this modification may inhibit its TLS functions through an intramolecular interaction between the monoubiquitin attached to <named-entity id="named-entity-29">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> and its UBZ domain, thereby masking its PCNA-binding region<bibr rid="b12 b13"/>. How cells resume replication by replicative polymerases after TLS polymerase&#x2013;mediated lesion bypass is not understood in detail, but it is known that <named-entity id="named-entity-30">PCNA</named-entity> can be targeted for deubiquitylation by the deubiquitinating enzyme <named-entity id="named-entity-31">USP1</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b14">14</bibrinl>).</p>
<p>In addition to its central importance in regulating TLS, ubiquitin-dependent signaling processes have a key role in many other cellular responses to DNA damage, including the repair of DNA interstrand cross-links and DSBs<bibr rid="b10 b15"/>. The multifunctional ubiquitin-selective chaperone <named-entity id="named-entity-32">p97</named-entity> (also known as <named-entity id="named-entity-33">valosin-containing protein</named-entity>; <named-entity id="named-entity-34">VCP</named-entity>) has been recently implicated as a mediator of important ubiquitin-dependent transactions in the DNA-damage response. By means of its AAA ATPase activity, <named-entity id="named-entity-35">p97</named-entity> remodels many ubiquitylated proteins and thus acts as a central regulator of many ubiquitin-dependent cellular processes<bibr rid="b16"/>. Depending on the substrate, <named-entity id="named-entity-36">p97</named-entity> can promote ubiquitin editing, proteasomal delivery or disassembly of protein complexes containing one or more ubiquitylated factors. Recent findings have demonstrated that <named-entity id="named-entity-37">p97</named-entity> promotes unfolding and subsequent degradation of ubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-38">CDT1</named-entity> in response to UV light<bibr rid="b17"/>, and that it facilitates displacement of <named-entity id="named-entity-39">RNF8</named-entity> and/or <named-entity id="named-entity-40">RNF168</named-entity>&#x2013;ubiquitylated client proteins from DSB-modified chromatin to permit recruitment of the DNA repair factor <named-entity id="named-entity-41">53BP1</named-entity> (refs. <bibrinl rid="b18">18</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b19">19</bibrinl>). To a large extent, the myriad of cellular <named-entity id="named-entity-42">p97</named-entity> functions are mediated by its interaction with many cofactors and adaptors that bind the N-terminal domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-43">p97</named-entity> via defined <named-entity id="named-entity-44">p97</named-entity>-interaction motifs, several of which have been identified<bibr rid="b16 b20"/>. Most of these accessory <named-entity id="named-entity-45">p97</named-entity> factors also have ubiquitin-binding domains, which may specifically direct <named-entity id="named-entity-46">p97</named-entity> to a particular subset of ubiquitylated proteins, subcellular compartments or cellular pathways<bibr rid="b16 b20"/>. However, the precise functions of most individual <named-entity id="named-entity-47">p97</named-entity> cofactors and adaptors are still poorly understood. Despite the important, emerging function of <named-entity id="named-entity-48">p97</named-entity> in promoting ubiquitin-mediated responses to genotoxic stress, it is not clear how <named-entity id="named-entity-49">p97</named-entity> is recruited to sites of DNA damage.</p>
<p>In this study, we searched for uncharacterized human proteins localizing to sites of DNA damage, and identify <named-entity id="named-entity-50">DVC1</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-51">C1orf124</named-entity>) as a DNA damage&#x2013;targeting <named-entity id="named-entity-52">p97</named-entity> adaptor. Through its ability to bind <named-entity id="named-entity-53">p97</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-54">PCNA</named-entity> and DNA damage&#x2013;associated ubiquitylations via defined sequence motifs, <named-entity id="named-entity-55">DVC1</named-entity> efficiently recruits <named-entity id="named-entity-56">p97</named-entity> to blocked replication forks, leading to removal of <named-entity id="named-entity-57">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from the stalled forks. We also find that the ability of <named-entity id="named-entity-58">DVC1</named-entity> to promote cellular responses to replication problems is evolutionarily conserved between humans and <i>C. elegans</i>. Our results provide mechanistic insight into how <named-entity id="named-entity-59">p97</named-entity> facilitates ubiquitin-dependent cellular responses to genotoxic stress.</p>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Results</sectitle>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Recruitment of human <named-entity id="named-entity-60">DVC1</named-entity> to stalled replication forks</sectitle>
<p>We screened a collection of CFP-tagged or YFP-tagged human open reading frames for their ability to accumulate at sites of DNA damage, using a microlaser irradiation&#x2013;based approach (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1a</sir>)<bibr rid="b21"/>. We found that <named-entity id="named-entity-61">C1orf124</named-entity>, an uncharacterized protein containing a ubiquitin-binding UBZ domain as well as a potential metalloprotease (SprT) domain (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1a</figr>), was recruited to microlaser irradiation&#x2013;induced DNA lesions (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1a</sir>). We refer to <named-entity id="named-entity-62">C1orf124</named-entity> (also known as <named-entity id="named-entity-63">Spartan</named-entity><bibr rid="b22"/>) as DNA damage&#x2013;targeting <named-entity id="named-entity-64">VCP</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-65">p97</named-entity>) adaptor <named-entity id="named-entity-66">C1orf124</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-67">DVC1</named-entity>). To gain more insight into the recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-68">DVC1</named-entity> to damaged DNA, we generated a cell line stably expressing AcGFP-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-69">DVC1</named-entity> (GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-70">DVC1</named-entity>) and assessed formation of GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-71">DVC1</named-entity> nuclear foci after various genotoxic insults. GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-72">DVC1</named-entity> formed foci in response to replication blocks induced by treatment with UV light, <named-entity id="named-entity-73">hydroxyurea</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-74">mitomycin C</named-entity> or cisplatin (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1c</figr>) but not in response to ionizing radiation or <named-entity id="named-entity-75">camptothecin</named-entity> treatment (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1c</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1b</sir>), both of which induce DNA DSBs. We also observed formation of UV light&#x2013;induced endogenous <named-entity id="named-entity-76">DVC1</named-entity> foci (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1d</figr>). Nuclear <named-entity id="named-entity-77">DVC1</named-entity> foci were present in a low proportion of unperturbed cells, and this fraction dramatically increased after UV irradiation (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1e</figr>), similar to what has been observed for other <named-entity id="named-entity-78">PCNA</named-entity>-associated proteins, such as TLS polymerases<bibr rid="b23"/>. Indeed, nuclear <named-entity id="named-entity-79">DVC1</named-entity> foci fully localized with <named-entity id="named-entity-80">PCNA</named-entity> (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1f</figr>), and their formation was restricted to cells in S phase (data not shown). After UV irradiation, <named-entity id="named-entity-81">DVC1</named-entity> also localized with RPA foci, generated in response to the formation of extended stretches of single-strand DNA upon stalling of the replication fork<bibr rid="b24"/> (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1g</figr>). Together, these data show that <named-entity id="named-entity-82">DVC1</named-entity> undergoes recruitment to blocked replisomes during S phase.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Cell cycle&#x2013;dependent regulation of <named-entity id="named-entity-83">DVC1</named-entity> expression</sectitle>
<p>We monitored the expression and localization pattern of <named-entity id="named-entity-84">DVC1</named-entity> during the cell cycle. We noted that endogenous <named-entity id="named-entity-85">DVC1</named-entity> was predominantly expressed during S and G2 phases of the cell cycle, closely matching the expression profile of known targets of the anaphase-promoting complex (APC), such as <named-entity id="named-entity-86">cyclin B1</named-entity> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2a</figr>), that are absent from cells in G1 phase<bibr rid="b25"/>. Upon exit from mitosis, <named-entity id="named-entity-87">DVC1</named-entity> expression was rapidly downregulated with kinetics similar to that of known APC&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-88">Cdh1</named-entity> targets such as <named-entity id="named-entity-89">cyclin A</named-entity>, and reaccumulated as cells entered S phase (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2b</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 2a,b</sir>). This suggested that <named-entity id="named-entity-90">DVC1</named-entity> was itself targeted for degradation by APC-<named-entity id="named-entity-91">Cdh1</named-entity>. Indeed, we found that expression of <named-entity id="named-entity-92">DVC1</named-entity> was strongly reduced upon overexpression of <named-entity id="named-entity-93">Cdh1</named-entity>, which causes activation of APC&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-94">Cdh1</named-entity> activity irrespective of cell-cycle stage<bibr rid="b26"/> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2c</figr>), whereas <named-entity id="named-entity-95">Cdh1</named-entity> knockdown notably elevated endogenous <named-entity id="named-entity-96">DVC1</named-entity> expression (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2d</figr>). Moreover, <named-entity id="named-entity-97">DVC1</named-entity> interacted with <named-entity id="named-entity-98">Cdh1</named-entity> and could be ubiquitylated by APC&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-99">Cdh1</named-entity> <i>in vitro</i> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 2c,d</sir>). We conclude that <named-entity id="named-entity-100">DVC1</named-entity> expression is cell cycle&#x2013;regulated and is restricted to cells in S, G2 and early M phases owing to its destruction mediated by APC&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-101">Cdh1</named-entity>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Ubiquitin-regulated <named-entity id="named-entity-102">DVC1</named-entity> recruitment to stalled replisomes</sectitle>
<p>Several proteins, including TLS polymerases, are recruited to <named-entity id="named-entity-103">PCNA</named-entity> at stalled replication forks via a ubiquitin-binding UBZ zinc-finger motif<bibr rid="b27"/>. Because <named-entity id="named-entity-104">DVC1</named-entity> contains a conserved C-terminal UBZ domain, we reasoned that relocalization of <named-entity id="named-entity-105">DVC1</named-entity> to sites of replication stress might similarly involve ubiquitin binding via this motif. To test this, we first asked whether the recombinant <named-entity id="named-entity-106">DVC1</named-entity> UBZ domain has ubiquitin-binding activity <i>in vitro</i>. We found that <named-entity id="named-entity-107">DVC1</named-entity> efficiently bound to both Lys48- and Lys63-linked ubiquitin chains, but not monoubiquitin, displaying preferential affinity for longer chains (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3a&#x2013;c</figr>). Inactivating point mutations (C456G and C459G) in the UBZ domain abolished <named-entity id="named-entity-108">DVC1</named-entity>&#x2013;ubiquitin interactions (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3a&#x2013;c</figr>), indicating that this motif is the predominant ubiquitin-binding determinant in <named-entity id="named-entity-109">DVC1</named-entity>. Mutation of the UBZ domain suppressed formation of UV light&#x2013;induced <named-entity id="named-entity-110">DVC1</named-entity> foci (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3d</figr>), suggesting that <named-entity id="named-entity-111">DVC1</named-entity> is recruited to ubiquitylation products generated at stalled replication forks. Coupled UBZ-dependent monoubiquitylation of <named-entity id="named-entity-112">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> inhibits its recruitment to stalled replication forks owing to an intramolecular interaction with the UBZ domain<bibr rid="b13"/>. We noted that <named-entity id="named-entity-113">DVC1</named-entity> was also monoubiquitylated in a UBZ-dependent manner (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3e,f</figr>), raising the possibility that <named-entity id="named-entity-114">DVC1</named-entity> monoubiquitylation prevented its focal accumulation in a similar manner. To test this, we generated <named-entity id="named-entity-115">DVC1</named-entity>-ubiquitin fusion constructs that mimicked constitutively monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-116">DVC1</named-entity> (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3a</figr>). We found that ubiquitin-fused <named-entity id="named-entity-117">DVC1</named-entity> was not recruited to UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci and did not undergo monoubiquitylation (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3e,g</figr>). Moreover, the ubiquitin-binding ability of this chimeric protein was strongly reduced compared to that of <named-entity id="named-entity-118">DVC1</named-entity> alone (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3e</figr>), suggesting that the UBZ domain was constitutively bound by the fused ubiquitin moiety, similar to what has been observed for <named-entity id="named-entity-119">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>&#x2013;ubiquitin fusions<bibr rid="b12"/>. Consistently, an I44A mutation in ubiquitin that disrupts its ability to interact with the UBZ domain<bibr rid="b28"/> fully restored the formation of foci and monoubiquitylation of the <named-entity id="named-entity-120">DVC1</named-entity>-ubiquitin chimera, and increased its ubiquitin-binding affinity (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3e,g</figr>). Whether UBZ-dependent coupled monoubiquitylation of <named-entity id="named-entity-121">DVC1</named-entity>, like that of <named-entity id="named-entity-122">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity><super>13</super>, has an active role in regulating the access of <named-entity id="named-entity-123">DVC1</named-entity> to stalled replication forks remains to be established. Together, these observations suggest that UBZ-mediated recognition of ubiquitylated factors is required for <named-entity id="named-entity-124">DVC1</named-entity> recruitment to blocked replication forks.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-125">DVC1</named-entity> interacts with <named-entity id="named-entity-126">PCNA</named-entity> via a canonical PIP box</sectitle>
<p>Many proteins associate with the replication machinery via a PCNA-binding PIP box motif<bibr rid="b29"/>. We noted that <named-entity id="named-entity-127">DVC1</named-entity> contains a canonical PIP box (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4a</figr>), and because <named-entity id="named-entity-128">DVC1</named-entity> localizes with <named-entity id="named-entity-129">PCNA</named-entity> at sites of replication stress (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1f</figr>), we tested whether <named-entity id="named-entity-130">DVC1</named-entity> is a <named-entity id="named-entity-131">PCNA</named-entity>-binding protein. Indeed, pull-down experiments revealed that <named-entity id="named-entity-132">DVC1</named-entity> interacted with <named-entity id="named-entity-133">PCNA</named-entity> both <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i>, in a manner fully dependent on the integrity of its PIP box but not of other motifs (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4b,c</figr> and data not shown). This <named-entity id="named-entity-134">PCNA</named-entity>-binding ability was essential for <named-entity id="named-entity-135">DVC1</named-entity> relocalization to distressed replication forks, as PIP box mutations resulted in impaired formation of UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear <named-entity id="named-entity-136">DVC1</named-entity> foci (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4d</figr>). The simultaneous requirement of PIP and UBZ motifs for retention of <named-entity id="named-entity-137">DVC1</named-entity> at sites of DNA damage resembles the mode of recruitment of Y-family TLS polymerases to <named-entity id="named-entity-138">PCNA</named-entity> at stalled replication forks, which depends on <named-entity id="named-entity-139">RAD18</named-entity>-mediated <named-entity id="named-entity-140">PCNA</named-entity> Lys164 monoubiquitylation<bibr rid="b11"/>. Consistently, as was the case with <named-entity id="named-entity-141">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-142">DVC1</named-entity> interacted with both ubiquitylated and unmodified forms of <named-entity id="named-entity-143">PCNA</named-entity> in a UV light&#x2013;dependent manner (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4c</figr>). However, we found that inhibiting UV light&#x2013;induced <named-entity id="named-entity-144">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation by depletion of <named-entity id="named-entity-145">RAD18</named-entity> did not affect the formation of <named-entity id="named-entity-146">DVC1</named-entity> foci, although recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-147">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-148">PCNA</named-entity> was efficiently inhibited, as expected (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4e</figr>). This suggested that although the PIP and UBZ domains are required for targeting <named-entity id="named-entity-149">DVC1</named-entity> to sites of replication stress, <named-entity id="named-entity-150">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation in itself is dispensable for such recruitment. Indeed, cells stably expressing a <named-entity id="named-entity-151">PCNA</named-entity> K164R mutant refractory to <named-entity id="named-entity-152">RAD18</named-entity>-dependent ubiquitylation were also deficient for recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-153">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> but not of <named-entity id="named-entity-154">DVC1</named-entity> to stalled replication forks (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4f</figr>), and <named-entity id="named-entity-155">DVC1</named-entity>, but not <named-entity id="named-entity-156">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, retained interaction with unmodified <named-entity id="named-entity-157">PCNA</named-entity> in <named-entity id="named-entity-158">RAD18</named-entity>-depleted cells (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4g</figr>). Moreover, overexpression of <named-entity id="named-entity-159">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, but not of <named-entity id="named-entity-160">DVC1</named-entity>, notably increased <named-entity id="named-entity-161">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation in a manner dependent on the UBZ domain (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4c,h</figr>), suggesting that <named-entity id="named-entity-162">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> binding to monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-163">PCNA</named-entity> protects it from deubiquitylation. We conclude that <named-entity id="named-entity-164">DVC1</named-entity> is recruited to stalled replication forks in a manner requiring its PIP and UBZ motifs but independent of <named-entity id="named-entity-165">PCNA</named-entity> ubiquitylation, suggesting that <named-entity id="named-entity-166">DVC1</named-entity> can recognize other, as-yet unknown ubiquitylation products at blocked replication forks. Knockdown of known DNA damage&#x2013;responsive ubiquitin ligases such as <named-entity id="named-entity-167">RNF8</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-168">RNF168</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-169">BRCA1</named-entity> and CUL4-<named-entity id="named-entity-170">DDB1</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-171">CDT2</named-entity> (refs. <bibrinl rid="b30">30</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b31">31</bibrinl>) did not detectably impair <named-entity id="named-entity-172">DVC1</named-entity> recruitment to UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1c</sir>).</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-173">DVC1</named-entity> is a DNA damage&#x2013;targeting <named-entity id="named-entity-174">p97</named-entity> adaptor</sectitle>
<p>To gain insight into the cellular functions of <named-entity id="named-entity-175">DVC1</named-entity>, we comprehensively mapped <named-entity id="named-entity-176">DVC1</named-entity>-interacting proteins. To this end, we expressed GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-177">DVC1</named-entity> in U2OS cells labeled by stable isotope labeling with amino acids in cell culture (SILAC)<bibr rid="b32"/> and analyzed proteins in GFP immunoprecipitates by mass spectrometry (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5a</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Table 1</sir>). As expected, both <named-entity id="named-entity-178">PCNA</named-entity> and ubiquitin were among the proteins most prominently identified in GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-179">DVC1</named-entity> immunoprecipitates (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5a</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Table 1</sir>). We also found substantial amounts of the <named-entity id="named-entity-180">p97</named-entity> ubiquitin-selective chaperone (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5a</figr>), which has been recently implicated in ubiquitin-mediated cellular responses to DNA damage<bibr rid="b16 b17 b18 b19"/>, and we confirmed by co-immunoprecipitation an avid interaction between GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-181">DVC1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-182">p97</named-entity> that was unaffected by DNA damage (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5b</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 3a</sir>). We noted that <named-entity id="named-entity-183">DVC1</named-entity> contains a highly conserved sequence matching the SHP box (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5c</figr>), a known p97-binding motif<bibr rid="b20"/>. Mutation of this sequence, but not of other conserved domains in <named-entity id="named-entity-184">DVC1</named-entity>, completely abolished the <named-entity id="named-entity-185">DVC1</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-186">p97</named-entity> interaction (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5b</figr>), suggesting that <named-entity id="named-entity-187">DVC1</named-entity> is a new <named-entity id="named-entity-188">p97</named-entity> adaptor. Consistently, high levels of <named-entity id="named-entity-189">p47</named-entity> (also known as <named-entity id="named-entity-190">NSFL1C</named-entity>), a <named-entity id="named-entity-191">p97</named-entity> adaptor that also contains an SHP box<bibr rid="b20"/>, outcompeted binding of <named-entity id="named-entity-192">DVC1</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-193">p97</named-entity> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 3b</sir>). Moreover, like other <named-entity id="named-entity-194">p97</named-entity> adaptors<bibr rid="b20"/>, <named-entity id="named-entity-195">DVC1</named-entity> bound to the N-terminal domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-196">p97</named-entity> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 3c</sir>).</p>
<p>We tested whether binding to <named-entity id="named-entity-197">p97</named-entity> was required for <named-entity id="named-entity-198">DVC1</named-entity> recruitment to stalled replication forks. Unlike mutation of the PIP and UBZ motifs, however, <named-entity id="named-entity-199">DVC1</named-entity> with F253A and L260A mutations in the SHP box (<named-entity id="named-entity-200">DVC1</named-entity> SHP*) was fully proficient for formation of nuclear foci (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5d</figr>), indicating that <named-entity id="named-entity-201">DVC1</named-entity> relocalization to sites of replication stress does not require <named-entity id="named-entity-202">p97</named-entity>. We reasoned that <named-entity id="named-entity-203">DVC1</named-entity> might instead promote recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-204">p97</named-entity> to blocked replisomes. To test this, we assessed whether <named-entity id="named-entity-205">p97</named-entity> forms UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci. We could not detect <named-entity id="named-entity-206">p97</named-entity> foci in naive cells, even when non&#x2013;chromatin-bound proteins were pre-extracted with detergents (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 4a</sir>). However, when wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-207">DVC1</named-entity> was overproduced in cells, both endogenous and ectopically expressed <named-entity id="named-entity-208">p97</named-entity> were readily detectable in detergent-resistant, UV light&#x2013;induced foci localizing with <named-entity id="named-entity-209">DVC1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-210">PCNA</named-entity> (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5e,f</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 4b</sir>). This required the ability of <named-entity id="named-entity-211">DVC1</named-entity> to interact with both <named-entity id="named-entity-212">p97</named-entity> and blocked replication forks, as neither expression of <named-entity id="named-entity-213">DVC1</named-entity> SHP* nor of <named-entity id="named-entity-214">DVC1</named-entity> with C456G and C459G mutations in the UBZ domain (<named-entity id="named-entity-215">DVC1</named-entity> UBZ*) induced formation of <named-entity id="named-entity-216">p97</named-entity> foci (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5f,g</figr>). Other cofactors implicated in chromatin-associated <named-entity id="named-entity-217">p97</named-entity> functions, including <named-entity id="named-entity-218">Ufd1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-219">Npl4</named-entity> (refs. <bibrinl rid="b16">16</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b17">17</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b19">19</bibrinl>), did not accumulate in UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci in an amount that we could detect, even when expressed with ectopic <named-entity id="named-entity-220">DVC1</named-entity>, and they did not promote focal accumulation of <named-entity id="named-entity-221">p97</named-entity> when overexpressed (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 4c&#x2013;e</sir>), suggesting that this ability may be exclusive to <named-entity id="named-entity-222">DVC1</named-entity>. Moreover, reducing <named-entity id="named-entity-223">Ufd1</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-224">Npl4</named-entity> expression did not impair the ability of <named-entity id="named-entity-225">DVC1</named-entity> to recruit <named-entity id="named-entity-226">p97</named-entity> to UV light&#x2013;induced foci (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 4f</sir>). Likewise, knockdown of <named-entity id="named-entity-227">DVC1</named-entity> did not affect known <named-entity id="named-entity-228">p97</named-entity>-dependent responses such as the degradation of ERAD substrates<bibr rid="b16"/> (data not shown). Together, these data demonstrate that <named-entity id="named-entity-229">DVC1</named-entity> is a new <named-entity id="named-entity-230">p97</named-entity> adaptor that selectively promotes its relocalization to blocked replication forks during S phase.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-231">DVC1</named-entity> promotes <named-entity id="named-entity-232">p97</named-entity>-mediated responses to stalled replication</sectitle>
<p><named-entity id="named-entity-233">p97</named-entity> has a key role in many ubiquitin-mediated cellular processes, and has been recently implicated as a mediator of ubiquitin-dependent events in the DNA-damage response<bibr rid="b16"/>. We reasoned that by recruiting <named-entity id="named-entity-234">p97</named-entity> to blocked replication forks, <named-entity id="named-entity-235">DVC1</named-entity> might promote <named-entity id="named-entity-236">p97</named-entity>-dependent responses to replication problems. The similar mode of recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-237">DVC1</named-entity> and TLS polymerases to UV light&#x2013;induced DNA damage<bibr rid="b8"/> prompted us to assess whether modulation of cellular <named-entity id="named-entity-238">DVC1</named-entity> expression affected TLS polymerase status. We noted that <named-entity id="named-entity-239">DVC1</named-entity>-depleted cells showed a pronounced persistence of UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear <named-entity id="named-entity-240">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> foci (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6a,b</figr>). This effect was phenocopied by an independent small interfering RNA (siRNA) to <i><named-entity id="named-entity-241">DVC1</named-entity></i> but not by knockdown of <named-entity id="named-entity-242">Ufd1</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-243">Npl4</named-entity>, consistent with the inability of these factors to form UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci (<figr rid="f6">Fig.6b</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Figs. 4c,d and 5a&#x2013;c</sir>). Moreover, <named-entity id="named-entity-244">DVC1</named-entity> depletion impaired the reduction in interaction between <named-entity id="named-entity-245">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> and monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-246">PCNA</named-entity> as well as the pool of chromatin-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-247">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, at late time points after UV irradiation (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6c</figr>). Likewise, overexpression of <named-entity id="named-entity-248">DVC1</named-entity> suppressed the interaction between <named-entity id="named-entity-249">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> and monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-250">PCNA</named-entity> (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6d</figr>). These observations could not be explained by an effect of <named-entity id="named-entity-251">DVC1</named-entity> on UV light&#x2013;induced <named-entity id="named-entity-252">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation and foci formation, or overall cell-cycle distribution, which were not markedly affected by <named-entity id="named-entity-253">DVC1</named-entity> knockdown or overexpression (<figr rid="f4">Figs. 4h</figr>,<figr rid="f6">6c,d</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 6a&#x2013;e</sir>). We surmised that such apparent <named-entity id="named-entity-254">DVC1</named-entity>-dependent displacement of <named-entity id="named-entity-255">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from stalled replication forks might be actively mediated by <named-entity id="named-entity-256">p97</named-entity>. Consistently, we found that enhancing <named-entity id="named-entity-257">p97</named-entity> recruitment to UV light&#x2013;induced foci by overexpression of wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-258">DVC1</named-entity> led to a notable removal of <named-entity id="named-entity-259">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from these structures (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6e,f</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 5d</sir>). This indicates that the presence of <named-entity id="named-entity-260">p97</named-entity> in UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci is inhibitory to the retention of <named-entity id="named-entity-261">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, and that <named-entity id="named-entity-262">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> might be displaced from foci by means of the segregase activity of <named-entity id="named-entity-263">p97</named-entity>. Consistent with this idea, we found that although ATPase-deficient <named-entity id="named-entity-264">p97</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-265">p97</named-entity>(E578Q)) was targeted to UV light&#x2013;induced foci by <named-entity id="named-entity-266">DVC1</named-entity> as efficiently as wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-267">p97</named-entity> was, it did not efficiently trigger <named-entity id="named-entity-268">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> removal from the foci (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6e,f</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 5d,e</sir>). Although no overt changes in overall <named-entity id="named-entity-269">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> expression were apparent under these conditions (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 5f</sir>), it remains to be established whether displacement of <named-entity id="named-entity-270">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from foci is mainly a consequence of <named-entity id="named-entity-271">p97</named-entity>-dependent extraction or degradation. Consistent with an important role of <named-entity id="named-entity-272">DVC1</named-entity> in restraining the interaction between <named-entity id="named-entity-273">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> and monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-274">PCNA</named-entity>, we observed an increased rate of UV light&#x2013;induced mutagenesis in <named-entity id="named-entity-275">DVC1</named-entity>-depleted cells (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6g</figr>), comparable to the effect of <named-entity id="named-entity-276">USP1</named-entity> knockdown, which increases <named-entity id="named-entity-277">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation<bibr rid="b14"/>. Moreover, knockdown of <named-entity id="named-entity-278">DVC1</named-entity> enhanced cellular sensitivity to cisplatin but not to ionizing radiation (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6h</figr>). These observations suggest that a key function of <named-entity id="named-entity-279">DVC1</named-entity> is to promote cellular responses to replication problems by facilitating <named-entity id="named-entity-280">p97</named-entity>-dependent processing of substrate proteins, such as <named-entity id="named-entity-281">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, directly at stalled replication forks.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-282">DVC1</named-entity> function is conserved between humans and <i>C. elegans</i></sectitle>
<p>We noted that <named-entity id="named-entity-283">DVC1</named-entity> is highly conserved during eukaryotic evolution and that a clear <named-entity id="named-entity-284">DVC1</named-entity> ortholog (<named-entity id="named-entity-285">T19B10.6</named-entity>, referred to here as <named-entity id="named-entity-286">DVC-1</named-entity>) exists in <i>C. elegans</i>. Although this protein lacks a canonical PIP box, the SHP, UBZ and SprT domains are present (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7a</figr>). To test whether <named-entity id="named-entity-287">DVC1</named-entity> function is conserved between humans and nematodes, we first analyzed the subcellular embryonic localization of <named-entity id="named-entity-288">DVC-1</named-entity> using a <named-entity id="named-entity-289">DVC-1</named-entity>&#x2013;GFP fusion protein. Although <named-entity id="named-entity-290">DVC-1</named-entity>&#x2013;GFP localized diffusely to the nucleoplasm in nondamaged embryos, it became concentrated in bright nuclear foci in response to UV light treatment in a subset of cells (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7b</figr>), similar to human <named-entity id="named-entity-291">DVC1</named-entity>. To probe the possible role of <named-entity id="named-entity-292">DVC-1</named-entity> during <i>C. elegans</i> development, we studied a <i><named-entity id="named-entity-293">dvc-1</named-entity></i> deletion strain, <i><named-entity id="named-entity-294">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i>, which contains a 1-kb deletion that removes part of the promoter region and the first three exons of the gene, and is therefore a predicted null allele (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7a</figr>). We observed no obvious developmental or behavioral defects in <i><named-entity id="named-entity-295">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> worms, but their brood sizes were smaller (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7c</figr> and data not shown). The reduced brood size was also phenocopied with <i><named-entity id="named-entity-296">dvc-1</named-entity></i> RNA interference (RNAi)-mediated knockdown (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7c</figr>), indicating that it indeed resulted from loss of <named-entity id="named-entity-297">DVC-1</named-entity> function. We observed no embryonic lethality in the <i><named-entity id="named-entity-298">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> strain; therefore the reduced brood size may reflect a defect in germ-cell proliferation. Because <named-entity id="named-entity-299">DVC-1</named-entity>&#x2013;GFP relocalized to UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci like human <named-entity id="named-entity-300">DVC1</named-entity> did, we hypothesized that the <i><named-entity id="named-entity-301">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> mutant might be sensitive to replication stress&#x2013;inducing agents. Indeed, we found that <i><named-entity id="named-entity-302">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> worms exhibited increased embryonic lethality compared to wild-type controls when exposed to UV light (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7d</figr>). Upon exposure of L1 larvae to <named-entity id="named-entity-303">hydroxyurea</named-entity>, we noted that <i><named-entity id="named-entity-304">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> worms displayed increased sterility compared to the wild type, whereas their fertility was similar in the absence of genotoxic stress (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7e</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 7</sir>). The <named-entity id="named-entity-305">hydroxyurea</named-entity> sensitivity of <i><named-entity id="named-entity-306">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> worms is similar to that observed when the <named-entity id="named-entity-307">p97</named-entity> worm orthologs <i><named-entity id="named-entity-308">cdc-48.1</named-entity></i> and <i><named-entity id="named-entity-309">cdc-48.2</named-entity></i> are knocked down via RNAi<bibr rid="b33"/>, and consistent with the conservation of the SHP box, we found that <named-entity id="named-entity-310">DVC-1</named-entity> interacted with <named-entity id="named-entity-311">p97</named-entity> as efficiently as human <named-entity id="named-entity-312">DVC1</named-entity> did (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7f</figr>). Finally, we observed prominent induction of RAD-51 foci in <named-entity id="named-entity-313">hydroxyurea</named-entity>-treated <i><named-entity id="named-entity-314">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> worms but not wild-type worms, indicating that loss of <named-entity id="named-entity-315">DVC-1</named-entity> function caused extensive DNA breakage when cells were challenged with replication stress&#x2013;inducing agents (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7g</figr>). These data demonstrate that the <i>C. elegans</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-316">DVC-1</named-entity> protein is required for embryonic survival and fertility after replication stress, indicating that the function of <named-entity id="named-entity-317">DVC1</named-entity> in protecting genome stability during DNA replication via <named-entity id="named-entity-318">p97</named-entity> is highly conserved during evolution.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Discussion</sectitle>
<p>The protein <named-entity id="named-entity-319">p97</named-entity> acts as a central mediator of ubiquitin-dependent cellular signaling processes throughout eukaryotic evolution<bibr rid="b16"/>. Many <named-entity id="named-entity-320">p97</named-entity> cofactors and adaptors have been identified<bibr rid="b16 b20"/>, yet our insight into how these target <named-entity id="named-entity-321">p97</named-entity> to particular cellular pathways and structures remains limited. Here we identify <named-entity id="named-entity-322">DVC1</named-entity>, as a new <named-entity id="named-entity-323">p97</named-entity> adaptor that selectively promotes its recruitment to blocked replication forks, where <named-entity id="named-entity-324">p97</named-entity> may effect ubiquitin-dependent processes elicited in response to replication problems. <named-entity id="named-entity-325">DVC1</named-entity> expression, unlike that of other known <named-entity id="named-entity-326">p97</named-entity> adaptors, is restricted to S and G2 phases of the cell cycle, consistent with a specific function of <named-entity id="named-entity-327">DVC1</named-entity> in promoting <named-entity id="named-entity-328">p97</named-entity>-dependent responses to challenged DNA replication. Whereas recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-329">DVC1</named-entity> to stalled replisomes requires both its PCNA-binding PIP box and C-terminal ubiquitin-binding UBZ motif, evidence suggests that unlike TLS polymerases, <named-entity id="named-entity-330">DVC1</named-entity> does not strictly require <named-entity id="named-entity-331">PCNA</named-entity> ubiquitylation for its accumulation at UV light&#x2013;induced nuclear foci. Because <named-entity id="named-entity-332">DVC1</named-entity> is associated with ubiquitylated forms of <named-entity id="named-entity-333">PCNA</named-entity> after replication blocks, at least under reversible cross-linking conditions, and given the strict dependency of <named-entity id="named-entity-334">DVC1</named-entity> foci on the integrity of its UBZ domain, the accumulation of <named-entity id="named-entity-335">DVC1</named-entity> at stalled replication forks may entail the recognition of a subset of ubiquitylated factors that includes but is not restricted to <named-entity id="named-entity-336">PCNA</named-entity>. Unlike the SHP and UBZ domains, the canonical PIP box is not conserved in <named-entity id="named-entity-337">DVC1</named-entity> orthologs in lower eukaryotes including <i>C. elegans</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-338">DVC-1</named-entity>, supporting the notion that <named-entity id="named-entity-339">DVC1</named-entity> recruitment to sites of replication stress can occur independently of <named-entity id="named-entity-340">PCNA</named-entity> ubiquitylation. The identity of the ubiquitylated factor(s) recognized by <named-entity id="named-entity-341">DVC1</named-entity> at blocked replication forks awaits determination.</p>
<p>Our findings are consistent with a model whereby <named-entity id="named-entity-342">DVC1</named-entity> specifically targets <named-entity id="named-entity-343">p97</named-entity> to stalled replisomes to facilitate ubiquitin- and <named-entity id="named-entity-344">p97</named-entity>-dependent responses to replication problems (<figr rid="f8">Fig. 8</figr>). Our data suggest that one function of <named-entity id="named-entity-345">DVC1</named-entity> is to promote <named-entity id="named-entity-346">p97</named-entity>-dependent displacement of <named-entity id="named-entity-347">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from <named-entity id="named-entity-348">PCNA</named-entity> at blocked replication forks. This may be an important mechanism for facilitating polymerase switching during TLS-mediated bypass of fork-blocking lesions and additionally may help to restrict the access of error-prone TLS polymerases to <named-entity id="named-entity-349">PCNA</named-entity>, which must be tightly regulated to prevent excessive mutagenesis. In agreement with this notion, depletion of <named-entity id="named-entity-350">DVC1</named-entity> enhanced UV light&#x2013;induced mutagenesis, likely owing to a reduced ability of cells to remove error-prone <named-entity id="named-entity-351">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from replication forks after lesion bypass. Whether <named-entity id="named-entity-352">DVC1</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-353">p97</named-entity> merely extracts <named-entity id="named-entity-354">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-355">PCNA</named-entity> or promotes its ubiquitin-dependent degradation remains to be resolved. Apart from the key role of <named-entity id="named-entity-356">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation in promoting TLS-mediated bypass of DNA damage, our insight into how polymerase exchanges are regulated during TLS remains limited. The notion that <named-entity id="named-entity-357">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation elicited in response to replication blocks remains elevated long after clearance of the damage and TLS polymerase foci<bibr rid="b34"/> suggests that mechanisms in addition to <named-entity id="named-entity-358">PCNA</named-entity> deubiquitylation may be actively engaged in promoting displacement of TLS polymerases from replisomes after lesion bypass. Our data indicate that the exchange of <named-entity id="named-entity-359">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> with a replicative polymerase may involve the ATPase activity of <named-entity id="named-entity-360">p97</named-entity> recruited to stalled replication forks via <named-entity id="named-entity-361">DVC1</named-entity>. Accordingly, TLS may join the growing number of ubiquitin-dependent responses to DNA damage that invoke <named-entity id="named-entity-362">p97</named-entity>-mediated processing of substrate proteins and complexes<bibr rid="b16"/>.</p>
<p>In addition to regulating the access of <named-entity id="named-entity-363">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-364">PCNA</named-entity>, it is possible that <named-entity id="named-entity-365">DVC1</named-entity> has a more general role in facilitating <named-entity id="named-entity-366">p97</named-entity>-mediated ubiquitin signaling events at stalled replication forks. In contrast, although <named-entity id="named-entity-367">p97</named-entity> has recently been shown to be important in mediating <named-entity id="named-entity-368">RNF8</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-369">RNF168</named-entity>-catalyzed ubiquitin-dependent responses to DSBs<bibr rid="b18 b19"/>, our data show that <named-entity id="named-entity-370">DVC1</named-entity> is not attracted to DSB sites, and it is dispensable for recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-371">p97</named-entity> and repair factors such as <named-entity id="named-entity-372">53BP1</named-entity> to these chromatin areas (A.M., S.B.-J. and N.M., unpublished observations). The function of <named-entity id="named-entity-373">DVC1</named-entity> in promoting cellular responses to replication blocks appears to be strongly conserved during evolution, as deletion of the <i>C. elegans</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-374">DVC-1</named-entity> also caused pronounced sensitivity to DNA replication blocks induced by UV light or <named-entity id="named-entity-375">hydroxyurea</named-entity>. Because the <named-entity id="named-entity-376">DVC1</named-entity> SHP box is conserved between worms and humans, we consider it likely that <named-entity id="named-entity-377">DVC-1</named-entity> also functions as an adaptor for CDC-48, the <i>C. elegans</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-378">p97</named-entity> ortholog. A recent study reported a function of <named-entity id="named-entity-379">DVC1</named-entity> in enhancing <named-entity id="named-entity-380">RAD18</named-entity>-dependent <named-entity id="named-entity-381">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation, and hence <named-entity id="named-entity-382">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> recruitment to blocked replication forks, in response to UV radiation<bibr rid="b22"/>. Our data contrast with these findings, as we found that <named-entity id="named-entity-383">DVC1</named-entity> is important in restraining, rather than promoting, the access of <named-entity id="named-entity-384">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> to ubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-385">PCNA</named-entity> via the ATPase activity of <named-entity id="named-entity-386">p97</named-entity>. Using several independent siRNAs, we could not reproduce an impact of <named-entity id="named-entity-387">DVC1</named-entity> depletion on <named-entity id="named-entity-388">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation and <named-entity id="named-entity-389">Rad18</named-entity> chromatin association (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6c</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2395-S1">Supplementary Fig. 6a,b</sir>); the reason for these discrepancies is unclear. <named-entity id="named-entity-390">Rad18</named-entity> was not among the many potential <named-entity id="named-entity-391">DVC1</named-entity>-interacting proteins identified in our unbiased mass spectrometry analysis, arguing against a primary function of <named-entity id="named-entity-392">DVC1</named-entity> in promoting recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-393">Rad18</named-entity> to sites of replication stress.</p>
<p>In addition to the UBZ, PIP and SHP motifs, <named-entity id="named-entity-394">DVC1</named-entity> also contains a conserved SprT domain, a putative metalloprotease domain whose function, as well as its importance in resolving replication problems, is unclear. The SprT domain in the <i>S. cerevisiae</i> protein <named-entity id="named-entity-395">wss1</named-entity> has been suggested to function as a promiscuous SUMO or ubiquitin protease with unusual substrate specificity<bibr rid="b35"/>. It is possible that <named-entity id="named-entity-396">DVC1</named-entity> could perform similar roles in the context of stalled replication forks, which are extensively regulated by ubiquitin- and SUMO-dependent signaling. However, we could not detect clear-cut ubiquitin or SUMO protease activity of the <named-entity id="named-entity-397">DVC1</named-entity> SprT domain, hence its biological role remains to be established.</p>
<p>In summary, our findings uncover <named-entity id="named-entity-398">DVC1</named-entity> as a specific DNA damage&#x2013;targeting adaptor for <named-entity id="named-entity-399">p97</named-entity>, providing important mechanistic insight into how <named-entity id="named-entity-400">p97</named-entity> is physically recruited to blocked replication forks. Additional studies of the biological functions of <named-entity id="named-entity-401">DVC1</named-entity> should yield a greater insight into the emerging importance of <named-entity id="named-entity-402">p97</named-entity> in promoting ubiquitin-dependent cellular responses to DNA damage.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Methods</sectitle>
<online-methods>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Plasmids and siRNA.</sectitle>
<p>The GFP-cDNA resource (<url>http://gfp-cdna.embl.de/</url>) for the initial screen for factors accumulating at microlaser-induced DNA damage was provided by J. Simpson and R. Pepperkok (European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany). Full-length human <i><named-entity id="named-entity-403">DVC1</named-entity></i> (<i><named-entity id="named-entity-404">SPRTN</named-entity></i>) cDNA was amplified by PCR and inserted into pAcGFP-C1 (Clontech) and pFlag-CMV2 (Sigma) to generate mammalian expression constructs for GFP- and <named-entity id="named-entity-405">Flag</named-entity>-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-406">DVC1</named-entity>, respectively. <i>C. elegans <named-entity id="named-entity-407">DVC-1</named-entity></i> cDNA was synthesized by Eurofins MWG and inserted into pEGFP-C1 (Clontech). A plasmid encoding GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-408">DVC1</named-entity>-ubiquitin chimera was generated by an in-frame insertion of a synthetically produced ubiquitin cDNA, encoding a protein lacking the C-terminal <named-entity id="named-entity-409">diglycine</named-entity> residues, between two EcoRI sites in the sequence encoding the <named-entity id="named-entity-410">DVC1</named-entity> C terminus and the multiple cloning site of pAcGFP-C1-<named-entity id="named-entity-411">DVC1</named-entity>. For expression of Strep-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-412">PCNA</named-entity>, sequence encoding <named-entity id="named-entity-413">PCNA</named-entity> (wild-type or K164R) was inserted into pcDNA4/TO (Invitrogen) containing sequence for an N-terminal streptavidin-hemagluttinin (Strep-HA) tag. For bacterial expression, <i><named-entity id="named-entity-414">DVC1</named-entity></i> was subcloned into pET29a (Novagen). A synthetic cDNA encoding N-terminally Strep-His<sub>10</sub>-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-415">PCNA</named-entity> (Eurofins MWG) was inserted into an untagged bacterial expression vector. Plasmids expressing Myc-Strep&#x2013;tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-416">p97</named-entity> wild-type and <named-entity id="named-entity-417">p97</named-entity>(E578Q) were a gift from K. Ramadan (University of Zurich). Plasmid expressing EGFP-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-418">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> was a gift from A. Lehmann (University of Sussex). Plasmids encoding <named-entity id="named-entity-419">Flag</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-420">Ufd1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-421">Flag</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-422">Npl4</named-entity> were gifts from S. Fang (University of Maryland) and G. Alexandru (University of Dundee), respectively. The <named-entity id="named-entity-423">DVC1</named-entity> PIP* (Y331A,F332A), UBZ* (C456G,C459G), SHP* (F253A,L260A) and SprT* (H111A), and <named-entity id="named-entity-424">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> UBZ* (D652A) point mutations were introduced using the QuikChange Site Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene). All constructs were verified by sequencing. Plasmid transfections were performed using FuGene 6 (Roche) according to the manufacturer's instructions. siRNA transfections were done with Lipofectamine RNAiMAX (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. siRNA target sequences used in this study were: Control (5&#x2032;-GGGAUACCUAGACGUUCUA-3&#x2032;), <named-entity id="named-entity-425">DVC1</named-entity>(#2) (5&#x2032;-ACGAUGAGGUGGAUGAGUA-3&#x2032;), <named-entity id="named-entity-426">DVC1</named-entity>(#7) (5&#x2032;-UCAAGUACCACCUGUAUUA-3&#x2032;), <named-entity id="named-entity-427">RAD18</named-entity> (5&#x2032;-ACUCAGUGUCCAACUUGCU-3&#x2032;), <named-entity id="named-entity-428">Ufd1</named-entity> (5&#x2032;-GUGGCCACCUACUCCAAAU-3&#x2032;), <named-entity id="named-entity-429">Npl4</named-entity> (5&#x2032;-CAGCCUCCUCCAACAAAUC-3&#x2032;) and <named-entity id="named-entity-430">Cdh1</named-entity> (5&#x2032;-UGAGAAGUCUCCCAGUCAG-3&#x2032;).</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Cell culture, flow cytometry, and clonogenic survival and <i>supF</i> mutagenesis assays.</sectitle>
<p>Human U2OS, HeLa and HEK293T cells were cultured in DMEM containing 10% FBS. To generate cell lines stably expressing GFP-tagged wild-type and mutant <named-entity id="named-entity-431">DVC1</named-entity> or GFP&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-432">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, U2OS cells were co-transfected with GFP constructs and pBabe-Puro plasmid, and positive clones were selected with <named-entity id="named-entity-433">puromycin</named-entity> as described<bibr rid="b36 b37"/>. Cell lines stably expressing Strep-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-434">PCNA</named-entity> wild-type or K164R mutant were obtained by selecting U2OS cells transfected with pcDNA4/TO-Strep-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-435">PCNA</named-entity> plasmids in medium containing zeocin (Invitrogen). Cells were exposed to the following doses of genotoxic agents and collected at the indicated times, unless otherwise stated: UV light (20 J/m<super>2</super>, 6 h), <named-entity id="named-entity-436">hydroxyurea</named-entity> (2 mM, 24 h), ionizing radiation (5 Gy, 1 h), <named-entity id="named-entity-437">mitomycin C</named-entity> (15 &#x3BC;M, 24 h) and cisplatin (30 &#x3BC;M pulse for 6 h). <named-entity id="named-entity-438">Nocodazole</named-entity> block and release were done as described<bibr rid="b38"/>. Cell-cycle profiles were determined by flow cytometric analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-439">propidium iodide</named-entity>&#x2013;stained cells using a FACSCalibur flow cytometer (BD Biosciences). For <named-entity id="named-entity-440">BrdU</named-entity> incorporation experiments, cells were pulse-labeled for 15 min with <named-entity id="named-entity-441">BrdU</named-entity> (10 &#x3BC;M) immediately before harvest, fixed in <named-entity id="named-entity-442">HCl</named-entity> and stained with BrdU antibody (GE Healthcare). Clonogenic survival assays and <i>supF</i> mutation frequency assays were done as described<bibr rid="b39 b40"/>. The pSP189 plasmid and MBM7070 strain were gifts from M. Seidman.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Immunochemical methods.</sectitle>
<p>Immunoblotting, immunoprecipitation and Strep-Tactin pull-downs were done as described<bibr rid="b41 b42"/>. GFP immunoprecipitation was performed with GFP-Trap agarose beads (Chromotek). To obtain chromatin-enriched fractions, cells were lysed in low-salt buffer (10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-443">HEPES</named-entity>, pH 7.5; 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-444">KCl</named-entity>; and 0.05% NP-40), and chromatin-associated proteins were released from the pellet by treatment with micrococcal nuclease. For reversible protein cross-linking, cells were lysed in low-salt buffer containing 2.5 mg/ml <named-entity id="named-entity-445">dithiobis succinimidyl propionate</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-446">DSP</named-entity>; Pierce) and incubated 30 min on ice. Excess <named-entity id="named-entity-447">DSP</named-entity> was quenched by addition of 1 M <named-entity id="named-entity-448">Tris</named-entity>. Antibodies used in this study included: rabbit polyclonal antibodies to <named-entity id="named-entity-449">DVC1</named-entity> (HPA025073, Human Protein Atlas), <named-entity id="named-entity-450">RAD18</named-entity> (ab57447, Abcam), RAD51 (29480002, Novus Biologicals), <named-entity id="named-entity-451">cyclin A</named-entity> (sc-751, Santa Cruz), &#x3B3;-<named-entity id="named-entity-452">H2AX</named-entity> (05-636, Millipore) and pH3(S10) (06-570, Millipore); mouse monoclonal antibodies to <named-entity id="named-entity-453">p97</named-entity> (ab11433, Abcam), <named-entity id="named-entity-454">RPA</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-455">p34</named-entity>; Mob 329-05, Diagnostic Biosystems), <named-entity id="named-entity-456">Flag</named-entity> (F1804, Sigma), ubiquitin (sc-8017, Santa Cruz), HA (sc-7392, Santa Cruz), Myc (sc-40, Santa Cruz), GFP (sc-9996, Santa Cruz), <named-entity id="named-entity-457">Ufd1</named-entity> (611642, BD Transduction Labs), Cyclin B (610220, BD Transduction Labs) and His<sub>6</sub> (631212, Clontech); mouse polyclonal to <named-entity id="named-entity-458">Npl4</named-entity> (ab68020, Abcam), and goat polyclonal antibodies to <named-entity id="named-entity-459">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> (AF3417, R&amp;D Systems) and <named-entity id="named-entity-460">MCM6</named-entity> (sc-9843, Santa Cruz).</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Immunofluorescence staining, microscopy and laser microirradiation.</sectitle>
<p>Cells were fixed in 4% <named-entity id="named-entity-461">formaldehyde</named-entity>, permeabilized with PBS containing 0.2% Triton X-100 for 5 min and incubated with primary antibodies diluted in DMEM for 1 h at room temperature. After staining with secondary antibodies (Alexa Fluor 488 and Alexa Fluor 568; Life Technologies) for 30 min, cover slips were mounted in Vectashield mounting medium (Vector Laboratories) containing the nuclear stain <named-entity id="named-entity-462">DAPI</named-entity>. Where indicated, cells were pre-extracted for 5 min with ice-cold CSK buffer (1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-463">PIPES</named-entity>, pH 6.8; 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-464">NaCl</named-entity>; 1.5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-465">MgCl<sub>2</sub></named-entity>; and 300 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-466">sucrose</named-entity>) supplemented with 0.5% Triton X-100 before fixation. Staining of <i>C. elegans</i> gonads was done as described<bibr rid="b43"/>. Images were acquired with an LSM 710 confocal microscope (Carl Zeiss Microimaging) mounted on Zeiss Axiovert 100M equipped with Plan-Apochromat &#xD7;40, 1.3 numerical aperture (NA) oil-immersion objective, using standard settings. Image acquisition and analysis was carried out with ZEN2010 software. Laser microirradiation to generate local DNA damage was done as described<bibr rid="b21"/>. For data quantification, at least 100 cells were counted in all experiments.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><i>In vitro</i> binding experiments.</sectitle>
<p>To obtain purified recombinant <named-entity id="named-entity-467">DVC1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-468">PCNA</named-entity>, Rosetta 2(DE3)pLysS competent bacteria (Novagen) were induced to express the proteins for 3 h at 18 &#xB0;C and lysed with Bugbuster (Novagen). Proteins were purified by Ni-NTA affinity chromatography followed by S-protein agarose (for S-<named-entity id="named-entity-469">DVC1</named-entity>-His<sub>6</sub>) or Strep-Tactin sepharose (for Strep-His<sub>10</sub>-<named-entity id="named-entity-470">PCNA</named-entity>). To analyze <i>in vitro</i> binding of <named-entity id="named-entity-471">DVC1</named-entity> to ubiquitin, purified recombinant wild-type or mutant forms of S-<named-entity id="named-entity-472">DVC1</named-entity>-His<sub>6</sub> were bound to S-protein agarose (Novagen) and incubated with free ubiquitin or ubiquitin chains (3&#x2013;7 linkages) (Boston Biochem) for 2 h at 4 &#xB0;C. Bound complexes were washed extensively in EBC buffer (50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-473">Tris</named-entity>, pH 7.5; 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-474">NaCl</named-entity>; 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-475">EDTA</named-entity>; 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-476">DTT</named-entity>; and 0.5% NP-40), and immobilized material was resolved by SDS-PAGE and analyzed by immunoblotting. Alternatively, <named-entity id="named-entity-477">DVC1</named-entity> binding to ubiquitin was analyzed by incubating total extracts of human cells expressing GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-478">DVC1</named-entity> constructs with ubiquitin immobilized on agarose beads (Enzo Life Sciences) for 1 h. To analyze <i>in vitro</i> binding between <named-entity id="named-entity-479">DVC1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-480">PCNA</named-entity>, purified recombinant Strep-His<sub>10</sub>-<named-entity id="named-entity-481">PCNA</named-entity> immobilized on Strep-Tactin sepharose (IBA BioTAGnology) was incubated with whole cell extracts of <i>E. coli</i> expressing wild-type or mutant S-<named-entity id="named-entity-482">DVC1</named-entity>-His<sub>6</sub> proteins for 1 h at 4 &#xB0;C. Bound complexes were washed extensively in EBC buffer.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Mass spectrometry-based analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-483">DVC1</named-entity>-interacting proteins.</sectitle>
<p>For SILAC, U2OS cells were cultured in medium containing either <named-entity id="named-entity-484"><sc>L</sc>-arginine</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-485"><sc>L</sc> -lysine</named-entity> or <sc>L</sc>-arginine-U-<super>13</super>C<sub>6</sub>-<super>15</super>N<sub>4</sub> and <sc>L</sc>-lysine-U-<super>13</super>C<sub>6</sub>-<super>15</super>N<sub>2</sub> (Cambridge Isotope Laboratories) as described previously<bibr rid="b32"/>. Cells were transfected with GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-486">DVC1</named-entity> or empty vector and lysed in modified RIPA buffer (50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-487">Tris</named-entity>, pH 7.5; 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-488">NaCl</named-entity>; 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-489">EDTA</named-entity>; 1% NP-40; and 0.1% <named-entity id="named-entity-490">sodium deoxycholate</named-entity>) supplemented with protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche) 48 h later, and GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-491">DVC1</named-entity> and its interacting proteins were enriched using GFP-Trap resin (Chromotek). Proteins were resolved by SDS-PAGE and in-gel digested with trypsin. Peptide fractions were analyzed on a quadrupole Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Q-Exactive, Thermo Scientific) equipped with a nanoflow HPLC system (Thermo Scientific) as described<bibr rid="b44"/>. Raw data files were analyzed using MaxQuant software (version 1.2.2.9) as described<bibr rid="b45"/>. <i>Z</i> scores were calculated based on the standard deviation estimated separately for ratios bigger and smaller than 1 as previously described<bibr rid="b45"/>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><i>C. elegans</i> strains, DNA construction and injection, and RNAi.</sectitle>
<p>Strains were cultured under standard conditions with <i>E. coli</i> OP50 at 20 &#xB0;C (ref. <bibrinl rid="b46">46</bibrinl>). We used the following worm strains: N2 Bristol (wild-type), RJP566 <i><named-entity id="named-entity-492">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> V (outcrossed 4&#xD7; to N2) and RJP625 <i><named-entity id="named-entity-493">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> V<i>; rpEx291(<named-entity id="named-entity-494">dvc-1</named-entity></i><b><i>&#x2237;</i></b><i>GFP + pmyo-2</i><b><i>&#x2237;</i></b><i>RFP)</i>.</p>
<p>The <named-entity id="named-entity-495">DVC-1</named-entity>&#x2013;GFP translational fusion was constructed by PCR amplifying the <i><named-entity id="named-entity-496">dvc-1</named-entity></i> promoter and genomic DNA (minus stop codon) with oRJP167 (5&#x2032;-aaaatctagatctgaaatagcttcagtgagatgag-3&#x2032;) and oRJP168 (5&#x2032;-ttttcccggggcccgagacagtaatccagatgtcc-3&#x2032;) and cloning in-frame into the pPD95.75 expression vector. The resultant construct was microinjected into <i><named-entity id="named-entity-497">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> worms at 0.1 ng/&#x3BC;l as a complex array with the co-transformation marker <i>myo-2</i><b><i>&#x2237;</i></b><i>RFP</i> at 2 ng/&#x3BC;l and PvuI-digested bacterial DNA at 120 ng/&#x3BC;l. RNAi was performed using the feeding method<bibr rid="b47"/>. Larvae were placed on <named-entity id="named-entity-498">IPTG</named-entity>-containing plates seeded with <i>Escherichia coli</i> ((HT115(DE3)) expressing <i><named-entity id="named-entity-499">dvc-1</named-entity></i> dsRNA or the vector-only control (L4440).</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Brood size assay and UV-light and hydroxyurea sensitivity assays.</sectitle>
<p>Brood sizes were assayed by picking individual L4 hermaphrodites onto fresh plates and transferring them onto fresh plates every 24 h to prevent overcrowding until egg-laying ceased. The progeny produced on each plate was counted 24 h after removal of the parent. For UV-light sensitivity measurements, staged young adults (24 h after L4) were irradiated with 120 J/m<super>2</super> of UV-C light, placed on individual plates 2 h after treatment and then left to lay eggs for 24 h. The progeny produced on each plate was counted 24 h after removal of the parent. To measure <named-entity id="named-entity-500">hydroxyurea</named-entity> sensitivity, staged L1 worms were picked to plates containing 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-501">hydroxyurea</named-entity>. Forty-eight hours after the L4 stage, worms were scored for sterility as assessed by the presence (nonsterile) or absence (sterile) of eggs in the gonad.</p>
</sec>
</online-methods>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Author contributions</sectitle>
<p>A.M., I.G.-S., K.K. and T.T. performed most of the experiments, supported by L.P., S.V.N., S.B.-J. and G.S. S.S. provided stable U2OS GFP&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-502">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> cells. P.B. and C.C. carried out MS experiments and analyzed data from MS experiments. C.L. and J.L. provided essential information and support for initiation of the project. S.B.-J. and N.M. supervised the project and analyzed data, with participation by R.H.-P. and R.P.; N.M. wrote the paper.</p></sec>
</bdy>
<bm>
<objects>
<fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
<figtl>Recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-503">DVC1</named-entity> to blocked replication forks.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Schematic of human <named-entity id="named-entity-504">DVC1</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-505">C1orf124</named-entity>), showing known conserved domains (numbers indicate residue positions). (<b>b</b>) Immunofluorescence analysis of &#x3B3;-<named-entity id="named-entity-506">H2AX</named-entity> in <i>YFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-507">DVC1</named-entity></i> plasmid&#x2013;transfected U2OS cells subjected to microlaser irradiation 1 h before fixation. (<b>c</b>) Fluorescence micrographs of U2OS cells stably expressing GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-508">DVC1</named-entity> and treated with indicated genotoxic agents. <named-entity id="named-entity-509">HU</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-510">hydroxyurea</named-entity>; IR, ionizing radiation. (<b>d</b>) Immunofluorescence of endogenous <named-entity id="named-entity-511">DVC1</named-entity> in mock-treated or UV light&#x2013;treated U2OS cells. (<b>e</b>) Quantification of GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-512">DVC1</named-entity> foci in cells treated as in <b>c</b> (mean and range of two experiments is shown). (<b>f</b>) Immunofluorescence of U2OS cells stably expressing One-STrEP&#x2013;hemaglutinin&#x2013;tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-513">PCNA</named-entity> (S-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-514">PCNA</named-entity>) transfected with <i>GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-515">DVC1</named-entity></i> plasmid and exposed to UV light before staining with anti-HA antibody. (<b>g</b>) Immunofluorescence of U2OS cells transfected with <i>GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-516">DVC1</named-entity></i> plasmid and exposed to UV light where indicated. Cells were pre-extracted or not with Triton X-100 and immunostained with <named-entity id="named-entity-517">RPA32</named-entity> antibody. All scale bars, 10 &#x3BC;m.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
<figtl>Cell cycle&#x2013;dependent regulation of <named-entity id="named-entity-518">DVC1</named-entity> by APC&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-519">Cdh1</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Immunofluorescence analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-520">DVC1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-521">cyclin B1</named-entity> expression in U2OS cells. Scale bar, 10 &#x3BC;m. (<b>b</b>) Immunoblots of HeLa cells growing exponentially (Exp) or collected at indicated times after <named-entity id="named-entity-522">nocodazole</named-entity> 'shake-off'. Whole-cell extracts (WCE) were probed with antibodies to indicated proteins. (<b>c</b>) Immunoblot analysis of WCEs from U2OS cells transfected with indicated plasmids probed with either GFP or Myc antibodies. (<b>d</b>) Immunoblot analysis using indicated antibodies of WCEs from U2OS cells 72 h after transfection with control (&#x2212;) or <i><named-entity id="named-entity-523">CDH1</named-entity></i> (+) siRNAs.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
<figtl>Ubiquitin-regulated recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-524">DVC1</named-entity> to stalled replisomes.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Schematics of <named-entity id="named-entity-525">DVC1</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-526">DVC1</named-entity>-ubiquitin fusion constructs used in this figure. Ub*, ubiquitin I44A. WT, wild type. (<b>b</b>) Immunoblot (IB) with ubiquitin (Ub) and His<sub>6</sub> antibodies of recombinant S-tag (S)-<named-entity id="named-entity-527">DVC1</named-entity>-His<sub>6</sub> with wild-type UBZ domain (WT) or with UBZ* bound to S-protein agarose incubated with purified free ubiquitin or Lys63-linked ubiquitin chains. (<b>c</b>) Same as in <b>b</b>, except that S-<named-entity id="named-entity-528">DVC1</named-entity>-His<sub>6</sub> was incubated with Lys48-linked ubiquitin chains. (<b>d</b>) Fluorescence micrograph of U2OS cells stably expressing GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-529">DVC1</named-entity> with wild-type UBZ (WT) or with *UBZ exposed to UV light. (<b>e</b>) Pull-down with ubiquitin agarose of HEK293T cells left untreated (&#x2013;) or transfected with indicated GFP-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-530">DVC1</named-entity> constructs and immunoblotting with GFP and GAPDH antibodies. WCE, whole-cell extract. The 'Ub' superscripts denote monoubiquitylated forms of the indicated proteins. (<b>f</b>) Analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-531">DVC1</named-entity> monoubiquitylation using extracts of U2OS cells transfected with plasmids encoding indicated constructs subjected to Strep-Tactin pulldown under denaturing conditions. Immunoblots were probed with anti-GFP antibody. (<b>g</b>) Fluorescence micrographs of U2OS cells transfected with plasmids encoding indicated GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-532">DVC1</named-entity> constructs and exposed to UV light. WT, full-length GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-533">DVC1</named-entity>. Scale bars, 10 &#x3BC;m.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-534">DVC1</named-entity> recruitment to stalled replication forks requires <named-entity id="named-entity-535">PCNA</named-entity> binding but not <named-entity id="named-entity-536">PCNA</named-entity> ubiquitylation.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Schematic of human <named-entity id="named-entity-537">DVC1</named-entity> with amino acids matching the PIP-box consensus motif in red. Residues mutated to generate the PIP* (PIP(Y331A,F332A)) are underlined. (<b>b</b>) <named-entity id="named-entity-538">DVC1</named-entity> binding to <named-entity id="named-entity-539">PCNA</named-entity> <i>in vitro</i> was analyzed by incubating purified Strep-<named-entity id="named-entity-540">PCNA</named-entity> bound to Strep-Tactin sepharose with whole cell lysates from <i>Escherichia coli</i> expressing indicated forms of recombinant (S)-<named-entity id="named-entity-541">DVC1</named-entity>-His<sub>6</sub>. Bound complexes were immunoblotted with anti-His<sub>6</sub> antibody (top) or probed with Ponceau S stain (bottom). (<b>c</b>) Chromatin-enriched fractions of U2OS cells expressing strep-hemagluttinin-<named-entity id="named-entity-542">PCNA</named-entity> (Strep-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-543">PCNA</named-entity>) transfected with plasmids encoding indicated proteins and exposed or not to UV light before lysis in the presence of reversible cross-linker were subjected to GFP immunoprecipitation (IP) followed by immunoblotting with HA and GFP antibodies. <named-entity id="named-entity-544">PCNA</named-entity><super>Ub(1)</super> indicates monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-545">PCNA</named-entity>. (<b>d</b>) Fluorescence micrographs of U2OS cells stably expressing GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-546">DVC1</named-entity> wild-type (WT) or PIP* cell lines exposed to UV light. (<b>e</b>) Fluorescence microscopy of U2OS cells transfected with siRNA to <i><named-entity id="named-entity-547">RAD18</named-entity></i> (the E3 ligase for <named-entity id="named-entity-548">PCNA</named-entity> monoubiquitylation) or nontargeting (control) siRNA, and subsequently transfected with plasmids encoding GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-549">DVC1</named-entity> or GFP&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-550">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> before exposure to UV light as indicated. (<b>f</b>) Immunofluorescence of fixed U2OS cells expressing Strep-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-551">PCNA</named-entity> WT or K164R mutant and transfected with GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-552">DVC1</named-entity> (top) or GFP&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-553">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> (bottom) plasmid before exposure to UV light and subsequent staining with anti-HA antibody. (<b>g</b>) Same as in <b>c</b>, except that cells were transfected with indicated siRNAs before transfection with plasmids encoding GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-554">DVC1</named-entity> or GFP&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-555">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>. (<b>h</b>) Immunoblot analysis of chromatin-enriched fractions of U2OS cells expressing Strep-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-556">PCNA</named-entity> transfected with indicated plasmids and exposed to UV light. All scale bars, 10 &#x3BC;m.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f5" type="bmp" entname="figf5">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-557">DVC1</named-entity> is a <named-entity id="named-entity-558">p97</named-entity> adaptor that promotes its recruitment to sites of replication stress.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) <i>Z</i>-score plot of MS-based analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-559">DVC1</named-entity>-interacting proteins. U2OS cells grown in light or heavy isotope&#x2013;containing SILAC media were transfected with plasmid encoding GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-560">DVC1</named-entity> or empty vector. Forward (heavy, GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-561">DVC1</named-entity>; light, GFP) and reverse (heavy, GFP; light, GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-562">DVC1</named-entity>) experiments were performed to minimize false positives. GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-563">DVC1</named-entity> and associated proteins enriched using GFP-Trap resin were analyzed by MS. Proteins with a <i>Z</i> score above 1.5 in both replicates are highlighted. (<b>b</b>) Immunoprecipitation (IP) analysis of U2OS cells transfected with empty vector (&#x2212;) or indicated GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-564">DVC1</named-entity> constructs and subjected to GFP immunoprecipitation followed by immunoblotting with anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-565">p97</named-entity> and anti-GFP antibodies. (<b>c</b>) Schematic showing amino acids of a conserved SHP box in <named-entity id="named-entity-566">DVC1</named-entity> matching the sequence of other SHP boxes in red. Residues mutated to generate SHP* are underlined. (<b>d</b>) Fluorescence micrographs of U2OS cells stably expressing GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-567">DVC1</named-entity> wild-type (WT) or SHP* exposed to UV light. (<b>e</b>) Immunofluorescence of UV light&#x2013;treated U2OS cells transfected with indicated plasmids and pre-extracted or not before staining with anti-Myc antibody. (<b>f</b>) Same as in <b>e</b>, except that cells were transfected with GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-568">DVC1</named-entity> constructs only and stained with anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-569">p97</named-entity> antibody. (<b>g</b>) Quantification of the experiment in <b>f</b>, with mean &#xB1; s.d. of three experiments. All scale bars, 10 &#x3BC;m.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f6" type="bmp" entname="figf6">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-570">DVC1</named-entity> promotes bypass of DNA damage and cell survival by facilitating <named-entity id="named-entity-571">p97</named-entity>-dependent displacement of DNA <named-entity id="named-entity-572">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-573">PCNA</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Fluorescence micrographs of U2OS cells stably expressing EGFP-tagged <named-entity id="named-entity-574">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> (GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-575">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>) and transfected with siRNAs and fixed at indicated times after exposure to UV light. Representative images are shown. Scale bar, 10 &#x3BC;m. (<b>b</b>) Quantification of data in <b>a</b>. Mean values and range of two independent experiments are shown. (<b>c</b>) Immunoprecipitation (IP) analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-576">PCNA</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-577">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> interaction. U2OS cells expressing Strep-HA-<named-entity id="named-entity-578">PCNA</named-entity> transfected with plasmids encoding GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-579">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> and treated as in <b>a</b> were lysed in the presence of reversible cross-linker and fractionated. Chromatin-enriched fractions were subjected to GFP immunoprecipitation and immunoblotted with anti-HA and anti-GFP antibodies. (<b>d</b>) Same as in <b>c</b>, except that cells were transfected with plasmids encoding indicated proteins instead of siRNAs. (<b>e</b>) Immunofluorescence analysis of pre-extracted U2OS cells transfected with plasmids encoding <named-entity id="named-entity-580">Flag</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-581">DVC1</named-entity>, GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-582">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity>, and <named-entity id="named-entity-583">p97</named-entity>-Myc wild-type (WT) or <named-entity id="named-entity-584">p97</named-entity>(E578Q)-Myc (EQ) and exposed to UV light. Cells were stained with Myc antibody. Mean and range of two experiments are shown. (<b>f</b>) Same as in <b>e</b>, except that cells containing <named-entity id="named-entity-585">p97</named-entity>-Myc foci were scored for formation of GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-586">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> foci. (<b>g</b>) <i>supF</i> mutation frequency analysis of siRNA-treated cells transfected with intact or UV light&#x2013;damaged <i>supF</i> plasmid. Results depict the mean (&#xB1; s.d.) of three experiments. (<b>h</b>) Clonogenic survival of siRNA-transfected U2OS cells treated with indicated doses of cisplatin (left) or ionizing radiation (right). Error bars, &#xB1; s.d. (<i>n</i> = 3). Data are from a representative of three experiments.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f7" type="bmp" entname="figf7">
<figtl>Loss of <i><named-entity id="named-entity-587">dvc-1</named-entity></i> results in replication stress sensitivity in <i>C. elegans</i>.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Domain structures of human <named-entity id="named-entity-588">DVC1</named-entity> (top) and <i>C. elegans</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-589">DVC-1</named-entity> (middle). Structure of <i><named-entity id="named-entity-590">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> deletion allele (bottom), probably a null allele (red bar represents the <i>ok260</i> deletion). The region used to drive GFP expression is shown in green. (<b>b</b>) Fluorescence micrographs of <i><named-entity id="named-entity-591">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> embryos expressing <named-entity id="named-entity-592">DVC-1</named-entity>&#x2013;GFP and exposed to UV light or not (120 J m<super>&#x2212;2</super>). (<b>c</b>) Brood sizes of hermaphrodites of strain <i><named-entity id="named-entity-593">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> or wild-type (N2) with RNAi-mediated knockdown of <i><named-entity id="named-entity-594">dvc-1</named-entity></i> (<i><named-entity id="named-entity-595">dvc-1</named-entity></i> RNAi) compared to control worms. <i>n</i> = 19&#x2013;20 (N2 versus <i>ok260</i>) and 8&#x2013;9 (control RNAi versus <i><named-entity id="named-entity-596">dvc-1</named-entity></i> RNAi). (<b>d</b>) Analysis of embryonic lethality of N2 and <i><named-entity id="named-entity-597">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i> 24 h after exposure of gonads of young adults to UV light (120 J m<super>&#x2212;2</super>). (<b>e</b>) <named-entity id="named-entity-598">Hydroxyurea</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-599">HU</named-entity>) sensitivity of N2 and <i><named-entity id="named-entity-600">dvc-1</named-entity>(ok260)</i>. L1 larvae were exposed to 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-601">HU</named-entity> and assayed for sterility 48 h after the L4 stage. All brood size and sensitivity experiments were performed in triplicate. ***<i>P</i> &lt; 0.0001, **<i>P</i> &lt; 0.05 (Mann-Whitney test). (<b>f</b>) Binding of GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-602">DVC1</named-entity> or GFP-CeDVC-1 to <named-entity id="named-entity-603">p97</named-entity> was analyzed by immunoblotting GFP immunoprecipitates of U2OS cells transfected with indicated plasmids with <named-entity id="named-entity-604">p97</named-entity> antibody. The <named-entity id="named-entity-605">DVC1</named-entity> SHP box (SHP box consensus residues in red) is fully conserved in <named-entity id="named-entity-606">DVC-1</named-entity> (top). (<b>g</b>) Immunofluorescence analysis of RAD-51 foci in dissected gonads from staged worms (48 h after the L4 stage) treated as in <b>e</b>. At least three gonads were analyzed in detail for each strain and condition. All scale bars, 10 &#x3BC;m.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f8" type="bmp" entname="figf8">
<figtl>Model of <named-entity id="named-entity-607">DVC1</named-entity> function in cellular responses to replication blocks.</figtl>
<caption><p>A combination of <named-entity id="named-entity-608">p97</named-entity>-, <named-entity id="named-entity-609">PCNA</named-entity>- and ubiquitin (Ub)-binding modules enables <named-entity id="named-entity-610">DVC1</named-entity> to function as a DNA damage&#x2013;targeting <named-entity id="named-entity-611">p97</named-entity> adaptor that specifically recruits it to ubiquitylated factors and <named-entity id="named-entity-612">PCNA</named-entity> at blocked replication forks, facilitating <named-entity id="named-entity-613">p97</named-entity>-dependent processing of client proteins associated with these structures. By means of its ATPase activity, <named-entity id="named-entity-614">p97</named-entity> may catalyze removal of <named-entity id="named-entity-615">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> from monoubiquitylated <named-entity id="named-entity-616">PCNA</named-entity>, restraining the access of <named-entity id="named-entity-617">Pol &#x3B7;</named-entity> to the replication machinery and promoting polymerase switching during TLS-mediated bypass of DNA damage.</p></caption></fig>
</objects>
<ack><p>We thank K. Ramadan (University of Zurich), A. Lehmann (University of Sussex), R. Pepperkok and J. Simpson (European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg), G. Alexandru (University of Dundee, UK), S. Fang (University of Maryland), M. Seidman (US National Institute on Aging), and members of the <i>Caenorhabditis</i> Genetics Center for providing reagents and worm strains, C. Doil and P. Menard for help with the initial screen for factors accumulating at laser-induced DNA damage, and J. Rouse and I. Dikic for communicating results before publication. This work was supported by grants from the Novo Nordisk Foundation, Danish Medical Research Council, the Danish Cancer Society, the Lundbeck Foundation, the Danish National Research Foundation and the European Research Council (Starting grant to R.P.).</p></ack>
<audecl conflct="no"/>
<bibl><bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hoeijmakers</snm>, <fnm>J.H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Genome maintenance mechanisms for preventing cancer</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>411</vid>, <ppf>366</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>374</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jackson</snm>, <fnm>S.P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bartek</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The DNA-damage response in human biology and disease</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>461</vid>, <ppf>1071</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1078</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ciccia</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Elledge</snm>, <fnm>S.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The DNA damage response: making it safe to play with knives</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>179</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>204</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Loeb</snm>, <fnm>L.A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Monnat</snm>, <fnm>R.J.</fnm> <suff>Jr.</suff></refau> <atl>DNA polymerases and human disease</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Genet.</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>594</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>604</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Branzei</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Foiani</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Maintaining genome stability at the replication fork</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>208</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>219</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Budzowska</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kanaar</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Mechanisms of dealing with DNA damage-induced replication problems</atl>. <jtl>Cell Biochem. Biophys.</jtl> <vid>53</vid>, <ppf>17</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>31</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Friedberg</snm>, <fnm>E.C.</fnm></refau> <atl>Suffering in silence: the tolerance of DNA damage</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>943</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>953</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sale</snm>, <fnm>J.E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lehmann</snm>, <fnm>A.R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Woodgate</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Y-family DNA polymerases and their role in tolerance of cellular DNA damage</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>141</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>152</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bergink</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jentsch</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Principles of ubiquitin and SUMO modifications in DNA repair</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>458</vid>, <ppf>461</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>467</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ulrich</snm>, <fnm>H.D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Walden</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Ubiquitin signalling in DNA replication and repair</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>479</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>489</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lehmann</snm>, <fnm>A.R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Translesion synthesis: Y-family polymerases and the polymerase switch</atl>. <jtl>DNA Repair (Amst.)</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>891</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>899</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bienko</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Ubiquitin-binding domains in Y-family polymerases regulate translesion synthesis</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>310</vid>, <ppf>1821</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1824</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bienko</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Regulation of translesion synthesis DNA polymerase eta by monoubiquitination</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>37</vid>, <ppf>396</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>407</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Huang</snm>, <fnm>T.T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Regulation of monoubiquitinated PCNA by DUB autocleavage</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>339</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>347</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Al-Hakim</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The ubiquitous role of ubiquitin in the DNA damage response</atl>. <jtl>DNA Repair (Amst.)</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>1229</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1240</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Meyer</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bug</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bremer</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Emerging functions of the VCP/p97 AAA-ATPase in the ubiquitin system</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>14</vid>, <ppf>117</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>123</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Raman</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Havens</snm>, <fnm>C.G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Walter</snm>, <fnm>J.C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Harper</snm>, <fnm>J.W.</fnm></refau> <atl>A genome-wide screen identifies p97 as an essential regulator of DNA damage-dependent CDT1 destruction</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>72</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>84</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Acs</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The AAA-ATPase VCP/p97 promotes 53BP1 recruitment by removing L3MBTL1 from DNA double-strand breaks</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>1345</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1350</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Meerang</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The ubiquitin-selective segregase VCP/p97 orchestrates the response to DNA double-strand breaks</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>1376</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1382</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yeung</snm>, <fnm>H.O.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Insights into adaptor binding to the AAA protein p97</atl>. <jtl>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</jtl> <vid>36</vid>, <ppf>62</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>67</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Falck</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bartkova</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bartek</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Distinct spatiotemporal dynamics of mammalian checkpoint regulators induced by DNA damage</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>255</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>260</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Centore</snm>, <fnm>R.C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yazinski</snm>, <fnm>S.A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tse</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zou</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Spartan/C1orf124, a reader of PCNA ubiquitylation and a regulator of UV-induced DNA damage response</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>46</vid>, <ppf>625</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>635</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kannouche</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Domain structure, localization, and function of DNA polymerase eta, defective in xeroderma pigmentosum variant cells</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>158</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>172</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Byun</snm>, <fnm>T.S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pacek</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yee</snm>, <fnm>M.C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Walter</snm>, <fnm>J.C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cimprich</snm>, <fnm>K.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Functional uncoupling of MCM helicase and DNA polymerase activities activates the ATR-dependent checkpoint</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>1040</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1052</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Peters</snm>, <fnm>J.M.</fnm></refau> <atl>The anaphase promoting complex/cyclosome: a machine designed to destroy</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>644</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>656</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sorensen</snm>, <fnm>C.S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Nonperiodic activity of the human anaphase-promoting complex-Cdh1 ubiquitin ligase results in continuous DNA synthesis uncoupled from mitosis</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>7613</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>7623</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hofmann</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Ubiquitin-binding domains and their role in the DNA damage response</atl>. <jtl>DNA Repair (Amst.)</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>544</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>556</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bomar</snm>, <fnm>M.G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pai</snm>, <fnm>M.T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tzeng</snm>, <fnm>S.R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>S.S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zhou</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structure of the ubiquitin-binding zinc finger domain of human DNA Y-polymerase eta</atl>. <jtl>EMBO Rep.</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>247</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>251</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Moldovan</snm>, <fnm>G.L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pfander</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jentsch</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>PCNA, the maestro of the replication fork</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>129</vid>, <ppf>665</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>679</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Havens</snm>, <fnm>C.G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Walter</snm>, <fnm>J.C.</fnm></refau> <atl>Mechanism of CRL4(Cdt2), a PCNA-dependent E3 ubiquitin ligase</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>25</vid>, <ppf>1568</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1582</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b31"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bekker-Jensen</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mailand</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl>Assembly and function of DNA double-strand break repair foci in mammalian cells</atl>. <jtl>DNA Repair (Amst.)</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>1219</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1228</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b32"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ong</snm>, <fnm>S.E.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Stable isotope labeling by amino acids in cell culture, SILAC, as a simple and accurate approach to expression proteomics</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell Proteomics</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>376</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>386</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b33"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mouysset</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Cell cycle progression requires the CDC-48UFD-1/NPL-4 complex for efficient DNA replication</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>105</vid>, <ppf>12879</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>12884</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b34"><reftxt><refau><snm>Niimi</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Regulation of proliferating cell nuclear antigen ubiquitination in mammalian cells</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>105</vid>, <ppf>16125</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>16130</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b35"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mullen</snm>, <fnm>J.R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>C.F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Brill</snm>, <fnm>S.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Wss1 is a SUMO-dependent isopeptidase that interacts genetically with the Slx5-Slx8 SUMO-targeted ubiquitin ligase</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>30</vid>, <ppf>3737</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3748</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b36"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bekker-Jensen</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Melander</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bartek</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Dynamic assembly and sustained retention of 53BP1 at the sites of DNA damage are controlled by Mdc1/NFBD1</atl>. <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>170</vid>, <ppf>201</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>211</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b37"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Mdc1 couples DNA double-strand break recognition by Nbs1 with its H2AX-dependent chromatin retention</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>23</vid>, <ppf>2674</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2683</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b38"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mailand</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Diffley</snm>, <fnm>J.F.</fnm></refau> <atl>CDKs promote DNA replication origin licensing in human cells by protecting Cdc6 from APC/C-dependent proteolysis</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>122</vid>, <ppf>915</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>926</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b39"><reftxt><refau><snm>Poulsen</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bekker-Jensen</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mailand</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl>Human RNF169 is a negative regulator of the ubiquitin-dependent response to DNA double-strand breaks</atl>. <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>197</vid>, <ppf>189</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>199</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b40"><reftxt><refau><snm>Parris</snm>, <fnm>C.N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Seidman</snm>, <fnm>M.M.</fnm></refau> <atl>A signature element distinguishes sibling and independent mutations in a shuttle vector plasmid</atl>. <jtl>Gene</jtl> <vid>117</vid>, <ppf>1</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5</ppl> (<cd year="1992">1992</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b41"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mailand</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bekker-Jensen</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bartek</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lukas</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Destruction of Claspin by SCFbetaTrCP restrains Chk1 activation and facilitates recovery from genotoxic stress</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>23</vid>, <ppf>307</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>318</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b42"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mailand</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>RNF8 ubiquitylates histones at DNA double-strand breaks and promotes assembly of repair proteins</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>887</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>900</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b43"><reftxt><refau><snm>Greiss</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hall</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ahmed</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gartner</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl><i>C. elegans</i> SIR-2.1 translocation is linked to a proapoptotic pathway parallel to cep-1/p53 during DNA damage-induced apoptosis</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>22</vid>, <ppf>2831</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2842</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b44"><reftxt><refau><snm>Michalski</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Mass spectrometry-based proteomics using Q Exactive, a high-performance benchtop quadrupole Orbitrap mass spectrometer</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell Proteomics</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>M111 011015</ppf> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b45"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cox</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mann</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>MaxQuant enables high peptide identification rates, individualized p.p.b.-range mass accuracies and proteome-wide protein quantification</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Biotechnol.</jtl> <vid>26</vid>, <ppf>1367</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1372</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b46"><reftxt><refau><snm>Brenner</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>The genetics of <i>Caenorhabditis elegans</i></atl>. <jtl>Genetics</jtl> <vid>77</vid>, <ppf>71</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>94</ppl> (<cd year="1974">1974</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b47"><reftxt><refau><snm>Timmons</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fire</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Specific interference by ingested dsRNA</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>395</vid>, <ppf>854</ppf> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></article>
