<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "../../../DTDs/NPG_XML_Article/NPG_XML_Article.dtd" [
<!ENTITY figf1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-F1//EN" "nsmb.2415-F1" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf2 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-F2//EN" "nsmb.2415-F2" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf3 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-F3//EN" "nsmb.2415-F3" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf4 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-F4//EN" "nsmb.2415-F4" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf5 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-F5//EN" "nsmb.2415-F5" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf6 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-F6//EN" "nsmb.2415-F6" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf7 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-F7//EN" "nsmb.2415-F7" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY tbl1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2415-T1//EN" "nsmb.2415-T1" NDATA ITEM>
]>
<article id="nsmb.2415" language="eng" relation="no">
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</jtl>
<vol>19</vol>
<iss>12</iss>
<idt>201212</idt>
<categ id="af"/>
<pp><spn>1242</spn><epn>1249</epn><cnt>8</cnt></pp>
<issn type="print">1545-9993</issn>
<issn type="electronic">1545-9985</issn>
<cpg><cpy>2012</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</cpn></cpg>
<suppinfo id="S1">
<suppobj extrefid="nsmb.2415-S1" format="pdf" filesize="9.76M"><title>Supplementary Text and Figures</title>
<descrip><p>Supplementary Figures 1&#x2013;7</p></descrip></suppobj>
</suppinfo>
<subject code="npg_subject_582"/>
<subject code="npg_subject_517"/>
<subject code="npg_subject_474"/>
<subject code="npg_subject_473"/>
<doi>10.1038/nsmb.2415</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Noncanonical E2 recruitment by the autophagy E1 revealed by <named-entity id="named-entity-1">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-2">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-3">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-4">Atg10</named-entity> structures</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Stephen E</fnm><snm>Kaiser</snm><inits>S E</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Kai</fnm><snm>Mao</snm><inits>K</inits><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<au><fnm>Asad M</fnm><snm>Taherbhoy</snm><inits>A M</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<au><fnm>Shanshan</fnm><snm>Yu</snm><inits>S</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a3"/></au>
<au><fnm>Jennifer L</fnm><snm>Olszewski</snm><inits>J L</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>David M</fnm><snm>Duda</snm><inits>D M</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a4"/></au>
<au><fnm>Igor</fnm><snm>Kurinov</snm><inits>I</inits><orf rid="a5"/></au>
<au><fnm>Alan</fnm><snm>Deng</snm><inits>A</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Timothy D</fnm><snm>Fenn</snm><inits>T D</inits><orf rid="a6"/></au>
<au><fnm>Daniel J</fnm><snm>Klionsky</snm><inits>D J</inits><orf rid="a2"/></au>
<cau><fnm>Brenda A</fnm><snm>Schulman</snm><inits>B A</inits><orf rid="a1"/><orf rid="a4"/><corf rid="c1"/></cau>
<aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Department of Structural Biology, St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</org>, <cty>Memphis</cty>, <st>Tennessee</st>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a2"/><org>Life Sciences Institute, University of Michigan</org>, <cty>Ann Arbor</cty>, <st>Michigan</st>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a3"/><org>Integrated Program in Biomedical Sciences, University of Tennessee Health Science Center</org>, <cty>Memphis</cty>, <st>Tennessee</st>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a4"/><org>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</org>, <cty>Memphis</cty>, <st>Tennessee</st>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a5"/><org>Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Cornell University</org>, <cty>Argonne</cty>, <st>Illinois</st>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<aff><oid id="a6"/><org>Department of Bioengineering, Stanford University</org>, <cty>Stanford</cty>, <st>California</st>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<caff><coid id="c1"/><email>brenda.schulman@stjude.org</email></caff>
</aug>
<hst>
<re year="2012" month="06" day="18"/>
<acc year="2012" month="09" day="18"/>
<pubdate type="aop" year="2012" month="11" day="11"/>
</hst>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="aop">
<title/>
<p>An early step in the autophagy process is the conjugation of the ubiquitin-like proteins (UBLs) Atg8 and Atg12 to their targets. Structural and functional experiments reveal how the autophagy E1 Atg7 uses a <i>trans</i> mechanism to catalyze the charging of the autophagy UBLs onto their respective carrier E2 proteins, Atg3 and Atg10.</p></edsumm>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="issue">
<title/>
<p>An early step in the autophagy process is the conjugation of the ubiquitin-like proteins (UBLs) Atg8 and Atg12 to their targets. Structural and functional experiments reveal how the autophagy E1 Atg7 uses a <i>trans</i> mechanism to catalyze the charging of the autophagy UBLs onto their respective carrier E2 proteins, Atg3 and Atg10.</p></edsumm>
<abs><p>Core functions of autophagy are mediated by ubiquitin-like protein (UBL) cascades, in which a homodimeric E1 enzyme, <named-entity id="named-entity-5">Atg7</named-entity>, directs the UBLs <named-entity id="named-entity-6">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-7">Atg12</named-entity> to their respective E2 enzymes, <named-entity id="named-entity-8">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-9">Atg10</named-entity>. Crystallographic and mutational analyses of yeast (<named-entity id="named-entity-10">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-11">Atg3</named-entity>)<sub>2</sub> and (<named-entity id="named-entity-12">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-13">Atg10</named-entity>)<sub>2</sub> complexes reveal noncanonical, multisite E1-E2 recognition in autophagy. <named-entity id="named-entity-14">Atg7</named-entity>'s unique N-terminal domain recruits distinctive elements from the <named-entity id="named-entity-15">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-16">Atg10</named-entity> 'backsides'. This, along with E1 and E2 conformational variability, allows presentation of 'frontside' <named-entity id="named-entity-17">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-18">Atg10</named-entity> active sites to the catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-19">cysteine</named-entity> in the C-terminal domain from the opposite <named-entity id="named-entity-20">Atg7</named-entity> protomer in the homodimer. Despite different modes of binding, the data suggest that common principles underlie conjugation in both noncanonical and canonical UBL cascades, whereby flexibly tethered E1 domains recruit E2s through surfaces remote from their active sites to juxtapose the E1 and E2 catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-21">cysteines</named-entity>.</p></abs></fm>
<bdy>
<p>In the eukaryotic process of autophagy, or 'self-eating', a double-membrane phagophore, the precursor to an autophagosome, engulfs a portion of the cytoplasm, and the autophagosome then fuses with lysosomes or the vacuole for degradation of the cytosolic contents. This can allow recycling of macromolecules when cells are starved of nutrients or elimination of defective or unneeded organelles or cytoplasmic assemblies.</p>
<p>Core functions of autophagy are mediated by noncanonical UBL cascades. Best characterized in the yeast <i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i>, the two UBLs <named-entity id="named-entity-22">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-23">Atg12</named-entity> are both activated by the same E1 enzyme, <named-entity id="named-entity-24">Atg7</named-entity>, which, by mechanisms that are not well understood, directs each UBL to an E2 enzyme, <named-entity id="named-entity-25">Atg3</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-26">Atg10</named-entity>, respectively<bibr rid="b1 b2 b3"/>. Ultimately, the <named-entity id="named-entity-27">Atg7</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-28">Atg3</named-entity> cascade ligates <named-entity id="named-entity-29">Atg8</named-entity>'s C-terminal <named-entity id="named-entity-30">glycine</named-entity> to phosphatidylethanolamine (PE). Here a tilde (~) denotes thioester- or peptide-bonded covalent complexes. <named-entity id="named-entity-31">Atg8</named-entity>~PE adducts are incorporated into the growing autophagosomal membrane in a process that is critical for its expansion, and <named-entity id="named-entity-32">Atg8</named-entity> also recruits cargo during selective autophagy<bibr rid="b4 b5"/>. The other autophagic UBL, <named-entity id="named-entity-33">Atg12</named-entity>, functions after <named-entity id="named-entity-34">Atg7</named-entity>- and <named-entity id="named-entity-35">Atg10</named-entity>-mediated ligation to <named-entity id="named-entity-36">Atg5</named-entity> to enhance <named-entity id="named-entity-37">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation<bibr rid="b6 b7 b8 b9 b10 b11"/>. The importance of <named-entity id="named-entity-38">Atg7</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-39">Atg3</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-40">Atg10</named-entity> and other components of the <named-entity id="named-entity-41">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-42">Atg12</named-entity> ligation pathways is reflected by numerous pathologies observed in cells, tissues and/or animals lacking these proteins<bibr rid="b12 b13 b14 b15"/>. Thus, it is of great significance to understand the molecular mechanisms underlying UBL conjugation in autophagy.</p>
<p>Enzymes in the Atg8 and <named-entity id="named-entity-43">Atg12</named-entity> conjugation cascades are termed noncanonical, owing to substantial differences from those for UBLs such as ubiquitin, <named-entity id="named-entity-44">NEDD8</named-entity> and SUMO<bibr rid="b16"/>. Unlike progress in understanding the structural characteristics of enzymes involved in canonical UBL conjugation cascades, knowledge of the noncanonical features underlying <named-entity id="named-entity-45">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-46">Atg12</named-entity> conjugation remains relatively rudimentary. Briefly, in canonical UBL cascades as well as noncanonical cascades in autophagy, an E1's structurally conserved adenylation domain binds the UBL and catalyzes its C-terminal adenylation<bibr rid="b17 b18 b19 b20"/>. However, in <named-entity id="named-entity-47">Atg7</named-entity>, the adenylation domain is a symmetric homodimer with two identical UBL-binding-and-adenylation active sites, whereas the adenylation domains from canonical E1s are pseudosymmetric and contain only a single UBL-binding-and-adenylation active site<bibr rid="b21 b22 b23"/>. The UBL C terminus subsequently becomes covalently attached to the E1 catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-48">cysteine</named-entity> by a thioester bond. In canonical E1s, the catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-49">cysteine</named-entity> is housed in a distinct domain<bibr rid="b18"/> that undergoes remarkable structural remodeling to form an E1~UBL thioester intermediate<bibr rid="b24"/>. By contrast, <named-entity id="named-entity-50">Atg7</named-entity>'s <named-entity id="named-entity-51">cysteine</named-entity> is in a flexible loop that crosses over the UBL-binding surface and approaches an autophagy UBL's C-terminal <named-entity id="named-entity-52">glycine</named-entity> in the adenylation active site<bibr rid="b21 b22 b23"/>. Thus, structurally, <named-entity id="named-entity-53">Atg7</named-entity> has a single C-terminal domain (CTD) that contains the elements for both UBL adenylation and formation of the <named-entity id="named-entity-54">Atg7</named-entity>~UBL thioester intermediate. Next, a UBL thioester is transferred to an E2 catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-55">cysteine</named-entity> in order to ultimately shuttle the activated UBL to targets. However, the mechanisms by which canonical and noncanonical E1s recruit their E2s differ completely. Canonical E1s recruit their cognate E2s by a selective ubiquitin-fold domain (UFD) at the C terminus of the same subunit that also harbors the adenylation active site and catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-56">cysteine</named-entity><bibr rid="b16 b25 b26"/>. By contrast, <named-entity id="named-entity-57">Atg7</named-entity> lacks a UFD and instead has a unique N-terminal domain (NTD) that binds autophagic E2s (refs. <bibrinl rid="b21">21</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b22">22</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b23">23</bibrinl>). For <named-entity id="named-entity-58">Atg3</named-entity> this was shown to use a unique <i>trans</i> architecture: <named-entity id="named-entity-59">Atg3</named-entity> binds the NTD of one <named-entity id="named-entity-60">Atg7</named-entity> and receives <named-entity id="named-entity-61">Atg8</named-entity> from the catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-62">cysteine</named-entity> of the opposite <named-entity id="named-entity-63">Atg7</named-entity> molecule in the homodimer<bibr rid="b21 b22 b23"/>.</p>
<p>The autophagy E2s also have distinctive features that raise questions about how both <named-entity id="named-entity-64">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-65">Atg10</named-entity> could bind <named-entity id="named-entity-66">Atg7</named-entity>. First, <named-entity id="named-entity-67">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-68">Atg10</named-entity> share little sequence homology. Although they both have core structures resembling a canonical E2 catalytic domain, with a concave &#x3B2;-sheet backside and the catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-69">cysteine</named-entity> at the front, their mechanisms of E1 binding are apparently noncanonical<bibr rid="b27 b28"/>. <named-entity id="named-entity-70">Atg3</named-entity> lacks any known catalytic residues other than the active site <named-entity id="named-entity-71">cysteine</named-entity> and also has a unique 'flexible region' (<named-entity id="named-entity-72">Atg3</named-entity>FR) that binds <named-entity id="named-entity-73">Atg7</named-entity> and a distinctive 'handle region' required for downstream steps in <named-entity id="named-entity-74">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation<bibr rid="b27"/>. A prior structure of a short peptide from the <named-entity id="named-entity-75">Atg3</named-entity>FR bound to the isolated <named-entity id="named-entity-76">Atg7</named-entity>NTD revealed the basis for their high-affinity interactions, although additional contact surfaces were implied<bibr rid="b21"/>. Also, it is unclear how <named-entity id="named-entity-77">Atg10</named-entity> binds <named-entity id="named-entity-78">Atg7</named-entity>: <named-entity id="named-entity-79">Atg10</named-entity> lacks an obvious flexible-region sequence, and an <named-entity id="named-entity-80">Atg7</named-entity> mutant at the <named-entity id="named-entity-81">Atg3</named-entity>FR-binding interface is defective for the <named-entity id="named-entity-82">Atg3</named-entity> pathway but not for the <named-entity id="named-entity-83">Atg10</named-entity> pathway <i>in vivo</i><bibr rid="b21"/>. Seemingly paradoxically, the isolated <named-entity id="named-entity-84">Atg3</named-entity>FR competes with <named-entity id="named-entity-85">Atg10</named-entity> for <named-entity id="named-entity-86">Atg7</named-entity> binding <i>in vitro</i>, and the <named-entity id="named-entity-87">Atg7</named-entity>-binding site on <named-entity id="named-entity-88">Atg3</named-entity>FR is not accessible in the prior structure of full-length <named-entity id="named-entity-89">Atg3</named-entity> (refs. <bibrinl rid="b23">23</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b27">27</bibrinl>).</p>
<p>Thus, to gain insights into how the autophagy E1 recognizes its E2s, we determined crystal structures of <named-entity id="named-entity-90">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-91">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-92">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-93">Atg10</named-entity> complexes from <i>S. cerevisiae</i>. The structures show how a single E1 enzyme uses the same surfaces to recognize distinctive features of two different E2s and how conformational changes and unique molecular architectures mediate active site juxtaposition for the noncanonical E1&#x2013;E2 complexes in autophagy.</p>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Results</sectitle>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Multisite recruitment of <named-entity id="named-entity-94">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-95">Atg10</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-96">Atg7</named-entity></sectitle>
<p>To visualize the juxtaposition of E1 and E2 catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-97">cysteines</named-entity>, which is required for UBL transfer, we performed cross-linking as follows: We purified versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-98">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-99">Atg10</named-entity> containing only a single <named-entity id="named-entity-100">cysteine</named-entity> at the active site, reacted the homobifunctional sulfhydryl cross-linker <named-entity id="named-entity-101">bismaleimidoethane</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-102">BMOE</named-entity>) with each E2 and desalted excess cross-linker. For <named-entity id="named-entity-103">Atg3</named-entity>, we added a version of <named-entity id="named-entity-104">Atg7</named-entity> lacking the C-terminal 17 residues disordered in prior crystals, and for <named-entity id="named-entity-105">Atg10</named-entity> we added a version of <named-entity id="named-entity-106">Atg7</named-entity> with this truncation and C39S C195S C375A mutations to reduce background cross-linking. Using this method, we obtained crystal structures of <named-entity id="named-entity-107">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;BMOE&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-108">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-109">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;BMOE&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-110">Atg10</named-entity> (hereafter referred to as <named-entity id="named-entity-111">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-112">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-113">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-114">Atg10</named-entity>) to 2.7- and 2.9-&#xC5; resolution, respectively (<tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>). Both contain one dimeric <named-entity id="named-entity-115">Atg7</named-entity> bound to two E2s per asymmetric unit.</p>
<p>The structure of <named-entity id="named-entity-116">Atg7</named-entity> resembles a bird, with the two NTDs corresponding to 'wings' extending away from the symmetric homodimeric CTD 'body' (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1a</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 2a</sir>). The relative NTD-CTD orientations differ by ~10&#xB0; between all the E2-bound and the unbound <named-entity id="named-entity-117">Atg7</named-entity> structures<bibr rid="b22"/>, which translates into ~40-&#xC5; differences in the distal-edge positions for the oblong NTD. The range of NTD positions observed upon superimposing the E2-bound and <named-entity id="named-entity-118">apo-Atg7</named-entity> structures over their CTDs resembles the flapping of a bird's wings. Conformational flexibility between the <named-entity id="named-entity-119">Atg7</named-entity>NTD and CTD is likely important to accommodate the different dimensions of the <named-entity id="named-entity-120">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-121">Atg10</named-entity> E2s and is consistent with prior small-angle X-ray scattering data<bibr rid="b21 b22"/>.</p>
<p>The E2 core domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-122">Atg7</named-entity>-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-123">Atg3</named-entity> superimposes well with the prior uncomplexed structure<bibr rid="b27"/>, although in the complex the <named-entity id="named-entity-124">Atg3</named-entity> catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-125">cysteine</named-entity> loop is substantially rearranged, and much of the handle region is not visible (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr>). In both the free and <named-entity id="named-entity-126">Atg7</named-entity>-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-127">Atg3</named-entity> structures, the majority of the flexible region is disordered, except for a small helical segment. However, this region of the <named-entity id="named-entity-128">Atg3</named-entity>FR is substantially displaced in the complex with <named-entity id="named-entity-129">Atg7</named-entity>: instead of packing against <named-entity id="named-entity-130">Atg3</named-entity>'s own E2 core domain, the flexible-region helix interacts with a distal groove in the 'shoulder' region of the <named-entity id="named-entity-131">Atg7</named-entity>NTD wing.</p>
<p>Despite little apparent overall sequence similarity, <named-entity id="named-entity-132">Atg10</named-entity> also generally resembles a canonical E2 core domain. Although the C-terminal structures differ between <named-entity id="named-entity-133">Atg3</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-134">Atg10</named-entity> and canonical E2s, their catalytic domains have in common an N-terminal helix, a backside four-stranded antiparallel &#x3B2;-sheet followed by the <named-entity id="named-entity-135">cysteine</named-entity> loop and a long central helix<bibr rid="b28"/> (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr>). One notable difference in <named-entity id="named-entity-136">Atg10</named-entity> when compared to <named-entity id="named-entity-137">Atg3</named-entity> and other E2s is C-terminal extension of the fourth &#x3B2;-strand and its continuation into a &#x3B2;-hairpin that leads to an additional strand incorporated into an extended &#x3B2;-sheet on the E2 backside (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr>).</p>
<p>Common <named-entity id="named-entity-138">Atg7</named-entity> surfaces recruit the E2s through extensive multipart interfaces involving (i) the shoulder portion of the <named-entity id="named-entity-139">Atg7</named-entity>NTD wing interacting with unique structures from the backsides of <named-entity id="named-entity-140">Atg3</named-entity> and of <named-entity id="named-entity-141">Atg10</named-entity>, (ii) the 'under-wing' portion of the NTD interacting with features along the length of the backsides of both E2s and (iii) the <named-entity id="named-entity-142">Atg7</named-entity> NTD-CTD junction cradling the edge of both E2s (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2a,b</figr>). <named-entity id="named-entity-143">Atg7</named-entity>'s multisite recruitment buries ~2,450 and ~1,830 &#xC5;<super>2</super> from <named-entity id="named-entity-144">Atg3</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-145">Atg10</named-entity>, respectively, which corresponds to ~30% of their exposed surfaces.</p>
<p>The structurally observed <named-entity id="named-entity-146">Atg7</named-entity>NTD recruitment of an autophagic E2 by its backside allows juxtaposition of the E2 frontside active site with the catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-147">cysteine</named-entity> in the CTD of the opposite <named-entity id="named-entity-148">Atg7</named-entity> molecule in the homodimer (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). This <i>trans</i> configuration agrees with previous biochemical studies of <named-entity id="named-entity-149">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-150">Atg3</named-entity> complexes. To test whether this <i>trans</i> architecture also exists in solution for <named-entity id="named-entity-151">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-152">Atg10</named-entity> complexes, we performed cross-linking based on previously described mixed dimer versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-153">Atg7</named-entity> (refs. <bibrinl rid="b21">21</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b22">22</bibrinl>). In the <i>trans</i> configuration, one <named-entity id="named-entity-154">Atg7</named-entity> molecule consists only of the CTD, which retains the catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-155">cysteine</named-entity> but lacks the E2-binding NTD. The other <named-entity id="named-entity-156">Atg7</named-entity> retains the E2-binding NTD but carries an active site <named-entity id="named-entity-157">cysteine</named-entity>-to-<named-entity id="named-entity-158">alanine</named-entity> substitution in the CTD. In the <i>cis</i> configuration, the <named-entity id="named-entity-159">Atg7</named-entity>CTD harbors a catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-160">cysteine</named-entity>-to-<named-entity id="named-entity-161">alanine</named-entity> mutation, and the full-length <named-entity id="named-entity-162">Atg7</named-entity> retains both the E2-binding NTD and the catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-163">cysteine</named-entity>. Mixed heterodimers are stabilized by an engineered salt bridge between <named-entity id="named-entity-164">glutamate</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-165">arginine</named-entity> substitutions in place of residues 511 and 524, respectively<bibr rid="b22"/>, and are ensured by a sequential two-tag purification strategy<bibr rid="b21"/>. After reacting single-<named-entity id="named-entity-166">cysteine</named-entity> versions of either <named-entity id="named-entity-167">Atg3</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-168">Atg10</named-entity> with <named-entity id="named-entity-169">BMOE</named-entity>, desalting and adding one of the two forms of <named-entity id="named-entity-170">Atg7</named-entity>, cross-linking was observed only with the <i>trans</i> version of <named-entity id="named-entity-171">Atg7</named-entity>, consistent with the crystallographic architectures (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2c</figr>).</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>E2 recruitment to a conserved <named-entity id="named-entity-172">Atg7</named-entity>NTD shoulder groove</sectitle>
<p>An ~30-&#xC5;-long, conserved hydrophobic groove in the shoulder region of the <named-entity id="named-entity-173">Atg7</named-entity>NTD wing anchors the two autophagy E2s in completely different ways. From <named-entity id="named-entity-174">Atg3</named-entity>, the unique flexible-region helix is embedded in the portion of the shoulder groove lined by Leu90, Phe93, Lys94, Lys98, Arg135, Tyr137, Trp139, Trp273, Lys280, Leu281, Pro283 and Val285 from the <named-entity id="named-entity-175">Atg7</named-entity>NTD (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3a</figr>), as in the prior structure of the isolated <named-entity id="named-entity-176">Atg7</named-entity>NTD bound to a short <named-entity id="named-entity-177">Atg3</named-entity>FR-helix peptide<bibr rid="b21"/>. Although the 45 residues preceding the flexible-region helix are disordered in the <named-entity id="named-entity-178">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-179">Atg3</named-entity> complex, there is patchy electron density corresponding to the residues following the helix. Notably, this unmodeled density traverses a basic surface in the middle of <named-entity id="named-entity-180">Atg7</named-entity>'s NTD, probably reflecting electrostatic interactions from up to 12 of the 20 residues in this <named-entity id="named-entity-181">Atg3</named-entity> region that are acidic or polar (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Figs. 3</sir> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">4</sir>). The importance of <named-entity id="named-entity-182">Atg7</named-entity>'s shoulder carrying <named-entity id="named-entity-183">Atg3</named-entity>'s flexible region is highlighted by the previous finding that deleting the flexible region substantially increases the <i>K</i><sub>d</sub> for <named-entity id="named-entity-184">Atg7</named-entity> binding<bibr rid="b21"/>.</p>
<p>From <named-entity id="named-entity-185">Atg10</named-entity>, the &#x3B2;-hairpin binds the edge of the shoulder groove (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3b</figr>). Here, <named-entity id="named-entity-186">Atg10</named-entity>'s Ile88, Asp89, Ile91 and Pro92 are enwrapped in a pocket formed by <named-entity id="named-entity-187">Atg7</named-entity>'s Arg135, Tyr137, Asn276, Val277, Gln278, Ala282, Pro283, Val285 and Asp287. The interaction is stabilized by salt bridges between <named-entity id="named-entity-188">Atg7</named-entity>'s Lys94 and <named-entity id="named-entity-189">Atg10</named-entity>'s Asp89, as well as between <named-entity id="named-entity-190">Atg7</named-entity>'s Asp287 and Ser290 and <named-entity id="named-entity-191">Atg10</named-entity>'s Lys95. Notably, the additional &#x3B2;-strand in <named-entity id="named-entity-192">Atg10</named-entity>'s sheet aligns with <named-entity id="named-entity-193">Atg7</named-entity>'s &#x3B2;-strand 15. This leads to formation of a ten-stranded interprotein &#x3B2;-sheet with five strands each from <named-entity id="named-entity-194">Atg10</named-entity>'s backside and <named-entity id="named-entity-195">Atg7</named-entity>'s NTD.</p>
<p>Comparison of <named-entity id="named-entity-196">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-197">Atg10</named-entity> contacts with the shoulder groove resolves previous seemingly contradictory findings. Some overlap of the interaction surfaces (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3c</figr>) explains why the <named-entity id="named-entity-198">Atg3</named-entity>FR competed with <named-entity id="named-entity-199">Atg10</named-entity> for binding to the <named-entity id="named-entity-200">Atg7</named-entity>NTD during gel filtration<bibr rid="b23"/>. Although we wished to further probe the competition, unfortunately we have not been able to purify <i>S. cerevisiae</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-201">Atg12</named-entity>. Thus, we developed an artificial enzyme assay: using high protein concentrations <i>in vitro</i>, we can observe non-native <named-entity id="named-entity-202">Atg7</named-entity>-mediated conjugation of <named-entity id="named-entity-203">Atg8</named-entity> onto <named-entity id="named-entity-204">Atg10</named-entity> at low levels. This reaction is inhibited by the short peptide corresponding to the <named-entity id="named-entity-205">Atg3</named-entity>FR helix (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3d</figr>), consistent with the structures.</p>
<p>Despite overlapping binding surfaces, the distinct E2 binding modes suggest that different <named-entity id="named-entity-206">Atg7</named-entity> residues from the shoulder groove have critical roles in recruiting <named-entity id="named-entity-207">Atg3</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-208">Atg10</named-entity>. In particular, the Pro283 side chain is central to the hydrophobic interaction with <named-entity id="named-entity-209">Atg3</named-entity>FR but is at the edge of the <named-entity id="named-entity-210">Atg10</named-entity>-binding surface. By contrast, Val285 is at the center of the hydrophobic interface with the <named-entity id="named-entity-211">Atg10</named-entity> &#x3B2;-hairpin but is on the edge of the <named-entity id="named-entity-212">Atg3</named-entity>-binding surface. At a more intermediate level, Tyr137 also has a modest role in the <named-entity id="named-entity-213">Atg3</named-entity> interaction but appears to stabilize the structure of the <named-entity id="named-entity-214">Atg10</named-entity>-binding site. We tested these concepts with <named-entity id="named-entity-215">Atg7</named-entity>-E2 catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-216">cysteine</named-entity> cross-linking assays (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3e,f</figr>). In agreement with the structures, mutation of <named-entity id="named-entity-217">Atg7</named-entity>'s Tyr137 had modest effects on cross-linking to both E2s. However, a P283D substitution shown previously to impair <named-entity id="named-entity-218">Atg7</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-219">Atg3</named-entity> interactions had little effect on <named-entity id="named-entity-220">Atg10</named-entity> cross-linking to <named-entity id="named-entity-221">Atg7</named-entity>, whereas a V285D substitution almost abolished <named-entity id="named-entity-222">Atg7</named-entity> cross-linking to <named-entity id="named-entity-223">Atg10</named-entity> but not to <named-entity id="named-entity-224">Atg3</named-entity>. Deleting <named-entity id="named-entity-225">Atg10</named-entity>'s &#x3B2;-hairpin (residues 86&#x2013;93) also substantially diminished cross-linking to <named-entity id="named-entity-226">Atg7</named-entity> (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3g</figr>). Thus, the <named-entity id="named-entity-227">Atg7</named-entity> shoulder groove is built to recruit distinct distal structures from the two E2s in such a way as to allow each of their catalytic centers to approach the <named-entity id="named-entity-228">Atg7</named-entity> active site.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>E2 positioning through backside and edge binding to <named-entity id="named-entity-229">Atg7</named-entity></sectitle>
<p>Although prior qualitative studies suggested that <named-entity id="named-entity-230">Atg3</named-entity>'s flexible region is essential for binding to <named-entity id="named-entity-231">Atg7</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b27">27</bibrinl>), additional contacts were implicated from the findings that <named-entity id="named-entity-232">Atg7</named-entity> binds weakly to <named-entity id="named-entity-233">Atg3</named-entity> lacking the flexible region, that <named-entity id="named-entity-234">Atg7</named-entity>'s NTD binds with higher affinity to full-length <named-entity id="named-entity-235">Atg3</named-entity> than to a peptide corresponding to <named-entity id="named-entity-236">Atg3</named-entity>'s flexible-region helix and that <named-entity id="named-entity-237">Atg3</named-entity> binds with higher affinity to full-length <named-entity id="named-entity-238">Atg7</named-entity> than to the isolated <named-entity id="named-entity-239">Atg7</named-entity>NTD<bibr rid="b21"/>. Indeed, more than 30 <named-entity id="named-entity-240">Atg7</named-entity> under-wing residues make more than 140 contacts to more than 25 residues from all four strands corresponding to the E2 core-domain backside of <named-entity id="named-entity-241">Atg3</named-entity> as well as to several additional <named-entity id="named-entity-242">Atg3</named-entity>-specific loops (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4a</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 5</sir>). Here, <named-entity id="named-entity-243">Atg7</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-244">Atg3</named-entity> interact through three regions that together comprise a roughly circular surface with an ~30-&#xC5; diameter. At the heart is a hydrophobic cluster involving <named-entity id="named-entity-245">Atg7</named-entity>'s Phe16 and Phe61 and <named-entity id="named-entity-246">Atg3</named-entity>'s Tyr168 and Phe189, buttressed by <named-entity id="named-entity-247">Atg7</named-entity>'s Lys14 and Asp18, and backside surface side chains from <named-entity id="named-entity-248">Atg3</named-entity>, including Ser54, Arg72, Lys73, Asp170 and the backbone oxygen from Ser191.</p>
<p>We tested roles of this extensive secondary <named-entity id="named-entity-249">Atg7</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-250">Atg3</named-entity> binding surface by using several assays. To probe interactions, we used our <named-entity id="named-entity-251">Atg7</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-252">Atg3</named-entity> catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-253">cysteine</named-entity> cross-linking assay, and to probe enzymatic activity, we examined <i>in vitro</i> pulse-chase transfer of [<super>32</super>P]<named-entity id="named-entity-254">Atg8</named-entity> from <named-entity id="named-entity-255">Atg7</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-256">Atg3</named-entity>. Consistent with key roles in stabilizing <named-entity id="named-entity-257">Atg7</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-258">Atg3</named-entity> interactions and positioning their active sites, multiple <named-entity id="named-entity-259">alanine</named-entity> substitutions in place of <named-entity id="named-entity-260">Atg7</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-261">Atg3</named-entity> surface residues at the hydrophobic center of this interface resulted in severe defects in both <i>in vitro</i> assays (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4b&#x2013;d</figr>). For the highly deleterious K14A F16A D18A mutant, we confirmed proper folding with a crystal structure of this mutant version of <named-entity id="named-entity-262">Atg7</named-entity>NTD (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 2b</sir> and <tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr>). By contrast, mutations at the distal edge&#x2014;<named-entity id="named-entity-263">Atg7</named-entity> D47A N50A K53A or <named-entity id="named-entity-264">Atg3</named-entity> K48A E51A Q302A D304A&#x2014;had little effect on <named-entity id="named-entity-265">Atg7</named-entity>-<named-entity id="named-entity-266">Atg3</named-entity> interactions <i>in vitro</i>.</p>
<p>To extend our analysis and study the effects of these <named-entity id="named-entity-267">Atg7</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-268">Atg3</named-entity> mutants <i>in vivo</i>, we examined their autophagy activity by four established methods: GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-269">Atg8</named-entity> localization, <named-entity id="named-entity-270">Pho8</named-entity>&#x394;60 and GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-271">Atg8</named-entity> processing assays and an <named-entity id="named-entity-272">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation assay (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4e,f</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 6</sir>). During autophagy, GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-273">Atg8</named-entity> becomes ligated to PE and becomes localized to punctate dots, whereas it remains diffusely localized in the cytoplasm in yeast strains deficient in <named-entity id="named-entity-274">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation. The second assay relies on <named-entity id="named-entity-275">Pho8</named-entity>&#x394;60, a mutant form of <named-entity id="named-entity-276">vacuolar alkaline phosphatase</named-entity>, with 60 N-terminal amino acid residues deleted, that normally remains in the cytosol and is transported into the vacuole only through autophagy<bibr rid="b29"/>. Measuring the activity of alkaline phosphatase thus reflects the level of autophagy. In the third assay, GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-277">Atg8</named-entity> is delivered into the vacuole when autophagy is induced. Although <named-entity id="named-entity-278">Atg8</named-entity> is degraded, the GFP moiety is relatively stable. Therefore, autophagy progression can be determined by the accumulation of free GFP<bibr rid="b30"/>. Finally, we monitored <named-entity id="named-entity-279">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation as a mobility shift on SDS-PAGE gels. Wild-type but not <i><named-entity id="named-entity-280">atg7</named-entity></i>&#x394; or <i><named-entity id="named-entity-281">atg3</named-entity></i>&#x394; cells transformed with empty vector displayed autophagy, as monitored by all four assays. Autophagy was restored in <i><named-entity id="named-entity-282">atg7</named-entity></i>&#x394; cells with a plasmid expressing either wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-283">Atg7</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-284">Atg7</named-entity> D47A N50A K53A and in <i><named-entity id="named-entity-285">atg3</named-entity></i>&#x394; cells expressing wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-286">Atg3</named-entity>. In contrast, autophagy was abolished in <i><named-entity id="named-entity-287">atg7</named-entity></i>&#x394; cells expressing <named-entity id="named-entity-288">Atg7</named-entity> K14A F16A D18A or <named-entity id="named-entity-289">Atg7</named-entity> F16A F61A or in <i><named-entity id="named-entity-290">atg3</named-entity></i>&#x394; cells expressing <named-entity id="named-entity-291">Atg3</named-entity> R72A K73A Y168A, all of which contain mutations that localize to the center of the hydrophobic interface.</p>
<p>We were surprised to find that although <named-entity id="named-entity-292">Atg3</named-entity> K48A E51A Q302A D304A, with mutations at the distal edge, showed little defect in <named-entity id="named-entity-293">Atg8</named-entity> transfer from <named-entity id="named-entity-294">Atg7</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-295">Atg3</named-entity> in our <i>in vitro</i> assays, these mutations severely disrupted autophagy (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4b,f</figr> and <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 6</sir>). Thus, it seemed possible that <named-entity id="named-entity-296">Atg3</named-entity> uses this surface for downstream interactions in the pathway. Accordingly, we examined <named-entity id="named-entity-297">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation with an <i>in vitro</i> assay in which <named-entity id="named-entity-298">Atg12</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-299">Atg5</named-entity> acts as an E3 and PE-containing liposomes provide substrate (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4g,h</figr>). Consistent with the <i>in vivo</i> data, this mutant version of <named-entity id="named-entity-300">Atg3</named-entity> is defective for generating the <named-entity id="named-entity-301">Atg8</named-entity>~PE product <i>in vitro</i>, which suggests potential roles for this surface in binding to E3 or substrate.</p>
<p>The <named-entity id="named-entity-302">Atg7</named-entity> NTD-CTD junction region is also functionally important, as deleting <named-entity id="named-entity-303">Atg7</named-entity> residues 290&#x2013;294 or inserting the flexible sequence GGSG after <named-entity id="named-entity-304">Atg7</named-entity>'s Leu291 leads to decreased cross-linking with <named-entity id="named-entity-305">Atg3</named-entity> (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4d,i</figr>). The insertion mutation was shown previously to decrease <named-entity id="named-entity-306">Atg7</named-entity>-mediated [<super>32</super>P]<named-entity id="named-entity-307">Atg8</named-entity> transfer to <named-entity id="named-entity-308">Atg3</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b21">21</bibrinl>), and here we also observed similar defects for the deletion (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4j</figr>).</p>
<p>The <named-entity id="named-entity-309">Atg7</named-entity> under-wing region also interacts with <named-entity id="named-entity-310">Atg10</named-entity>'s backside and edge (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5a</figr>). However, unlike interactions with <named-entity id="named-entity-311">Atg3</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-312">Atg7</named-entity>'s under-wing contacts to <named-entity id="named-entity-313">Atg10</named-entity> are dispersed and lack a distinct center and thus may arise from crystallization or conformations imposed by cross-linking. Accordingly, multiple <named-entity id="named-entity-314">alanine</named-entity> substitutions in the under-wing region of <named-entity id="named-entity-315">Atg7</named-entity> had only a minor effect on cross-linking to <named-entity id="named-entity-316">Atg10</named-entity> (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5b</figr>). Furthermore, aligning either the <named-entity id="named-entity-317">Atg7</named-entity>NTDs or the E2s from the <named-entity id="named-entity-318">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-319">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-320">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-321">Atg10</named-entity> complexes reveals relative displacement of the structural elements mediating interactions and different relative <named-entity id="named-entity-322">Atg7</named-entity>NTD and CTD orientations for juxtaposition of <named-entity id="named-entity-323">Atg7</named-entity>'s active site with those of the two E2s (<figr rid="f1">Figs. 1a</figr> and <figr rid="f2">2a,b</figr> and <figr rid="f2">5c</figr>).</p>
<p>At the near edge, Ser290 and Leu291 from <named-entity id="named-entity-324">Atg7</named-entity>'s NTD-CTD junction interact with <named-entity id="named-entity-325">Atg10</named-entity>'s Leu96 and Leu98, with continued interactions involving the N-terminal helix of <named-entity id="named-entity-326">Atg7</named-entity>'s NTD. Here, <named-entity id="named-entity-327">Atg7</named-entity>'s Gln300 and Lys307 contact the backbone oxygens of Leu98 and Pro99 as well as Glu103 from <named-entity id="named-entity-328">Atg10</named-entity>. Additional electron density connecting <named-entity id="named-entity-329">Atg10</named-entity>'s Val108 and Gly124 that is too low quality for accurate modeling reflects further contact with <named-entity id="named-entity-330">Atg7</named-entity>'s NTD-CTD junction. Indeed, either deleting or inserting residues at the <named-entity id="named-entity-331">Atg7</named-entity> NTD-CTD junction resulted in decreased cross-linking to <named-entity id="named-entity-332">Atg10</named-entity> (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5b</figr>).</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><named-entity id="named-entity-333">Atg7</named-entity> binding unmasks conserved E2 active site architectures</sectitle>
<p>For both <named-entity id="named-entity-334">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-335">Atg10</named-entity>, the E2 active site is on the opposite face from the noncovalent <named-entity id="named-entity-336">Atg7</named-entity>-binding regions. In complex with <named-entity id="named-entity-337">Atg7</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-338">Atg3</named-entity>'s catalytic Cys234 is surface exposed and is connected to additional patchy electron density that presumably corresponds to the <named-entity id="named-entity-339">BMOE</named-entity> also linked to <named-entity id="named-entity-340">Atg7</named-entity>'s catalytic Cys507 ~7 &#xC5; away. Here, <named-entity id="named-entity-341">Atg3</named-entity>'s <named-entity id="named-entity-342">cysteine</named-entity> loop is substantially rearranged from the conformation observed in free <named-entity id="named-entity-343">Atg3</named-entity>, in which Cys234 is buried<bibr rid="b27"/> (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6a</figr>). <named-entity id="named-entity-344">Atg10</named-entity>'s catalytic Cys133 is not observed in either complex in the asymmetric unit, which suggests that <named-entity id="named-entity-345">Atg10</named-entity>'s <named-entity id="named-entity-346">cysteine</named-entity> loop is also conformationally flexible. Nonetheless, the location of <named-entity id="named-entity-347">Atg10</named-entity>'s Cys133 can be approximated on the basis of the positions of His131 visible in one <named-entity id="named-entity-348">Atg10</named-entity> and of Pro132 in the other <named-entity id="named-entity-349">Atg10</named-entity> in the asymmetric unit. These are consistent with the subsequent Cys133 residue approaching <named-entity id="named-entity-350">Atg7</named-entity>'s Cys507.</p>
<p>Despite <named-entity id="named-entity-351">Atg10</named-entity>'s catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-352">cysteine</named-entity> not being visible and the limited resolution of our data, comparison of the <named-entity id="named-entity-353">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-354">Atg10</named-entity> structures suggests a common active site architecture: <named-entity id="named-entity-355">Atg3</named-entity>'s catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-356">cysteine</named-entity> is flanked by Tyr179 and His232, and <named-entity id="named-entity-357">Atg10</named-entity>'s Tyr73 and His131 are in parallel locations (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6b</figr>). Notably, these are among the few amino acids shared between the sequences of Atg3s and Atg10s, which suggests key functions (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 4</sir>). Indeed, <named-entity id="named-entity-358">Atg3</named-entity> Y179A decreases pulse-chase transfer of [<super>32</super>P]<named-entity id="named-entity-359">Atg8</named-entity> from <named-entity id="named-entity-360">Atg7</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-361">Atg3</named-entity>, and both mutants are defective in <named-entity id="named-entity-362">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation <i>in vitro</i>, with a more pronounced defect observed for H232A (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6c,d</figr>). Notably, these catalytic residues are required for <named-entity id="named-entity-363">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-364">Atg10</named-entity> function <i>in vivo</i> (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6e,f</figr>).</p>
<p>The conformation of the <named-entity id="named-entity-365">Atg7</named-entity> <named-entity id="named-entity-366">cysteine</named-entity> loop when cross-linked to the E2s also differs from that in previous structures<bibr rid="b21 b22 b23"/>. Prior studies had revealed that in the absence of a UBL, the <named-entity id="named-entity-367">Atg7</named-entity> <named-entity id="named-entity-368">cysteine</named-entity> loop packs closely against the UBL-binding surface, with Cys507 facing toward the E1. However, in complex with <named-entity id="named-entity-369">Atg8</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-370">Atg7</named-entity>'s <named-entity id="named-entity-371">cysteine</named-entity> loop is separated from the CTD and crosses over <named-entity id="named-entity-372">Atg8</named-entity>'s C terminus. Notably, in different crystals of <named-entity id="named-entity-373">Atg7</named-entity>CTD&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-374">Atg8</named-entity> complexes, <named-entity id="named-entity-375">Atg7</named-entity>'s residues 504&#x2013;508 are observed in different conformations, with Cys507 facing either toward or away from <named-entity id="named-entity-376">Atg8</named-entity>'s C-terminal <named-entity id="named-entity-377">glycine</named-entity><bibr rid="b22 b23"/>. When cross-linked to the E2s but in the absence of a UBL, <named-entity id="named-entity-378">Atg7</named-entity>'s <named-entity id="named-entity-379">cysteine</named-entity> loop adopts a hybrid conformation, with residues 490&#x2013;505 packing against <named-entity id="named-entity-380">Atg7</named-entity>'s UBL binding site, as observed previously, and residues 506&#x2013;508 more open to allow Cys507 to face an E2 active site (<figr rid="f6">Fig. 6g</figr>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Discussion</sectitle>
<p>The <named-entity id="named-entity-381">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-382">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-383">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-384">Atg10</named-entity> crystal structures have revealed how the noncanonical E1 <named-entity id="named-entity-385">Atg7</named-entity> recognizes its two cognate but distinct E2s. Both <named-entity id="named-entity-386">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-387">Atg10</named-entity> are recruited by their E2 core-domain backsides to a broad surface extending over much of the unique <named-entity id="named-entity-388">Atg7</named-entity>NTD and including the junction with the <named-entity id="named-entity-389">Atg7</named-entity>CTD. Notably, <named-entity id="named-entity-390">Atg3</named-entity>- and <named-entity id="named-entity-391">Atg10</named-entity>-specific insertions anchor the complexes through docking in a distal <named-entity id="named-entity-392">Atg7</named-entity>NTD groove. <named-entity id="named-entity-393">Atg7</named-entity>NTD-mediated E2 backside recruitment, coupled with conformational flexibility, allows presentation of the active sites on the frontsides of <named-entity id="named-entity-394">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-395">Atg10</named-entity> to the remote catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-396">cysteine</named-entity> in the UBL-binding CTD from the opposite <named-entity id="named-entity-397">Atg7</named-entity> monomer in the homodimer.</p>
<p>In addition to functioning with these two divergent E2s, <named-entity id="named-entity-398">Atg7</named-entity> is distinct among E1s in activating two divergent UBLs, <named-entity id="named-entity-399">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-400">Atg12</named-entity>. It is currently thought that <named-entity id="named-entity-401">Atg8</named-entity> is strictly directed to <named-entity id="named-entity-402">Atg3</named-entity> as its specific E2 for ligation to PE<bibr rid="b31"/>, with <named-entity id="named-entity-403">Atg10</named-entity> being the exclusive E2 for <named-entity id="named-entity-404">Atg12</named-entity> ligation to <named-entity id="named-entity-405">Atg5</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b32">32</bibrinl>). However, there is much cross-talk between the pathways. For example, the <named-entity id="named-entity-406">Atg12</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-407">Atg5</named-entity> complex is an E3 that promotes <named-entity id="named-entity-408">Atg8</named-entity> transfer from <named-entity id="named-entity-409">Atg3</named-entity>'s active site to PE<bibr rid="b6"/>. Conversely, in mammalian cells, <named-entity id="named-entity-410">Atg3</named-entity> overexpression facilitates formation of the <named-entity id="named-entity-411">Atg12</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-412">Atg5</named-entity> complex<bibr rid="b33"/>, and during mitophagy <named-entity id="named-entity-413">Atg3</named-entity> can also act as an <named-entity id="named-entity-414">Atg12</named-entity> E2 mediating self-modification<bibr rid="b34"/>. Irrespective of whether there are circumstances under which <named-entity id="named-entity-415">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-416">Atg12</named-entity> could both function with <named-entity id="named-entity-417">Atg3</named-entity> and/or <named-entity id="named-entity-418">Atg10</named-entity>, it is clear that, at least <i>in vitro</i>, <named-entity id="named-entity-419">Atg8</named-entity> is preferentially transferred to <named-entity id="named-entity-420">Atg3</named-entity>.</p>
<p>Two speculative models emerge for how <named-entity id="named-entity-421">Atg7</named-entity> UBL and E2 specificity could be established. Briefly, we made a model of <named-entity id="named-entity-422">Atg3</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-423">Atg7</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-424">Atg8</named-entity> by superimposing the <named-entity id="named-entity-425">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-426">Atg3</named-entity> structure with a prior <named-entity id="named-entity-427">Atg7</named-entity>CTD&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-428">Atg8</named-entity> structure<bibr rid="b23"/> and (i) docked the <named-entity id="named-entity-429">Atg8</named-entity> globular domain, (ii) transplanted residues 490&#x2013;506 from the <named-entity id="named-entity-430">Atg7</named-entity> <named-entity id="named-entity-431">cysteine</named-entity> loop in the <named-entity id="named-entity-432">Atg8</named-entity>-bound complex and (iii) positioned <named-entity id="named-entity-433">Atg8</named-entity>'s C-terminal tail as in a thioester complex by superimposing it on <named-entity id="named-entity-434">Atg7</named-entity>'s <named-entity id="named-entity-435">cysteine</named-entity> loop, residues 504&#x2013;506, from the structures lacking <named-entity id="named-entity-436">Atg8</named-entity> (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7a</figr>). The structural model reveals the <named-entity id="named-entity-437">Atg7</named-entity> <named-entity id="named-entity-438">cysteine</named-entity> loop contacting both <named-entity id="named-entity-439">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-440">Atg3</named-entity>. Thus, the <named-entity id="named-entity-441">Atg7</named-entity> <named-entity id="named-entity-442">cysteine</named-entity> loop may be the sensor that transmits signals between the UBL and the E2 for optimal interaction and/or catalysis of UBL transfer. The second mechanism is suggested by a parallel model of <named-entity id="named-entity-443">Atg10</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-444">Atg7</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-445">Atg12</named-entity> (<figr rid="f7">Fig. 7b</figr>). Here, <named-entity id="named-entity-446">Atg10</named-entity>'s residues 133&#x2013;145, including Cys133, are not modeled because they were not visible in the electron density. However, the locations of the adjoining <named-entity id="named-entity-447">Atg10</named-entity> residues Pro132 and Met146 suggest that the E2 <named-entity id="named-entity-448">cysteine</named-entity> loop may also directly recognize its cognate UBL during the transthiolation reaction. Future structural studies of <named-entity id="named-entity-449">Atg3</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-450">Atg7</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-451">Atg8</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-452">Atg10</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-453">Atg7</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-454">Atg12</named-entity> complexes will be required to understand the extent to which the E1 and E2 <named-entity id="named-entity-455">cysteine</named-entity> loops or other features dictate UBL specificity of E1-to-E2 transfer in autophagy.</p>
<p>In addition to having implications for autophagy, our data also broadly show how one E1 uses the same surfaces to bind distinctive elements from two different E2s. Although the mechanisms by which <named-entity id="named-entity-456">Atg7</named-entity> recruits <named-entity id="named-entity-457">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-458">Atg10</named-entity> differ from those by which canonical E1 UFDs recruit E2s (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 7</sir>), some common principles emerge: In all cases, E2s are anchored to E1 domains through surfaces remote from the active sites, with the E1 domains probably rotating to bring the E1 and E2 catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-459">cysteines</named-entity> into proximity for catalysis<bibr rid="b16 b25"/>. Furthermore, <named-entity id="named-entity-460">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-461">Atg10</named-entity> now join a long list of E2s for which key interactions involve the backside &#x3B2;-sheet<bibr rid="b35"/> (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2415-S1">Supplementary Fig. 7</sir>). Many E2s for ubiquitin, and also the SUMO E2 <named-entity id="named-entity-462">Ubc9</named-entity> (refs. <bibrinl rid="b36">36</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b37">37</bibrinl>,<bibrinl rid="b38">38</bibrinl>), backside bind noncovalently to their cognate UBL. This can promote polyUBL chain synthesis through unknown mechanisms<bibr rid="b35 b38"/>. For the ubiquitin E2 <named-entity id="named-entity-463">Ube2g2</named-entity>, backside binding to a helix from the E3 <named-entity id="named-entity-464">gp78</named-entity> allosterically promotes polyubiquitin chain synthesis<bibr rid="b39 b40"/>. Notably, the E2 Rad6 can backside bind in a mutually exclusive manner to ubiquitin or to a helix from the E3 <named-entity id="named-entity-465">Rad18</named-entity>, the latter restraining activity to monoubiquitination<bibr rid="b41"/>. As with ubiquitin and SUMO E2s, <named-entity id="named-entity-466">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-467">Atg10</named-entity> make numerous protein-protein interactions in addition to those with <named-entity id="named-entity-468">Atg7</named-entity>. It will be interesting in the future to learn whether other E2-mediated steps in autophagy, such as during <named-entity id="named-entity-469">Atg12</named-entity>~<named-entity id="named-entity-470">Atg5</named-entity> enhancement of <named-entity id="named-entity-471">Atg8</named-entity> transfer from <named-entity id="named-entity-472">Atg3</named-entity> to PE, also involve interactions near or at autophagy E2 backsides.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Methods</sectitle>
<online-methods>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Constructs, peptides and proteins for <i>in vitro</i> studies.</sectitle>
<p>All sequences in this study are from the budding yeast <i>S. cerevisiae</i>. Constructs were generated by standard methods and coding regions verified by automated sequencing. <named-entity id="named-entity-473">Atg7</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-474">Atg3</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-475">Atg3</named-entity>FR, <named-entity id="named-entity-476">Atg8</named-entity> and variants were prepared as described<bibr rid="b21"/>. <named-entity id="named-entity-477">Atg10</named-entity> was expressed as a GST fusion in RIL codon&#x2013;enhanced BL21(DE3) (Agilent), purified by glutathione affinity and following treatment with thrombin by anion exchange and gel-filtration chromatography. For <named-entity id="named-entity-478">Atg7</named-entity><i>cis</i>, His<sub>6</sub>-TEV-<named-entity id="named-entity-479">Atg7</named-entity> R511E) and GST-thrombin-<named-entity id="named-entity-480">Atg7</named-entity><sub>289&#x2013;630</sub> C507A E524R&#x2014;and for <named-entity id="named-entity-481">Atg7</named-entity><i>trans</i>, His<sub>6</sub>-TEV-<named-entity id="named-entity-482">Atg7</named-entity> C507A R511E and GST-thrombin-<named-entity id="named-entity-483">Atg7</named-entity><sub>289&#x2013;630</sub> E524R&#x2014;were coexpressed with the His<sub>6</sub> fusion from pRSF-Duet and the GST fusion from pGEX-4T1.</p>
<p>For the <named-entity id="named-entity-484">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-485">Atg3</named-entity> crystals, <named-entity id="named-entity-486">Atg3</named-entity> C41A C76A C83A (<named-entity id="named-entity-487">Atg3</named-entity>Cys234only) and <named-entity id="named-entity-488">Atg7</named-entity><sub>1&#x2013;613</sub> were reduced with 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-489">DTT</named-entity> and purified by using an SD200 column, in 20 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-490">HEPES</named-entity>, pH 7.0, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-491">NaCl</named-entity>. Approximately 0.5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-492">Atg3</named-entity>Cys234only was mixed with 5&#xD7; <named-entity id="named-entity-493">bismaleimidoethane</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-494">BMOE</named-entity>, Pierce) on ice for &gt;1 h, followed by desalting (PD-10, GE) to remove unreacted cross-linker. <named-entity id="named-entity-495">Atg3</named-entity>Cys234only~BMOE (3 &#x3BC;M) and <named-entity id="named-entity-496">Atg7</named-entity><sub>1&#x2013;613</sub> (1.5 &#x3BC;M) were mixed for 20 s, and the cross-linking was quenched with 50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-497">DTT</named-entity>. <named-entity id="named-entity-498">Atg7</named-entity><sub>1&#x2013;613</sub>~BMOE~<named-entity id="named-entity-499">Atg3</named-entity>Cys234only (referred to as <named-entity id="named-entity-500">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-501">Atg3</named-entity> in the main text) was purified by anion exchange and gel filtration into a final buffer of 50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-502">HEPES</named-entity>, pH 7.0, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-503">NaCl</named-entity>, 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-504">DTT</named-entity>, concentrated to 12.5 mg ml<super>&#x2212;1</super>, divided into aliquots, flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x2212;80 &#xB0;C. <named-entity id="named-entity-505">Atg10</named-entity> C26S C137S (<named-entity id="named-entity-506">Atg10</named-entity>Cys133only) cross-linked to <named-entity id="named-entity-507">Atg7</named-entity><sub>1&#x2013;613</sub> C39S C195S C375A (referred to as <named-entity id="named-entity-508">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-509">Atg10</named-entity> in the main text) was prepared similarly, except <named-entity id="named-entity-510">BMOE</named-entity> was added to ~0.2 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-511">Atg10</named-entity> C26S C137S; cross-linking was carried out with 1.2 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-512">Atg7</named-entity><sub>1&#x2013;613</sub> C39S C195S C375A and 2.4 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-513">Atg10</named-entity>Cys133only; the final buffer was 25 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-514">HEPES</named-entity>, pH 7.0, 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-515">NaCl</named-entity>, 5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-516">DTT</named-entity>; and <named-entity id="named-entity-517">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-518">Atg10</named-entity> was concentrated to 7 mg ml<super>&#x2212;1</super>. <named-entity id="named-entity-519">Atg7</named-entity>NTD K14A F16A D18A was prepared as described<bibr rid="b21"/>, except it was concentrated to ~90 mg ml<super>&#x2212;1</super> before crystallization.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Crystallization, data collection and structure determination.</sectitle>
<p>Crystals of <named-entity id="named-entity-520">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-521">Atg3</named-entity> were grown by microseeding a room-temperature sitting drop of 2 &#x3BC;l <named-entity id="named-entity-522">Atg7</named-entity><sub>1&#x2013;613</sub>~BMOE~<named-entity id="named-entity-523">Atg3</named-entity>Cys234only with 1.4 &#x3BC;l well solution of 100 mM sodium citrate, pH 5.8, 13.5% PEG 4000, 10% <named-entity id="named-entity-524">isopropanol</named-entity>, 5% <named-entity id="named-entity-525">dioxane</named-entity> and 88 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-526">ammonium sulfate</named-entity> and cryoprotected in well solution supplemented with 15% <named-entity id="named-entity-527">glycerol</named-entity> and 15% <named-entity id="named-entity-528">ethylene glycol</named-entity> before data collection at APS 24-ID-E (<i>&#x3BB;</i> = 0.9792 &#xC5;) at 100 K. Crystals of <named-entity id="named-entity-529">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-530">Atg10</named-entity> were grown by microseeding a room-temperature sitting drop of 400 nl <named-entity id="named-entity-531">Atg7</named-entity><sub>1&#x2013;613</sub> C39S C195S C375A~BMOE~<named-entity id="named-entity-532">Atg10</named-entity>Cys133only in 25 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-533">HEPES</named-entity>, pH 7.0, 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-534">NaCl</named-entity>, 5 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-535">DTT</named-entity> with 400 nl well solution containing 76.5 mM Na/K phosphate, pH 6.5, 9 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-536">Tris</named-entity>, pH 8.5, 153 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-537">NaCl</named-entity>, 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-538">glycine</named-entity>, 72 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-539">Na/K tartrate</named-entity>, 19.125% PEG 1000, 0.045% PEG 5000MME and 4.5% <named-entity id="named-entity-540">dioxane</named-entity> and cryoprotected in well solution supplemented with 30% <named-entity id="named-entity-541">glycerol</named-entity> before data collection at APS 24-ID-C (<i>&#x3BB;</i> = 0.9795 &#xC5;) at 100 K. Crystals of <named-entity id="named-entity-542">Atg7</named-entity>NTD K14A F16A D18A were grown at 4 &#xB0;C in 7.2% <named-entity id="named-entity-543">isopropanol</named-entity>, 50 mM citrate buffer, pH 4.1, and 0.1M <named-entity id="named-entity-544">potassium thiocyanate</named-entity> and cryoprotected in solution consisting of 75 &#x3BC;l well buffer mixed with 25 &#x3BC;l <named-entity id="named-entity-545">isopropanol</named-entity>, before data collection at ALS 8.2.2 (<i>&#x3BB;</i> = 0.979 &#xC5;) at 100 K.</p>
<p>Data were processed with HKL2000 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b42">42</bibrinl>). Phases were determined by molecular replacement using Phaser<bibr rid="b43"/> with the following search models. For <named-entity id="named-entity-546">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-547">Atg3</named-entity>: <named-entity id="named-entity-548">Atg7</named-entity>NTD<bibr rid="b21"/>, <named-entity id="named-entity-549">Atg7</named-entity>CTD<bibr rid="b21"/>, <named-entity id="named-entity-550">Atg3</named-entity> (lacking the flexible region)<bibr rid="b27"/>; for <named-entity id="named-entity-551">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-552">Atg10</named-entity>: <named-entity id="named-entity-553">Atg7</named-entity>NTD<bibr rid="b21"/> and <named-entity id="named-entity-554">Atg7</named-entity>CTD<bibr rid="b21"/>, with <named-entity id="named-entity-555">Atg10</named-entity> built manually into clear density through bootstrapping approaches; and for <named-entity id="named-entity-556">Atg7</named-entity>NTD K14A F16A D18A: <named-entity id="named-entity-557">Atg7</named-entity>NTD<bibr rid="b21"/> were used. The structures were completed by cycles of manual rebuilding by using Coot<bibr rid="b44"/> and refinement by using FFX<bibr rid="b45"/> and Phenix<bibr rid="b46"/>. For both copies of <named-entity id="named-entity-558">Atg3</named-entity> in the asymmetric unit, the first three turns of the handle-region helix were modeled into weak, but obviously helical, density for the backbone on the basis of the prior structure of uncomplexed <named-entity id="named-entity-559">Atg3</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b27">27</bibrinl>). Otherwise, several loops in <named-entity id="named-entity-560">Atg7</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-561">Atg3</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-562">Atg10</named-entity> and the <named-entity id="named-entity-563">BMOE</named-entity> cross-link not visible in the electron density were not modeled in the structures.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle><i>In vitro</i> biochemical and biophysical assays.</sectitle>
<p>Assays for pulse-chase transfer of [<super>32</super>P]<named-entity id="named-entity-564">Atg8</named-entity> from <named-entity id="named-entity-565">Atg7</named-entity> to <named-entity id="named-entity-566">Atg3</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-567">BMOE</named-entity> cross-linking between the single-<named-entity id="named-entity-568">cysteine</named-entity> version of <named-entity id="named-entity-569">Atg3</named-entity> (Cys234only) and <named-entity id="named-entity-570">Atg7</named-entity>, and <i>in vitro</i> ligation of <named-entity id="named-entity-571">Atg8</named-entity> to PE were performed as described previously<bibr rid="b21"/>. Cross-linking assays were performed at a range of concentrations of <named-entity id="named-entity-572">Atg7</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-573">Atg3</named-entity> (Cys234only) or <named-entity id="named-entity-574">Atg10</named-entity> (a single-<named-entity id="named-entity-575">cysteine</named-entity> version with Cys133only, with C26A and C137A), for between 30&#x2013;120 s, and results shown are similar to those obtained over a range of concentrations and times on different days. Cross-linking experiments using the <i>cis</i> and <i>trans</i> versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-576">Atg7</named-entity> in <figr rid="f2">Figure 2c</figr> contained 1 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-577">Atg7</named-entity> (<i>cis</i> or <i>trans</i>) and 2 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-578">Atg3</named-entity> or <named-entity id="named-entity-579">Atg10</named-entity>. <named-entity id="named-entity-580">Atg7</named-entity>x<named-entity id="named-entity-581">Atg3</named-entity> cross-linking experiments detected by western blotting contained 60 nM wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-582">Atg7</named-entity> and 120 nM <named-entity id="named-entity-583">Atg3</named-entity> (Cys234only). Reactions in <figr rid="f3">Figure 3f</figr> contained 60 nM wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-584">Atg7</named-entity> and 120 nM <named-entity id="named-entity-585">Atg10</named-entity> (Cys133only) and in <figr rid="f3">Figures 3g</figr> and <figr rid="f5">5b</figr> contained 150 nM <named-entity id="named-entity-586">Atg7</named-entity> and 300 nM <named-entity id="named-entity-587">Atg10</named-entity>. Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-588">Atg7</named-entity> western blots of the cross-linking assays used antibody (cat. no. SC8965, Santa Cruz) at 1:250 dilution. The reaction forcing <named-entity id="named-entity-589">Atg8</named-entity> onto <named-entity id="named-entity-590">Atg10</named-entity> in <figr rid="f3">Figure 3d</figr> contained 1 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-591">Atg7</named-entity>, 60 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-592">Atg8</named-entity>, 40 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-593">Atg10</named-entity> and 500 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-594">Atg3</named-entity><super>FRpep</super>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Yeast media and growth conditions.</sectitle>
<p>Yeast cells were grown in rich (YPD; 1% yeast extract, 2% peptone and 2% <named-entity id="named-entity-595">glucose</named-entity>) or synthetic minimal (SMD; 0.67% yeast nitrogen base, 2% <named-entity id="named-entity-596">glucose</named-entity> and auxotrophic amino acids and vitamins as needed) medium. For nitrogen-starvation conditions, synthetic medium lacking nitrogen (SD-N; 0.17% yeast nitrogen base without <named-entity id="named-entity-597">ammonium sulfate</named-entity> or amino acids and 2% <named-entity id="named-entity-598">glucose</named-entity>) was used.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Yeast plasmids and strains.</sectitle>
<p>pCu414, pCuPA416 and pGFPATG8(405) have been reported previously<bibr rid="b47 b48 b49"/>. To generate pCuATG3(414), the open reading frame of wild-type or mutant <i><named-entity id="named-entity-599">ATG3</named-entity></i> was amplified by PCR from the corresponding pGEX bacterial expression vector and cloned into the BamHI and SalI sites of pCu414. To generate pCuPAATG7(416), the open reading frame of wild-type or mutant <i><named-entity id="named-entity-600">ATG7</named-entity></i> was amplified by PCR from the corresponding pGEX bacterial expression vector and cloned into the ClaI and SalI sites of pCuPA416.</p>
<p>The yeast strains used in this study are KDM1222 (SEY6210 <i>GFP</i>-<i><named-entity id="named-entity-601">ATG8</named-entity>(405) <named-entity id="named-entity-602">atg3</named-entity></i>&#x394;<i>&#x2237;HIS3</i>, this study), KDM1223 (SEY6210 <i>GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-603">ATG8</named-entity>(405) <named-entity id="named-entity-604">atg7</named-entity></i>&#x394;<i>&#x2237;HIS3</i>, this study), KDM1225 (SEY6210 <i>GFP</i>-<i><named-entity id="named-entity-605">ATG8</named-entity>(405)</i>, this study), KDM1402 (SEY6210 <i><named-entity id="named-entity-606">pho13</named-entity></i>&#x394; <i><named-entity id="named-entity-607">pho8</named-entity></i>&#x394;<i>60 <named-entity id="named-entity-608">atg3</named-entity></i>&#x394;<i>&#x2237;LEU2</i>, this study), KDM1404 (SEY6210 <i><named-entity id="named-entity-609">pho13</named-entity></i>&#x394; <i><named-entity id="named-entity-610">pho8</named-entity></i>&#x394;<i>60 <named-entity id="named-entity-611">atg7</named-entity></i>&#x394;<i>&#x2237;LEU2</i>, this study), SEY6210 (MAT&#x3B1; <i>ura3-52 leu2-3,112 his3-</i>&#x394;<i>200 trp1-</i>&#x394;<i>901 lys2-801 suc2-</i>&#x394;<i>9 mel GAL</i><bibr rid="b50"/>) and WLY176 (SEY6210 <i><named-entity id="named-entity-612">pho13</named-entity></i>&#x394; <i><named-entity id="named-entity-613">pho8</named-entity></i>&#x394;<i>60</i> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b51">51</bibrinl>)).</p>
<p>For gene disruption, the entire coding regions were replaced with <i>Kluyvermomyces lactis LEU2</i> and <i>Saccharomyces kluyveri HIS3</i> genes by using PCR primers containing ~40 bases identical to the flanking regions of the open reading frames. To construct GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-614">Atg8</named-entity> strains, the integrative plasmid pGFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-615">ATG8</named-entity>(405) was linearized with AflII and integrated into the <i>LEU2</i> locus.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Yeast assays.</sectitle>
<p>The GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-616">Atg8</named-entity> processing and <named-entity id="named-entity-617">Pho8</named-entity>&#x394;60 assays to monitor autophagy progression were performed as previously described<bibr rid="b52"/>. For the alkaline phosphatase assay, yeast were grown in either synthetic minimal SMD (+) or nitrogen-starvation SD-N (&#x2212;) medium, as indicated. Two A<sub>600</sub> equivalents of yeast cells were harvested and resuspended in 150 &#x3BC;l lysis buffer (20 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-618">PIPES</named-entity>, pH 7.0, 0.5% Triton X-100, 50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-619">KCl</named-entity>, 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-620">potassium acetate</named-entity>, 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-621">MgSO<sub>4</sub></named-entity>, 10 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-622">ZnSO<sub>4</sub></named-entity> and 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-623">PMSF</named-entity>). The cells were lysed by vortexing with glass beads for 5 min, extract (50 &#x3BC;l) was added to 450 &#x3BC;l reaction buffer (250 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-624">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 8.5, 0.4% Triton X-100, 10 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-625">MgSO<sub>4</sub></named-entity> and 1.25 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-626">nitrophenylphosphate</named-entity>), and samples were incubated for ~15 min at 30 &#xB0;C before reactions were terminated by addition of 500 &#x3BC;l of stop buffer (2 M <named-entity id="named-entity-627">glycine</named-entity>, pH 11). Production of <named-entity id="named-entity-628">nitrophenol</named-entity> was monitored by measuring the absorbance at 400 nm with a spectrophotometer (DU-640B; Beckman Coulter), and the <named-entity id="named-entity-629">nitrophenol</named-entity> concentration was calculated by using Beer's law with &#x25B;400 = 18,000 M<super>&#x2212;1</super> cm<super>&#x2212;1</super>. Protein concentration in the extracts was measured with the Pierce BCA assay (Thermo Fisher Scientific), and one activity unit was defined as nmol <named-entity id="named-entity-630">nitrophenol</named-entity>/min/mg protein. The activity for wild type with empty vector was set to 100%, and the other activities were normalized. Error bars (s.d.) were obtained from three independent repeats. Pgk1 loading controls are shown. Assays monitoring <named-entity id="named-entity-631">Atg8</named-entity>~PE formation and GFP-<named-entity id="named-entity-632">Atg8</named-entity> localization in yeast were performed as previously described<bibr rid="b53 b54"/>. Antibodies for <named-entity id="named-entity-633">Atg8</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b55">55</bibrinl>) and <named-entity id="named-entity-634">Atg3</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b56">56</bibrinl>) were used at 1:3,000 and 1:2,000 dilutions, respectively. GFP was detected with anti-YFP antibody JL-8 (Clontech cat. no. 632381) at 1:5,000 dilution. Anti-Pgk1 was provided by J. Thorner (University of California, Berkeley, California, USA) and used at 1:500,000 dilution. Anti&#x2013;PA tag western blots used cat. no. Z0113 (Dako, Denmark; no longer commercially available) antibody at 1:10,000 dilution.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Accession codes.</sectitle>
<p>Structure factor data and coordinates for <named-entity id="named-entity-635">Atg7</named-entity>NTD K14A F16A D18A, <named-entity id="named-entity-636">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-637">Atg10</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-638">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-639">Atg3</named-entity> have been deposited to the RCS PDB, with accession codes <accession type="pdb" status="primary">4GSJ</accession>, <accession type="pdb" status="primary">4GSK</accession> and <accession type="pdb" status="primary">4GSL</accession>, respectively.</p>
</sec>
</online-methods>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Author contributions</sectitle>
<p>S.E.K., J.L.O., D.M.D., I.K. and T.D.F. performed the X-ray crystallography experiments. S.E.K., A.M.T., S.Y., J.L.O. and A.D. purified wild-type and mutant proteins and performed <i>in vitro</i> biochemical assays. K.M. performed all yeast experiments. B.A.S., along with S.E.K. and D.J.K., oversaw experiments and prepared the manuscript with input from all authors.</p>
</sec>
</bdy>
<bm>
<objects>
<fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
<figtl>Overall structures of the autophagy E1 <named-entity id="named-entity-645">Atg7</named-entity> and E2s <named-entity id="named-entity-646">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-647">Atg10</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Structure of <named-entity id="named-entity-648">Atg7</named-entity> from the complex with <named-entity id="named-entity-649">Atg3</named-entity> is shown in violet, indicating key structural features involved in E2 binding on one of the two protomers in the <named-entity id="named-entity-650">Atg7</named-entity> homodimer. The adenylation active site and catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-651">cysteine</named-entity>&#x2013;containing CTD from the opposite protomer (pink) was superimposed with all other structures of <named-entity id="named-entity-652">Atg7</named-entity> (green, apo, ref. <bibrinl rid="b22">22</bibrinl>, PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">3VH2</accession>; gray, protomer 1 from the cross-linked (denoted with x) <named-entity id="named-entity-653">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-654">Atg3</named-entity> complex; blue and light blue, the two protomers from the cross-linked <named-entity id="named-entity-655">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-656">Atg10</named-entity> complex) showing different NTD-CTD orientations and catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-657">cysteine</named-entity> locations among the structures. The two proteins from each dimer are indicated by (1) and (2). (<b>b</b>) Crystal structures of unbound <named-entity id="named-entity-658">Atg3</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b27">27</bibrinl>) (gray, PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">2DYT</accession>), <named-entity id="named-entity-659">Atg7</named-entity>-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-660">Atg3</named-entity> (cyan), <named-entity id="named-entity-661">Atg7</named-entity>-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-662">Atg10</named-entity> (slate) and the ubiquitin E2 <named-entity id="named-entity-663">UbcH5B</named-entity> (red, PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">2C4O</accession>) superimposed over their E2 core domains, indicating key structural features. Catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-664">cysteine</named-entity> thiols are shown as spheres, except in <named-entity id="named-entity-665">Atg10</named-entity>, in which the <named-entity id="named-entity-666">cysteine</named-entity> loop (dotted lines) is not visible in the electron density, so a sphere marks the location of the C&#x3B1; from the preceding Pro132. HR, handle region.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
<figtl>Overall <i>trans</i> architectures of autophagy E1&#x2013;E2 complexes.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Structure of catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-667">cysteine</named-entity>-to-<named-entity id="named-entity-668">cysteine</named-entity> cross-linked <named-entity id="named-entity-669">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-670">Atg3</named-entity> complex, with the two <named-entity id="named-entity-671">Atg7</named-entity> protomers in the homodimer in violet and pink, the two <named-entity id="named-entity-672">Atg3</named-entity> molecules in teal and cyan and their catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-673">cysteines</named-entity> shown as spheres. In the crystal, <named-entity id="named-entity-674">Atg3</named-entity> binds noncovalently to the NTD from one <named-entity id="named-entity-675">Atg7</named-entity> protomer, and its catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-676">cysteine</named-entity>, approaching that from the opposite <named-entity id="named-entity-677">Atg7</named-entity> in the homodimer, is circled. The circled <named-entity id="named-entity-678">cysteines</named-entity> are cross-linked by <named-entity id="named-entity-679">BMOE</named-entity>. The two proteins from each dimer are indicated by (1) and (2). (<b>b</b>) Structure of catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-680">cysteine</named-entity>-to-<named-entity id="named-entity-681">cysteine</named-entity> cross-linked <named-entity id="named-entity-682">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-683">Atg10</named-entity> complex, with the two <named-entity id="named-entity-684">Atg7</named-entity> protomers in the homodimer in violet and pink, the two <named-entity id="named-entity-685">Atg10</named-entity> molecules in teal and cyan. <named-entity id="named-entity-686">Atg7</named-entity> catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-687">cysteines</named-entity> are shown as spheres, as is the C&#x3B1; from Pro132 (molecule 1) and His131 (molecule 2) of <named-entity id="named-entity-688">Atg10</named-entity>. For the <named-entity id="named-entity-689">Atg10s</named-entity>, the catalytic Cys133 and loop are represented with dotted lines. In the crystal, <named-entity id="named-entity-690">Atg10</named-entity> binds noncovalently to the NTD from one <named-entity id="named-entity-691">Atg7</named-entity> protomer, and its catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-692">cysteine</named-entity> loop, approaching that from the opposite <named-entity id="named-entity-693">Atg7</named-entity> in the homodimer, is circled. The circled <named-entity id="named-entity-694">cysteines</named-entity> are cross-linked by <named-entity id="named-entity-695">BMOE</named-entity>. (<b>c</b>) Coomassie-stained SDS-PAGE showing <named-entity id="named-entity-696">BMOE</named-entity> cross-linking between catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-697">cysteine</named-entity>&#x2013;only versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-698">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-699">Atg10</named-entity> and <i>cis</i>-<named-entity id="named-entity-700">Atg7</named-entity>c or <i>trans</i>-<named-entity id="named-entity-701">Atg7</named-entity>t <named-entity id="named-entity-702">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-703">Atg7</named-entity>CTD heterodimers. In <named-entity id="named-entity-704">Atg7</named-entity>c, only full-length <named-entity id="named-entity-705">Atg7</named-entity> has an active site <named-entity id="named-entity-706">cysteine</named-entity>; in <named-entity id="named-entity-707">Atg7</named-entity>t, only the CTD has a catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-708">cysteine</named-entity>. Control reactions were pretreated with <named-entity id="named-entity-709">DTT</named-entity> as indicated to eliminate <named-entity id="named-entity-710">BMOE</named-entity> cross-linking. The numbers on the left of the blot are molecular weight standards.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-711">Atg7</named-entity>NTD shoulder groove interactions with autophagy E2s.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>,<b>b</b>) Close-up view of the <named-entity id="named-entity-712">Atg7</named-entity> (violet) shoulder groove interactions with the helix from <named-entity id="named-entity-713">Atg3</named-entity>FR (cyan) (<b>a</b>) or with the <named-entity id="named-entity-714">Atg10</named-entity> &#x3B2;-hairpin (cyan) (<b>b</b>). Loops not modeled in the <named-entity id="named-entity-715">Atg3</named-entity> structure are shown as dotted lines. (<b>c</b>) Close-up of shoulder grooves upon superimposing NTDs from <named-entity id="named-entity-716">Atg7</named-entity> (pink and violet) in complexes with <named-entity id="named-entity-717">Atg3</named-entity> (cyan, bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-718">Atg7</named-entity>(3)) and <named-entity id="named-entity-719">Atg10</named-entity> (slate, bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-720">Atg7</named-entity>(10)). (<b>d</b>) Coomassie-stained SDS-PAGE showing artificial <named-entity id="named-entity-721">Atg8</named-entity> conjugation to <named-entity id="named-entity-722">Atg10</named-entity>, in the absence or presence of a peptide corresponding to residues 130&#x2013;142 from the <named-entity id="named-entity-723">Atg3</named-entity>FR (<named-entity id="named-entity-724">Atg3</named-entity><super>FRpep</super>). (<b>e</b>,<b>f</b>) Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-725">Atg7</named-entity> western blot showing <named-entity id="named-entity-726">BMOE</named-entity> cross-linking between a catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-727">cysteine</named-entity>&#x2013;only version of <named-entity id="named-entity-728">Atg3</named-entity> (<b>e</b>) or <named-entity id="named-entity-729">Atg10</named-entity> (<b>f</b>) and wild-type (WT) and indicated shoulder groove mutants of <named-entity id="named-entity-730">Atg7</named-entity>. (<b>g</b>) Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-731">Atg7</named-entity> western blot showing <named-entity id="named-entity-732">BMOE</named-entity> cross-linking between a catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-733">cysteine</named-entity>&#x2013;only version of <named-entity id="named-entity-734">Atg10</named-entity> with otherwise wild-type sequence, or with residues 86&#x2013;93 of the &#x3B2;-hairpin deleted, and <named-entity id="named-entity-735">Atg7</named-entity>.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-736">Atg7</named-entity> under-wing and NTD-CTD&#x2013;junction interactions with <named-entity id="named-entity-737">Atg3</named-entity>'s backside and edge.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Close-up of the <named-entity id="named-entity-738">Atg7</named-entity> (violet) under-wing interactions with <named-entity id="named-entity-739">Atg3</named-entity> (cyan), focused on the central hydrophobic cluster at the heart of the interaction. Interacting side chains are shown as sticks with oxygens in red and nitrogens in blue, with electrostatic interactions noted with dashed lines. (<b>b</b>,<b>c</b>) Autoradiograms showing time course of pulse-chase [<super>32</super>P]<named-entity id="named-entity-740">Atg8</named-entity> transfer from wild-type or mutant versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-741">Atg7</named-entity> to wild-type or backside mutant versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-742">Atg3</named-entity> (<b>b</b>) or also a shoulder groove mutant of <named-entity id="named-entity-743">Atg7</named-entity> (<b>c</b>). (<b>d</b>) Western analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-744">BMOE</named-entity> cross-linking between a catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-745">cysteine</named-entity>&#x2013;only version of <named-entity id="named-entity-746">Atg3</named-entity> and the indicated under-wing mutants of <named-entity id="named-entity-747">Atg7</named-entity> or mutants with a GGSG insertion after <named-entity id="named-entity-748">Atg7</named-entity>'s Leu291 or deletion of residues 290&#x2013;294 at the NTD-CTD junction. (<b>e</b>,<b>f</b>) Western analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-749">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation in wild-type or <i><named-entity id="named-entity-750">atg7</named-entity></i>&#x394; yeast expressing PA-tagged (P-) wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-751">Atg7</named-entity> or mutants (<b>e</b>) or in wild-type or <i><named-entity id="named-entity-752">atg3</named-entity></i>&#x394; yeast expressing wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-753">Atg3</named-entity> or mutants (<b>f</b>). Presence or absence of nitrogen in the medium is indicated. Pgk1 is shown as a loading control. (<b>g</b>,<b>h</b>) Coomassie-stained urea SDS-PAGE showing <i>in vitro</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-754">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation in assays with wild-type or the indicated under-wing mutant versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-755">Atg7</named-entity> (<b>g</b>) or the indicated backside and distal-edge mutant versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-756">Atg3</named-entity> (<b>h</b>). (<b>i</b>) Close-up of the <named-entity id="named-entity-757">Atg7</named-entity> (violet) NTD-CTD junction interaction with <named-entity id="named-entity-758">Atg3</named-entity> (cyan). (<b>j</b>) Autoradiogram showing time course of pulse-chase [<super>32</super>P]<named-entity id="named-entity-759">Atg8</named-entity> transfer to <named-entity id="named-entity-760">Atg3</named-entity> from wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-761">Atg7</named-entity> or a version with the NTD-CTD junction (residues 290&#x2013;294) deleted.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f5" type="bmp" entname="figf5">
<figtl><named-entity id="named-entity-762">Atg7</named-entity> under-wing and NTD-CTD junction interactions with <named-entity id="named-entity-763">Atg10</named-entity>'s backside and edge.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Top, close-up of the <named-entity id="named-entity-764">Atg7</named-entity> (violet) under-wing and NTD-CTD junction interactions with <named-entity id="named-entity-765">Atg10</named-entity> (cyan), with zoomed-in view of the interactions emanating from the &#x3B2;-hairpin shown below rotated ~45&#xB0; around the <i>y</i> axis. Interacting side chains are shown as sticks with oxygens in red and nitrogens in blue, with electrostatic interactions noted with dashed lines. Red x denotes <named-entity id="named-entity-766">BMOE</named-entity> cross-link between <named-entity id="named-entity-767">Atg7</named-entity> Cys507 and <named-entity id="named-entity-768">Atg10</named-entity> Cys133. (<b>b</b>) Anti-<named-entity id="named-entity-769">Atg7</named-entity> western blot showing <named-entity id="named-entity-770">BMOE</named-entity> cross-linking between a catalytic <named-entity id="named-entity-771">cysteine</named-entity>&#x2013;only version of <named-entity id="named-entity-772">Atg10</named-entity> and the indicated under-wing (left) mutants of <named-entity id="named-entity-773">Atg7</named-entity> or versions with a GGSG insertion after <named-entity id="named-entity-774">Atg7</named-entity>'s Leu291 or deletion of residues 290&#x2013;294 at the NTD-CTD junction (right). (<b>c</b>) Structures of the <named-entity id="named-entity-775">Atg7</named-entity> complexes cross-linked to <named-entity id="named-entity-776">Atg10</named-entity> (violet and cyan) or to <named-entity id="named-entity-777">Atg3</named-entity> (gray and slate) superimposed on either the <named-entity id="named-entity-778">Atg7</named-entity>NTD (top) or over the <named-entity id="named-entity-779">Atg10</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-780">Atg3</named-entity> E2 core domains (bottom).</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f6" type="bmp" entname="figf6">
<figtl>The <named-entity id="named-entity-781">Atg7</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-782">Atg3</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-783">Atg10</named-entity> catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-784">cysteine</named-entity> loops: autophagy E1 and E2 active site conformational variability.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Superposition of prior structure of <named-entity id="named-entity-785">Atg3</named-entity> alone (gray, PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">2DYT</accession>)<bibr rid="b27"/> and <named-entity id="named-entity-786">Atg7</named-entity>-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-787">Atg3</named-entity> (cyan) reveals reorientation of the catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-788">cysteine</named-entity> loop. <named-entity id="named-entity-789">Atg7</named-entity> is not shown, for simplification. (<b>b</b>) Superposition of <named-entity id="named-entity-790">Atg7</named-entity>-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-791">Atg3</named-entity> (cyan) and <named-entity id="named-entity-792">Atg10</named-entity> (slate) reveals common positions for conserved <named-entity id="named-entity-793">tyrosine</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-794">histidine</named-entity> residues. (<b>c</b>) Autoradiograms showing time course of [<super>32</super>P]<named-entity id="named-entity-795">Atg8</named-entity> transfer from <named-entity id="named-entity-796">Atg7</named-entity> to wild-type or Y179A or H232A mutant versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-797">Atg3</named-entity>. (<b>d</b>) Coomassie-stained urea SDS-PAGE showing <i>in vitro</i> <named-entity id="named-entity-798">Atg8</named-entity> lipidation in assays containing wild-type or Y179A or H232A mutant versions of <named-entity id="named-entity-799">Atg3</named-entity>. (<b>e</b>,<b>f</b>) <named-entity id="named-entity-800">Pho8</named-entity>&#x394;60 activity monitored in wild-type, <i><named-entity id="named-entity-801">atg3</named-entity></i>&#x394; or <i><named-entity id="named-entity-802">atg10</named-entity></i>&#x394; yeast harboring vectors expressing wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-803">Atg3</named-entity> (<b>e</b>), PA-tagged wild-type <named-entity id="named-entity-804">Atg10</named-entity> (<b>f</b>) or mutants. Error bars (s.d.) were obtained from three independent repeats. Western blot for <named-entity id="named-entity-805">Atg3</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-806">Atg10</named-entity> and Pgk1 loading control is shown below. SMD, synthetic minimal medium; SD-N, synthetic medium lacking nitrogen. (<b>g</b>) Superposition of the adenylation domains from prior structures<bibr rid="b21 b22 b23"/> of unbound <named-entity id="named-entity-807">Atg7</named-entity> (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">3VH2</accession>) or <named-entity id="named-entity-808">Atg8</named-entity>-bound <named-entity id="named-entity-809">Atg7</named-entity>CTD (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">3RUI</accession>) and the cross-linked <named-entity id="named-entity-810">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-811">Atg3</named-entity> complex described here, with the two <named-entity id="named-entity-812">Atg7</named-entity> protomers colored in light and dark gray, orange and brown, and pink and violet, respectively. <named-entity id="named-entity-813">Atg3</named-entity> is shown in cyan. Catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-814">cysteine</named-entity> sulfur atoms (or an oxygen in PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">3RUI</accession>, which contains a C507S mutation) are shown as spheres.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f7" type="bmp" entname="figf7">
<figtl>Models of autophagy UBL&#x2013;E1&#x2013;E2 complexes.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Model of portion of homodimeric <named-entity id="named-entity-815">Atg7</named-entity> (violet and pink, with <named-entity id="named-entity-816">cysteine</named-entity> loop in red and catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-817">cysteine</named-entity> sulfur a sphere) thioester linked to <named-entity id="named-entity-818">Atg8</named-entity> (lime, with C terminus shown as sphere) bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-819">Atg3</named-entity> (cyan, with catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-820">cysteine</named-entity> sulfur a sphere). Loops in <named-entity id="named-entity-821">Atg3</named-entity> not visible in the complex with <named-entity id="named-entity-822">Atg7</named-entity> are shown as dotted lines. (<b>b</b>) Model of portion of homodimeric <named-entity id="named-entity-823">Atg7</named-entity> (violet and pink, with <named-entity id="named-entity-824">cysteine</named-entity> loop in red and catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-825">cysteine</named-entity> sulfur a sphere) thioester linked to <named-entity id="named-entity-826">Atg12</named-entity> (lime, with C terminus shown as sphere) bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-827">Atg10</named-entity> (cyan, with C&#x3B1; from Pro132 preceding the catalytic Cys133 a sphere). The catalytic-<named-entity id="named-entity-828">cysteine</named-entity> loop in <named-entity id="named-entity-829">Atg10</named-entity> not visible in the complex with <named-entity id="named-entity-830">Atg7</named-entity> is shown as a dotted line.</p></caption></fig>
<table id="t1" tocentry="0" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0" orient="port" pgwide="0" tabcols="4">
<title>Data collection and refinement statistics</title>
<tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="center">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<spanspec namest="1" nameend="4" spanname="1to4" align="left"/>
<thead valign="top">
<row rowsep="1"><entry/>
<entry align="center"><named-entity id="named-entity-640">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;BMOE&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-641">Atg3</named-entity></entry>
<entry align="center"><named-entity id="named-entity-642">Atg7</named-entity>&#x2013;BMOE&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-643">Atg10</named-entity></entry>
<entry align="center"><named-entity id="named-entity-644">Atg7</named-entity>NTD (K14A F16A D18A)</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row><entry><b>Data collection</b></entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>Space group</entry>
<entry align="center"><i>C</i>2</entry>
<entry align="center"><i>P</i>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2</entry>
<entry align="center"><i>P</i>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2</entry></row>
<row><entry>Cell dimensions</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;<i>a</i>, <i>b</i>, <i>c</i> (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">281.6, 125.1, 71.1</entry>
<entry align="center">120.6, 146.2, 108.4</entry>
<entry align="center">56.8, 74.6, 76.5</entry></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;<i>&#x3B1;</i>, <i>&#x3B2;</i>, <i>&#x3B3;</i> (&#xB0;)</entry>
<entry align="center">90, 103.3, 90</entry>
<entry align="center">90, 90, 90</entry>
<entry align="center">90, 90, 90</entry></row>
<row><entry>Resolution (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">40&#x2013;2.7 (2.8&#x2013;2.7)</entry>
<entry align="center">50&#x2013;2.9 (3.0&#x2013;2.9)</entry>
<entry align="center">50&#x2013;1.7 (1.76&#x2013;1.70)</entry></row>
<row><entry><i>R</i><sub>sym</sub></entry>
<entry align="center">0.08 (0.56)</entry>
<entry align="center">0.13 (0.77)</entry>
<entry align="center">0.06 (0.32)</entry></row>
<row><entry><i>I</i> / &#x3C3;<i>I</i></entry>
<entry align="center">17.8 (1.8)</entry>
<entry align="center">9.9 (1.6)</entry>
<entry align="center">46.4 (3.0)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Completeness (%)</entry>
<entry align="center">99.5 (99.0)</entry>
<entry align="center">99.1 (99.3)</entry>
<entry align="center">96.3 (77.4)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Redundancy</entry>
<entry align="center">4.1 (4.0)</entry>
<entry align="center">3.2 (3.3)</entry>
<entry align="center">6.5 (4.0)</entry></row>
<row><entry><b>Refinement</b></entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>Resolution (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">37&#x2013;2.7</entry>
<entry align="center">50&#x2013;2.9</entry>
<entry align="center">46&#x2013;1.7</entry></row>
<row><entry>No. reflections</entry>
<entry align="center">64,763</entry>
<entry align="center">42,709</entry>
<entry align="center">35,168</entry></row>
<row><entry><i>R</i><sub>work</sub> / <i>R</i><sub>free</sub></entry>
<entry align="center">0.193 / 0.246</entry>
<entry align="center">0.236 / 0.286</entry>
<entry align="center">0.176 / 0.207</entry></row>
<row><entry>No. atoms</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Protein</entry>
<entry align="center">12,507</entry>
<entry align="center">11,423</entry>
<entry align="center">2,329</entry></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Ligand/ion</entry>
<entry align="center">2</entry>
<entry align="center">2</entry>
<entry align="center">0</entry></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Water</entry>
<entry align="center">43</entry>
<entry align="center">0</entry>
<entry align="center">257</entry></row>
<row><entry><i>B</i> factors</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Protein</entry>
<entry align="center">70.62</entry>
<entry align="center">79.67</entry>
<entry align="center">29.72</entry></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Ligand/ion</entry>
<entry align="center">80.23</entry>
<entry align="center">90.41</entry>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Water</entry>
<entry align="center">45.88</entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">38.55</entry></row>
<row><entry>R.m.s. deviations</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Bond lengths (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">0.009</entry>
<entry align="center">0.004</entry>
<entry align="center">0.006</entry></row>
<row rowsep="1"><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Bond angles (&#xB0;)</entry>
<entry align="center">1.214</entry>
<entry align="center">0.842</entry>
<entry align="center">1.005</entry></row>
<row>
<entry spanname="1to4" align="left"><fn id="t1-fn1" type="footnote"><p>One crystal was used per data set. Values in parentheses are for highest-resolution shell.</p></fn></entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</objects>
<ack><p>This work was supported by American Lebanese Syrian Associated Charities (ALSAC), the Howard Hughes Medical Institute, St. Jude Cancer Center grant 5P30CA021765 and US National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant R01GM077053 to B.A.S. and NIH grant R01GM053396 to D.J.K. B.A.S. is an Investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. We are grateful to C. Regni and A. Williams for help in early stages of this project, M. Frank and C. Rock (St. Jude Children's Research Hospital, Memphis, Tennessee, USA) for providing liposomes and D.W. Miller, S. Bozeman, D.J. Miller, Y. Qiu and J. Bollinger for administrative, computational or technical support. The Northeastern Collaborative Access Team is supported by NIH National Center for Research Resources RR-15301, Advanced Photon Source (APS) by US Department of Energy (US DOE) W-31-109-ENG-38, Advanced Light Source (ALS) by US DOE DE-AC02-05CH11231. Anti-Pgk1 antibody was provided by J. Thorner (University of California, Berkeley, California, USA).</p></ack>
<audecl conflct="no"/>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ohsumi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mizushima</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl>Two ubiquitin-like conjugation systems essential for autophagy</atl>. <jtl>Semin. Cell Dev. Biol.</jtl> <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>231</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>236</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Nakatogawa</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Suzuki</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kamada</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ohsumi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <atl>Dynamics and diversity in autophagy mechanisms: lessons from yeast</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>458</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>467</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Geng</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The Atg8 and Atg12 ubiquitin-like conjugation systems in macroautophagy</atl>. <jtl>EMBO Rep.</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>859</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>864</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kirkin</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>A role for NBR1 in autophagosomal degradation of ubiquitinated substrates</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>33</vid>, <ppf>505</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>516</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lamark</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kirkin</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dikic</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Johansen</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl>NBR1 and p62 as cargo receptors for selective autophagy of ubiquitinated targets</atl>. <jtl>Cell Cycle</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>1986</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1990</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hanada</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The Atg12-Atg5 conjugate has a novel E3-like activity for protein lipidation in autophagy</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>282</vid>, <ppf>37298</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>37302</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Suzuki</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The pre-autophagosomal structure organized by concerted functions of <i>APG</i> genes is essential for autophagosome formation</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>5971</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5981</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mizushima</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Dissection of autophagosome formation using Apg5-deficient mouse embryonic stem cells</atl>. <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>152</vid>, <ppf>657</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>668</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kuma</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mizushima</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ishihara</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ohsumi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <atl>Formation of the approximately 350-kDa Apg12-Apg5&#xB7;Apg16 multimeric complex, mediated by Apg16 oligomerization, is essential for autophagy in yeast</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>277</vid>, <ppf>18619</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>18625</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Suzuki</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ohsumi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <atl>Molecular machinery of autophagosome formation in yeast, <i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i></atl>. <jtl>FEBS Lett.</jtl> <vid>581</vid>, <ppf>2156</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2161</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Fujita</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The Atg16L complex specifies the site of LC3 lipidation for membrane biogenesis in autophagy</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Biol. Cell</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>2092</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2100</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Shintani</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Autophagy in health and disease: a double-edged sword</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>306</vid>, <ppf>990</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>995</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kundu</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Thompson</snm>, <fnm>C.B.</fnm></refau> <atl>Autophagy: basic principles and relevance to disease</atl>. <jtl>Annu. Rev. Pathol.</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>427</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>455</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Levine</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kroemer</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Autophagy in the pathogenesis of disease</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>132</vid>, <ppf>27</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>42</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mizushima</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Levine</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cuervo</snm>, <fnm>A.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Autophagy fights disease through cellular self-digestion</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>451</vid>, <ppf>1069</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1075</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Schulman</snm>, <fnm>B.A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Harper</snm>, <fnm>J.W.</fnm></refau> <atl>Ubiquitin-like protein activation by E1 enzymes: the apex for downstream signalling pathways</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>319</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>331</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Walden</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The structure of the APPBP1&#x2013;UBA3-NEDD8-ATP complex reveals the basis for selective ubiquitin-like protein activation by an E1</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>1427</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1437</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Walden</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Podgorski</snm>, <fnm>M.S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schulman</snm>, <fnm>B.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Insights into the ubiquitin transfer cascade from the structure of the activating enzyme for NEDD8</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>422</vid>, <ppf>330</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>334</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lois</snm>, <fnm>L.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lima</snm>, <fnm>C.D.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structures of the SUMO E1 provide mechanistic insights into SUMO activation and E2 recruitment to E1</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>24</vid>, <ppf>439</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>451</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schindelin</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structural insights into E1-catalyzed ubiquitin activation and transfer to conjugating enzymes</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>134</vid>, <ppf>268</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>278</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Taherbhoy</snm>, <fnm>A.M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Atg8 transfer from Atg7 to Atg3: a distinctive E1&#x2013;E2 architecture and mechanism in the autophagy pathway</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>451</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>461</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Noda</snm>, <fnm>N.N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Structural basis of Atg8 activation by a homodimeric E1, Atg7</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>462</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>475</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hong</snm>, <fnm>S.B.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Insights into noncanonical E1 enzyme activation from the structure of autophagic E1 Atg7 with Atg8</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>1323</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1330</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Olsen</snm>, <fnm>S.K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Capili</snm>, <fnm>A.D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lu</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tan</snm>, <fnm>D.S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lima</snm>, <fnm>C.D.</fnm></refau> <atl>Active site remodelling accompanies thioester bond formation in the SUMO E1</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>463</vid>, <ppf>906</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>912</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Huang</snm>, <fnm>D.T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Structural basis for recruitment of Ubc12 by an E2 binding domain in NEDD8's E1</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>341</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>350</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Tokg&#xF6;z</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>E1&#x2013;E2 interactions in ubiquitin and Nedd8 ligation pathways</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>287</vid>, <ppf>311</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>321</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yamada</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The crystal structure of Atg3, an autophagy-related ubiquitin carrier protein (E2) enzyme that mediates Atg8 lipidation</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>282</vid>, <ppf>8036</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>8043</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yamaguchi</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Structural insights into Atg10-mediated formation of the autophagy-essential Atg12-Atg5 conjugate</atl>. <jtl>Structure</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>1244</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1254</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Noda</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Matsuura</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wada</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ohsumi</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <atl>Novel system for monitoring autophagy in the yeast <i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i></atl>. <jtl>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</jtl> <vid>210</vid>, <ppf>126</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>132</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Shintani</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Cargo proteins facilitate the formation of transport vesicles in the cytoplasm to vacuole targeting pathway</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>279</vid>, <ppf>29889</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>29894</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b31"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ichimura</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>A ubiquitin-like system mediates protein lipidation</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>408</vid>, <ppf>488</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>492</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b32"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mizushima</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>A protein conjugation system essential for autophagy</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>395</vid>, <ppf>395</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>398</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b33"><reftxt><refau><snm>Tanida</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tanida-Miyake</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Komatsu</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ueno</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kominami</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl>Human Apg3p/Aut1p homologue is an authentic E2 enzyme for multiple substrates, GATE-16, GABARAP, and MAP-LC3, and facilitates the conjugation of hApg12p to hApg5p</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>277</vid>, <ppf>13739</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>13744</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b34"><reftxt><refau><snm>Radoshevich</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>ATG12 conjugation to ATG3 regulates mitochondrial homeostasis and cell death</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>142</vid>, <ppf>590</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>600</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b35"><reftxt><refau><snm>Brzovic</snm>, <fnm>P.S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lissounov</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Christensen</snm>, <fnm>D.E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hoyt</snm>, <fnm>D.W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klevit</snm>, <fnm>R.E.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>UbcH5/ubiquitin noncovalent complex is required for processive BRCA1-directed ubiquitination</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>873</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>880</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b36"><reftxt><refau><snm>Capili</snm>, <fnm>A.D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lima</snm>, <fnm>C.D.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structure and analysis of a complex between SUMO and Ubc9 illustrates features of a conserved E2-Ubl interaction</atl>. <jtl>J. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>369</vid>, <ppf>608</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>618</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b37"><reftxt><refau><snm>Duda</snm>, <fnm>D.M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Structure of a SUMO-binding-motif mimic bound to Smt3p-Ubc9p: conservation of a non-covalent ubiquitin-like protein-E2 complex as a platform for selective interactions within a SUMO pathway</atl>. <jtl>J. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>369</vid>, <ppf>619</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>630</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b38"><reftxt><refau><snm>Knipscheer</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>van Dijk</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Olsen</snm>, <fnm>J.V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mann</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sixma</snm>, <fnm>T.K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Noncovalent interaction between Ubc9 and SUMO promotes SUMO chain formation</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>26</vid>, <ppf>2797</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2807</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b39"><reftxt><refau><snm>Das</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Allosteric activation of E2-RING finger-mediated ubiquitylation by a structurally defined specific E2-binding region of gp78</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>34</vid>, <ppf>674</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>685</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b40"><reftxt><refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Mechanistic insights into active site-associated polyubiquitination by the ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme Ube2g2</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>106</vid>, <ppf>3722</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3727</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b41"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hibbert</snm>, <fnm>R.G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Huang</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Boelens</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sixma</snm>, <fnm>T.K.</fnm></refau> <atl>E3 ligase Rad18 promotes monoubiquitination rather than ubiquitin chain formation by E2 enzyme Rad6</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>108</vid>, <ppf>5590</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5595</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b42"><reftxt><refau><snm>Otwinowski</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Minor</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <atl>Processing of X-ray diffraction data collected in oscillation mode</atl>. <jtl>Methods Enzymol.</jtl> <vid>276</vid>, <ppf>307</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>326</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b43"><reftxt><refau><snm>McCoy</snm>, <fnm>A.J.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Phaser crystallographic software</atl>. <jtl>J. Appl. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>658</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>674</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b44"><reftxt><refau><snm>Emsley</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lohkamp</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Scott</snm>, <fnm>W.G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cowtan</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Features and development of Coot</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>66</vid>, <ppf>486</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>501</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b45"><reftxt><refau><snm>Fenn</snm>, <fnm>T.D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schnieders</snm>, <fnm>M.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Polarizable atomic multipole X-ray refinement: weighting schemes for macromolecular diffraction</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>957</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>965</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b46"><reftxt><refau><snm>Adams</snm>, <fnm>P.D.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>66</vid>, <ppf>213</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>221</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b47"><reftxt><refau><snm>Labb&#xE9;</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Thiele</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Copper ion inducible and repressible promoter systems in yeast</atl>. <jtl>Methods Enzymol.</jtl> <vid>306</vid>, <ppf>145</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>153</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b48"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Huang</snm>, <fnm>W.-P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Stromhaug</snm>, <fnm>P.E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Convergence of multiple autophagy and cytoplasm to vacuole targeting components to a perivacuolar membrane compartment prior to de novo vesicle formation</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>277</vid>, <ppf>763</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>773</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b49"><reftxt><refau><snm>Geng</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nair</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yasumura-Yorimitsu</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Post-Golgi Sec proteins are required for autophagy in <i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i></atl>. <jtl>Mol. Biol. Cell</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>2257</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2269</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b50"><reftxt><refau><snm>Robinson</snm>, <fnm>J.S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Banta</snm>, <fnm>L.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Emr</snm>, <fnm>S.D.</fnm></refau> <atl>Protein sorting in <i>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</i>: isolation of mutants defective in the delivery and processing of multiple vacuolar hydrolases</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>4936</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>4948</ppl> (<cd year="1988">1988</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b51"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kanki</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>A genomic screen for yeast mutants defective in selective mitochondria autophagy</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Biol. Cell</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>4730</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>4738</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b52"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yen</snm>, <fnm>W.-L.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The conserved oligomeric Golgi complex is involved in double-membrane vesicle formation during autophagy</atl>. <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>188</vid>, <ppf>101</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>114</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b53"><reftxt><refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cuervo</snm>, <fnm>A.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Seglen</snm>, <fnm>P.O.</fnm></refau> <atl>Methods for monitoring autophagy from yeast to human</atl>. <jtl>Autophagy</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>181</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>206</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b54"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cheong</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Biochemical methods to monitor autophagy-related processes in yeast</atl>. <jtl>Methods Enzymol.</jtl> <vid>451</vid>, <ppf>1</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>26</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b55"><reftxt><refau><snm>Huang</snm>, <fnm>W.-P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Scott</snm>, <fnm>S.V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The itinerary of a vesicle component, Aut7p/Cvt5p, terminates in the yeast vacuole via the autophagy/Cvt pathways</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>275</vid>, <ppf>5845</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5851</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b56"><reftxt><refau><snm>Kim</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Huang</snm>, <fnm>W.-P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Klionsky</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Membrane recruitment of Aut7p in the autophagy and cytoplasm to vacuole targeting pathways requires Aut1p, Aut2p, and the autophagy conjugation complex</atl>. <jtl>J. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>152</vid>, <ppf>51</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>64</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
</bibl></bm></article>
