<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "http://www.rsc.org/dtds/rscart36.dtd">
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>C39950001057</ms-id>
    <doi>10.1039/C39950001057</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>C3</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>
</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>10</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>1057</fpage>
      <lpage>1058</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>2</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1995</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>C3</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1995</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Syntheses of tetranuclear tungsten sulfide clusters with raft-type and tetrahedral core structures</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Shigeki</fname>
            <surname>Kuwata</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Yasushi</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Masanobu</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Reaction of [W(N<inf>2</inf>)<inf>2</inf>(PMe<inf>2</inf>Ph)<inf>4</inf>] with (Me<inf>3</inf>Si)<inf>2</inf>S–MeOH gives a raft-type tetratungsten sulfide cluster [W<inf>4</inf>(µ<inf>3</inf>-S)<inf>4</inf>(SH)<inf>2</inf>(PMe<inf>2</inf>Ph)<inf>6</inf>]<bo>2</bo>, which is converted to a tetrahedral cluster [W<inf>4</inf>(µ-S)<inf>6</inf>(PMe<inf>2</inf>Ph)<inf>4</inf>]<bo>5</bo> upon treatment with SnCl<inf>2</inf> followed by reduction with Na/Hg; the molecular structures of <bo>2</bo> and <bo>5</bo> are determined by X-ray crystallography.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p>  J. CHEM. SOC. CHEM. COMMUN. 1995  Syntheses of Tetranuclear Tungsten Sulfide Clusters with Raft-type and Tetrahedral  Core Structures  Shigeki Kuwata Yasushi Mizobe and Masanobu Hidai*  Department of Chemistry and Biotechnology Faculty of Engineering The University of Tokyo Hongo Bunkyo-ku  Tokyo 113 Japan  Reaction of [W(N2)2(PMe2Ph)41  with (Me3SiI2S-MeOH gives a raft-type tetratungsten sulfide cluster  [W4(~.3-S)2(~-S)4(SH)*(PMe2Ph)sl2 5 upon treatment  which is converted to a tetrahedral cluster [W&amp;L-S)~(PM~~P~)~]  with SnCI2 followed by reduction with Na/Hg; the molecular structures of 2 and 5 are determined by X-ray  crystaIIog rap h y.  Transition-metal sulfide clusters have been the subject of  increased attention as synthetic analogues for non-molecular  sulfides,’ which show unique physical properties such as  superconductivity in Chevrel phases. </p>
      <p>Structural properties2 and  reactivities of sulfide clusters are also of significant interest in  relation to biological3 and industrial4 catalysis. These potential  characteristics of sulfide clusters prompted us to investigate the  preparation of di- and tri-ruthenium complexes with bridging  sulfur-donor ligands? and mixed-metal sulfide clusters contain-  ing WRU~,~ PtRu2,6 Pd2Ru2,6 and PdMo37 cores for some of  which intriguing reactivities towards various substrates includ-  ing alkynes H2 CO alkyl halides and hydrazines have already  been demonstrated. In this paper we wish to report the  syntheses of two types of novel tetratungsten sulfide clusters  containing either a raft-type or a tetrahedral core framework  (Scheme 1). </p>
      <p> 1 with Treatment of ~is-[w(N~)~(PMe~Ph)~] (Me3Si)2S  (2 equiv. per 1) and MeOH (10 equiv. per 1) in toluene at  50°C for 4 h under vacuum afforded [W&amp;-s)2-(pS)4(SH)2(PMe2Ph),I 2 in 43% yield as dark green microcry-  stals upon recrystallization from THF-diethyl ether.? A single-crystal X-ray analysis has shown that 2 consists of the  tetranuclear tungsten core arranged in a raft-type or planar  butterfly geometry (Fig. l).$ The w4s6 framework comprises  two fused incomplete cubanes in a face-sharing manner; the two  W3 triangles are capped by p3-sulfide ligands and the four  peripheral W-W edges in the raft are bridged by p-sulfide  ligands. The sulfur atom terminally bound to the wingtip  tungsten proved to be a thiol sulfur atom since the final Fourier  map unambiguously showed the presence of a hydrogen atom  attached to this sulfur. </p>
      <p>This is further confirmed by the  appearance of a weak v(SH) band at 2512 cm-1 in the IR  spectrum (KBr disk). There are 10 d electrons in 2 correspond-ing to the existence of five W-W bonds. These structural  features allow us to tentatively assign a 14-electron d2  configuration to the wingtip tungstens with two W-W bonds  and an 1 8-electron d3 configuration to the hinge tungstens with  three W-W bonds respectively. It is to be noted that bond  ii /’ 2  4 5  Scheme 1Reagents and conditions i (Me3Si)2S MeOH toluene 50 “C; ii  SnCI2 THF reflux; iii Na/Hg THF room temp. (P = PMe2Ph)  distances betweeno the wingtip W and the p-S  [2.274(2)-2.279(2) A] are substantially shorter than those  between the hinge W and the p-S [2.435(3) A]. </p>
      <p> When 1 was treated with (Me3Si)zS alone at 50°C no  reaction occurred. This suggests that hydrogen sulfide gener-  ated in situ from (Me3Si)2S and MeOH reacts with 1 to give the  tetranuclear sulfide cluster 2. Indeed the ‘H NMR spectrum of  the reaction mixture obtained from treatment of 1 with H2S gas  indicated the formation of 2 although the isolation of pure 2 in  high yield has not yet been successful. Oxidative addition of  hydrogen sulfide to low-valent metal complexes provides a  potential synthetic method to prepare sulfide clusters.* As to  related reactions reported to date [W(PMe3)4(q2-CH2PMe2)H]  is known to react with H2S to give a mononuclear bis(su1fide)  complex [W(S)2(PMe3)4]  ,9 while the reactions of trans-[Mo(N2)2(PMePh2)4] with thiols produce mononuclear hy-  dride-thiolate complexes [MoH(SR)3(PMePhz)] (R =  C6H2R’,-2,4,6; R’ = Me Pri).lo It is also to be noted that the  isostructural Mo cluster [Mo4(p3-s),(p-s)4(sH)2(PMe3)6] 3  was prepared from the reaction of [Mo~S(S~)~]~-  with PMe3-  butylamine and characterised by X-ray analysis. </p>
      <p> Reaction of 2 with SnC12 (1 equiv. per 2) in THF at reflux  resulted in the formation of the chloro-substituted cluster  [W4(p3-S)2(p-S)4C12(PMe2Ph)6]4 which has been charac-  terised by IR ’H and 31P{ lH} NMR spectroscopy as well as  X-ray analysis.§ The core structure of 4 is identical with that of  2 and this also substantiates the characterisation of the terminal  sulfur atom in 2 as a thiol type sulfur atom. </p>
      <p>Saito and coworkers  have recently reported that similar replacement of the SH group  in 3 by a chloride ligand also takes place to afford the  corresponding Mo cluster l2  We have further found that treatment of W5Wrv2 cluster 4  with an excess amount of Na/Hg in THF at room temperature  Fig. 1Molecular structure of 2 (carbon and hydrogen atoms are omitted for  clarity). The molecule has a crystallographically imposed inversion centre.  Selected bond distances (A) W( 1)-W( 1‘) 2.8373(8) W( 1)-W(2)  2.81 14(7j W(l)-W(2’j 2.81 18(6) W(1)-S(l) 2.380(2) W(1)-S(1’)  2.374(2) W( l)-S(2) 2.435(3) W( 1)-S(3) 2.435(3) W(2)-S(1’) 2.393(2)  W(2)-S(2’) 2.279(2) W(2)-S(3 j 2.274(2) W(2)-S(4) 2.390(2) W( 1)-P( 1)  2.606(3) W(I)-P(2) 2.592(2) W(2)-P(3) 2.5 13(3). </p>
      <p>      P"'  n  Fig. 2 Molecular structure of 5 (carbon and hydrogen atoms are omitted for  clarity). The molecule has a crystallographically imposed S4 axis passing  through S(1) and S(1'). Selected bond distances (A) and angles (") W-W'  2.634(3) W-W" 2.634(2) W-S( 1) 2.32( 1) W-S(2) 2.323(7) W-P  2.533( lo) W'-W-WN 60.00(3) W"-W-W" 60.00(6) S(1)-W-S(2)  119.98(3) S(2)-W-S(2") 119.99(6) S(1)-W-P 88.8(3) S(2)-W-P  89.q2).  gives the W1114 cluster [W4(p-s)6(PMe,Ph)4] 5 in 10%yield as  purple crystals upon recrystallization from THF-diethyl ether.f  The structure of 5 determined by X-ray analysis consists of an  almost regular tetrahedron of tungsten atoms with each edge  bridged by a p-sulfido ligand; the W4S6P4 core has pseudo Td  symmetry (Fig. </p>
      <p>2).$ The W-W bond lengths in 5 [2.634(3) A]  are substantially shorter than those in 2 [2.8114(7)-2.8373(8) A]. There are six W-W bonds which is consistent with the  presence of 12 d electrons in 5.  The w4s6 framework in 5 may be regarded as an adamant-  anoid core which occurs in the cubic metal sulfide lattice  known as the sphalerite or zinc blende structure. However the  coordination geometry around the W atom in 5 is fairly distorted  from an ideal tetrahedral environment [S-W-P 89.2 S-W-S  120.0' (mean)] due to the presence of W-W interactions. Atom  connectivity of this type has previously been observed only in  some discrete cluster molecules containing post-transition  metals such as [MloS4(SPh)16]4-(M = Zn Cd)13 and  [Ge4S6Br4],14 although thiolate-bridged M4(SR)6 adamant-  anoid cores are more precedented.15  Reductive condensation of sulfide-chloride clusters is now  known as a practical synthetic method for sulfide clusters.16  However reductive core rearrangement of sulfide clusters  maintaining the cluster nuclearity is less common and the  present results may give a new rational route to prepare novel  cluster cores. </p>
      <p>Further studies on the reactivities of tetratungsten  sulfide clusters 2 4 and 5 towards organic inorganic and  organometallic compounds are now in progress.  This work was financially supported by the Ministry of  Education Science and Culture Japan.  Received 17th February 1995; Corn. </p>
      <p>5100979K  J. CHEM. SOC. CHEM. COMMUN. 1995  Footnotes  t 1H NMR ([2Hs]THF) 6 8.12-7.06 (m 30 H PMe2Ph) 2.34 (d 12 H J  = 7.9 Hz wingtip PMe2Ph) 1.61 1.35 (br d 12 H each J = 6.8 Hz hinge  PMe2Ph). Signals due to SH protons were not assignable. 31P( 1H) NMR  ([2Hs]THF) 6 -17.9 (lJwp = 175 Hz wingtip PMe2Ph) -52.3 (IJW =  167 Hz hinge PMe2Ph).  $ Crystal data for 2 M = 1822.79; monoclinic space group P2Jc a =  11.158(4) b = 21.408(1) c = 13.765(1) A fi = 113.53(1)" V =  3014(1) A3,Z = 2 D = 2.008 g ~m-~  p = 80.83 cm-l F(000) = 1740  R = 0.037 and R = 0.026 for 298 variables and 4266 unique reflections  [Z &gt; 3.00(0]. For 5 M = 1480.35; tetrasonal space group Z41/amd a =  23.160(4) c = 9.939(4) A V = 5331(2) A3 Z = 4 D,= 1.844 g cm-3 p  = 89.86 cm-l F(000) = 2752 R = 0.049 and R = 0.047 for 61 variables  and 717 unique reflections [I &gt; 3.00(1)]. </p>
      <p>Intensity data were collected on a  Rigaku AFC7R diffractometer with the use of graphite-monochromated  Mo-Ka radiation and corrected for Lorentz-polarization effect as well as for  absorption (v scans). Structure solution and refinements were carried out by  using the TEXSAN program package. Atomic coordinates thermal  parameters and bond lengths and angles have been deposited at the  Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre. See Information for Authors  Issue No. 1.  Q Yield 63%. lH NMR ([2Hs]THF) 6 7.98-7.08 (m 30 H PMe2Ph) 2.15  (br d 12 H J = 7.9 Hz wingtip PMe2Ph) 1.27 (br s 12 H hinge PMe2Ph).  A signal ascribed to another hinge PMe2Ph might be overlapping on the  signals of non-deuteriated THF at 6 1.73. </p>
      <p>31P{ 'H] NMR ([2Hs]THF) 6  -18.3 (br s wingtip PMe2Ph) -52.6 (s lJwp = 169 Hz hinge PMe2Ph).  Details of the structure of 4 will be reported elsewhere.  7 lH NMR ([2Hs]THF) 6 8.00-7.25 (m 20 H PMe2Ph) 2.42 (d 24 H J =  6.3 Hz PMeZPh). 31P(1H) NMR ([2Hs]THF) 6 -3.8 (s lJWp=  141 Hz).  References  1 S. C. Lee and R. H. Holm Angew. Chem. Znt. Ed. Engl. 1990,29,840;  J. R. Long and R. H. Holm J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1994,116,9987.  2 I. Dance and K. Fisher Prog. Znorg. Chem. 1994,41 637.  3 Adv. Znorg. Chem. 1992,38; J. M. Berg and R. H. Holm in Metal Ions  in Biology ed. T. G. Spiro Wiley New York 1982 vol. 4 p. 1.  4 M. Rakowski DuBois Chem. Rev. 1989,89 1; U. Riaz 0.J. Cumow  and M. D. Curtis J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1994,116,4357. </p>
      <p> 5 M. Hidai Y. Mizobe and H. Matsuzaka J. Organomet. Chem. 1994  473 1 and references therein; H. Matsuzaka Y. Takagi and M. Hidai  Oi-ganometallics 1994 13 13; A. Takahashi Y. Mizobe and M. Hidai  Chem. Lett. 1994 371; Y. Mizobe K. Hashizume T. Murai and M.  Hidai J. Chem. SOC. Chem. Commun. 1994 1051; S. Kuwata Y.  Mizobe and M. Hidai Znorg. Chem. 1994 33 3619; M. Nishio H.  Matsuzaka Y. Mizobe T. Tanase and M. Hidai Organometallics 1994  13 4214.  6 Y. Mizobe M. Hosomizu J. Kawabata and M. Hidai J. Chem. SOC.  Chem. Commun.,. 1991 1226; S. Kuwata Y. Mizobe and M. Hidai  J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1993 115 8499.  7 T. Murata Y. Mizobe H. Gao Y. Ishii T. Wakabayashi F. Nakano T.  Tanase S. Yano M. Hidai I. Echizen H. Nanikawa and S. Motomura  J. Am. </p>
      <p>Chem. Sue. 1994,116 3389.  8 F. Cecconi C. A. Ghilardi and S. Midollini Znorg. Chem. 1983 22  3802; F. Bottomley G. 0. Egharevba and P. S. White J. Am. Chem.  Soc. 1985 107 4353.  9 D. Rabinovich and G. Parkin J.Am. Chem. SOC.,1991 113 5904.  10 D. L. Hughes N. J. Lazarowych M. J. Maguire R. H. Morris and R. L.  Richards J. Chem. SOC.,Dalton Trans. 1995 5.  11 K. Tsuge H. Imoto and T. Saito Znorg. Chem. 1992 31,4715.  12 S. Mita K. Tsuge H. Imoto and T. Saito The 43rd Symposium on  Coordination Chemistry of Japan Sendai Japan 1993 2A08.  13 I. G. Dance A. Choy and M. L. Scudder J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1984,106  6285.  14 S. Pohl Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 1976 15 162.  15 I. G. Dance Polyhedron 1986 5 1037.  16 T. Saito N. Yamamoto T. Nagase T. Tsuboi K. Kobayashi T.  Yamagata H. Imoto and K. Unoura Znorg. Chem. 1990 29 764; T.  Saito A. Yoshikawa T. Yamagata H. hot0 and K. Unoura Znorg.  Chem. 1989,28,3588.     </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. C.</fname>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. H.</fname>
            <surname>Holm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. Engl.</title>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volumeno>29</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>840</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. R.</fname>
            <surname>Long</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. H.</fname>
            <surname>Holm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>116</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>9987</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I.</fname>
            <surname>Dance</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Fisher</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Prog. Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>41</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>637</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <citation><title>Adv. Inorg. Chem.</title>, <year>1992</year>, <biblscope>38</biblscope>;</citation>
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>J. M.</fname><surname>Berg</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>R. H.</fname><surname>Holm</surname></citauth>, in <title>Metal Ions in Biology</title>, ed. <editor>T. G. Spiro</editor>, <citpub>Wiley</citpub>, <pubplace>New York</pubplace>, <year>1982</year>, vol. 4, <biblscope>p. 1</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Rakowski DuBois</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Rev.</title>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volumeno>89</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Riaz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>O. J.</fname>
            <surname>Cumow</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. D.</fname>
            <surname>Curtis</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>116</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>4357</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Matsuzaka</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Organomet. Chem.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>473</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <citext>and references therein;</citext>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Matsuzaka</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Takagi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Organometallics</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>13</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>13</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A.</fname>
            <surname>Takahashi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Lett.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>371</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Hashizume</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Murai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Chem. Commun.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1051</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Kuwata</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>33</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3619</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Nishio</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Matsuzaka</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Tanase</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Organometallics</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>13</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>4214</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hosomizu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Kawabata</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Chem. Commun.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1226</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Kuwata</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volumeno>115</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8499</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Murata</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Mizobe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Gao</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Ishii</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Wakabayashi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Nakano</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Tanase</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Yano</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Hidai</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I.</fname>
            <surname>Echizen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Nanikawa</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Motomura</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volumeno>116</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3389</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Cecconi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. A.</fname>
            <surname>Ghilardi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Midollini</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volumeno>22</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3802</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Bottoniley</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. O.</fname>
            <surname>Egharevba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. S.</fname>
            <surname>White</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volumeno>107</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>4353</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D.</fname>
            <surname>Rabinovich</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Parkin</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>113</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5904</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. L.</fname>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. J.</fname>
            <surname>Lazarowych</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. J.</fname>
            <surname>Maguire</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. H.</fname>
            <surname>Morris</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. L.</fname>
            <surname>Richards</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Dalton Trans.</title>
          <year>1995</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit11">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Tsuge</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Imoto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Saito</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volumeno>31</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>4715</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit12">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Mita</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>K.</fname><surname>Tsuge</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>H.</fname><surname>Imoto</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Saito</surname></citauth>, <title>The 43rd Symposium on Coordination Chemistry of Japan</title>, <citpub>Sendai</citpub>, <pubplace>Japan</pubplace>, <year>1993</year>, <biblscope>2A08</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit13">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I. G.</fname>
            <surname>Dance</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A.</fname>
            <surname>Choy</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. L.</fname>
            <surname>Scudder</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volumeno>106</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6285</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit14">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Pohl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. Engl.</title>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volumeno>15</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>162</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit15">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I. G.</fname>
            <surname>Dance</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Polyhedron</title>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volumeno>5</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1037</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit16">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Saito</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Nagase</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Tsuboi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Yamagata</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Imoto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Unoura</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volumeno>29</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>764</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Saito</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A.</fname>
            <surname>Yoshikawa</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Yamagata</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Imoto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Unoura</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volumeno>28</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3588</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
