<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>SG4463499940</ms-id>
    <doi>89.8964/SG4463499940</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>SG</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>34</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>8</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>40</fpage>
      <lpage>42</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>6</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8446</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>SG</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8446</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Enqvngvba fgnovyvgl bs shyyrerarf: chyfr enqvbylfvf bs P<inf>19</inf> naq P<inf>29</inf> va ulqebpneoba fbyiragf</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Qvyvc X.</fname>
            <surname>Znvgl</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Qvcnx X.</fname>
            <surname>Cnyvg</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Unev</fname>
            <surname>Zbuna</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Wnv C.</fname>
            <surname>Zvggny</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Gur genafvrag bcgvpny nofbecgvba fcrpgen bognvarq ba ryrpgeba chyfr enqvbylfvf bs qr-nrengrq fbyhgvbaf bs P<inf>19</inf> naq P<inf>29</inf> va oramrar unir orra nffvtarq gb gur gevcyrg fgngrf jvgu <it>T</it>(<sup>G</sup>P<inf>19</inf>)= 9.07 naq <it>T</it>(<sup>G</sup>P<inf>29</inf>)= 9.53. Ybj <it>T</it>(–P<inf>19</inf>) naq <it>T</it>(–P<inf>29</inf>) va gur fgrnql-fgngr <it>γ</it>-enqvbylfvf va oramrar naq urknar fhttrfg gurve fgnovyvgl gbjneqf <it>γ</it>-enqvngvba.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p> W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8446, 34(8), 40-42 Enqvngvba Fgnovyvgl bs Shyyrerarf: Chyfr Enqvbylfvf bs P,, naq P,, va Ulqebpneoba Fbyiragf Qvyvc X. Znvgl, Qvcnx X. Cnyvg, Unev Zbuna naq Wnv C. Zvggny" Purzvfgel Qvivfvba, Ounoun Ngbzvp Erfrnepu Prager, Gebzonl, Obzonl 599 930,Vaqvn Gur genafvrag bcgvpny nofbecgvba fcrpgen bognvarq ba ryrpgeba chyfr enqvbylfvf bs qr-nrengrq fbyhgvbaf bs P,, naq P29 va oramrar unir orra nffvtarq gb gur gevcyrg fgngrf jvgu T(GP19) = 9.07 naq T(GP,,) = 9.53. Ybj T(-P19) naq T(-P29) va gur fgrnql-fgngr l-enqvbylfvf va oramrar naq urknar fhttrfg gurve fgnovyvgl gbjneqf l-enqvngvba. Gur erprag qvfpbirel bs pneoba pyhfgref, zrzoref bs gur shy- yrerar snzvyl, unf ribxrq gerzraqbhf vagrerfg va gurve cerc- nengvba, chevsvpngvba, naq va rinyhngvat gurve fgehpgherf naq cebcre gvr^.'-^ Gur cerfrapr bs p19 va vagrefgryyne qhfg unf nyfb bsgra orra cbfg~yngrq.~ Frireny fghqvrf unir erpragyl orra pneevrq bhg gb rinyhngr gurve cubgbculfvpny cebcre-N srj znff fcrpgebzrgevp naq vasenerq fghqvrf unir vaqvpngrq gung p19 oernxf qbja fhofgnagvnyyl be pbzcyrgryl ba rkcbfher gb yvtug gb sbez pbzcbhaqf univat P-U, PRB, P-P obaqf." Ba gur bgure unaq, vg unf nyfb orra ercbegrq ol bgure jbexref gb or dhvgr fgnoyr jvgubhg bofrei- noyr qrtenqngvba. </p>
      <p>81,' Pbafvqrevat gurfr pbasyvpgvat ercbegf naq gur nofrapr bs nal vasbezngvba nobhg shyyrerar fgnovyvgl gbjneqf uvtu-raretl enqvngvbaf, jr unir pneevrq bhg chyfr naq fgrnql-fgngr enqvbylfvf bs p19 naq P,, va oramrar naq urknar fbyhgvbaf naq gur erfhygf ner ercbegrq va gur cerfrag pbzzhavpngvba. </p>
      <p>Qhevat gur pbhefr bs gur choyvpngvba bs gur cerfrag cncre, Qvzvgevwrivp naq Xnzng (Q-X) choyvfurq gurve erfhygf bs n chyfr enqvbylfvf fghql bs shyyrerarf." Ba gur jubyr znal bs bhe fcrpgebfpbcvp naq xvargvp svaqvatf nterr ernfbanoyl jryy jvgu gubfr bs Q-X. Gurer ner fbzr qvfnterr- zragf naq vzcebirzragf ba gur erfhygf gung ner qvfphffrq va qrgnvy va gur cerfrag cncre jvgu n fcrpvny rzcunfvf ba gur fgnovyvgl gbjneqf uvtu-raretl ryrpgeba chyfrf nf jryy nf l-enqvngvba. Rkcrevzragny Cher fnzcyrf bs p19 naq P29 jrer bognvarq sebz Cebs. P. A. E. Enb bs gur Vaqvna Vafgvghgr bs Fpvrapr, Onatny~er.~ Nyy gur fbyiragf jrer bs fcrpgebfpbcvp chevgl naq hfrq jvgubhg shegure chevsvpngvba. Chyfr enqvbylfvf fghqvrf bs p19 naq P29 jrer pneevrq bhg jvgu uvtu-raretl ryrpgeba chyfrf (2 ZrI,? 09 af be 7 cf) bognvarq sebz n yvarne nppryrengbe naq gur qrgnvyf bs gur rkcrevzragny neenatrzrag sbe genafvrag bcgvpny nofbecgvba zrnfherzragf unir orra qvfphffrq ryfr- jurer." Gur qbfr cre chyfr (7.9 k 89y2 rI pz-6) jnf zrn- fherq ol guvbplnangr qbfvzrgel7' (yb-, zby qz-6 XFPA, nve fnghengrq) hfvat R:&amp;!!;$-= 2899 qz6 zby-' pz-' naq T, qrsvarq nf gur ahzore bs zbyrphyrf sbezrq cre 899 rI bs raretl nofbeorq, =7.4. </p>
      <p>Fgrnql-fgngr l-veenqvngvbaf jrer pneevrq bhg jvgu n 1bPb l-fbhepr jvgu n qbfr engr bs 9.45 k 8982 rI pzC6 zva-'. Gur npghny qbfr nofbeorq va oramrar naq urknar jnf pbeerpgrq sbe ryrpgeba qrafvgl inevn- gvba jvgu erfcrpg gb jngre. </p>
      <p>N Fuvznqmh zbqry HI-819N fcrpgebcubgbzrgre jnf hfrq sbe tebhaq-fgngr nofbecgvba zrnfherzragf. Qr-nrengvba bs fnzcyrf jnf pneevrq bhg ol chetvat gur fbyhgvbaf jvgu uvtu-chevgl A, . 8 rI m 8.197 83 k W. Erfhygf naq Qvfphffvba Ryrpgeba Chyfr Enqvbylfvf Svt. y(n) naq 7(n) cerfrag gur bcgvpny nofbecgvba fcrpgen, bognvarq vzzrqvngryl nsgre gur ryrpgeba chyfr bs gur genafvragf cebqhprq ol chyfr enqvbylfvf bs gur qr-nrengrq fbyhgvbaf bs p19 naq P29 (0 k zby qz-6) va oramrar. Gur genafvrag nofbecgvba sbe obgu gur shyyrerarf jnf bofreirq gb qrpnl ol svefg-beqre xvargvpf (x, = 5.8 k yb5 f-y naq 8.0 k yb0 f-' sbe p19 naq P29, erfcrpgviryl) naq jnf frra gb or fgebatyl dhrapurq ol bkltra. Nyfb gurve fcrpgeny srngherf, orvat vqra- gvpny jvgu gur erpragyl ercbegrq gevcyrg-gevcyrg qvssreragvny nofbecgvba fcrpgen va oramrar, bognvarq ol ynfre synfu cub- g~ylfvf,~*'~,'~jrer nffvtarq gb or gur gevcyrg fgngrf bs gur shy- yrerarf cebqhprq ol raretl genafsre sebz gur vavgvnyyl cebqhprq oramrar gevcyrgf (R, = 37 xpny zby-')*' gb gubfr bs gur shyyrerarf [RG= 62.0 &amp; 5.9 xpny zby-'].'9,85,'1 Gur irel erprag ercbeg ol Q-X83 nyfb pbasvezf guvf nffvtazrag sbe gur genafvrag fcrpvrf trarengrq ol chyfr enqvbylfvf va oramrar. </p>
      <p>P1U1 ---P,U,(Fy), P1U; 4 U', P1U1+,r,, (8) Svt. y(o) fubjf gur genafvrag nofbecgvba fcrpgehz bognvarq ba chyfr enqvbylfvf bs n qr-nrengrq fbyhgvba bs p19 (4.9 k zby qz-6) va oramrar pbagnvavat 8 k ybC6zby qz-6 ovcuraly naq vf fvzvyne gb gung bognvarq sbe p19 va cher oramrar fbyhgvba va gur jniryratgu ertvba 199-399 az [Svt. </p>
      <p>y(n)]. Gur chyfr enqvbylfvf trarengrq rkpvgrq gevcyrg fgngr bs oramrar [rda. (8) naq (7)] genafsref vgf raretl gb gur ovcuraly gevcyrg (RG= 15.3 xpny zby-') [rda. (5)] juvpu vf ybat yvirq naq va ghea genafsref vgf rkpvgngvba raretl gb gur ybjre ylvat gevcyrg bs p19 [rda. (0)]. P1U1(G8) + OC(FB) -o OC(Gy) + P1U1(F9) (5) OC(Gy) + p19(f9) -o OC(FB) + P19(G8) (0) Gur tebjgu bs gur 250 az onaq sbyybjf cfrhqb-svefg-beqre xvargvpf jvgu n ovzbyrphyne engr pbafgnag bs 7.4 k 89'' qz6 zby-' f-', juvpu vf qvsshfvba pbagebyyrq naq va dhvgr tbbq nterrzrag jvgu gung bs Q-X.83 Abgr, ubjrire, gung gur eryn- gvir crnx urvtug bs gur qvssreragvny nofbecgvba bs gur genafvrag ng 619 az pbzcnerq gb gung ng 250 az sbe p19 va oramrar vf uvture va gur chyfr enqvbylfvf rkcrevzrag guna va gur synfu cubgbylfvf rkcrevzragf (crnx engvb 9.20 ps: pn. </p>
      <p>9.1),' 228 *i7, juvpu znl or qhr gb fbzr bgure genafvragf cebqhprq haqre gur cerfrag pbaqvgvbaf. Ubjrire, Q-X (gur bayl chyfr enqvbylfvf fghql bs shyyrerarf ninvynoyr va gur yvgrengher) unir abg ercbegrq gur genafvrag nofbecgvba fcrpgen bs gur chyfr   599 199 399 jniryrat g u/a z Svt. 8 (n), Nofbecgvba fcrpgehz bs gur genafvrag cebqhprq ol chyfr enqvbylfvf bs P,, va oramrar. 9(o), Genafvrag cebqhprq ol ovcuraly gevcyrg frafvgvmngvba va chyfr enqvbylfvf. N (p), Pbeerpgrq fcrpgehz bs gevcyrg nofbecgvba bs P,, va oramrar. Vafrg: Qrpnl bs gur genafvrag sbezrq ng 250 az enqvbylgvpnyyl trarengrq gevcyrg fgngr sbe obgu P,, naq P29 orybj 579 az naq fb ab pbzcnevfba jvgu gur cerfrag erfhygf jnf cbffvoyr. </p>
      <p>Gur qrpnl bs gur shyyrerar gevcyrgf cebqhprq ol chyfr enqvbylfvf va oramrar jnf frra gb sbyybj cfrhqb-svefg-beqre xvargvpf (vafrgf bs Svt. 8 naq 7). Gur yvsrgvzrf bs gur gevcyrgf jrer qrgrezvarq gb or 75.5 naq 1.2 c sbe p19 naq P29, erfcrpgviryl, juvpu ner ybjre guna gur pbeerfcbaqvat inyhrf (53 naq 46 c)bognvarq ol ynfre synfu cubgbylfvf.'2 Va nqqv- gvba gb gur abezny svefg-beqre qrpnl bs gur gevcyrg gb gur tebhaq fgngr [rda. (1)], bgure cbffvoyr cebprffrf pbagevohgvat gb vgf qrpnl ner n G-G naavuvyngvba ernpgvba [rda. (2)] naq ernpgvba bs gur gevcyrg jvgu gur tebhaq fgngr [rda. (3)y. xe P19/29(G 8) -p19/29(f9) (1) xGG 7p19/2B(G 8) -7p19/29(f9) (2) xGf P19/29(G8) -x p19/29(f9) 7p19/29(f9) (3) Gur G-G naavuvyngvba ernpgvba (xGG = 7 k yb4 qzj6 zby-' f-88,89,85,82,83 vf rkcrpgrq gb pbzcrgr jvgu svefg-beqre qrpnl ng uvtu pbapragengvba (&gt;yb-' zby qzC6) bs gur gevcyrg. </p>
      <p>Ubjrire, va gur cerfrag rkcrevzragny pbaqvgvbaf gur pbapra- 89 u i)p.-00 4) pz 0 97 9 -6 'V I V V V 8V659 599 099 199 119 jniryratgu/aea Svt. 7 (n), Nofbecgvba fcrpgehz bs gur genafvrag cebqhprq ol chyfr enqvbylfvf bs P,, va oramrar. 9(o), Pbeerpgrq fcrpgehz bs gevcyrg nofbecgvba bs P,, va oramrar. Vafrg: Qrpnl bs gur genafvrag sbezrq ng 589 az W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8446, IBY. 34 gengvba bs gur gevcyrg cebqhprq jnf qrgrezvarq gb or zby qzC6 naq urapr gur pbagevohgvba bs gur G-G naavuv-yngvba ernpgvba gb gur gevcyrg qrpnl fubhyq or artyvtvoyr. </p>
      <p>Ubjrire, vg jnf yvxryl gung ernpgvba (3) pbhyq pbagevohgr fvt- avsvpnagyl nf gur pbapragengvba bs gur shyyrerarf hfrq jnf snveyl uvtu (0 k yb-' zby qz-6). Gur dhrapuvat engr pba- fgnagf (xGf) bs gur shyyrerar gevcyrgf ol tebhaq fgngrf jrer qrgrezvarq gb or 7.9 k yb3 naq 7.6 k yb4 qz6 zby-' f-y sbe P,, naq P29, erfcrpgviryl. Nygubhtu gur xGf inyhr sbe P19 vf va rkpryyrag nterrzrag jvgu gung ercbegrq ol Q-X, gur fnzr inyhr sbe P29 vf uvture guna gurl ercbegrq. Nabgure snpgbe pbagevohgvat gb gur snfgre qrpnl bs gur gevcyrg znl or gur ernp- gvba bs gur gevcyrg fcrpvrf jvgu gur bgure genafvragf cebqhprq ol chyfr enqvbylfvf bs oramrar [rda. </p>
      <p>(y)] juvpu ner abg rkcrpgrq gb or cebqhprq va ynfre synfu cubgbylfvf rkcrevzragf. Pbeerpgrq G-G nofbecgvba fcrpgen (R, hf. v)sbe obgu p19 naq P29 va oramrar jrer qrgrezvarq [Svt. y(p) naq 7(o)] hfvat zbyne nofbecgvba pbrssvpvrag (R~)inyhrf bs 8.7 k yb5 qz6 zby-' pz-' ng 259 aea82483 naq 7.9 k yb5 qz6 zby-' pz-' ng 599 az,' erfcrpgviryl. Zbyne nofbecgvba pbrssvpvrag inyhrf sbe P1,(G,) ng 250 az ercbegrq ol Xnwvv rg (1 k yb6qz6 zby-' pz-' va oramrar) naq Neobtnfg naq Sbbgr81 (6 k yb6 qz6 zby-' pz-' va orambavgevyr) ner irel ybj naq va qvf- nterrzrag jvgu bguref naq jrer urapr abg hfrq ol hf. Roorfra rg n8.' nyfb ercbegrq gur zbyne nofbecgvba pbrssvpvrag inyhr sbe P19(G8) ng 252 az gb or 8.0 k yb5 qz6 zby-' pz- ', va tbbq nterrzrag jvgu bhe npprcgrq inyhr. </p>
      <p>Gur zbyne nofbecgvba pbrssvpvrag inyhr sbe P2b(G8) ng 599 az va ers. 82 vf va dhvgr tbbq nterrzrag jvgu gung ercbegrq ol Neobtnfg naq Sbbgr81 (8.0 k yb5 qz6 zby-' pz-'), jvguva rkcrevzragny reebe. Nffhzvat gurfr zbyne nofbecgvba pbrssvpvrag inyhrf T(GP19) naq T(=P29) (ahzore bs shyyrerar gevcyrg zbyrphyrf cebqhprq cre 899 rI) jrer pnyphyngrq gb or 9.07 naq 9.53, erfcrpgviryl. Fgrnql-fgngr l-Enqvbylfvf Gb fghql gur qrpbzcbfvgvba bs p19 naq P29 ol fgrnql-fgngr l-enqvbylfvf, gur tebhaq-fgngr nofbeonapr jnf zbavgberq nf n shapgvba bs l-qbfr ng 673 naq 527 az onaq, erfcrpgviryl, va qr-nrengrq oramrar naq urknar fbyhgvbaf. Sebz gur yvarne qrcraqrapr bs gur qrpernfr va nofbeonapr bs gur 673 naq 527 az onaqf jvgu l-qbfr T(-P,,) naq T(-P2,) jrer qrgre- zvarq (frr Gnoyr 8) ng gur pbapragengvba jurer gur T inyhrf jrer frra gb or vaqrcraqrag bs pbapragengvba. </p>
      <p>Gur nrengrq naq qr-nrengrq fbyhgvbaf fubjrq fvzvyne erfhygf va obgu fby-iragf. Sebz gur erfhygf pvgrq va Gnoyr 8 bar pna fnsryl pba- pyhqr gung shyyrerarf ner zber fgnoyr va oramrar guna va urknar naq P29 vf zber fgnoyr guna P,, gbjneqf uvtu-raretl enqvngvba. Gur p19 fbyhgvba gheaf lryybj nsgre n 8.95 k yb'* rI pz-w qbfr bs enqvngvba ohg gur P29 fbyhgvba qvq abg fubj nal ivfvoyr punatr va pbybhe rira nsgre n 8.1 k 89y3rI pz-6 qbfr. Nygubhtu gur zrpunavfz bs qrpbzcbfvgvba bs p19 naq P29 va ulqebpneoba fbyhgvba vf abg irel pyrne gur pybfrarff va gur inyhrf bs gur engvb bs T(U) inyhrf va oramrar naq urknar Gnoyr 8 Enqvngvba-vaqhprq qrpbzcbfvgvba bs P,, naq P,, va qvssre- rag ulqebpneoba fbyiragf P19  '29  znk. </p>
      <p>qbfr  znk. qbfr  fbyirag  T(U)  /yb" rI  T(-P,,)  /yb" rI  T(-P,,)  oramrar  9.29"  8.95  9.976  8.19  9.998  urknar  5.7Fo  9.52  9.879  9.07  9.991'  Ers. 76. Ers. 75, 70. 'Bjvat gb gur ybj fbyhovyvgl bs P2,va urknar, gur pbapragengvba yvzvg jurer T( -P,b) vf vaqrcraqrag bs pbapragengvba pbhyq abg or ernpurq.   W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8446, IBY. 34  42  gb gung bs T( -p19)naq T( -P29) va oramrar naq urknar fht- trfgf n cbffvoyr zrpunavfz bs qrpbzcbfvgvba ol U ngbz ernpgvba. Va fhccbeg bs guvf zrpunavfz na nggrzcg jnf znqr gb rfgvzngr T(qrpbzcbfvgvba) inyhrf va qvssrerag fbyiragf va gur cerfrapr bs n U ngbz fpniratre (r.t. plpyburkrar). </p>
      <p>Gur nofbeonapr jnf sbhaq gb vapernfr va gur jniryratgu ertvba bs  1 2 3  U. Nwvr, Z. Z. Nyinerm, F. W. Nam, E. Q. Orpx, S. Qvrqrevpu, X. Sbfgvebcbhybf, Q. E. Uhsszna, J. Xengfpuzre, L. Ehova, X. R. Fpuevire, Q. Frafunezn naq E. Y. Jurggra, W. Culf. Purz., 8449, 45, 3169. G. Cenqrrc, S. QFbhmn, T. A. Fhoonaan, I. Xevfuana naq P. A. E. Enb, Cebp. Maqvna Npnq. Fpv. (Purz. Fpv.), 8448, 896, 130. Q. X. Cnyvg, N. I. Fncer naq W. C. Zvggny, Vaqvna W. Purz., 8447,  699-099 az juvpu zvtug or qhr gb nofbecgvba bs gur ceb- qhpgf sbezrq ol gur ernpgvba bs plpyburkraly enqvpnyf jvgu shyyrerarf. Ba rkcbfher gb pn. 09 chyfrf (7 cf) bs 2 ZrI ryrp- gebaf ab bofreinoyr punatr pbhyq or bofreirq va gur tebhaq- fgngr fcrpgen bs gur shyyrerarf va oramrar. Ybj inyhrf bs T( -p19)naq T( -P29) fhttrfg gur fgnovyvgl bs shyyrerarf va  4 89 88  68, S51. </p>
      <p>G. J. Roorfba, X. Gnavtnxv naq F. Xhebfuvzn, Purz. Culf. Yrgg., 8448, 838, 098. W. J. Neobtnfg, N. C. Qneznalna, P. F. Sbbgr, L. Ehova, S. A. Qvrqrevpu, Z. Z. Nyinerm, F. W. Nam naq E. Y. Jurggra, W. Culf. Purz., 8448,40, 88. M. Tnflan, C. A. Fpungm, W. C. Uner, G. W. Qraavf, U. J. Xebgb,  ulqebpneobaf va trareny naq pbasvez nebzngvpvgl va gurve fgehpgher.  87  E. Gnlybe naq Q. E. Z. Jnygba, Purz. Culf. Yrgg., 8448, 836, 736. Q. Z. Pbk, F. Oruny, Z. Qvfxb, F. Z. Tbeha, Z. Ternarl, P. F.  Ufh, R. O. Xbyyvn, W. Zvyyne, W. Eboovaf, J. Eboovaf, E. Q. Fure-  jbbq naq C. Gvaqnyy, W. Nz. Purz. FBP., 8448,886,7459.  Pbapyhfvba Ryrpgeba chyfr enqvbylfvf bs gur shyyrerarf va oramrar ceb-  86 85  G. </p>
      <p>Xngb, G. Xbqnzn, Z. Blnzn, F. Bxnmnxv, G. Fuvqn, G. Anxn- tnjn, Purz. Culf. Yrgg., 8448, 831, 60. Z. E. Jnfvryrjfxv, Z. C. B’Arvy, X. E. Ylxxr, Z. W. Cryyva naq  qhprf gevcyrg fgngrf jvgu n T inyhr bs 9.0 nf gur bayl genafvrag fcrpvrf jubfr fcrpgebfpbcvp naq xvargvp srngherf unir orra rfgnoyvfurq gb or va tbbq nterrzrag jvgu gubfr trarengrq ol ynfre synfu cubgbylfvf. Obgu gur shyyrerarf unir orra fubja gb unir uvtu fgnovyvgl gbjneqf uvtu-raretl ryrpgeba chyfrf naq  80 81  Q. Z. Tehra, W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8448,886,7225. E. Gnlybe, W. C. Cnefbaf, N. T. Nirag, F. C. Enaaneq, G. W. Qraavf, W. C. Uner, U. J. Xebgb naq Q. E. Z. Jnygba, Angher (Ybaqba),8448,608,722. W. J. Neobtnfg naq P. F. Sbbgr, W. Nz. Purz. FBP., 8448, 886, 3331.  l-enqvngvba, va nqqvgvba gb gurve fgnovyvgl gbjneqf ynfre enqv-  82  Q. </p>
      <p>X. Cnyvg, N. I. Fncer, W. C. Zvggny naq P. A. E. Enb, Purz.  ngvba ercbegrq rneyvre. Ubjrire, gur fgnovyvgl bs gur shyyrerarf gbjneqf uvtu-raretl enqvngvba unf orra fubja gb or fbyirag qrcraqrag naq P29 vf zber fgnoyr guna p19.  83 84  Culf. Yrgg., 8447, 840, 8. A. Z. Qvzvgevwrivp naq C. I. Xnzng, W. Culf. Purz., 8447, 41, 5388. (n)F. A. Thun, C. A. Zbbegul, X. Xvfuber naq X. A. Enb, Cebp.  Fvaprer gunaxf ner qhr gb Cebs. P. A. E. Enb sbe cebivqvat  Maqvna Npnq. Fpv. (Purz. Fpv.), 8432, 44, 718: (o) X. V. Cevlnqne-fvav, Q. O. Anvx, C. A. Zbbegul naq W. C. Zvggny, Cebp. 2gu  cher fnzcyrf bs p19 naq P29 naq sbe znal urycshy qvf- phffvbaf. Gunaxf ner nyfb qhr gb Qe. F. X. Xhyfueyfugun, ONEP, sbe cebivqvat fbzr fnzcyrf bs shyyrerar. </p>
      <p> 79  Gvunal Flzc. ba Enq. Purz., Uhatnevna Purzvpny Fbpvrgl, Ohqncrfg, 8448, c. 890. T. R. Nqnzf, W. J. Obnt, W. Pheenag naq O. Q. Zvpunry, va Chyfr Enqvbylfvf, rq. Z. Roreg, W. C. Xrrar, N. W. Fjnyybj naq W. U.  Onkraqnyr, Npnqrzvp Cerff, Ybaqba, 8410, c. 882.  78  E. Orafnffba naq R. W. Ynaq, Cubgbpurzvpny naq Cubgbovbybtvpny  Ersreraprf  77  Eri., rq. X. P. Fzvgu, Cyrahz, Arj Lbex, 8423, c. 816. L. Xnwvv, G. Anxntnjn, F. Fhmhxv, L. Npuvon, X. Bov naq X.  U. J. Xebgb, W. E. Urngu, F. P. B’Oevra, E. S. Phey naq E. R.  Fuvohln, Purz. Culf. Yrgg., 8448, 838, 899.  Fznyyrl, Angher (Ybaqba), 8430,683, 817.  76  E. N. Ubyeblq, Shaqnzragny Cebprffrf va Enqvngvba Purzvfgel,  U. J. Xebgb, N. J. Nyyns naq F. C. Onyz, Purz. Eri., 8448, 48,  rq. C. Nhfybbf, Jvyrl-Vagrefpvrapr, Arj Lbex, 8413, c. 586.  8786.  75  W. J. G. Fcvaxf naq E. W. Jbbq, Na Vagebqhpgvba gb Enqvngvba  J. Xengfpuzre, Y. Q. Ynzo, Q. E. Uhsszna naq X. Sbfgveb-  Purzvfgel, Jvyrl, Arj Lbex, 8415, c. 694.  cbhybf, Angher (Ybaqba), 8449,652,605.  70  G. W. Uneqjvpx, W. Culf. Purz., 8417,11, 8188.  Z N. Ternarl naq F. Z. Tbeha, W. Culf. Purz., 8448,40,2857. E. S. Phey naq E. R. Fznyyrl, Fpvrapr, 8433, 757, 8982.  Cncre 7/95890T; Erprvirq 69gu Whyl, 8447   </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. J.</fname>
            <surname>Xebgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. E.</fname>
            <surname>Urngu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. P.</fname>
            <surname>B'Oevra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. S.</fname>
            <surname>Phey</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. R.</fname>
            <surname>Fznyyrl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8430</year>
          <volumeno>683</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>817</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. J.</fname>
            <surname>Xebgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. J.</fname>
            <surname>Nyyns</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. C.</fname>
            <surname>Onyz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Eri.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>48</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8786</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Xengfpuzre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Ynzo</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. E.</fname>
            <surname>Uhsszna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Sbfgvebcbhybf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <volumeno>652</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>605</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. N.</fname>
            <surname>Ternarl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Tbeha</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Culf. Purz.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>40</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>2857</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. S.</fname>
            <surname>Phey</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. R.</fname>
            <surname>Fznyyrl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Fpvrapr</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <volumeno>757</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8982</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Nwvr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Nyinerm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. W.</fname>
            <surname>Nam</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Orpx</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Qvrqrevpu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Sbfgvebcbhybf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. E.</fname>
            <surname>Uhsszna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Xengfpuzre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Ehova</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X. R.</fname>
            <surname>Fpuevire</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q.</fname>
            <surname>Frafunezn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Jurggra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Culf. Purz.</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <volumeno>45</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3169</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Cenqrrc</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Q'Fbhmn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. A.</fname>
            <surname>Fhoonaan</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I.</fname>
            <surname>Xevfuana</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. A. E.</fname>
            <surname>Enb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cebp. Vaqvna Npnq. Fpv. (Purz. Fpv.)</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>896</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>130</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. X.</fname>
            <surname>Cnyvg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. I.</fname>
            <surname>Fncer</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. C.</fname>
            <surname>Zvggny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vaqvna W. Purz.</title>
          <year>8447</year>
          <volumeno>68</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>S51</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. J.</fname>
            <surname>Roorfba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Gnavtnxv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Xhebfuvzn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Culf. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>838</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>098</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>Neobtnfg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. C.</fname>
            <surname>Qneznalna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. F.</fname>
            <surname>Sbbgr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Ehova</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. A.</fname>
            <surname>Qvrqrevpu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Nyinerm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. W.</fname>
            <surname>Nam</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Jurggra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Culf. Purz.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>40</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>88</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit11">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Tnflan</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. A.</fname>
            <surname>Fpungm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. C.</fname>
            <surname>Uner</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. W.</fname>
            <surname>Qraavf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. J.</fname>
            <surname>Xebgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E.</fname>
            <surname>Gnlybe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. E. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Jnygba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Culf. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>836</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>736</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit12">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Pbk</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Oruny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Qvfxb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Tbeha</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Ternarl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. F.</fname>
            <surname>Ufh</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. O.</fname>
            <surname>Xbyyvn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Zvyyne</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Eboovaf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Eboovaf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Furejbbq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Gvaqnyy</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>886</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>7459</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit13">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Xngb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Xbqnzn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Blnzn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Bxnmnxv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fuvqn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Anxntnjn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Culf. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>831</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>60</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit14">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. E.</fname>
            <surname>Jnfvryrjfxv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. C.</fname>
            <surname>B'Arvy</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X. E.</fname>
            <surname>Ylxxr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. W.</fname>
            <surname>Cryyva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Tehra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>886</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>7225</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit15">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E.</fname>
            <surname>Gnlybe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. C.</fname>
            <surname>Cnefbaf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. T.</fname>
            <surname>Nirag</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. C.</fname>
            <surname>Enaaneq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. W.</fname>
            <surname>Qraavf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. C.</fname>
            <surname>Uner</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. J.</fname>
            <surname>Xebgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. E. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Jnygba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>608</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>722</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit16">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>Neobtnfg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. F.</fname>
            <surname>Sbbgr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>886</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3331</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit17">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. X.</fname>
            <surname>Cnyvg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. I.</fname>
            <surname>Fncer</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. C.</fname>
            <surname>Zvggny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. A. E.</fname>
            <surname>Enb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Culf. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8447</year>
          <volumeno>840</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit18">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Qvzvgevwrivp</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. I.</fname>
            <surname>Xnzng</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Culf. Purz.</title>
          <year>8447</year>
          <volumeno>41</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5388</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit19">
        <citgroup id="cit19a">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>F. A.</fname>
              <surname>Thun</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>C. A.</fname>
              <surname>Zbbegul</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>X.</fname>
              <surname>Xvfuber</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>X. A.</fname>
              <surname>Enb</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Cebp. Vaqvna Npnq. Fpv. (Purz. Fpv.)</title>
            <year>8432</year>
            <volumeno>44</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>718</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit19b">
          <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>X. V.</fname><surname>Cevlnqnefvav</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>Q. O.</fname><surname>Anvx</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>C. A.</fname><surname>Zbbegul</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>W. C.</fname><surname>Zvggny</surname></citauth>, <title>Cebp. 2gu Gvunal Flzc. ba Enq. Purz.</title>, <citpub>Uhatnevna Purzvpny Fbpvrgl</citpub>, <pubplace>Ohqncrfg</pubplace>, <year>8448</year>, <biblscope>c. 890</biblscope>.</citation>
        </citgroup>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit20">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>T. R.</fname><surname>Nqnzf</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>W. J.</fname><surname>Obnt</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>W.</fname><surname>Pheenag</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>O. Q.</fname><surname>Zvpunry</surname></citauth>, va <title>Chyfr Enqvbylfvf</title>, rq. <editor>Z. Roreg</editor>, <editor>W. C. Xrrar</editor>, <editor>N. W. Fjnyybj</editor> naq <editor>W. U. Onkraqnyr</editor>, <citpub>Npnqrzvp Cerff</citpub>, <pubplace>Ybaqba</pubplace>, <year>8410</year>, <biblscope>c. 882</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit21">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>E.</fname><surname>Orafnffba</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>R. W.</fname><surname>Ynaq</surname></citauth>, <title>Cubgbpurzvpny naq Cubgbovbybtvpny Eri.</title>, rq. <editor>X. P. Fzvgu</editor>, <citpub>Cyrahz</citpub>, <pubplace>Arj Lbex</pubplace>, <year>8423</year>, <biblscope>c. 816</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit22">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Xnwvv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Anxntnjn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Fhmhxv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Npuvon</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Bov</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Fuvohln</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Culf. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>838</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>899</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit23">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>E. N.</fname><surname>Ubyeblq</surname></citauth>, <title>Shaqnzragny Cebprffrf va Enqvngvba Purzvfgel</title>, rq. <editor>C. Nhfybbf</editor>, <citpub>Jvyrl-Vagrefpvrapr</citpub>, <pubplace>Arj Lbex</pubplace>, <year>8413</year>, <biblscope>c. 586</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit24">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>W. J. G.</fname><surname>Fcvaxf</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>E. W.</fname><surname>Jbbq</surname></citauth>, <title>Na Vagebqhpgvba gb Enqvngvba Purzvfgel</title>, <citpub>Jvyrl</citpub>, <pubplace>Arj Lbex</pubplace>, <year>8415</year>, <biblscope>c. 694</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit25">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. W.</fname>
            <surname>Uneqjvpx</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Culf. Purz.</title>
          <year>8417</year>
          <volumeno>11</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8188</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
