<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../DTDs/rscart36.dtd">
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>C39910000552</ms-id>
    <doi>10.1039/C39910000552</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>C3</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>
</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>8</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>552</fpage>
      <lpage>554</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>3</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1991</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>C3</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1991</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Synthesis and structure of a perpendicular bridging alkylidyneamine ligand in [W<inf>2</inf>(η-C<inf>5</inf>H<inf>4</inf>Pr<sup>i</sup>)<inf>2</inf>Cl<inf>4</inf>(µ-Cl)(µ-EtCNH)]</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Qian</fname>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Montserrat</fname>
            <surname>Ferrer</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Malcolm L. H.</fname>
            <surname>Green</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Patrick C.</fname>
            <surname>McGowan</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Philip</fname>
            <surname>Mountford</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Victor S. B.</fname>
            <surname>Mtetwa</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Treatment of the W___ENT___W triply-bonded dimers [W<inf>2</inf>(η-C<inf>5</inf>H<inf>4</inf>R)<inf>2</inf>Cl<inf>4</inf>](R = Pr<sup>i</sup> or Me) with R′CN (R′= Me, Et, or Ph) followed by HCl gas affords the complexes [W<inf>2</inf>(η-C<inf>5</inf>H<inf>4</inf>R)<inf>2</inf>Cl<inf>4</inf>(µ-Cl)(µ-R′CNH)] in quantitative yield; the X-ray crystal structure for R = Pr<sup>i</sup>, R′= Et reveals a perpendicular bridging EtCNH ligand.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p>  J. CHEM. SOC. CHEM. COMMUN. 1991  Synthesis and Structure of a Perpendicular Bridging Alkylidyneamine Ligand in  [W2(q-C5H4Pri)2C14( @I)( p-EtCNH)]  Qian Feng,a Montserrat Ferrer,a Malcolm L. H. Green,*a Patrick C. McGowan,a Philip Mountforda and  Victor S. B. Mtetwab  a Inorganic Chemistry Laboratory South Parks Road Oxford OX1 3QR UK  b University of Swaziland P/B 4 Kwaluseni Manzini Swaziland  Treatment of the WsW triply-bonded dimers [W2(q-C5H4R)2C14] = Pri or Me) with R’CN (R’ = Me Et or Ph) (R  followed by HCI gas affords the complexes [W~(~-CF,H,R)~CI~(~-CI)(~-CI)(~-R’CNH)] in quantitative yield; the X-ray  crystal structure for R = Pri R’ = Et reveals a perpendicular bridging EtCNH ligand.  Alkyne complexes of the general types 1-111 (X= C)are well perpendicular bridge p-alkylidyneamine complexes (I,X = N) established in organo-transition metal chemistry. </p>
      <p>However have not been described. Here we report the synthesis and  although the closely-related alkylidyneamine ligand (RCNR’) characterisation of the perpendicular bridge p-alkylidyne-  has been found to coordinate to metal centres in terminal2 (11 amine derivatives [W2(q-C5H4R)2C1~(p-C1)(p-R’CNH)] (R =  X = N) and parallel bridging3 (111 X = N) modes Pri or Me; R’ = Me Et or Ph).       J. CHEM. SOC. CHEM. COMMUN. 1991  Treatment of toluene solutions of the W=W triply-bonded  compounds [W2(q-C5H4R)2C14] (1 R = Pri a or Me b)4with  nitriles (R'CN) affords brown compounds the analytical and  spectroscopic datat for which are consistent with com-pounds containing a p-(a + n)-bound nitrile ligand  [W2(q-C5H4R)2Cl4(p-(o+ n)-R'CN}](R' = Me 2 Et 3 or  Ph 4; R = Pri a or Me b). </p>
      <p> Thus the 1H and 13C NMR spectra of 2-4 show resonances  assignable to two diastereotopic q-C5H4R ligands and to a  coordinated R'CN ligand. In the 13C NMR spectra the  resonances for the internal carbon atoms of the R'CN ligand  appear at 6 ca. 240 and possess 183W satellites (where  observed) of the proper intensity for a carbon atom bonded to  one tungsten atom [11(13C-l83W) ca. 95 Hz; satellite intensity  ca. 14% by area]. There is no evidence for a v(CkN)  absorption in the IR spectra of 2-4 and since submission of  our manuscript we have obtained preliminary results of an  X-ray crystal structure determination of 3b that confirm  the p-(a + n) mode of coordination of the nitrile ligand  illustrated. </p>
      <p>Complexes containing a p-(0 + n)-nitrile moiety  have been reported previously.5  R R'  I II m  t Satisfactory analyses have been obtained for all the new compounds  except 5a which could only be obtained as an oily solid contaminated  by varying quantities of solvent.  Selected spectroscopic data IR data cm-1 KBr. NMR data 1H 300  MHz 13C-{ lH} 75.5 MHz as 6 relative to SiMe4,a in [2H6]ben~ene,b  in [2H2]dichloromethane,c in [2H6]dimethyl sulphoxide relative  intensity coupling constant (J in Hz) and assignment; for virtual  multiplets the apparent coupling constant is not given; J refers to the  'H-lH coupling constant unless stated otherwise. 2a 1H NMR:a 6.33  5.60 (2 X virtual q 2 X lH 2 x q-C5H4Pri) 5.42 (overlapping 2 x  virtual q 2H 2 X q-C5H4Pri) 5.33,5.28,5.20,4.99 (4 x virtual q 4 x  lH 4 X q-C5H4Pri) 3.42 [s 3H y-(0 + n)-MeCN] 3.22 2.91 (2 x  sept 2 x 1H J6.9,2 x CHMe2) 1.30-1.0 (4 x d 4 x 3H,J6.9,4 x  CHMe2). </p>
      <p>13C-{1H} NMRa 240.7 (1J[13C-183W] 98 [ca. 14.1% by area)  p-(o + n)-MeCN] 130.8,130.4 (2 x CPri) 105.4,105.0,103.4,101.8  100.8,97.8,90.7 [8 x CH (7-C5H4Pri); two signals overlapping] 29.2  28.8 (2 x CHMe2) 26.3 [y-(a + n)-MeCN] 23.8,23.0,22.7,22.4 (4 x  CHMe2).  2b 'H NMRF 5.88 5.65 5.40 (3 x virtual q 3 x lH 3 x  q-C5H4Me) 5.35 (overlapping 2 x virtual q 2H 2 x q-C5H4Me)  5.20 5.05,4.67 (3 x virtual q 3 x lH 3 x q-C5H4Me) 3.35 [s 3H  y-(a + n)-MeCN] 2.15 2.07 (2 X s 2 X 3H 2 X q-C5H4Me).  5a 1H NMR:b 6.20 (br m 2H 2 x q-C5H4Pri) 5.89 (br s lH  y-MeCNH) 5.73,5.17 4.78 (3 x br m 3 x 2H 3 x q-C5H4Pri) 3.91  (s 3H y-MeCNH) 3.52 (sept 2H J6.9 CHMe2) 1.45 1.38 (2 x d  2 X 6H J 6.9 2 X CHMe2). </p>
      <p>13C-{1H} NMR:b 141 [1J(13C-l*3W) 34  (ca. 26% by area) y-MeCNH] 134.8 (CPr') 114.6,105.7,100.4,98.8  [4 X CH (q-C5H4Pri)] 28.1 (CHMe2) 27.2 (p-MeCNH) 22.5,21.5 (2  x CHMe2). IR v(N-H) 3342.  5b IH NMR:' 9.54 (br s lH y-MeCNH) 5.99,5.95,5.50,5.47 (4  X br m 4 X 2H 4 X q-C5H4Me) 3.71 (s 3H y-MeCNH) 2.53 (s 6H  q-C5H4Me).  8 1H NMR:b 6.99 5.79 5.74 (3 X virtual q 3 X lH 3 X  q-C5H4Pri) 5.67 (2 x overlapping virtual q 2H 2 x q-C5H4Pri) 5.59  (virtual q lH q-C5H4Pri) 5.53 [d of virtual q lH 3J(lH-31P) 7.5  q-C5H4Pri] 4.46 (d of q lH 2J 16.1 3J7.3 CH2Me) 4.36 (virtual q  lH q-C5H4Pri) 4.07 (d of q lH 2J 15.1 3J7.3 CH2Me) 3.84 (d of q  lH 2J 15.1 3J7.3 CH2Me) 3.39 (d of q lH 2J 16.1 3J 7.3 CH2Me)  2.95(sept,1H,J7.3,CHMe2),2.35(sept,1H,J7.3,CHMe2),1.68[d  9H 2J(lH-3lP) 8.8 PMe3] 1.27 (d 3H J 7.3 CHMe2) 1.21  (overlapping 2 X d and t 9H CHMe2 and CH2Me) 1.10 (t 3H 57.3  CH2Me) 1.00 (d 3H J 7.3 CHMe2). </p>
      <p>13C-{lH) NMR? 141.4 [d  2J(13C-31P) 7 y-C2Et2] 138.4 132.6 (2 X CPri) 121.3 [d 2J(13C-31P)  7 y-C2Et2] 106.2 103.3 102.2 98.3 95.6 91.5 89.9 89.6 [8 X CH  (q-C5H4Pri)] 31.4 [d 3J(*3C-31P) 7 CH2Me] 29.9 (CH2Me) 28.7  28.2 (2 x CHMe2) 23.1,22.9,22.4 21.6 (4 x CHMez) 18.8 17.7 (2  x CH2Me) 15.7 [d 1J(13C-31P) 28 PMe31.  553  Treatment of toluene solutions of 2-4 with HC1 gas  affords the purple complexes [W2(q-C5H4R)2C14( p-Cl)(p-R'CNH)](R' = Me 5 Et 6 or Ph 7; R = Pri a or Me b)  in near-quantitative yields. </p>
      <p>The molecular structure of [W2(q-C5H4Pri)2C14( p-Cl) (p-EtCNH)] 6a$ as determined by single  crystal X-ray diffraction is shown in Fig. 1.The compound 6a  consists of two mutually eclipsed W(q- C5H4Pri)C12 fragments  linked by bridging C1 and EtCNH groups.$ If the q-C5H4Pri  rings are considered to occupy single coordination sites and  any metal-metal bond is ignored then 6a may be described as a  confacial bioctahedron. The W-W bond length [2.9359(4) A]  in 6a is substantially lengthened from that of the precursor  [W2(q-C5H4Pri)2C14] [la W=W = 2.3678(6) A] and the C-N  bond length [1.405(8) A]is notably lon er than those observed  for q2-RCNR' complexes (1.22-1.30 R).2 These observations  suggest extensive donation of electron density from the  ditungsten centre to vacant n* orbitals of the p-EtCNH ligand  in a manner analogous to that proposed to occur for dinuclear  p-alkyne complexes (I X = CR').la  The solution 1H and 13C NMR data for 5-7 are consistent  with the maintenance of structures analogous to that of 661. </p>
      <p> Thus the 1H NMR spectra show resonances assignable to a  diastereotopic -q-C5H4R ring and to a R'CNH ligand the N-H  resonance appearing as a broad signal at 6 ca. 6 (in  [2H2]dichloromethane) or 6 ca. 10 (in [2H6]dimethyl sulphox-  ide). The 13C NMR spectra also show resonances assignable to  q-C5H4R and R' moieties. An additional singlet at 6 ca. 145  laR=Pi  IbR=Me  R'  7  $ Crystal data for 6a C19H28C15NW2,M = 815A1 crystal size = ca. </p>
      <p> 0.15 x 0.25 x 0.30 mm monoclinic space group nl/c a = 7.347(1)  b = 13.840(2) c = 22.767(4) A p = 94.41(2)" V = 2300.7 A3,2 = 4  D,= 2.354 g cm-3 y(Mo-Ka) = 108.05 cm-1 F(OO0) = 1528 scan  mode 0-20 T = 293 K 2 &lt; 28 &lt; 50° total unique data 4044 number  of observations [I &gt; 3a(Z)] 3164 number of variables 245 observa-  tiondvariables 12.9 Rmerge = 0.041 R = 0.028 R = 0.033  (Chebyshev; parameters 21.4 -16.7 16.2 -0.580). Data were  collected on an Enraf-Nonius CAD4-F diffractometer . The structure  was solved using Patterson and Fourier syntheses and refined by  full-matrix least-squares procedures with anisotropic thermal  parameters for all non-hydrogen atoms. Hydrogen atoms attached to  C were placed in calculated positions. </p>
      <p>Crystallographic calculations  were carried out using the CRYSTALS suite of programs7 on a Micro  VAX 3800 computer in the Chemical Crystallography Laboratory  Oxford. Atomic coordinates bond lengths and angles and thermal  parameters have been deposited at the Cambridge Crystallographic  Data Centre. See Notice to Authors Issue No. 1.  B The N-H atom could not be located from a Fourier difference  synthesis but its position may be inferred from the IR and NMR data.       Et  'Pi  /PM.  t  Fig. 1Molecular structure of [W2(q-CSH4Pri)2C14(p-C1)( p-EtCNH)]  6a. Hydrogen atoms omitted for clarity. Selected bond lengths (A) and angles (") as follows W(l)-W(2) 2.9359(4) W(l)-Cl( 1) 2.462(2)  W( 1)-C1(2) 2.454(2) W( l)-Cl( 3) 2.434(2) W( 1)-N( 1) 2.064( 6)  W( 1)-C( 1) 2.100(7) W( l)-Cpcent(i) 2.03 W(2)-C1( 3) 2.443(2)  W (2)-Cl(4) 2.479(2) W( 2)-C1(5) 2.420( 2) W (2)-N( 1) 2.049( 6)  W(2)-C( 1) 2.106(7) W(2)-Cpcent(~) 2.04; W( l)-Cl( 3)-W(2) 74.02( 5)  C(2)-C(l)-N(1) 126.6(6) Cpcent(l)-w(1)-W(2) 121* 1 Cpcent(2)-W(2)-W(1) 121.9 where Cpcent(l) and Cpcent(2) refer to the computed  q-C5H4Pri centroids for W( 1) and W(2) respectively. </p>
      <p> which (where observed) shows 183W satellites of the proper  intensity for a carbon atom bonded to two tungsten atoms is  assigned to the internal carbon atom of the pR'CNH ligand.  A sharp band at ca. 3340 cm-1 in the IR spectra of 5-7 is  assigned as v(N-H) ; the isotopomer [W2(q-C5H4Pri)2C14(  p-Cl)(p-MeCND)] 5a4 prepared from la and MeCN followed  by treatment with DC1 shows a band assignable to v(N-D) at  2486 cm-1. </p>
      <p> We have also prepared the related perpendicular bridge  p-alkyne complex [W2(q-C5H4Pri)2C13( p-Cl)( p-C2Et2)-  (PMe3)] 8 from [W2(q-C5H4Pri)2C14(  p-C2Et2)]6 and PMe3.  The analytical and spectroscopic data for 8 strongly support a  structure analogous to those 5-7. Thus the 1H and 13C NMR  spectra of 8 show resonances assignable to two types of  J. CHEM. SOC. CHEM. COMMUN. 1991  diastereotopic q-C5H4Pri and Et groups and an additional  doublet at 6 1.68 is assigned to a PMe3 ligand. Resonances  assignable to the internal carbon atoms of the p-C2Et2 ligand  are observed as doublets at 6 141.4 and 121.3 [21(13C-31P)  7 Hz] the low field shift being in the range observed for the  internal C atoms of the y-R'CNH ligands in 5-7. </p>
      <p>The  compounds 5-8 are valence isoelectronic and further highlight  the close relationship between the R'CNH and RCCR'  ligands.  In conclusion we have shown for the first time that the  RCNH ligand can coordinate in a perpendicular bridging  manner analogous to that well-established for alkynes.  We thank the Chinese government C.I.R.I.T. of  Generalitat de Catalunya and the D.E.N.I. for support (to  Q. F. M. F. and P. C. McG. respectively).  Received 10th January 1991; Corn. 1I001 291  References  (a) D. M. Hoffman R. Hoffmann and C. R. Fisel J. Am. Chem.  SOC.,1982 104 3858; (b)M. J. Winter Adv. Organornet. Chem.  1989 29 101; (c) W. E. Buhro and M. H. Chisholm Adv.  Organomet. Chem. 1987 27 311; (d) R. S. Dickson and P. J. </p>
      <p> Fraser Adv. Organomet. Chem. 1974 12 323; (e)P. R. Raithby  and M. J. Rosales Adv. Znorg. Chem. Radiochem. 1986,29 169  and references cited therein.  R. D. Adams and D. F. Chodosh Znorg. Chern. 1978 17 41;  W. R. Roper G. E. Taylor J. M. Waters and L. J. Wright.  J. Organomet. Chem. 1978 157 C27; F. Van Bolhnis E. J. M.  deBoer and J. H. Teuben J. Organomet. Chem. 1979,170,299; G.  Bellachioma G. Cardaci and P. Zanazzi Znorg. Chem. 1987 26  84; M. Pasquali S. Gambarotta C. Floriani A. Chiesi-Villa and C.  Gaustini Znorg. Chem. 1981 20 165; A. K. McMullen 1. P.  Rothwell and J. C. Huffman J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1985 107 1072;  F. H. Elmer T. D. Tilley A. H. Rheingold and S. J. Geib  J. Organomet. Chem. 1988 358 169; A. C. Sullivan G.  Wilkinson M. Motevalli and M. </p>
      <p>B. Hursthouse J. Chem. SOC.  Dalton Trans. 1988 53; L. R. Chamberlain L. D. Durfee P. E.  Fanwick L. Kobriger S. L. Latesky A. K. McMullen I. P.  Rothwell K. Folting J. C. Huffman W. E. Streib and R. Wang J.  Am. Chem. SOC. 1987 109 390; M. Bochmann L. M. Wilson  M. B. Hursthouse and R. L. Short Organometallics,1987,6,2557.  R. D. Adams D. A. Katahira and L.-W. Yang J. Organomet.  Chem.,1981,219,85; H. tom Dieck J. Klaus and J. Kopf J. Chem.  Soc. Chem. Commun. 1982 574; R. D. Adams Z. Dawoodi  D. F. Foust and B. E. Segmuller J. Am. Chem. SOC. 1983 105  831; R. D. Adams and D. F. Foust Organometallics,1983,2,323;  R. D. Adams and N. M. Golembeski J. Organomet. Chem. 1979  239 1979; C. Mahe H. Patin J.-Y. Le Marouille and A. Benolt  Organometallics,1983,2 1051; J. </p>
      <p>Dupont M. Pfeffer J. C. Daran  and Y. Jeannin Organometallics,1987 6 899; R. D. Adams and  N. M. Golembeski Znorg. Chem. 1978,17,1969; R. D. Adams and  N. M. Golembeski J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1979 101,2579; H. Patin  G. Mignani C. Mahe J.-Y. Le Marouille A. Benoit D.  Grandjean and G. Levesque J. Organomet. Chem. 1981 208  c39.  M. L. H. Green and P. Mountford J. Chem. Soc. Chem.  Commun. 1989 732; M. L. H. Green J. D. Hubert and P.  Mountford J. Chern. SOC. Dalton Trans. 1990 3793.  M. H. Chisholm F. A. Cotton M. W. Extine and L. A. Rankel  J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1979,100,807; M. H. Chisholm J. C. Huffman  and N. S. Marchant J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1983 105 6162; M. H.  Chisholm K. Folting J. C. Huffman and N. S. Marchant  Polyhedron 1984 3 1033.  6 M. L. H. Green and P. Mountford Organometallics,1990,9 886.  7 D. J. Watkin J. R. Carruthers and P. W. Betteridge CRYSTALS  User Guide Chemical Crystallography Laboratory University of  Oxford 1985.     </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <citgroup id="cit1a">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>D. M.</fname>
              <surname>Hoffman</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>R.</fname>
              <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>C. R.</fname>
              <surname>Fisel</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
            <year>1982</year>
            <volumeno>104</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>3858</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1b">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>M. J.</fname>
              <surname>Winter</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Adv. Organomet. Chem.</title>
            <year>1989</year>
            <volumeno>29</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>101</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1c">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>W. E.</fname>
              <surname>Buhro</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>M. H.</fname>
              <surname>Chisholm</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Adv. Organomet. Chem.</title>
            <year>1987</year>
            <volumeno>27</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>311</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1d">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>R. S.</fname>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>P. J.</fname>
              <surname>Fraser</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Adv. Organomet. Chem.</title>
            <year>1974</year>
            <volumeno>12</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>323</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1e">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>P. R.</fname>
              <surname>Raithby</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>M. J.</fname>
              <surname>Resales</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Adv. Inorg. Chem. Radiochem.</title>
            <year>1986</year>
            <volumeno>29</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>169</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
          <citext>, and references cited therein.</citext>
        </citgroup>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. F.</fname>
            <surname>Chodosh</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volumeno>17</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>41</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. R.</fname>
            <surname>Roper</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. E.</fname>
            <surname>Taylor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. M.</fname>
            <surname>Waters</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L. J.</fname>
            <surname>Wright</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Organomet. Chem.</title>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volumeno>157</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>C27</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Van Bolhnis</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. J. M.</fname>
            <surname>deBoer</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. H.</fname>
            <surname>Teuben</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Organomet. Chem.</title>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volumeno>170</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>299</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Bellachioma</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Cardaci</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Zanazzi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volumeno>26</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>84</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Pasquali</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Gambarotta</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Floriani</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A.</fname>
            <surname>Chiesi-Villa</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Gaustini</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volumeno>20</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>165</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. K.</fname>
            <surname>McMullen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I. P.</fname>
            <surname>Rothwell</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. C.</fname>
            <surname>Huffman</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volumeno>107</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1072</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. H.</fname>
            <surname>Elsner</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. D.</fname>
            <surname>Tilley</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. H.</fname>
            <surname>Rheingold</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. J.</fname>
            <surname>Geib</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Organomet. Chem.</title>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volumeno>358</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>169</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. C.</fname>
            <surname>Sullivan</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Wilkinson</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Motevalli</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. B.</fname>
            <surname>Hursthouse</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Dalton Trans.</title>
          <year>1988</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>53</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L. R.</fname>
            <surname>Chamberlain</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L. D.</fname>
            <surname>Durfee</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. E.</fname>
            <surname>Fanwick</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Kobriger</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. L.</fname>
            <surname>Latesky</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. K.</fname>
            <surname>McMullen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I. P.</fname>
            <surname>Rothwell</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Folting</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. C.</fname>
            <surname>Huffman</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. E.</fname>
            <surname>Streib</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R.</fname>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volumeno>109</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>390</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Bochmann</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L. M.</fname>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. B.</fname>
            <surname>Hursthouse</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. L.</fname>
            <surname>Short</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Organometallics</title>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volumeno>6</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>2557</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. A.</fname>
            <surname>Katahira</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.-W.</fname>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Organomet. Chem.</title>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volumeno>219</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>85</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>torn Dieck</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Klaus</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Kopf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Chem. Commun.</title>
          <year>1982</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>574</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Dawoodi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. F.</fname>
            <surname>Foust</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>B. E.</fname>
            <surname>Segmuller</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volumeno>105</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>831</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. F.</fname>
            <surname>Foust</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Organometallics</title>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volumeno>2</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>323</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. M.</fname>
            <surname>Golembeski</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Organomet. Chem.</title>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volumeno>239</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1979</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Mahe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Patin</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.-Y.</fname>
            <surname>Le Marouille</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A.</fname>
            <surname>Benolt</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Organometallics</title>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volumeno>2</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1051</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Dupont</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Pfeffer</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. C.</fname>
            <surname>Daran</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Jeannin</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Organometallics</title>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volumeno>6</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>899</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. M.</fname>
            <surname>Golembeski</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volumeno>17</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1969</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. M.</fname>
            <surname>Golembeski</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volumeno>101</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>2579</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Patin</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Mignani</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Mahe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.-Y.</fname>
            <surname>Le Marouille</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A.</fname>
            <surname>Benoit</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D.</fname>
            <surname>Grandjean</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Levesque</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Organomet. Chem.</title>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volumeno>208</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>C39</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. L. H.</fname>
            <surname>Green</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Mountford</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Chem. Commun.</title>
          <year>1989</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>732</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. L. H.</fname>
            <surname>Green</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. D.</fname>
            <surname>Hubert</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Mountford</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Dalton Trans.</title>
          <year>1990</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3793</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. H.</fname>
            <surname>Chisholm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. A.</fname>
            <surname>Cotton</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. W.</fname>
            <surname>Extine</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L. A.</fname>
            <surname>Rankel</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volumeno>100</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>807</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. H.</fname>
            <surname>Chisholm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. C.</fname>
            <surname>Huffman</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. S.</fname>
            <surname>Marchant</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volumeno>105</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6162</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. H.</fname>
            <surname>Chisholm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Folting</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. C.</fname>
            <surname>Huffman</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. S.</fname>
            <surname>Marchant</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Polyhedron</title>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volumeno>3</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1033</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. L. H.</fname>
            <surname>Green</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Mountford</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Organometallics</title>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volumeno>9</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>886</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <citation type="other"><citauth><fname>D. J.</fname><surname>Watkin</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>J. R.</fname><surname>Carruthers</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>P. W.</fname><surname>Betleridge</surname></citauth>, <title>CRYSTALS User Guide, Chemical Crystallography Laboratory</title>, <citpub>Universily of Oxford</citpub>, <year>1985</year>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
