<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../DTDs/rscart36.dtd">
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>FT9908602163</ms-id>
    <doi>10.1039/FT9908602163</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>FT</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>86</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>12</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>2163</fpage>
      <lpage>2167</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>5</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1990</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>FT</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1990</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Kinetics for the surface-controlled dissolution of a powder dispersion with a log-normal distribution in particle size</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Andrew</fname>
            <surname>Mills</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Hefin L.</fname>
            <surname>Davies</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Michael S.</fname>
            <surname>Garley</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>A model has been developed describing the kinetics of a simple surface-controlled dissolution reaction involving a powder dispersion with a log-normal (log-Gaussian) distribution in particle size. The model was then used to analyse previously published kinetic data on the dissolution of a polydispersed powder suspension. The results of this analysis allowed the calculation of the relative volume (%)<it>vs.</it> particle diameter for the powder and this compared favourably with the plot of the experimentally determined results.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p> J. CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1990, 86(12), 2163-2167 Kinetics for the Surface-controlled Dissolution of a Powder Dispersion with a log-Normal Distribution in Particle Size Andrew Mills,” Hefin L. Davies and Michael S. Garley Department of Chemistry, University College of Swansea, Singleton Park, Swansea SA2 8PP A model has been developed describing the kinetics of a simple surface-controlled dissolution reaction involv- ing a powder dispersion with a log-normal (log-Gaussian) distribution in particle size. The model was then used to analyse previously published kinetic data on the dissolution of a polydispersed powder suspension. The results of this analysis allowed the calculation of the relative volume (%) vs. particle diameter for the powder and this compared favourably with the plot of the experimentally determined results. Dissolution of particulate matter is of importance to many subjects including : mineralogy, hydrometallurgy and nuclear plant decontamination. </p>
      <p>Given the clear, widespread relevance of this subject to industry, it is not surprising to note that in the past much of the research into the area had been directed toward improving the associated technology.’ In more recent years, however, interest in more fundamental studies has grown. For example, the kinetics of metal oxide dissolution, via either a reductive or an oxidative mechanism, have attracted considerable attention recently and a significant attempt has been made to relate the kinetics of dissolution to the structure, composition and morphology of the oxide and the nature of the reactant.2-6 In a recent paper by Segal and Sellers3 on the kinetics of reductive dissolution of a dispersion of nickel ferrite powder by tris(pico1inato) vanadium(I1) it was noted that if the oxide particles were not of the same size (Le. not monodispersed) but rather comprised many different sizes (i.e.polydispersed) then the observed kinetics of dissolution would show a sig- nificant deviation from the often used simple cubic rate law when the degree of dissolution was large, i.e. </p>
      <p>typically &gt;75% ; this deviation would increase with increasing dissolution, although, in practice, analytical errors start to become impor- tant at &gt;90% dissolution. To illustrate this point these workers took as a crude example a distribution of equal masses of particles of size I, 2r, 3r, 4r and 5r and showed that the predicted dissolution kinetics obeyed the cubic rate law for a uniform distribution of particles of size 2.5 over the first 60% of dissolution and showed an increasingly positive deviation with increasing dissolution above 60%. </p>
      <p>It has been found that in many cases the particle size dis- tribution in a powder suspension obeys the log-normal dis- tribution law7 and in this paper we examine what happens to the observed kinetics of dissolution of a powder suspension when it is polydispersed and the dispersion in particle size fits a log-normal distribution. The predictions arising from this model are then tested using previously published’ decay data on the reductive dissolution of a polydispersed oxide suspen- sion for which some particle size distribution data are also available.8 The Cubic Rate Law/log-Normal Model Let us consider the general dissolution reaction aX + bY -,cZ + dQ (1) where X is a heterogeneous powder suspension which dis- solves to form Z upon exposure to Y, which in turn forms Q as a result of the reaction. </p>
      <p>The terms a, b, c and d are the appropriate reaction stoichiometries, Y, Z and Q are homo- geneous species and it is assumed that their removal does not limit the rate of dissolution. It is also assumed that the rate of dissolution of powder particles involves reaction at the par- ticle surface as the controlling step and, therefore, is pro- portional to the instantaneous surface area. </p>
      <p>In practice the dissolution of a powder suspension often appears to fit this simple Thus, in reaction (1) for a suspension of n powder particles of compound X of radius I, the rate of disso- lution will be given by drnldt = -nkA (2) where rn is the mass of undissolved particles of X (in g), A is the instantaneous surface area due to a particle and k is the rate constant (in g s-’ m-2). The rate constant will depend upon the nature of X and the concentration of Z. If the par- ticles are spherical, then A = 4d. Substituting for A into eqn (1)and integrating gives the simple cubic rate law2 1 -{rnJrn,)’/3 = kt/(r,p) (3) where rn, and rn, are the total masses of undissolved particles at t = 0 and t, respectively. </p>
      <p>(Note that in this model t cannot exceed rop/k, since after this time no particles are left.) The term ro refers to the initial size of the particles of X (in m) at t = 0, and p is the density of X (in g m-3). In practice,’-6 the dissolution of a powder suspension is frequently monitored indirectly via the appearance of one of the dissolution pro- ducts, e.g. Z in this case. From eqn (3) the following equation can be derived: (4) where [Z], and [Z], are the concentrations of Z at t and t = co,respectively. This is another version of the ‘simple’ cubic rate law from which it is expected that a plot of (1 -[Z]J[Z],)’/3 DS. t should be a straight line with a gradient equal to k/(rop). In practice, the parameter k/(r,p) is often taken as kobs and, in more detailed studies, has been exam- ined as a function of [XI, [yl and temperature. </p>
      <p>The results of this work can then be used to predict the kinetics of disso- lution via eqn (3) or (4) for a wide range of reaction condi- tions using the model presented above.’-6 A basic assumption made in the derivation of eqn (3) and (4) is that the powder suspension is monodispersed. In prac- tice, however, it may be polydispersed and, as a result, the observed kinetics for its dissolution will not obey the simple cubic rate law. As noted in the introduction, in many cases it has been shown that the particle size distribution in a powder suspension, or colloid, is best described by the log-normal   2164 distribution law,’ i.e. n = ii exp(-x2) (5) and yx = In(r/F) (6) where n is the number of particles of radius, r, fi is the number of particles with the number average radius i; and y is a measure of the width of the distribution. </p>
      <p>Fig. 1 illustrates the effect of y on the particle size distribution, as predicted by eqn (5)and (6). If we assume that in the powder suspension the distribu- tion in size of the powder particles of X obeys the log-normal law, then, from eqn (6) for reaction (1) at t = 0, each initial particle radius, r,, will be related to the number average initial radius i;, by the expression r, = Fo exp(yx). (7) In addition, from eqn (5)and (6) the mass of particles of X of initial radius ro at t = 0 will be mx, = ,,where mx, = ,= 474 exp(3yx)ii exp( -x2)p/3. </p>
      <p>(8) It follows that at t = 0 the total mass due to undissolved par- ticles ofX will be given by X=00 m,=,(total) = C mx,t=O. (9) x= -m From eqn (3) and (SH7)at a time t after the start of the reaction, where r,p/k 3 t 3 0, the mass due to undissolved particles of X of radius ro ,i.e. mx,,will be mx, = 474 exp(3yx)ii exp( -x2) x PC 1 -kt exp(-yx)/(F, PI1 3/3 (10) with the condition that when t &gt; roy/k, mX,,= 0. Thus, within the constraints of this condition, at any time t during the corrosion reaction the total mass due to undissolved par- 1 5 0.5 \ \ \ 1 2 3 4 r/f Fig. 1. Plot of n/ii us. r/? for y values of (a)0, (b)0.5,(c) 1 and (d)2. These curves were calculated using eqn (5)and (6). </p>
      <p>J. CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1990, VOL. 86 ticles of X will be x= 00 m,(total) = C mx,,. x= -a&gt; Combining eqn (8)-(11) yields the following expression m,(total)’,= m,=,(total) where z = kt/(F,p). (13) As noted previously, in an experimental study of the disso- lution of a powder suspension, either the ratio m,(total)/m,= ,(total) or, more usually, the ratio [Z],/[Z]ai is determined as a function of time. The two ratios are related to each other and the theoretical quantity rn,(total)/rn,=,(total) (= fir) by the following simple expression ~m,(total)/rn,= ,(total) = m,(t otal)/m, ,( total) = 1 -CZlJCZJ,. (14) It is appropriate at this point to introduce a term which we shall refer to asf(x, z) or the ‘fractional mass’ and define it as the ratio of the mass of undissolved particles at time z which had an initial radius r,, to the total mass of undissolved par- ticles at t = 0, i.e.f(x, z) = mx,r/m,=,(total). </p>
      <p>Fig. 2 illustrates how f(x, z) varies with z and x over the range ro/Fo = 24.5 (x = 4) to ro/Fo = 0.041 (x = -4) when y = 0.8. The results illustrated in fig. 2 highlight the general observation that in the initial part of the dissolution reaction the smaller particles are consumed and that, consequently, as the reaction pro- ceeds, the average particle radius increases from its initial value of F, . Fundamental to the cubic rate law for the dissolution of a monodisperse powder suspension is eqn (2). However, since A = 47cr2, m = 4nr3np/3 and dr/dt = (dm/dt)(dr/drn), it fol-lows that dr/dt = -k/p (1 sj i.e. </p>
      <p>the rate of change of the radius of the powder particles is independent of the radius. This would also be true in the -.I -4 X Fig. 2. Plot off(x, 7) us. T for y = 0.8, calculated using eqn (SH10).   J. CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1990, VOL. 86 cubic rate law/log-normal model. Thus, the rate of change of the radius of the very large particles would be the same as the rate of change of the very small particles. This would lead to the overall effect that as the reaction proceeds the kinetics will become increasingly dominated by the larger particles. Interestingly, the integrated form of this equation, i.e. I, = F,[exp(yx) -z] (16) shows how the radius of the particles varies with z. </p>
      <p>In eqn (7) it is clear that for a given distribution, i.e. fixed value of y, the term x defines the initial particle radius, ro, in terms of the number average initial particle radius, To. Thus, in fig. 2 we can see how f(x, z) for a number of particles with different values of r0, and therefore x, varies with time. However, it is interesting to see how not onlyf(x, z) varies with z, but also how the particle size r,, which starts off at ro, varies with z. In fig. 3 we have attempted to illustrate this effect for y = 0.8 by plottingf(x, z) as a function of z and x’, where x’ is given by the following expression x’ = x + ln[l -z exp(-yx)]/y. (17) The term x’ is related to rr in the same way that x is related to r0, i.e. </p>
      <p>yx’ = ln(r,/Fo); eqn (17) is derived from eqn (16) by eliminating rr/Fo. As you might expect, fig. 3 shows that as f(x, z) decreases so does x’ (and, therefore, so does r,). In addition, fig, 3 shows that regardless of the initial particle radius at a given value of x’, say x’ = -1 for example, the change in z required before the particles are very small, say x‘ = -4, is constant (in this case AT = 0.4082) as expected given eqn (1 5). For any value of y, the area under thef(x, z)us. x curve at any time z (see fig. 2) is equal to rn,(total)/m,,,(total), i.e. = p,. In a typical cubic law plot [rn,(t~tal)/rn,=~(total)]’~~or fif13 is plotted against z arid fig. 4 illustrates how D:’3, calcu-lated using the log-normal/cubic rate law model, varies with z for a series of different values of 1’. </p>
      <p>If the powder suspension is monodisperse y = 0, and the kinetics of dissolution should obey the ‘simple’ cubic rate law which predicts that a plot of [j,‘I3 us. z, should be a straight line with a gradient = 1, as illustrated in fig. 4 curve (a). However, it is clear from the other curves in fig. 4,that the greater the distribution width of particle sizes, i.e. the greater the value of y, the more sig- nificant the deviation from linearity observed in a typical cubic-law plot of the predicted decay data, even though the initial number average particle size for all the dispersions is the same, i.e. F, . N 0’  5  10  7  Fig. 4. Plot  of  { =[rn,(t~tal)/m,=,(total)]’’~= [rn,(total)/  rn,=,(t~tal)J’/~}us. </p>
      <p>7 for y values of (a)0, (b)0.5, (c) 1, (4 1.5 and (e) 2. The term B1I3was calculated using eqn (1 2). From the above discussion it follows that if, in the general dissolution reaction (l), the powder suspension of X com-prises particles whose sizes are distributed in a log-normal fashion, then the simple-cubic-law plot of [rn,(total)/ rn,lo(total)]”3 {or (1 -[Z],/[Z],)‘/3} us. t will not be linear but instead deviate in the manner shown in fig. 4,for example by curves (b)and (c). The width of the distribution, y, can be ascertained by plotting the experimental data in the form of [rn,(t~tal)/rn,=,(total)]’~~{or (1 -[Z],/[Z],)’/3) vs. In t, and then matching up the curve obtained with a theoretical plot of B,’l3 us. </p>
      <p>In z, calculated for a particular value of y, such as one of those illustrated in fig. 5. Another, possibly simpler method for finding the value of y for the powder suspension of X is to determine the following ratio = t0.2/tO.8 (18) where to.2 is the time taken for [rn,(t~tal)/rn,=~(total)]”~to go from unity to 0.2 and to.* is the time taken for [rn,(t~tal)/rn,=~(total)]”~to reach 0.8. The quantity r can be determined as a function of y from the theoretical plots of /?,‘I3 us. z and the results are illustrated in fig. 6. Given that the dissolution reaction under study exhibits the same type of deviation from the simple cubic rate law as illustrated in fig. 4, by curve (b)for example, then, it is possible to calculate via eqn (18) a value for r,say r’,which can then be used to read one or two values for y from fig. </p>
      <p>6. In practice, the true value of y is usually the smaller of these two values, since with most dispersions it is unusual to find y &gt; 1.75. Once the value for y has been determined for a powder dispersion it should be possible to match up the experimen- tally determined dissolution curve, plotted in the form of [rn,(t~tal)/rn,=~(total)][or (1 -[Z]J[Z],)’/3] us. In t, and1/3 the theoretical curve, plotted in the form fi,‘l3 us. In z, pre-dicted for that particular value of y, via eqn (12). As indicated in eqn (13), when these two curves are matched up, the differ- ence between the values of In z and In t for any point where “I  -L  0  L  8  X,  In 7  Fig. </p>
      <p>3. Plot of.f(x,z) us. 7 and x‘, where x’ is a measure of rr, calcu-lated using eqn (17), andf(x, z) was calculated using eqn (SH10).  Fig. 5. Plot of and (e)2.  us. In 7 for y values of (a) 0, (b)0.5, (c) 1, (4 1.5    2166 0 i 2 3 4 Y Fig. 6. Plot of r us. y, where r was calculated using eqn (18) with data from theoretical plots of the type illustrated in fig. 4. @,'I3)= [rn,(total)/rn, = o(total)]'I3 {or (1 -[Z]J[Z] m)1/3} will be ln(k/Fop). If the number average radius, Fo , has been deter- mined by an independent particle size analysis technique, such as dynamic light scattering, then the rate constant, k, can be calculated. J. CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1990, VOL. 86 derived relating the relative volume as a function of r/F,,, for any powder for which y is known: 100 exp(3yx)exp( -x2) (19)relative volume (%) = C exp(3yx)exp(-x2) . </p>
      <p>From the results illustrated in fig. 7, y for the nickel ferrite particles appears to be 0.8; thus, using eqn (19), it is possible to generate the plot of % relative volume us. rp0 for the powder, and this is illustrated in fig. 8. Using a sample of nickel ferrite with a particle diameter of 27 pm (obtained by sieving the powder), Sellars and co-workers3,* found that the decay obeys the simple cubic rate law and kobs [=(k/F,p)] is equal to 13.3 x min-l, from In z 2.5 3.5 L.5 5.5 6.5 1-1 0, ia 0.5-0 -2 -1 0 1 2 In t Fig. 7. Plot of the dissolution kinetic data, as reported by Segal and seller^,^ in the form of { = [rn,(t~tal)/rn,,~(total)]"~)us. In t (bottom scale) for a polydispersed suspension of nickel ferrite par- Superimposed onto these points is the model calculated (.).ticles curve of 81/3us. </p>
      <p>In z (top scale) for y = 0.8, which provides a good fit to the data. Testing the Model As noted in the Introduction, Segal and Sellers3 have re- ported that the kinetics of reductive dissolution of nickel ferrite particles by tris(pico1inato) vanadium(I1) deviate from the simple cubic law at high percentage dissolutions, although the simple rate law provides a good general model with which to elucidate the general features of the reaction. The positive deviation noted by Segal and Sellers3 is much as predicted by the cubic rate law/log-normal model, illustrated in fig. </p>
      <p>4 by the curves (bHe). We have plotted their data in the form (1 -[Z]J[Z],)'/3 us. In t, together with a theoreti- cal plot of ln@t/3) us. In z, for y = 0.8 (solid line), for which there is a good match in shape. The difference between In z and In t, is (-1.94 -2.5) = -4.44, thus we estimate that k/Fo p is 0.01 18. From these results, it would appear that the distribution in size of the nickel ferrite particles may obey the log-normal law and that this would explain the observed deviation from the simple cubic rate law noted by Segal and seller^.^ It is appropriate to note at this point that Segal and Sellers3 were able to show that the deviation from the simple cubic rate law exhibited by their nickel ferrite particles was most likely due to a distribution in particle size. </p>
      <p>This they achieved by sieving the powder, thereby obtaining a narrow distribution, and examining by tris(pico1inato) vanadium(r1) the kinetics of its dissolution, which were found to obey the simple cubic rate law very well. Sellers and co-workers have reported in a separate article' the observed variation of relative volume us. particle diameter for the nickel ferrite powder; that these data are for the same sample of nickel ferrite has been confirmed el~ewhere.~ From the log-normal distribution law the following equation can be 5 10 1'5 r/P Fig. 8. Plot of relative volume us. r/F0 for y = 0.8, calculated using eqn (19).   J. </p>
      <p>CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1990, VOL. 86 particle diameter/pm Fig. 9. Plot of (a)relative volume us. particle diameter for the nickel ferrite powder used by Sellers and co-workers* to obtain the non- simple cubic plot dissolution decay data illustrated in fig. 7 (solid line) and (b) % relative volume us. particle diameter, calculated using the curve in fig. 8 and a value of Yo = 6 pm (broken line). The first plot is copyright 01983 Electric Power Research Institute. EPRI NP-3 177 Development of LOMZ Chemical Decontamination Tech-nology. Reprinted with permission. which it can be calculated that k/p = 7.18 x m min-'. However, using the results of Segal and Sellers3 for the unsieved nickel ferrite powder and the theoretical model, we have already estimated that k/Y, p is 0.01 18. </p>
      <p>Thus, combining these two pieces of information it is possible to estimate that the number-average particle size for the unsieved nickel ferrite powder, i.e. Yo, is =7.18 x 10-8/0.0118 = 6.08 x m. In fig. 9 we have plotted the % relative volume us. particle diameter reported by Sellers and co-workers.8 On the same figure we have plotted relative volume vs. particle diameter, determined by cutting and weighing appropriate sections of the curve in fig. 8 given Yo = 6 pm. The reasonable match between the experimentally and theoretically determined plots provides support for the cubic rate lawflog-normal model. Conclusion The cubic rate lawflog-normal model for the dissolution of a polydispersion can be used to extract from the observed simple cubic rate law plot of the decay data the width of the distribution in powder particle size and the parameter k/l;,p. </p>
      <p>If the number-average initial particle size is known, then k can be calculated. The model allows the kinetics of disso- lution of a polydispersed powder suspension to be simulated for a wide range of conditions. This approach to particle dis- solution kinetics may be extended by considering size dis- tribution functions other than the log-normal function, e.g. the normal distribution function. It is worth noting that although deviations from the cubic rate law can be caused by a distribution of the sizes of the powder particle, other factors which can change as dissolution proceeds include : surface roughness, particle shape, exposure of crystallographic planes that are more (or less) reactive" and the accumulation of difficult to dissolve components or impurities on the surface. </p>
      <p>All these factors could also cause the kinetics to deviate from the simple cubic rate law as the reaction proceeds. We thank the S.E.R.C. for supporting this work. References M. G. Segal and R. M. Sellers, Adv. Inorg. Bioinorg. Mechn., 1984,3, 97. M. G. Segal and R. M. Sellers, J. Chem. SOC., Chem. Commun., 1980,991. M. G. Segal and R. M. Sellers, J. Chem. SOC., Faraday Trans. I, 1982,78,1149. R. M. Sellers and W. J. Williams, Faraday Discuss. Chem. SOC., 1984, 77, 265. M. G. Segal and W. J. Williams, J. Chem. SOC.,Faraday Trans. 1, 1986, 82, 3245. A. B. O'Brien, M. G. Segal and W. J. Williams, J. Chem. SOC., Faraday Trans. I, 1987,83, 371. R. R. Irani and C. F. Callis, Particle Size: Measurement, Znter- pretation and Application (Wiley, New York, 1963), chap. 4. D. Bradbury, M. G. Segal, R. M. Sellers, T. Swan and C. J. Wood, Development of LOMZ Chemical Decontamination Tech- nology, EPRI NP-3 177, Electric Power Research Institute, Palo Alto, California, 1983. 9 R. M. Sellers, private communication, 1990. 10 G. C. Allen, C. Kirby and R. M. Sellers, J. Chem. SOC., Faraday Trans. 1,1988,84,355. Paper 9/04884G; Received 15th November, 1989  </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. G.</fname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. M.</fname>
            <surname>Sellers</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Adv. Inorg. Bioinorg. Mechn.</title>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volumeno>3</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>97</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. G.</fname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. M.</fname>
            <surname>Sellers</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Chem. Commun.</title>
          <year>1980</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>991</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. G.</fname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. M.</fname>
            <surname>Sellers</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Faraday Trans. 1</title>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volumeno>78</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1149</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. M.</fname>
            <surname>Sellers</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Faraday Discuss. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volumeno>77</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>265</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. G.</fname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Faraday Trans. 1</title>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volumeno>82</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3245</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. B.</fname>
            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. G.</fname>
            <surname>Segal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Faraday Trans. 1</title>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volumeno>83</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>371</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>R. R.</fname><surname>Irani</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>C. F.</fname><surname>Callis</surname></citauth>, <title>Particle Size: Measurement, Interpretation and Application</title>(<citpub>Wiley</citpub>, <pubplace>New York</pubplace>, <year>1963</year>), <biblscope>chap. 4</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>D.</fname><surname>Bradbury</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>M. G.</fname><surname>Segal</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>R. M.</fname><surname>Sellers</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Swan</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>C. J.</fname><surname>Wood</surname></citauth>, <title>Development of LOMI Chemical Decontamination Technology, EPRI NP-3177, Electric Power Research Institute</title>, <citpub>Palo Alto</citpub>, <pubplace>California</pubplace>, <year>1983</year>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <citation type="other"><citauth><fname>R. M.</fname><surname>Sellers</surname></citauth>, private communication, <year>1990</year>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. C.</fname>
            <surname>Allen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Kirby</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. M.</fname>
            <surname>Sellers</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Chem. Soc., Faraday Trans. 1</title>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volumeno>84</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>355</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
