<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "http://www.rsc.org/dtds/rscart36.dtd">
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>FT9938900095</ms-id>
    <doi>10.1039/FT9938900095</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>FT</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>89</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>1</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>95</fpage>
      <lpage>97</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>3</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1993</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>FT</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>1993</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Radiation stability of fullerenes: pulse radiolysis of C<inf>60</inf> and C<inf>70</inf> in hydrocarbon solvents</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Dilip K.</fname>
            <surname>Maity</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Dipak K.</fname>
            <surname>Palit</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Hari</fname>
            <surname>Mohan</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Jai P.</fname>
            <surname>Mittal</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>The transient optical absorption spectra obtained on electron pulse radiolysis of de-aerated solutions of C<inf>60</inf> and C<inf>70</inf> in benzene have been assigned to the triplet states with <it>G</it>(<sup>T</sup>C<inf>60</inf>)= 0.52 and <it>G</it>(<sup>T</sup>C<inf>70</inf>)= 0.48. Low <it>G</it>(–C<inf>60</inf>) and <it>G</it>(–C<inf>70</inf>) in the steady-state <it>γ</it>-radiolysis in benzene and hexane suggest their stability towards <it>γ</it>-radiation.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p> J. CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1993, 89(1), 95-97 Radiation Stability of Fullerenes: Pulse Radiolysis of C,, and C,, in Hydrocarbon Solvents Dilip K. Maity, Dipak K. Palit, Hari Mohan and Jai P. Mittal" Chemistry Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Trombay, Bombay 400 085,India The transient optical absorption spectra obtained on electron pulse radiolysis of de-aerated solutions of C,, and C70 in benzene have been assigned to the triplet states with G(TC60) = 0.52 and G(TC,,) = 0.48. Low G(-C60) and G(-C70) in the steady-state y-radiolysis in benzene and hexane suggest their stability towards y-radiation. The recent discovery of carbon clusters, members of the ful- lerene family, has evoked tremendous interest in their prep- aration, purification, and in evaluating their structures and proper tie^.'-^ The presence of c60 in interstellar dust has also often been post~lated.~ Several studies have recently been carried out to evaluate their photophysical proper-A few mass spectrometric and infrared studies have indicated that c60 breaks down substantially or completely on exposure to light to form compounds having C-H, CEO, C-C bonds." On the other hand, it has also been reported by other workers to be quite stable without observ- able degradation. </p>
      <p>16,' Considering these conflicting reports and the absence of any information about fullerene stability towards high-energy radiations, we have carried out pulse and steady-state radiolysis of c60 and C,, in benzene and hexane solutions and the results are reported in the present communication. </p>
      <p>During the course of the publication of the present paper, Dimitrijevic and Kamat (D-K) published their results of a pulse radiolysis study of fullerenes." On the whole many of our spectroscopic and kinetic findings agree reasonably well with those of D-K. There are some disagree- ments and improvements on the results that are discussed in detail in the present paper with a special emphasis on the stability towards high-energy electron pulses as well as y-radiation. Experimental Pure samples of c60 and C70 were obtained from Prof. C. N. R. Rao of the Indian Institute of Science, Bangal~re.~ All the solvents were of spectroscopic purity and used without further purification. Pulse radiolysis studies of c60 and C70 were carried out with high-energy electron pulses (7 MeV,? 50 ns or 2 ps) obtained from a linear accelerator and the details of the experimental arrangement for transient optical absorption measurements have been discussed else- where." The dose per pulse (2.0 x 10l7 eV cm-3) was mea- sured by thiocyanate dosimetry2' (lo-, mol dm-3 KSCN, air saturated) using E:&amp;!!;$-= 7100 dm3 mol-' cm-' and G, defined as the number of molecules formed per 100 eV of energy absorbed, =2.9. </p>
      <p>Steady-state y-irradiations were carried out with a 6oCo y-source with a dose rate of 0.94 x 1017 eV cmP3 min-'. The actual dose absorbed in benzene and hexane was corrected for electron density varia- tion with respect to water. </p>
      <p>A Shimadzu model UV-160A spectrophotometer was used for ground-state absorption measurements. De-aeration of samples was carried out by purging the solutions with high-purity N, . 1 eV z 1.602 18 x J. Results and Discussion Electron Pulse Radiolysis Fig. l(a) and 2(a) present the optical absorption spectra, obtained immediately after the electron pulse of the transients produced by pulse radiolysis of the de-aerated solutions of c60 and C70 (5 x mol dm-3) in benzene. The transient absorption for both the fullerenes was observed to decay by first-order kinetics (k, = 4.1 x lo4 s-l and 1.5 x lo5 s-' for c60 and C70, respectively) and was seen to be strongly quenched by oxygen. Also their spectral features, being iden- tical with the recently reported triplet-triplet differential absorption spectra in benzene, obtained by laser flash pho- t~lysis,~*'~,'~were assigned to be the triplet states of the ful- lerenes produced by energy transfer from the initially produced benzene triplets (E, = 82 kcal mol-')*' to those of the fullerenes [ET= 37.5 &amp; 4.0 kcal mol-'].'0,14,'6 The very recent report by D-K18 also confirms this assignment for the transient species generated by pulse radiolysis in benzene. </p>
      <p>C6H6 ---C,H,(Sl), C6H; 9 H', C6H6+,e,, (1) Fig. l(b) shows the transient absorption spectrum obtained on pulse radiolysis of a de-aerated solution of c60 (9.0 x mol dm-3) in benzene containing 1 x loP3mol dm-3 biphenyl and is similar to that obtained for c60 in pure benzene solution in the wavelength region 600-800 nm [Fig. </p>
      <p>l(a)]. The pulse radiolysis generated excited triplet state of benzene [eqn. (1) and (2)] transfers its energy to the biphenyl triplet (ET= 64.8 kcal mol-') [eqn. (4)] which is long lived and in turn transfers its excitation energy to the lower lying triplet of c60 [eqn. (5)]. C6H6(T1) + BP(SO) -b BP(Tl) + C6H6(S0) (4) BP(Tl) + c60(s0) -b BP(SO) + C60(T1) (5) The growth of the 745 nm band follows pseudo-first-order kinetics with a bimolecular rate constant of 2.9 x 10'' dm3 mol-' s-', which is diffusion controlled and in quite good agreement with that of D-K.18 Note, however, that the rela- tive peak height of the differential absorption of the transient at 360 nm compared to that at 745 nm for c60 in benzene is higher in the pulse radiolysis experiment than in the flash photolysis experiments (peak ratio 0.75 cf: ca. </p>
      <p>0.6),' 771 *v2, which may be due to some other transients produced under the present conditions. However, D-K (the only pulse radiolysis study of fullerenes available in the literature) have not reported the transient absorption spectra of the pulse   400 600 800 waveleng t h/n m Fig. 1 (a), Absorption spectrum of the transient produced by pulse radiolysis of C,, in benzene. 0(b), Transient produced by biphenyl triplet sensitization in pulse radiolysis. A (c), Corrected spectrum of triplet absorption of C,, in benzene. Inset: Decay of the transient formed at 745 nm radiolytically generated triplet state for both C,, and C70 below 420 nm and so no comparison with the present results was possible. </p>
      <p>The decay of the fullerene triplets produced by pulse radiolysis in benzene was seen to follow pseudo-first-order kinetics (insets of Fig. 1 and 2). The lifetimes of the triplets were determined to be 24.4 and 6.7 p for c60 and C70, respectively, which are lower than the corresponding values (48 and 93 p)obtained by laser flash photolysis.'7 In addi- tion to the normal first-order decay of the triplet to the ground state [eqn. (6)], other possible processes contributing to its decay are a T-T annihilation reaction [eqn. (7)] and reaction of the triplet with the ground state [eqn. (8)l. kr C60/70(T 1) -c60/70(s0) (6) kTT 2c60/7O(T 1) -2c60/70(s0) (7) kTs C60/70(T1) -k c60/70(s0) 2c60/70(s0) (8) The T-T annihilation reaction (kTT = 2 x lo9 dmw3 mol-' s-11,10,14,17,18 is expected to compete with first-order decay at high concentration (&gt;lo-' mol dmP3) of the triplet. </p>
      <p>However, in the present experimental conditions the concen- 10 h v)c.-55 9) cm 5 02 0 -3 'I V I I I 1I340 400 500 600 660 wavelength/nrn Fig. 2 (a), Absorption spectrum of the transient produced by pulse radiolysis of C,, in benzene. 0(b), Corrected spectrum of triplet absorption of C,, in benzene. Inset: Decay of the transient formed at 410 nm J. CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1993, VOL. 89 tration of the triplet produced was determined to be mol dmP3 and hence the contribution of the T-T annihi-lation reaction to the triplet decay should be negligible. </p>
      <p>However, it was likely that reaction (8) could contribute sig- nificantly as the concentration of the fullerenes used was fairly high (5 x lo-' mol dm-3). The quenching rate con- stants (kTs) of the fullerene triplets by ground states were determined to be 2.0 x lo8 and 2.3 x lo9 dm3 mol-' s-l for C,, and C70, respectively. Although the kTs value for C60 is in excellent agreement with that reported by D-K, the same value for C70 is higher than they reported. Another factor contributing to the faster decay of the triplet may be the reac- tion of the triplet species with the other transients produced by pulse radiolysis of benzene [eqn. </p>
      <p>(l)] which are not expected to be produced in laser flash photolysis experiments. Corrected T-T absorption spectra (E, us. i)for both c60 and C70 in benzene were determined [Fig. l(c) and 2(b)] using molar absorption coefficient (E~)values of 1.2 x lo4 dm3 mol-' cm-' at 740 nrn17918 and 2.0 x lo4 dm3 mol-' cm-' at 400 nm,' respectively. Molar absorption coefficient values for C6,(T,) at 745 nm reported by Kajii et (6 x lo3dm3 mol-' cm-' in benzene) and Arbogast and Foote16 (3 x lo3 dm3 mol-' cm-' in benzonitrile) are very low and in dis- agreement with others and were hence not used by us. Ebbesen et a1.' also reported the molar absorption coefficient value for C60(T1) at 747 nm to be 1.5 x lo4 dm3 mol-' cm- ', in good agreement with our accepted value. </p>
      <p>The molar absorption coefficient value for C7o(T1) at 400 nm in ref. 17 is in quite good agreement with that reported by Arbogast and Foote16 (1.5 x lo4 dm3 mol-' cm-'), within experimental error. Assuming these molar absorption coefficient values G(TC60) and G(=C70) (number of fullerene triplet molecules produced per 100 eV) were calculated to be 0.52 and 0.48, respectively. Steady-state y-Radiolysis To study the decomposition of c60 and C70 by steady-state y-radiolysis, the ground-state absorbance was monitored as a function of y-dose at 328 and 472 nm band, respectively, in de-aerated benzene and hexane solutions. From the linear dependence of the decrease in absorbance of the 328 and 472 nm bands with y-dose G(-C,,) and G(-C7,) were deter- mined (see Table 1) at the concentration where the G values were seen to be independent of concentration. </p>
      <p>The aerated and de-aerated solutions showed similar results in both sol-vents. From the results cited in Table 1 one can safely con- clude that fullerenes are more stable in benzene than in hexane and C70 is more stable than C,, towards high-energy radiation. The c60 solution turns yellow after a 1.04 x lo'* eV cm-j dose of radiation but the C70 solution did not show any visible change in colour even after a 1.6 x 10l8eV cm-3 dose. Although the mechanism of decomposition of c60 and C70 in hydrocarbon solution is not very clear the closeness in the values of the ratio of G(H) values in benzene and hexane Table 1 Radiation-induced decomposition of C,, and C,, in differ- ent hydrocarbon solvents C60  '70  max. </p>
      <p>dose  max. dose  solvent  G(H)  /lo" eV  G(-C,,)  /lo" eV  G(-C,,)  benzene  0.70"  1.04  0.023  1.60  0.001  hexane  4.2Sb  0.47  0.120  0.52  0.006'  Ref. 23. Ref. 24, 25. 'Owing to the low solubility of C7,in hexane, the concentration limit where G( -C,o) is independent of concentration could not be reached.   J. CHEM. SOC. FARADAY TRANS., 1993, VOL. 89  97  to that of G( -c60)and G( -C70) in benzene and hexane sug- gests a possible mechanism of decomposition by H atom reaction. In support of this mechanism an attempt was made to estimate G(decomposition) values in different solvents in the presence of a H atom scavenger (e.g. cyclohexene). </p>
      <p>The absorbance was found to increase in the wavelength region of  6 7 8  H. Ajie, M. M. Alvarez, S. J. Anz, R. D. Beck, F. Diederich, K. Fostiropoulos, D. R. Huffman, W. Kratschmer, Y. Rubin, K. E. Schriver, D. Sensharma and R. L. Whetten, J. Phys. Chem., 1990, 94, 8630. T. Pradeep, F. DSouza, G. N. Subbanna, V. Krishnan and C. N. R. Rao, Proc. Zndian Acad. Sci. (Chem. Sci.), 1991, 103, 685. D. K. Palit, A. V. Sapre and J. P. Mittal, Indian J. Chem., 1992,  300-500 nm which might be due to absorption of the pro- ducts formed by the reaction of cyclohexenyl radicals with fullerenes. On exposure to ca. 50 pulses (2 ps) of 7 MeV elec- trons no observable change could be observed in the ground- state spectra of the fullerenes in benzene. Low values of G( -c60)and G( -C70) suggest the stability of fullerenes in  9 10 11  31, F46. </p>
      <p>T. W. Ebbeson, K. Tanigaki and S. Kuroshima, Chem. Phys. Lett., 1991, 181, 501. J. W. Arbogast, A. P. Darmanyan, C. S. Foote, Y. Rubin, F. N. Diederich, M. M. Alvarez, S. J. Anz and R. L. Whetten, J. Phys. Chem., 1991,95, 11. Z. Gasyna, P. N. Schatz, J. P. Hare, T. J. Dennis, H. W. Kroto,  hydrocarbons in general and confirm aromaticity in their structure.  12  R. Taylor and D. R. M. Walton, Chem. Phys. Lett., 1991, 183, 283. D. M. Cox, S. Behal, M. Disko, S. M. Gorun, M. Greaney, C. S.  Hsu, E. B. Kollia, J. Millar, J. Robbins, W. Robbins, R. D. Sher-  wood and P. Tindall, J. Am. Chem. SOC., 1991,113,2940.  Conclusion Electron pulse radiolysis of the fullerenes in benzene pro-  13 14  T. </p>
      <p>Kato, T. Kodama, M. Oyama, S. Okazaki, T. Shida, T. Naka- gawa, Chem. Phys. Lett., 1991, 186, 35. M. R. Wasielewski, M. P. O’Neil, K. R. Lykke, M. J. Pellin and  duces triplet states with a G value of 0.5 as the only transient species whose spectroscopic and kinetic features have been established to be in good agreement with those generated by laser flash photolysis. Both the fullerenes have been shown to have high stability towards high-energy electron pulses and  15 16  D. M. Gruen, J. Am. Chem. SOC.,1991,113,2774. R. Taylor, J. P. Parsons, A. G. Avent, S. P. Rannard, T. J. Dennis, J. P. Hare, H. W. Kroto and D. R. M. Walton, Nature (London),1991,351,277. J. W. Arbogast and C. S. Foote, J. Am. Chem. SOC., 1991, 113, 8886.  y-radiation, in addition to their stability towards laser radi-  17  D. </p>
      <p>K. Palit, A. V. Sapre, J. P. Mittal and C. N. R. Rao, Chem.  ation reported earlier. However, the stability of the fullerenes towards high-energy radiation has been shown to be solvent dependent and C70 is more stable than c60.  18 19  Phys. Lett., 1992, 195, 1. N. M. Dimitrijevic and P. V. Kamat, J. Phys. Chem., 1992, 96, 4811. (a)S. N. Guha, P. N. Moorthy, K. Kishore and K. N. Rao, Proc.  Sincere thanks are due to Prof. C. N. R. Rao for providing  Zndian Acad. Sci. (Chem. Sci.), 1987, 99, 261: (b) K. I. Priyadar-sini, D. B. Naik, P. N. Moorthy and J. P. Mittal, Proc. 7th  pure samples of c60 and C70 and for many helpful dis- cussions. Thanks are also due to Dr. S. K. Kulshrlshtha, BARC, for providing some samples of fullerene. </p>
      <p> 20  Tihany Symp. on Rad. Chem., Hungarian Chemical Society, Budapest, 1991, p. 105. G. E. Adams, J. W. Boag, J. Currant and B. D. Michael, in Pulse Radiolysis, ed. M. Ebert, J. P. Keene, A. J. Swallow and J. H.  Baxendale, Academic Press, London, 1965, p. 117.  21  R. Bensasson and E. J. Land, Photochemical and Photobiological  References  22  Rev., ed. K. C. Smith, Plenum, New York, 1978, p. 163. Y. Kajii, T. Nakagawa, S. Suzuki, Y. Achiba, K. Obi and K.  H. W. Kroto, J. R. Heath, S. C. O’Brien, R. F. Curl and R. E.  Shibuya, Chem. Phys. Lett., 1991, 181, 100.  Smalley, Nature (London), 1985,318, 162.  23  R. A. Holroyd, Fundamental Processes in Radiation Chemistry,  H. W. Kroto, A. W. Allaf and S. P. Balm, Chem. Rev., 1991, 91,  ed. P. Ausloos, Wiley-Interscience, New York, 1968, p. 413.  1213.  24  J. W. T. Spinks and R. J. Wood, An Introduction to Radiation  W. Kratschmer, L. D. Lamb, D. R. Huffman and K. Fostiro-  Chemistry, Wiley, New York, 1964, p. 309.  poulos, Nature (London), 1990,347,354.  25  T. J. Hardwick, J. Phys. Chem., 1962,66, 1611.  M A. Greaney and S. M. Gorun, J. Phys. Chem., 1991,95,7142. R. F. Curl and R. E. Smalley, Science, 1988, 242, 1017.  Paper 2/04105G; Received 30th July, 1992   </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H. W.</fname>
            <surname>Kroto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. R.</fname>
            <surname>Heath</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. C.</fname>
            <surname>O'Brien</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. F.</fname>
            <surname>Curl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. E.</fname>
            <surname>Smalley</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Nature (London)</title>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volumeno>318</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>162</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H. W.</fname>
            <surname>Kroto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. W.</fname>
            <surname>Allaf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. P.</fname>
            <surname>Balm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Rev.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>91</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1213</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Kratschmer</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L. D.</fname>
            <surname>Lamb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. R.</fname>
            <surname>Huffman</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Fostiropoulos</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Nature (London)</title>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volumeno>347</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>354</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. A.</fname>
            <surname>Greaney</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. M.</fname>
            <surname>Gorun</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Phys. Chem.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>95</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>7142</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. F.</fname>
            <surname>Curl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. E.</fname>
            <surname>Smalley</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Science</title>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volumeno>242</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1017</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Ajie</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. M.</fname>
            <surname>Alvarez</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. J.</fname>
            <surname>Anz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Beck</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Diederich</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Fostiropoulos</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. R.</fname>
            <surname>Huffman</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Kratschmer</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Rubin</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K. E.</fname>
            <surname>Schriver</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D.</fname>
            <surname>Sensharma</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. L.</fname>
            <surname>Whetten</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Phys. Chem.</title>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volumeno>94</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8630</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Pradeep</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>D'Souza</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. N.</fname>
            <surname>Subbanna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V.</fname>
            <surname>Krishnan</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. N. R.</fname>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Proc. Indian Acad. Sci. (Chem. Sci.)</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>103</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>685</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. K.</fname>
            <surname>Palit</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. V.</fname>
            <surname>Sapre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. P.</fname>
            <surname>Mittal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Indian J. Chem.</title>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volumeno>31</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>F46</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. W.</fname>
            <surname>Ebbeson</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Tanigaki</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Kuroshima</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Phys. Lett.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>181</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>501</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. W.</fname>
            <surname>Arbogast</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. P.</fname>
            <surname>Darmanyan</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. S.</fname>
            <surname>Foote</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Rubin</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. N.</fname>
            <surname>Diederich</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. M.</fname>
            <surname>Alvarez</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. J.</fname>
            <surname>Anz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. L.</fname>
            <surname>Whetten</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Phys. Chem.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>95</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>11</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit11">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Gasyna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. N.</fname>
            <surname>Schatz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. P.</fname>
            <surname>Hare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. J.</fname>
            <surname>Dennis</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H. W.</fname>
            <surname>Kroto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R.</fname>
            <surname>Taylor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. R. M.</fname>
            <surname>Walton</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Phys. Lett.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>183</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>283</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit12">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. M.</fname>
            <surname>Cox</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Behal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Disko</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. M.</fname>
            <surname>Gorun</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Greaney</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. S.</fname>
            <surname>Hsu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. B.</fname>
            <surname>Kollia</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Millar</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Robbins</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Robbins</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. D.</fname>
            <surname>Sherwood</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Tindall</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>113</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>2940</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit13">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Kato</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Kodama</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Oyama</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Okazaki</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Shida</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Nakagawa</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Phys. Lett.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>186</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>35</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit14">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. R.</fname>
            <surname>Wasielewski</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. P.</fname>
            <surname>O'Neil</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K. R.</fname>
            <surname>Lykke</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M. J.</fname>
            <surname>Pellin</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. M.</fname>
            <surname>Gruen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>113</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>2774</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit15">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R.</fname>
            <surname>Taylor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. P.</fname>
            <surname>Parsons</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. G.</fname>
            <surname>Avent</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. P.</fname>
            <surname>Rannard</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. J.</fname>
            <surname>Dennis</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. P.</fname>
            <surname>Hare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H. W.</fname>
            <surname>Kroto</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. R. M.</fname>
            <surname>Walton</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Nature (London)</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>351</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>277</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit16">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. W.</fname>
            <surname>Arbogast</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. S.</fname>
            <surname>Foote</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>113</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8886</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit17">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>D. K.</fname>
            <surname>Palit</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. V.</fname>
            <surname>Sapre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. P.</fname>
            <surname>Mittal</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. N. R.</fname>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Phys. Lett.</title>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volumeno>195</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit18">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. M.</fname>
            <surname>Dimitrijevic</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. V.</fname>
            <surname>Kamat</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Phys. Chem.</title>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volumeno>96</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>4811</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit19">
        <citgroup id="cit19a">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>S. N.</fname>
              <surname>Guha</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>P. N.</fname>
              <surname>Moorthy</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>K.</fname>
              <surname>Kishore</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>K. N.</fname>
              <surname>Rao</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Proc. Indian Acad. Sci. (Chem. Sci.)</title>
            <year>1987</year>
            <volumeno>99</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>261</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit19b">
          <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>K. I.</fname><surname>Priyadarsini</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>D. B.</fname><surname>Naik</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>P. N.</fname><surname>Moorthy</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>J. P.</fname><surname>Mittal</surname></citauth>, <title>Proc. 7th Tihany Symp. on Rad. Chem.</title>, <citpub>Hungarian Chemical Society</citpub>, <pubplace>Budapest</pubplace>, <year>1991</year>, <biblscope>p. 105</biblscope>.</citation>
        </citgroup>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit20">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>G. E.</fname><surname>Adams</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>J. W.</fname><surname>Boag</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>J.</fname><surname>Currant</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>B. D.</fname><surname>Michael</surname></citauth>, in <title>Pulse Radiolysis</title>, ed. <editor>M. Ebert</editor>, <editor>J. P. Keene</editor>, <editor>A. J. Swallow</editor> and <editor>J. H. Baxendale</editor>, <citpub>Academic Press</citpub>, <pubplace>London</pubplace>, <year>1965</year>, <biblscope>p. 117</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit21">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>R.</fname><surname>Bensasson</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>E. J.</fname><surname>Land</surname></citauth>, <title>Photochemical and Photobiological Rev.</title>, ed. <editor>K. C. Smith</editor>, <citpub>Plenum</citpub>, <pubplace>New York</pubplace>, <year>1978</year>, <biblscope>p. 163</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit22">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Kajii</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Nakagawa</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Suzuki</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Achiba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Obi</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>K.</fname>
            <surname>Shibuya</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Chem. Phys. Lett.</title>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volumeno>181</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>100</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit23">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>R. A.</fname><surname>Holroyd</surname></citauth>, <title>Fundamental Processes in Radiation Chemistry</title>, ed. <editor>P. Ausloos</editor>, <citpub>Wiley-Interscience</citpub>, <pubplace>New York</pubplace>, <year>1968</year>, <biblscope>p. 413</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit24">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>J. W. T.</fname><surname>Spinks</surname></citauth> and <citauth><fname>R. J.</fname><surname>Wood</surname></citauth>, <title>An Introduction to Radiation Chemistry</title>, <citpub>Wiley</citpub>, <pubplace>New York</pubplace>, <year>1964</year>, <biblscope>p. 309</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit25">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. J.</fname>
            <surname>Hardwick</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>J. Phys. Chem.</title>
          <year>1962</year>
          <volumeno>66</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1611</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
