<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>SG4493197816</ms-id>
    <doi>89.8964/SG4493197816</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>SG</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>31</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>87</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>7816</fpage>
      <lpage>7812</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>0</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8449</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>SG</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8449</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Xvargvpf sbe gur fhesnpr-pbagebyyrq qvffbyhgvba bs n cbjqre qvfcrefvba jvgu n ybt-abezny qvfgevohgvba va cnegvpyr fvmr</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Naqerj</fname>
            <surname>Zvyyf</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Ursva Y.</fname>
            <surname>Qnivrf</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Zvpunry F.</fname>
            <surname>Tneyrl</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>N zbqry unf orra qrirybcrq qrfpevovat gur xvargvpf bs n fvzcyr fhesnpr-pbagebyyrq qvffbyhgvba ernpgvba vaibyivat n cbjqre qvfcrefvba jvgu n ybt-abezny (ybt-Tnhffvna) qvfgevohgvba va cnegvpyr fvmr. Gur zbqry jnf gura hfrq gb nanylfr cerivbhfyl choyvfurq xvargvp qngn ba gur qvffbyhgvba bs n cbylqvfcrefrq cbjqre fhfcrafvba. Gur erfhygf bs guvf nanylfvf nyybjrq gur pnyphyngvba bs gur eryngvir ibyhzr (%)<it>if.</it> cnegvpyr qvnzrgre sbe gur cbjqre naq guvf pbzcnerq snibhenoyl jvgu gur cybg bs gur rkcrevzragnyyl qrgrezvarq erfhygf.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p> W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, 31(87), 7816-7812 Xvargvpf sbe gur Fhesnpr-pbagebyyrq Qvffbyhgvba bs n Cbjqre Qvfcrefvba jvgu n ybt-Abezny Qvfgevohgvba va Cnegvpyr Fvmr Naqerj Zvyyf,” Ursva Y. Qnivrf naq Zvpunry F. Tneyrl Qrcnegzrag bs Purzvfgel, Havirefvgl Pbyyrtr bs Fjnafrn, Fvatyrgba Cnex, Fjnafrn FN7 3CC N zbqry unf orra qrirybcrq qrfpevovat gur xvargvpf bs n fvzcyr fhesnpr-pbagebyyrq qvffbyhgvba ernpgvba vaibyi- vat n cbjqre qvfcrefvba jvgu n ybt-abezny (ybt-Tnhffvna) qvfgevohgvba va cnegvpyr fvmr. Gur zbqry jnf gura hfrq gb nanylfr cerivbhfyl choyvfurq xvargvp qngn ba gur qvffbyhgvba bs n cbylqvfcrefrq cbjqre fhfcrafvba. Gur erfhygf bs guvf nanylfvf nyybjrq gur pnyphyngvba bs gur eryngvir ibyhzr (%) if. cnegvpyr qvnzrgre sbe gur cbjqre naq guvf pbzcnerq snibhenoyl jvgu gur cybg bs gur rkcrevzragnyyl qrgrezvarq erfhygf. Qvffbyhgvba bs cnegvphyngr znggre vf bs vzcbegnapr gb znal fhowrpgf vapyhqvat : zvarenybtl, ulqebzrgnyyhetl naq ahpyrne cynag qrpbagnzvangvba. </p>
      <p>Tvira gur pyrne, jvqrfcernq eryrinapr bs guvf fhowrpg gb vaqhfgel, vg vf abg fhecevfvat gb abgr gung va gur cnfg zhpu bs gur erfrnepu vagb gur nern unq orra qverpgrq gbjneq vzcebivat gur nffbpvngrq grpuabybtl.’ Va zber erprag lrnef, ubjrire, vagrerfg va zber shaqnzragny fghqvrf unf tebja. Sbe rknzcyr, gur xvargvpf bs zrgny bkvqr qvffbyhgvba, ivn rvgure n erqhpgvir be na bkvqngvir zrpunavfz, unir nggenpgrq pbafvqrenoyr nggragvba erpragyl naq n fvtavsvpnag nggrzcg unf orra znqr gb eryngr gur xvargvpf bs qvffbyhgvba gb gur fgehpgher, pbzcbfvgvba naq zbecubybtl bs gur bkvqr naq gur angher bs gur ernpgnag.7-1 Va n erprag cncre ol Frtny naq Fryyref6 ba gur xvargvpf bs erqhpgvir qvffbyhgvba bs n qvfcrefvba bs avpxry sreevgr cbjqre ol gevf(cvpb8vangb) inanqvhz(V8) vg jnf abgrq gung vs gur bkvqr cnegvpyrf jrer abg bs gur fnzr fvmr (Yr. abg zbabqvfcrefrq) ohg engure pbzcevfrq znal qvssrerag fvmrf (v.r.cbylqvfcrefrq) gura gur bofreirq xvargvpf bs qvffbyhgvba jbhyq fubj n fvt- avsvpnag qrivngvba sebz gur bsgra hfrq fvzcyr phovp engr ynj jura gur qrterr bs qvffbyhgvba jnf ynetr, v.r. </p>
      <p>glcvpnyyl &gt;20% ; guvf qrivngvba jbhyq vapernfr jvgu vapernfvat qvffbyhgvba, nygubhtu, va cenpgvpr, nanylgvpny reebef fgneg gb orpbzr vzcbe- gnag ng &gt;49% qvffbyhgvba. Gb vyyhfgengr guvf cbvag gurfr jbexref gbbx nf n pehqr rknzcyr n qvfgevohgvba bs rdhny znffrf bs cnegvpyrf bs fvmr V, 7e, 6e, 5e naq 0e naq fubjrq gung gur cerqvpgrq qvffbyhgvba xvargvpf borlrq gur phovp engr ynj sbe n havsbez qvfgevohgvba bs cnegvpyrf bs fvmr 7.0 bire gur svefg 19% bs qvffbyhgvba naq fubjrq na vapernfvatyl cbfvgvir qrivngvba jvgu vapernfvat qvffbyhgvba nobir 19%. </p>
      <p>Vg unf orra sbhaq gung va znal pnfrf gur cnegvpyr fvmr qvf- gevohgvba va n cbjqre fhfcrafvba borlf gur ybt-abezny qvf- gevohgvba ynj2 naq va guvf cncre jr rknzvar jung unccraf gb gur bofreirq xvargvpf bs qvffbyhgvba bs n cbjqre fhfcrafvba jura vg vf cbylqvfcrefrq naq gur qvfcrefvba va cnegvpyr fvmr svgf n ybt-abezny qvfgevohgvba. Gur cerqvpgvbaf nevfvat sebz guvf zbqry ner gura grfgrq hfvat cerivbhfyl choyvfurq’ qrpnl qngn ba gur erqhpgvir qvffbyhgvba bs n cbylqvfcrefrq bkvqr fhfcra- fvba sbe juvpu fbzr cnegvpyr fvmr qvfgevohgvba qngn ner nyfb ninvynoyr.3 Gur Phovp Engr Ynj/ybt-Abezny Zbqry Yrg hf pbafvqre gur trareny qvffbyhgvba ernpgvba nK + oL -,pM + qD (8) jurer K vf n urgrebtrarbhf cbjqre fhfcrafvba juvpu qvf- fbyirf gb sbez M hcba rkcbfher gb L, juvpu va ghea sbezf D nf n erfhyg bs gur ernpgvba. </p>
      <p>Gur grezf n, o, p naq q ner gur nccebcevngr ernpgvba fgbvpuvbzrgevrf, L, M naq D ner ubzb- trarbhf fcrpvrf naq vg vf nffhzrq gung gurve erzbiny qbrf abg yvzvg gur engr bs qvffbyhgvba. Vg vf nyfb nffhzrq gung gur engr bs qvffbyhgvba bs cbjqre cnegvpyrf vaibyirf ernpgvba ng gur cne- gvpyr fhesnpr nf gur pbagebyyvat fgrc naq, gurersber, vf ceb- cbegvbany gb gur vafgnagnarbhf fhesnpr nern. </p>
      <p>Va cenpgvpr gur qvffbyhgvba bs n cbjqre fhfcrafvba bsgra nccrnef gb svg guvf fvzcyr Guhf, va ernpgvba (8) sbe n fhfcrafvba bs a cbjqre cnegvpyrf bs pbzcbhaq K bs enqvhf V, gur engr bs qvffb- yhgvba jvyy or tvira ol qeayqg = -axN (7) jurer ea vf gur znff bs haqvffbyirq cnegvpyrf bs K (va t), N vf gur vafgnagnarbhf fhesnpr nern qhr gb n cnegvpyr naq x vf gur engr pbafgnag (va t f-’ z-7). Gur engr pbafgnag jvyy qrcraq hcba gur angher bs K naq gur pbapragengvba bs M. Vs gur cne- gvpyrf ner fcurevpny, gura N = 5q. Fhofgvghgvat sbe N vagb rda (8)naq vagrtengvat tvirf gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj7 8 -{eaWea,)’/6 = xg/(e,c) (6) jurer ea, naq ea, ner gur gbgny znffrf bs haqvffbyirq cnegvpyrf ng g = 9 naq g, erfcrpgviryl. </p>
      <p>(Abgr gung va guvf zbqry g pnaabg rkprrq ebc/x, fvapr nsgre guvf gvzr ab cnegvpyrf ner yrsg.) Gur grez eb ersref gb gur vavgvny fvmr bs gur cnegvpyrf bs K (va z) ng g = 9, naq c vf gur qrafvgl bs K (va t z-6). Va cenpgvpr,’-1 gur qvffbyhgvba bs n cbjqre fhfcrafvba vf serdhragyl zbavgberq vaqverpgyl ivn gur nccrnenapr bs bar bs gur qvffbyhgvba ceb- qhpgf, r.t. M va guvf pnfr. Sebz rda (6) gur sbyybjvat rdhngvba pna or qrevirq: (5) jurer [M], naq [M], ner gur pbapragengvbaf bs M ng g naq g = pb,erfcrpgviryl. Guvf vf nabgure irefvba bs gur ‘fvzcyr’ phovp engr ynj sebz juvpu vg vf rkcrpgrq gung n cybg bs (8 -[M]W[M],)’/6 QF. g fubhyq or n fgenvtug yvar jvgu n tenqvrag rdhny gb x/(ebc). Va cenpgvpr, gur cnenzrgre x/(e,c) vf bsgra gnxra nf xbof naq, va zber qrgnvyrq fghqvrf, unf orra rknz- varq nf n shapgvba bs [KV, [ly naq grzcrengher. </p>
      <p>Gur erfhygf bs guvf jbex pna gura or hfrq gb cerqvpg gur xvargvpf bs qvffb- yhgvba ivn rda (6) be (5) sbe n jvqr enatr bs ernpgvba pbaqv- gvbaf hfvat gur zbqry cerfragrq nobir.’-1 N onfvp nffhzcgvba znqr va gur qrevingvba bs rda (6) naq (5) vf gung gur cbjqre fhfcrafvba vf zbabqvfcrefrq. Va cenp- gvpr, ubjrire, vg znl or cbylqvfcrefrq naq, nf n erfhyg, gur bofreirq xvargvpf sbe vgf qvffbyhgvba jvyy abg borl gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj. Nf abgrq va gur vagebqhpgvba, va znal pnfrf vg unf orra fubja gung gur cnegvpyr fvmr qvfgevohgvba va n cbjqre fhfcrafvba, be pbyybvq, vf orfg qrfpevorq ol gur ybt-abezny   7815 qvfgevohgvba ynj,’ v.r. a = vv rkc(-k7) (0) naq lk = Va(e/S) (1) jurer a vf gur ahzore bs cnegvpyrf bs enqvhf, e, sv vf gur ahzore bs cnegvpyrf jvgu gur ahzore nirentr enqvhf v; naq l vf n zrnfher bs gur jvqgu bs gur qvfgevohgvba. </p>
      <p>Svt. 8 vyyhfgengrf gur rssrpg bs l ba gur cnegvpyr fvmr qvfgevohgvba, nf cerqvpgrq ol rda (0)naq (1). Vs jr nffhzr gung va gur cbjqre fhfcrafvba gur qvfgevoh- gvba va fvmr bs gur cbjqre cnegvpyrf bs K borlf gur ybt-abezny ynj, gura, sebz rda (1) sbe ernpgvba (8) ng g = 9, rnpu vavgvny cnegvpyr enqvhf, e,, jvyy or eryngrq gb gur ahzore nirentr vavgvny enqvhf v;, ol gur rkcerffvba e, = Sb rkc(lk). (2) Va nqqvgvba, sebz rda (0)naq (1) gur znff bs cnegvpyrf bs K bs vavgvny enqvhf eb ng g = 9 jvyy or zk, = ,,jurer zk, = ,= 525 rkc(6lk)vv rkc( -k7)c/6. </p>
      <p>(3) Vg sbyybjf gung ng g = 9 gur gbgny znff qhr gb haqvffbyirq cne- gvpyrf bsK jvyy or tvira ol K=99 z,=,(gbgny) = P zk,g=B. (4) k= -z Sebz rda (6) naq (FU2)ng n gvzr g nsgre gur fgneg bs gur ernpgvba, jurer e,c/x 6 g 6 9, gur znff qhr gb haqvffbyirq cnegvpyrf bs K bs enqvhf eb ,v.r. zk,,jvyy or zk, = 525 rkc(6lk)vv rkc( -k7) k CP 8 -xg rkc(-lk)/(S, CV8 6/6 (89) jvgu gur pbaqvgvba gung jura g &gt; ebl/x, zK,,= 9. Guhf, jvguva gur pbafgenvagf bs guvf pbaqvgvba, ng nal gvzr g qhevat gur pbeebfvba ernpgvba gur gbgny znff qhr gb haqvffbyirq cne- 8 0 9.0 \ \ \ 8 7 6 5 e/s Svt. 8. Cybg bs a/vv hf. e/? sbe l inyhrf bs (n)9, (o)9.0,(p) 8 naq (q)7. Gurfr pheirf jrer pnyphyngrq hfvat rda (0)naq (1). </p>
      <p>W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, IBY. 31 gvpyrf bs K jvyy or k= 99 z,(gbgny) = P zk,,. k= -n&gt; Pbzovavat rda (3)-(88) lvryqf gur sbyybjvat rkcerffvba z,(gbgny)’,= z,=,(gbgny) jurer m = xg/(S,c). (86) Nf abgrq cerivbhfyl, va na rkcrevzragny fghql bs gur qvffb- yhgvba bs n cbjqre fhfcrafvba, rvgure gur engvb z,(gbgny)/z,= ,(gbgny) be, zber hfhnyyl, gur engvb [M],/[M]nv vf qrgrezvarq nf n shapgvba bs gvzr. Gur gjb engvbf ner eryngrq gb rnpu bgure naq gur gurbergvpny dhnagvgl ea,(gbgny)/ea,=,(gbgny) (= sve) ol gur sbyybjvat fvzcyr rkcerffvba ~z,(gbgny)/ea,= ,(gbgny) = z,(g bgny)/z, ,( gbgny) = 8 -PMyWPMW,. (85) Vg vf nccebcevngr ng guvf cbvag gb vagebqhpr n grez juvpu jr funyy ersre gb nfs(k, m) be gur ‘senpgvbany znff’ naq qrsvar vg nf gur engvb bs gur znff bs haqvffbyirq cnegvpyrf ng gvzr m juvpu unq na vavgvny enqvhf e,, gb gur gbgny znff bs haqvffbyirq cne- gvpyrf ng g = 9, v.r.s(k, m) = zk,e/z,=,(gbgny). </p>
      <p>Svt. 7 vyyhfgengrf ubj s(k, m) inevrf jvgu m naq k bire gur enatr eb/Sb = 75.0 (k = 5) gb eb/Sb = 9.958 (k = -5) jura l = 9.3. Gur erfhygf vyyhfgengrq va svt. 7 uvtuyvtug gur trareny bofreingvba gung va gur vavgvny cneg bs gur qvffbyhgvba ernpgvba gur fznyyre cnegvpyrf ner pbafhzrq naq gung, pbafrdhragyl, nf gur ernpgvba ceb- prrqf, gur nirentr cnegvpyr enqvhf vapernfrf sebz vgf vavgvny inyhr bs S, . Shaqnzragny gb gur phovp engr ynj sbe gur qvffbyhgvba bs n zbabqvfcrefr cbjqre fhfcrafvba vf rda (7). Ubjrire, fvapr N = 52pe7, z = 5ae6ac/6 naq qe/qg = (qz/qg)(qe/qea), vg sby-ybjf gung qe/qg = -x/c (8 fw v.r. </p>
      <p>gur engr bs punatr bs gur enqvhf bs gur cbjqre cnegvpyrf vf vaqrcraqrag bs gur enqvhf. Guvf jbhyq nyfb or gehr va gur -.V -5 K Svt. 7. Cybg bss(k, 2) hf. G sbe l = 9.3, pnyphyngrq hfvat rda (FU89).   W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, IBY. 31 phovp engr ynj/ybt-abezny zbqry. Guhf, gur engr bs punatr bs gur enqvhf bs gur irel ynetr cnegvpyrf jbhyq or gur fnzr nf gur engr bs punatr bs gur irel fznyy cnegvpyrf. Guvf jbhyq yrnq gb gur birenyy rssrpg gung nf gur ernpgvba cebprrqf gur xvargvpf jvyy orpbzr vapernfvatyl qbzvangrq ol gur ynetre cnegvpyrf. Vagrerfgvatyl, gur vagrtengrq sbez bs guvf rdhngvba, v.r. V, = S,[rkc(lk) -m] (81) fubjf ubj gur enqvhf bs gur cnegvpyrf inevrf jvgu m. </p>
      <p>Va rda (2) vg vf pyrne gung sbe n tvira qvfgevohgvba, v.r. svkrq inyhr bs l, gur grez k qrsvarf gur vavgvny cnegvpyr enqvhf, eb, va grezf bs gur ahzore nirentr vavgvny cnegvpyr enqvhf, Gb. Guhf, va svt. 7 jr pna frr ubj s(k, m) sbe n ahzore bs cnegvpyrf jvgu qvssrerag inyhrf bs e9, naq gurersber k, inevrf jvgu gvzr. Ubjrire, vg vf vagrerfgvat gb frr ubj abg bayls(k, m) inevrf jvgu m, ohg nyfb ubj gur cnegvpyr fvmr e,, juvpu fgnegf bss ng eb, inevrf jvgu m. Va svt. 6 jr unir nggrzcgrq gb vyyhfgengr guvf rssrpg sbe l = 9.3 ol cybggvats(k, m) nf n shapgvba bs m naq k’, jurer k’ vf tvira ol gur sbyybjvat rkcerffvba k’ = k + ya[y -m rkc(-lk)]/l. (82) Gur grez k’ vf eryngrq gb ee va gur fnzr jnl gung k vf eryngrq gb e9, v.r. </p>
      <p>lk’ = ya(e,/Sb); rda (82) vf qrevirq sebz rda (81) ol ryvzvangvat ee/Sb. Nf lbh zvtug rkcrpg, svt. 6 fubjf gung nf s(k, m) qrpernfrf fb qbrf k’ (naq, gurersber, fb qbrf e,). Va nqqvgvba, svt, 6 fubjf gung ertneqyrff bs gur vavgvny cnegvpyr enqvhf ng n tvira inyhr bs k’, fnl k’ = -8 sbe rknzcyr, gur punatr va m erdhverq orsber gur cnegvpyrf ner irel fznyy, fnl k‘ = -5, vf pbafgnag (va guvf pnfr NG = 9.5937) nf rkcrpgrq tvira rda (8 0). Sbe nal inyhr bs l, gur nern haqre gurs(k, m)hf. k pheir ng nal gvzr m (frr svt. 7) vf rdhny gb ea,(gbgny)/z,,,(gbgny), v.r. = c,. Va n glcvpny phovp ynj cybg [ea,(g~gny)/ea,=~(gbgny)]’~~be svs86 vf cybggrq ntnvafg m nevq svt. 5 vyyhfgengrf ubj Q:’6, pnyph-yngrq hfvat gur ybt-abezny/phovp engr ynj zbqry, inevrf jvgu m sbe n frevrf bs qvssrerag inyhrf bs 8’. </p>
      <p>Vs gur cbjqre fhfcrafvba vf zbabqvfcrefr l = 9, naq gur xvargvpf bs qvffbyhgvba fubhyq borl gur ‘fvzcyr’ phovp engr ynj juvpu cerqvpgf gung n cybg bs [w,‘V6 hf. m, fubhyq or n fgenvtug yvar jvgu n tenqvrag = 8, nf vyyhfgengrq va svt. 5 pheir (n). Ubjrire, vg vf pyrne sebz gur bgure pheirf va svt. 5,gung gur terngre gur qvfgevohgvba jvqgu bs cnegvpyr fvmrf, v.r. gur terngre gur inyhr bs l, gur zber fvt- avsvpnag gur qrivngvba sebz yvarnevgl bofreirq va n glcvpny phovp-ynj cybg bs gur cerqvpgrq qrpnl qngn, rira gubhtu gur vavgvny ahzore nirentr cnegvpyr fvmr sbe nyy gur qvfcrefvbaf vf gur fnzr, v.r. S, . A 9’  0  89  2  Svt. 5. Cybg  bs  { =[ea,(g~gny)/z,=,(gbgny)]’’~= [ea,(gbgny)/  ea,=,(g~gny)W’/~}hf. </p>
      <p>2 sbe l inyhrf bs (n)9, (o)9.0, (p) 8, (5 8.0 naq (r) 7. Gur grez O8V6jnf pnyphyngrq hfvat rda (8 7). Sebz gur nobir qvfphffvba vg sbyybjf gung vs, va gur trareny qvffbyhgvba ernpgvba (y), gur cbjqre fhfcrafvba bs K pbz-cevfrf cnegvpyrf jubfr fvmrf ner qvfgevohgrq va n ybt-abezny snfuvba, gura gur fvzcyr-phovp-ynj cybg bs [ea,(gbgny)/ ea,yb(gbgny)]”6 {be (8 -[M],/[M],)‘/6} hf. g jvyy abg or yvarne ohg vafgrnq qrivngr va gur znaare fubja va svt. 5,sbe rknzcyr ol pheirf (o)naq (p). Gur jvqgu bs gur qvfgevohgvba, l, pna or nfpregnvarq ol cybggvat gur rkcrevzragny qngn va gur sbez bs [ea,(g~gny)/ea,=,(gbgny)]’~~{be (8 -[M],/[M],)’/6) if. Va g, naq gura zngpuvat hc gur pheir bognvarq jvgu n gurbergvpny cybg bs O,’y6 hf. </p>
      <p>Va m, pnyphyngrq sbe n cnegvphyne inyhr bs l, fhpu nf bar bs gubfr vyyhfgengrq va svt. 0. Nabgure, cbffvoyl fvzcyre zrgubq sbe svaqvat gur inyhr bs l sbe gur cbjqre fhfcrafvba bs K vf gb qrgrezvar gur sbyybjvat engvb = g9.7/gB.3 (83) jurer gb.7 vf gur gvzr gnxra sbe [ea,(g~gny)/ea,=~(gbgny)]”~gb tb sebz havgl gb 9.7 naq gb.* vf gur gvzr gnxra sbe [ea,(g~gny)/ea,=~(gbgny)]”~gb ernpu 9.3. Gur dhnagvgl e pna or qrgrezvarq nf n shapgvba bs l sebz gur gurbergvpny cybgf bs /?,‘V6 hf. m naq gur erfhygf ner vyyhfgengrq va svt. 1. Tvira gung gur qvffbyhgvba ernpgvba haqre fghql rkuvovgf gur fnzr glcr bs qrivngvba sebz gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj nf vyyhfgengrq va svt. 5, ol pheir (o)sbe rknzcyr, gura, vg vf cbffvoyr gb pnyphyngr ivn rda (83) n inyhr sbe e,fnl e’,juvpu pna gura or hfrq gb ernq bar be gjb inyhrf sbe l sebz svt. </p>
      <p>1. Va cenpgvpr, gur gehr inyhr bs l vf hfhnyyl gur fznyyre bs gurfr gjb inyhrf, fvapr jvgu zbfg qvfcrefvbaf vg vf hahfhny gb svaq l &gt; 8.20. Bapr gur inyhr sbe l unf orra qrgrezvarq sbe n cbjqre qvfcrefvba vg fubhyq or cbffvoyr gb zngpu hc gur rkcrevzra- gnyyl qrgrezvarq qvffbyhgvba pheir, cybggrq va gur sbez bs [ea,(g~gny)/ea,=~(gbgny)][be (8 -[M]W[M],)’/6] hf. Va g, naq8/6 gur gurbergvpny pheir, cybggrq va gur sbez sv,‘y6 hf. Va m, cer-qvpgrq sbe gung cnegvphyne inyhr bs l, ivn rda (87). Nf vaqvpngrq va rda (86), jura gurfr gjb pheirf ner zngpurq hc, gur qvssre- rapr orgjrra gur inyhrf bs Va m naq Va g sbe nal cbvag jurer “V  -Y  9  Y  3  K,  Va 2  Svt. </p>
      <p>6. Cybg bs.s(k,m) hf. 2 naq k‘, jurer k’ vf n zrnfher bs ee, pnyph-yngrq hfvat rda (82), naqs(k, m) jnf pnyphyngrq hfvat rda (FU89).  Svt. 0. Cybg bs naq (r)7.  hf. Va 2 sbe l inyhrf bs (n) 9, (o)9.0, (p) 8, (5 8.0    7811 9 v 7 6 5 L Svt. 1. Cybg bs e hf. l, jurer e jnf pnyphyngrq hfvat rda (83) jvgu qngn sebz gurbergvpny cybgf bs gur glcr vyyhfgengrq va svt. 5. @,'V6)= [ea,(gbgny)/ea, = b(gbgny)]'V6 {be (8 -[M]W[M] z)8/6} jvyy or ya(x/Sbc). Vs gur ahzore nirentr enqvhf, Sb , unf orra qrgre- zvarq ol na vaqrcraqrag cnegvpyr fvmr nanylfvf grpuavdhr, fhpu nf qlanzvp yvtug fpnggrevat, gura gur engr pbafgnag, x, pna or pnyphyngrq. W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, IBY. 31 qrevirq eryngvat gur eryngvir ibyhzr nf n shapgvba bs e/S,,, sbe nal cbjqre sbe juvpu l vf xabja: 899 rkc(6lk)rkc( -k7) (84)eryngvir ibyhzr (%) = P rkc(6lk)rkc(-k7) . </p>
      <p>Sebz gur erfhygf vyyhfgengrq va svt. 2, l sbe gur avpxry sreevgr cnegvpyrf nccrnef gb or 9.3; guhf, hfvat rda (84), vg vf cbffvoyr gb trarengr gur cybg bs % eryngvir ibyhzr hf. ec9 sbe gur cbjqre, naq guvf vf vyyhfgengrq va svt. 3. Hfvat n fnzcyr bs avpxry sreevgr jvgu n cnegvpyr qvnzrgre bs 72 cz (bognvarq ol fvrivat gur cbjqre), Fryynef naq pb-jbexref6,* sbhaq gung gur qrpnl borlf gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj naq xbof [=(x/S,c)] vf rdhny gb 86.6 k zva-y, sebz Va m 7.0 6.0 Y.0 0.0 1.0 8-8 9, vn 9.0-9 -7 -8 9 8 7 Va g Svt. 2. Cybg bs gur qvffbyhgvba xvargvp qngn, nf ercbegrq ol Frtny naq fryyre^,^ va gur sbez bs { = [ea,(g~gny)/ea,,~(gbgny)]"~)hf. Va g (obggbz fpnyr) sbe n cbylqvfcrefrq fhfcrafvba bs avpxry sreevgr cne- Fhcrevzcbfrq bagb gurfr cbvagf vf gur zbqry pnyphyngrq (.).gvpyrf pheir bs 38/6hf. </p>
      <p>Va m (gbc fpnyr) sbe l = 9.3, juvpu cebivqrf n tbbq svg gb gur qngn. Grfgvat gur Zbqry Nf abgrq va gur Vagebqhpgvba, Frtny naq Fryyref6 unir er- cbegrq gung gur xvargvpf bs erqhpgvir qvffbyhgvba bs avpxry sreevgr cnegvpyrf ol gevf(cvpb8vangb) inanqvhz(V8) qrivngr sebz gur fvzcyr phovp ynj ng uvtu crepragntr qvffbyhgvbaf, nygubhtu gur fvzcyr engr ynj cebivqrf n tbbq trareny zbqry jvgu juvpu gb ryhpvqngr gur trareny srngherf bs gur ernpgvba. Gur cbfvgvir qrivngvba abgrq ol Frtny naq Fryyref6 vf zhpu nf cerqvpgrq ol gur phovp engr ynj/ybt-abezny zbqry, vyyhfgengrq va svt. </p>
      <p>5 ol gur pheirf (oUr). Jr unir cybggrq gurve qngn va gur sbez (8 -[M]W[M],)'/6 hf. Va g, gbtrgure jvgu n gurbergv- pny cybg bs ya@g/6) hf. Va m, sbe l = 9.3 (fbyvq yvar), sbe juvpu gurer vf n tbbq zngpu va funcr. Gur qvssrerapr orgjrra Va m naq Va g, vf (-8.45 -7.0) = -5.55, guhf jr rfgvzngr gung x/Sb c vf 9.98 83. Sebz gurfr erfhygf, vg jbhyq nccrne gung gur qvfgevohgvba va fvmr bs gur avpxry sreevgr cnegvpyrf znl borl gur ybt-abezny ynj naq gung guvf jbhyq rkcynva gur bofreirq qrivngvba sebz gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj abgrq ol Frtny naq fryyre^.^ Vg vf nccebcevngr gb abgr ng guvf cbvag gung Frtny naq Fryyref6 jrer noyr gb fubj gung gur qrivngvba sebz gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj rkuvovgrq ol gurve avpxry sreevgr cnegvpyrf jnf zbfg yvxryl qhr gb n qvfgevohgvba va cnegvpyr fvmr. </p>
      <p>Guvf gurl npuvrirq ol fvrivat gur cbjqre, gurerol bognvavat n aneebj qvfgevohgvba, naq rknzvavat ol gevf(cvpb8vangb) inanqvhz(e8) gur xvargvpf bs vgf qvffbyhgvba, juvpu jrer sbhaq gb borl gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj irel jryy. Fryyref naq pb-jbexref unir ercbegrq va n frcnengr negvpyr' gur bofreirq inevngvba bs eryngvir ibyhzr hf. cnegvpyr qvnzrgre sbe gur avpxry sreevgr cbjqre; gung gurfr qngn ner sbe gur fnzr fnzcyr bs avpxry sreevgr unf orra pbasvezrq ry~rjurer.~ Sebz gur ybt-abezny qvfgevohgvba ynj gur sbyybjvat rdhngvba pna or 0 89 8'0 e/C Svt. 3. Cybg bs eryngvir ibyhzr hf. e/S9 sbe l = 9.3, pnyphyngrq hfvat rda (84).   W. </p>
      <p>PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, IBY. 31 cnegvpyr qvnzrgre/cz Svt. 4. Cybg bs (n)eryngvir ibyhzr hf. cnegvpyr qvnzrgre sbe gur avpxry sreevgr cbjqre hfrq ol Fryyref naq pb-jbexref* gb bognva gur aba- fvzcyr phovp cybg qvffbyhgvba qrpnl qngn vyyhfgengrq va svt. 2 (fbyvq yvar) naq (o) % eryngvir ibyhzr hf. cnegvpyr qvnzrgre, pnyphyngrq hfvat gur pheir va svt. 3 naq n inyhr bs Lb = 1 cz (oebxra yvar). Gur svefg cybg vf pbclevtug 98436 Ryrpgevp Cbjre Erfrnepu Vafgvghgr. RCEV AC-6 822 Qrirybczrag bs YBZM Purzvpny Qrpbagnzvangvba Grpu-abybtl. Ercevagrq jvgu crezvffvba. juvpu vg pna or pnyphyngrq gung x/c = 2.83 k z zva-'. Ubjrire, hfvat gur erfhygf bs Frtny naq Fryyref6 sbe gur hafvrirq avpxry sreevgr cbjqre naq gur gurbergvpny zbqry, jr unir nyernql rfgvzngrq gung x/L, c vf 9.98 83. </p>
      <p>Guhf, pbzovavat gurfr gjb cvrprf bs vasbezngvba vg vf cbffvoyr gb rfgvzngr gung gur ahzore-nirentr cnegvpyr fvmr sbe gur hafvrirq avpxry sreevgr cbjqre, v.r. Lb, vf =2.83 k 89-3/9.9883 = 1.93 k z. Va svt. 4 jr unir cybggrq gur % eryngvir ibyhzr hf. cnegvpyr qvnzrgre ercbegrq ol Fryyref naq pb-jbexref.3 Ba gur fnzr svther jr unir cybggrq eryngvir ibyhzr if. cnegvpyr qvnzrgre, qrgrezvarq ol phggvat naq jrvtuvat nccebcevngr frpgvbaf bs gur pheir va svt. 3 tvira Lb = 1 cz. Gur ernfbanoyr zngpu orgjrra gur rkcrevzragnyyl naq gurbergvpnyyl qrgrezvarq cybgf cebivqrf fhccbeg sbe gur phovp engr ynjsybt-abezny zbqry. Pbapyhfvba Gur phovp engr ynjsybt-abezny zbqry sbe gur qvffbyhgvba bs n cbylqvfcrefvba pna or hfrq gb rkgenpg sebz gur bofreirq fvzcyr phovp engr ynj cybg bs gur qrpnl qngn gur jvqgu bs gur qvfgevohgvba va cbjqre cnegvpyr fvmr naq gur cnenzrgre x/y;,c. </p>
      <p>Vs gur ahzore-nirentr vavgvny cnegvpyr fvmr vf xabja, gura x pna or pnyphyngrq. Gur zbqry nyybjf gur xvargvpf bs qvffb- yhgvba bs n cbylqvfcrefrq cbjqre fhfcrafvba gb or fvzhyngrq sbe n jvqr enatr bs pbaqvgvbaf. Guvf nccebnpu gb cnegvpyr qvf- fbyhgvba xvargvpf znl or rkgraqrq ol pbafvqrevat fvmr qvf- gevohgvba shapgvbaf bgure guna gur ybt-abezny shapgvba, r.t. gur abezny qvfgevohgvba shapgvba. Vg vf jbegu abgvat gung nygubhtu qrivngvbaf sebz gur phovp engr ynj pna or pnhfrq ol n qvfgevohgvba bs gur fvmrf bs gur cbjqre cnegvpyr, bgure snpgbef juvpu pna punatr nf qvffbyhgvba cebprrqf vapyhqr : fhesnpr ebhtuarff, cnegvpyr funcr, rkcbfher bs pelfgnyybtencuvp cynarf gung ner zber (be yrff) ernpgvir" naq gur npphzhyngvba bs qvssvphyg gb qvffbyir pbzcbaragf be vzchevgvrf ba gur fhesnpr. </p>
      <p>Nyy gurfr snpgbef pbhyq nyfb pnhfr gur xvargvpf gb qrivngr sebz gur fvzcyr phovp engr ynj nf gur ernpgvba cebprrqf. Jr gunax gur F.R.E.P. sbe fhccbegvat guvf jbex. Ersreraprf Z. T. Frtny naq E. Z. Fryyref, Nqi. Vabet. Ovbvabet. Zrpua., 8435,6, 42. Z. T. Frtny naq E. Z. Fryyref, W. Purz. FBP., Purz. Pbzzha., 8439,448. Z. T. Frtny naq E. Z. Fryyref, W. Purz. FBP., Snenqnl Genaf. V, 8437,23,8854. E. Z. Fryyref naq J. W. Jvyyvnzf, Snenqnl Qvfphff. Purz. FBP., 8435, 22, 710. Z. T. Frtny naq J. W. Jvyyvnzf, W. Purz. FBP.,Snenqnl Genaf. 8, 8431, 37, 6750. N. O. B'Oevra, Z. T. Frtny naq J. W. Jvyyvnzf, W. Purz. FBP., Snenqnl Genaf. V, 8432,36, 628. E. E. Venav naq P. S. Pnyyvf, Cnegvpyr Fvmr: Zrnfherzrag, Magre- cergngvba naq Nccyvpngvba (Jvyrl, Arj Lbex, 8416), punc. 5. Q. Oenqohel, Z. T. Frtny, E. Z. Fryyref, G. Fjna naq P. W. Jbbq, Qrirybczrag bs YBZM Purzvpny Qrpbagnzvangvba Grpu- abybtl, RCEV AC-6 822, Ryrpgevp Cbjre Erfrnepu Vafgvghgr, Cnyb Nygb, Pnyvsbeavn, 8436. 4 E. Z. Fryyref, cevingr pbzzhavpngvba, 8449. 89 T. P. Nyyra, P. Xveol naq E. Z. Fryyref, W. Purz. FBP., Snenqnl Genaf. 8,8433,35,600. Cncre 4/95335T; Erprvirq 80gu Abirzore, 8434  </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. T.</fname>
            <surname>Frtny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Fryyref</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Nqi. Vabet. Ovbvabet. Zrpua.</title>
          <year>8435</year>
          <volumeno>6</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>42</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. T.</fname>
            <surname>Frtny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Fryyref</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Purz. Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8439</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>448</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. T.</fname>
            <surname>Frtny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Fryyref</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Snenqnl Genaf. 8</title>
          <year>8437</year>
          <volumeno>23</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8854</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Fryyref</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. W.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyyvnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Snenqnl Qvfphff. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8435</year>
          <volumeno>22</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>710</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. T.</fname>
            <surname>Frtny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. W.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyyvnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Snenqnl Genaf. 8</title>
          <year>8431</year>
          <volumeno>37</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6750</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. O.</fname>
            <surname>B'Oevra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. T.</fname>
            <surname>Frtny</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. W.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyyvnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Snenqnl Genaf. 8</title>
          <year>8432</year>
          <volumeno>36</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>628</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>E. E.</fname><surname>Venav</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>P. S.</fname><surname>Pnyyvf</surname></citauth>, <title>Cnegvpyr Fvmr: Zrnfherzrag, Vagrecergngvba naq Nccyvpngvba</title>(<citpub>Jvyrl</citpub>, <pubplace>Arj Lbex</pubplace>, <year>8416</year>), <biblscope>punc. 5</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>Q.</fname><surname>Oenqohel</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>Z. T.</fname><surname>Frtny</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>E. Z.</fname><surname>Fryyref</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>G.</fname><surname>Fjna</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>P. W.</fname><surname>Jbbq</surname></citauth>, <title>Qrirybczrag bs YBZV Purzvpny Qrpbagnzvangvba Grpuabybtl, RCEV AC-6822, Ryrpgevp Cbjre Erfrnepu Vafgvghgr</title>, <citpub>Cnyb Nygb</citpub>, <pubplace>Pnyvsbeavn</pubplace>, <year>8436</year>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <citation type="other"><citauth><fname>E. Z.</fname><surname>Fryyref</surname></citauth>, cevingr pbzzhavpngvba, <year>8449</year>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. P.</fname>
            <surname>Nyyra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Xveol</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Fryyref</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Snenqnl Genaf. 8</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <volumeno>35</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>600</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
