<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>SG4493197602</ms-id>
    <doi>89.8964/SG4493197602</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>SG</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>31</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>86</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>7602</fpage>
      <lpage>7619</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>5</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8449</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>SG</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8449</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>N gurbergvpny fghql bs gur vasenerq nofbecgvba fcrpgen bs ynetr jngre pyhfgref</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Vna C.</fname>
            <surname>Ohssrl</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Jvyyvnz Olref</fname>
            <surname>Oebja</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>U. Nynfgnve</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Jr ercbeg gur erfhygf bs n zbyrphyne-qlanzvpf fghql bs n srj ynetr jngre pyhfgref, va cnegvphyne (U<inf>7</inf>B)<inf>79</inf>, jubfr vasenerq fcrpgen ner bs vagrerfg va pbaarpgvba jvgu ngzbfcurevp nofbecgvba curabzran. Gur zbyrphyrf ner nffhzrq gb or evtvq naq gb vagrenpg jvgu gur ZPL cnve cbgragvny nppbeqvat gb pynffvpny zrpunavpf. Gur irybpvgl naq qvcbyr nhgbpbeeryngvba shapgvbaf ner bognvarq ol pbzchgre fvzhyngvba ng inevbhf grzcrengherf naq gur pbeerfcbaqvat cbjre fcrpgen pbzchgrq nf shapgvbaf bs serdhrapl. Gur erfhygf fubj gung gur pyhfgref haqretb fbzr xvaq bs genafvgvba (zrygvat) nebhaq 799 X, naq gung qenzngvp punatrf bpphe va gur nofbecgvba fcrpgen orgjrra 9 X naq ebbz grzcrengherf. Vg vf pbapyhqrq gung gur erfhygf bognvarq fb sne fhccbeg gur vqrn gung gur bofreirq nabznybhf nofbecgvba bs sne-vasenerq enqvngvba ol gur ngzbfcurer pbhyq or qhr gb ynetr ‘yvdhvq’ jngre pyhfgref.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p> W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449,31(86), 7602-7619 N Gurbergvpny Fghql bs gur Vasenerq Nofbecgvba Fcrpgen bs Ynetr Jngre Pyhfgref Vna C. Ohssrl naq Jvyyvnz Olref Oebja* Qrcnegzrag bs Purzvfgel, Havirefvgl bs Znapurfgre, Znapurfgre Z 86 4CY U. Nynfgnve Troovr Qrcnegzrag bs Ryrpgevpny Ratvarrevat, Vzcrevny Pbyyrtr, Ybaqba FJ2 Jr ercbeg gur erfhygf bs n zbyrphyne-qlanzvpf fghql bs n srj ynetr jngre pyhfgref, va cnegvphyne (U,B),, , jubfr vasenerq fcrpgen ner bs vagrerfg va pbaarpgvba jvgu ngzbfcurevp nofbecgvba curabzran. Gur zbyrphyrf ner nffhzrq gb or evtvq naq gb vagrenpg jvgu gur ZPL cnve cbgragvny nppbeqvat gb pynffvpny zrpunavpf. Gur irybpvgl naq qvcbyr nhgbpbeeryngvba shapgvbaf ner bognvarq ol pbzchgre fvzhyngvba ng inevbhf grzcrengherf naq gur pbe- erfcbaqvat cbjre fcrpgen pbzchgrq nf shapgvbaf bs serdhrapl. </p>
      <p>Gur erfhygf fubj gung gur pyhfgref haqretb fbzr xvaq bs genafvgvba (zrygvat) nebhaq 799 X, naq gung qenzngvp punatrf bpphe va gur nofbecgvba fcrpgen orgjrra 9 X naq ebbz grzcrengherf. Vg vf pbapyhqrq gung gur erfhygf bognvarq fb sne fhccbeg gur vqrn gung gur bofreirq nabznybhf nofbecgvba bs sne-vasenerq enqvngvba ol gur ngzbfcurer pbhyq or qhr gb ynetr ‘ yvdhvq ’ jngre pyhfgref. Gb nppbhag sbe vasenerq naq zvyyvzrger-jnir nofbecgvba va gur ngzbfcurer, juvpu unf orra rkgrafviryl fghqvrq sbe znal lrnef,8-87 vg vf arprffnel gb vaibxr gur cerfrapr bs incbhe- cunfr jngre fcrpvrf va nqqvgvba gb zbabzrevp U79 zby-rphyrf.y y Gur bayl fcrpvrf jvgu gurezbqlanzvp cebcregvrf fhpu gung vgf rdhvyvoevhz pbapragengvba vf fvtavsvpnag haqre ngzbfcurevp pbaqvgvbaf vf gur qvzre, ohg obgu gur fcrpgen naq npbhfgvp orunivbhe npghnyyl bofreirq bire n enatr bs grz- crengherf cbvag gb gur rkvfgrapr bs ynetre pyhfgref (U79), jubfr pbapragengvbaf ner zhpu terngre guna gur rdhvyvoevhz Obygmznaa inyhrf. </p>
      <p>Gur rkvfgrapr bs fhpu zrgnfgnoyr fcrpvrf unf ybat orra xabja sebz gur fhcrefnghengvba cebqhprq va pybhq punzoref ol nqvnongvp rkcnafvba naq ol hygenivbyrg cubgba^,'^ ohg gurve erpbtavgvba va gur ngzbfcurer vf pbzcn- engviryl erprag.” Crefhnfvir nethzragf sbe pbafvqrevat pyhfgref pbzcbfrq bs pn. 79 naq 19 zbabzre havgf yrq gb gur gurbergvpny vairfgvtn- gvba bs frzv-evtvq zbyrphyne zbqryf bs gurfr naq vagrezrqvngr fvmrf hfvat zbyrphyne zrpunavpf (ZZ).yY81 Pnyphyngvbaf bs gur vagrezbyrphyne ivoengvba zbqrf fubjrq gung abar bs gur fznyyre fgnoyr frzv-evtvq pyhfgref jnf cerqvpgrq gb unir nofbecgvba jniryratguf va gur fho-zvyyvzrger ertvba nf erdhverq ol bofreingvba. </p>
      <p>Bayl gur 19-zre jvgu na vpbfnurqeny fgehpgher unq rvtrajnirahzoref yrff guna 89 pz-’,ohg gur cerqvpgrq qvcbyr vagrafvgvrf jrer gbb fznyy gb nppbhag sbe gur bofreingvbaf. 80*81 Gur checbfr bs gur cerfrag cncre vf gb ercbeg gur erfhygf bs n zbyrphyne qlanzvpf (ZQ) pbzchgre fvzhyngvba bs gur vagrezbyrphyne nofbecgvba fcrpgen’ nffhzvat gung pynffvpny zrpunavpf vf nqrdhngr gb fghql gur ybj-jnirahzore ertvba (&amp;yb9 pz-’) bs znwbe vagrerfg. Fvapr zbfg trareny checbfr ZQ cebtenzf ner vagraqrq sbe ohyx fvzhyngvba naq nffhzr crevbqvp obhaqnel pbaqvgvba^,'^ n arj cebtenz sbe pyhfgref jnf jevggra vapbecbengvat gur ZPL cbgragvnyV3 gb zbqry gur vagrenpgvbaf bs gur jngre zbyrphyrf. </p>
      <p>Ahzrebhf ZQ ehaf jrer cresbezrq sbe pyhfgref bs qvssrerag fvmrf ng n frevrf bs vapernf- vat grzcrengherf, naq gurbergvpny nofbecgvba fcrpgen jrer pnyphyngrq ol Sbhevre-genafsbezvat gur qvcbyr naq irybpvgl nhgbpbeeryngvba shapgvbaf. Arne nofbyhgr mreb gur ZQ fcrpgen pybfryl erfrzoyr gur ZZ abezny zbqrf, naq ng nyy grzcrengherf gur erfhygf sbe (U,B),, ner irel fvzvyne gb gubfr bs Cyhzzre naq Pura,” cebivqvat purpxf ba bhe erfhygf. Nf gur grzcrengher vapernfrf gb gung bs gur rkcrevzragny bofre- ingvbaf (719-699 X), nyy gur pyhfgref fghqvrq nccrne gb ‘zryg’, naq gur qbzvanag nofbecgvba zbirf gb ybjre serdhrapvrf (9-899 pz-’). </p>
      <p>Vaqrrq, znal bs gur pnyphyngrq fcrpgen unir frireny ybj-serdhrapl, uvtu-vagrafvgl crnxf, juvpu vf n irel rkpvgvat erfhyg fhccbegvat gur ulcbgurfvf gung gur bofreirq nabznybhf nofbecgvba vf qhr gb ynetr ‘yvdhvq’ jngre pyhfgref. Erfhygf naq Qvfphffvba Zbyrphyne-qlanzvpf Pnyphyngvbaf N cebtenz pnyyrq ZQU79 jnf jevggra gb cresbez gur ZQ pnyphyngvbaf. Ernqvyl ninvynoyr cebtenzf sbe ZQ pnyphyngvbaf fhssre sebz gjb qenjonpxf. (v) Gurl ner sbe yvdhvq fvzhyngvbaf. Guvf znxrf gurz varssvpvrag gb hfr sbe pyhfgre fvzhyngvbaf, jurer gurer ner ab crevbqvp obhaqnel pbaqvgvbaf. (vv) Gur cbgragvny sbezf hfrq ner qvssrerag sebz gung bs gur ZPL cbgragvny. Gur ZPL cbgragvny jnf hfrq sbe gur ZQ pnyph-yngvbaf, fb gung gur erfhygf pbhyq or pbzcnerq jvgu gubfr bognvarq ol zbyrphyne zrpunavpf.81 ZQU79 hfrf gur yrnc-sebt nytbevguz sbe gur prager-bs- znff zbgvba,79 naq gur ebgngvbany zbgvba vf unaqyrq ol n zrgubq nyfb qrfpevorq ol Svapunz” juvpu hfrf dhngreavba cnenzrgref gb qrfpevor bevragngvba fcnpr. </p>
      <p>N creraavny ceboyrz jvgu zbyrphyne-qlanzvpf fvzhyngvbaf vf ubj ynetr gb znxr gur gvzr fgrc orgjrra cbvagf ng juvpu pbbeqvangrf naq irybpvgvrf ner pnyphyngrq. Gur inyhr hfrq va guvf jbex vf 7.0 k f, juvpu vf fhssvpvragyl fznyy gb npuvrir raretl pbafreingvba gb 8 cneg va yb5 guebhtubhg na ZQ eha. Vg vf arprffnel gb hfr fhpu n fznyy gvzr fgrc orpnhfr gur zbzragf bs varegvn bs gur jngre zbyrphyr ner fb fznyy. Inevbhf pyhfgref jrer fghqvrq hfvat ZQU79, gur trareny zrgubq orvat nf sbyybjf. </p>
      <p>Gur vavgvny trbzrgel bs rnpu pyhfgre vf bcgvzvmrq jvgu erfcrpg gb cbgragvny raretl. (Gurfr zvavzhz-raretl fgehpgherf jrer bognvarq sebz rneyvre jbex.85) Va ZQ grezf gurfr ner fgehpgherf ng 9 X. Gur pyhfgre vf gura tvira n pregnva nzbhag bs xvargvp raretl fhpu gung vgf grzcrengher nsgre rdhvyvoevhz vf pn. 87.0 X. Arkg gur pyhfgre vf fhowrpgrq gb n frevrf bs plpyrf va juvpu vg vf urngrq ol pn. 87.0 X naq gura nyybjrq gb rdhvyvoengr (pn. 8999 gvzr fgrcf ner erdhverq sbe rdhvyvoengvba). Nsgre rdhvyvoengvba gur zbgvba vf nyybjrq gb cebprrq sbe pn. 59999 gvzr fgrcf juvyr gur iryb- pvgvrf naq pbbeqvangrf ner erpbeqrq sbe nanylfvf. Va cevapvcyr gur ZQ ehaf ng rnpu grzcrengher fubhyq or ybat rabhtu sbe nyy gur ulqebtra obaqf va gur pyhfgre gb or oebxra naq ersbezrq. Va cenpgvpr guvf vf gbb gvzr-pbafhzvat. </p>
      <p>Ng ybj grz- crengherf gur pyhfgre trbzrgel ng gur raq bs n eha vf nyzbfg hapunatrq ng yrnfg nf sne nf gur pbaarpgvivgl vf pbaprearq.   7603 629 5679 u 7 29 f 779 829 879 -609 -699 -709 -799 -v09 raretl/xW zby-' Svt. 8. Cybg bs grzcrengher (X) hf. gbgny raretl (xW cre zby bs pyhfgre) sbe n 8Mzbyrphyr pyhfgre (U,B),,, fubjvat gur oernx-hc bs gur pyhfgre ng grzcrengherf nobir pn. 729 X. Gur qbqrpnurqen8 fgehpgher fghqvrq ol Cyhzzre naq Pura ergnvarq vgf vagrtevgl hc gb 680 X. N fvzvyne grzcrengher jnf ernpurq va guvf jbex. Nf gur pyhfgref ernpu gurfr uvtu grz- crengherf gurl ortva gb oernx hc. Gb ortva jvgu guvf vaibyirf gur oernxvat bs ulqebtra obaqf bayl ;zbyrphyrf qb abg ortva gb rincbengr sebz gur pyhfgre hagvy zbfg bs gur bevtvany fgehp- gher unf orra qrfgeblrq. </p>
      <p>Jura ulqebtra obaqf oernx gur pyhfgre vf rssrpgviryl pbbyrq, nf frra va svt. 8. Grzcrengher Qrcraqrapr bs Pyhfgre Raretl Cyhzzre naq PuraVt cebqhprq n cybg bs gbgny pyhfgre raretl ntnvafg gur vagreany xvargvp grzcrengher sbe gur 79-zbyrphyr pyhfgre gurl fghqvrq. Gur rdhvinyrag cybg bs gur erfhygf bs guvf jbex vf fubja va svt. 7 naq vf irel fvzvyne gb gung bognvarq ol Cyhzzre naq Pura. Gur fybcr bs gur tencu vf gur urng pncnp- vgl bs gur pyhfgre. Cyhzzre naq Pura nfpevorq gur punatr va fybcr ng pn. 799 X gb n xvaq bs zrygvat. Gurl bognvarq n urng pncnpvgl bs 51 W X-y zby-' cre zbyrphyr sbe grzcrengherf orybj gur cunfr punatr ng 799 X naq 894 W X-' zby-' cre zbyrphyr nobir vg. </p>
      <p>Gur pbeerfcbaqvat inyhrf qrqhprq sebz svt. 7 ner 55.7 naq 898. Guvf nterrzrag vf erznexnoyr, tvira gung Cyhzzre naq Pura qvq abg nffhzr gung gur jngre zby- rphyrf jrer evtvq ohg vapyhqrq gur vagreany ivoengvbaf va gurve zbqry, naq hfrq n prageny sbepr cnve cbgragvny juvpu vf fvtavsv- pnagyl qvssrerag va sbez sebz gur ZPL cbgragvny. Va guvf jbex pyhfgref bs 87 naq 60 zbyrphyrf jrer nyfb urngrq sebz ybj gb uvtu grzcrengherf. Gurfr pyhfgref haqretb fbzr xvaq bs punatr ng pn. 790 naq 769 X, erfcrpgviryl, ohg gur angher bs gur punatr vf abg fb pyrne (frr svt. 8naq 6). Nhgbpbeeryngvba Shapgvbaf naq Cbjre Fcrpgen Gur znva ernfba sbe pneelvat bhg gur ZQ fvzhyngvbaf jnf gb pnyphyngr gur cbjre fcrpgen juvpu ner eryngrq gb gur nofbec- W. </p>
      <p>PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, IBY. 31 -609 -599 -509 p V-R -099 m&gt;C 0 -009 -199 -10P V879 829 779 729 679 GVX Svt. 7. Cybg bs gbgny pyhfgre raretl (xW cre zby bs pyhfgre) hf. grz-crengher (X) sbe n 79-zbyrphyr pyhfgre (U,B),, ,fubjvat 'zrygvat' ng pn. 799 X. -209 -309 -409 p V-R 26 -8909 C p -8809 -870P -860959 39 879 819 799 759 739 G/X Svt. 6. Cybg bs gbgny pyhfgre raretl (xW cre zby bs pyhfgre) hf. grz-crengher (X) sbe n 60-zbyrphyr pyhfgre (U,B),, , fubjvat n genafvgvba ng PD. 769 X.   W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, IBY. 31 gvba fcrpgen bs pyhfgref. Gur irybpvgl nhgbpbeeryngvba shapgvba vf qrsvarq nf jurer ixg) vf gur fcrrq bs na ngbz va gur pyhfgre ng gvzr g; gur natyr oenpxrgf vaqvpngr gung n gurezbqlanzvp nirentr vf gnxra. </p>
      <p>Guvf vf qbar ol nirentvat gur evtug-unaq fvqr bs rda (8) bire frireny gvzr bevtvaf. Gur serdhrapl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz vf tvira ol s(b) = el(g)pbf(bg)qg. (7) Boivbhfyl guvf vagrteny pnaabg or pnyphyngrq bire na vasvavgr gvzr vagreiny. Gur ynetre gur hccre yvzvg bs gur vagrteny, gur orggre gur pnyphyngrq cbjre fcrpgehz nccebkvzngrf gb gur gurbergvpny bar tvira ol rda (7). Gur npphenpl bs gur pnyph- yngvbaf qrcraqf ba gur yratgu bs gur zbyrphyne-qlanzvpf eha naq gur ahzore bs gvzr bevtvaf bire juvpu rda (8) vf nire- ntrq. Vqrnyyl gur gvzr, G, bire juvpu l(g) vf pnyphyngrq fubhyq or ynetr rabhtu fb gung l(g &gt; G) vf rssrpgviryl mreb. </p>
      <p>Gur vagrafvgl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz vf pnyphyngrq sebz gur qvcbyr nhgbpbeeryngvba shapgvba, juvpu vf qrsvarq nf (6) jurer c(g) vf gur gbgny pyhfgre qvcbyr zbzrag ng gvzr g, naq gur natyr oenpxrgf vaqvpngr na nirentr bire n ahzore bs gvzr bevtvaf, nf jvgu rda (8). Va cenpgvpr C(g) qbrf abg nccebnpu mreb qhevat gur ZQ ehaf, fb vg vf arprffnel gb hfr n pbeerpgrq qvcbyr zbzrag tvira ol C'J = J)-pe (5) jurer sv vf gur nirentr qvcbyr irpgbe sbe rnpu gvzr bevtva. Gur vagrafvgl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz vf tvira ol t(b) = /?(g)pbf(bg) qg. (0)e Gur serdhrapl naq vagrafvgl qvfgevohgvba fcrpgen ng ybj grzcrengherf (svt. 5 naq 0) ner irel fvzvyne gb gur serdhrapl qvfgevohgvba uvfgbtenzf naq yvar vagrafvgl fcrpgen bognvarq ol abezny-zbqr nanylfvf bs gur vavgvny trbzrgevrf hfrq sbe gur ZQ ehaf. </p>
      <p>Guvf tvirf pbasvezngvba gung nyy gur pnyphyngvbaf ner orvat cresbezrq cebcreyl ol ZQU79 naq gur nanylfvf cebtenzf. Nf gur pyhfgre'f grzcrengher vapernfrf gur ser- dhrapl qvfgevohgvba punatrf, fb gung zbfg bs gur ivoengvbaf bpphe ng ybjre serdhrapvrf (frr svt. 1). Gur fuvsg bs gur nofbec- gvba vagrafvgl gb ybj serdhrapvrf vf rira zber cebabhaprq 9.38 % 9 899 799 699 599 099 199 299 399 499 ybb9 8899 jnirahzore/pz -Svt. 5. Serdhrapl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz s(j) va havgf bs gur gvzr fgrc (9.70 sf) ntnvafg jnirahzore (pz-') sbe n 79-zre (U,B),, jvgu na vavgvny qbqrpnurqen8 pbasvthengvba ng 87.0 X. 899 799 699 599 099 199 299 399 499 8999 8899 jnirahzore/pz-' Svt. </p>
      <p>0. Vagrafvgl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz t(j) va havgf bs gur gvzr fgrc ntnvafg jnirahzore (na-') sbe gur 79-zre (U,B),, va svt. 6 ng gur fnzr grzcrengher, 87.0 X. (svt. 2). Guvf fuvsg va serdhrapl qvfgevohgvba naq vapernfr va ybj-serdhrapl nofbecgvba jnf bofreirq va nyy pyhfgref sbe juvpu gurfr pnyphyngvbaf jrer cresbezrq. Nabgure vagrerfgvat srngher bs gur vagrafvgl qvfgevohgvba fcrpgen vf gung irel uvtu- vagrafvgl, ybj-serdhrapl nofbecgvbaf nccrne ng pregnva grz- crengherf (svt. 3), bayl gb qvfnccrne naq or ercynprq ng uvture grzcrengherf ol uvtu-vagrafvgl nofbecgvba ng qvssrerag ser- dhrapvrf. Gur nofbecgvba fubja va svt. 3 vf fb vagrafr gung vg fubjf hc pyrneyl va gur qvcbyr nhgbpbeeryngvba shapgvba (svt. </p>
      <p>4). Vg vf vagrerfgvat gb abgr gung gurfr uvtu-vagrafvgl yvarf ner 9.09b*19888 -9.898'' 8 ' " "'" 9 899 799 699 599 099 199 299 399 499 ybb9 8899 jnirahzore/pz-' Svt. 1. Serdhrapl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz s(b)va havgf bs gur gvzr fgrc ntnvafg jnirahzore (pz-') sbe n 79-zre (U,B),, ng 735.2 X. 5 7 9 -7 -55 " " " ' " " 9 899 799 699 599 099 199 299 399 499 89998899 jnirahz ore/pz -' Svt. 2. Vagrafvgl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz qb) va havgf bs gur gvzr fgrc ntnvafg jnirahzore (pz-')sbe n 79-zre (U,B),, ng 735.2 X.   7619 W. PURZ. FBP. SNENQNL GENAF., 8449, IBY. 31 p75-8.9,77-79 -83-6 ,-89; -8 ' ' ' ' ' . ,899 799 699 599 099 199 2992 399 499 89998899 jnirahzorespz-' Svt. 3. </p>
      <p>Vagrafvgl qvfgevohgvba cbjre fcrpgehz t(b) va havgf bs gur gvzr fgrc ntnvafg jnirahzore (pz-') sbe n 87-zre (U,B),, ng 18.6 X, fubjvat vagrafr ybj-serdhrapl nofbecgvba orybj 09 pz-'. fhcrevzcbfrq ba gur onfvp pyhfgre fcrpgehz, juvpu punatrf bayl fybjyl nf gur pyhfgre vf urngrq. Pbapyhfvbaf Gur zbfg vzcbegnag trareny pbapyhfvba juvpu pna or qenja sebz gur zbyrphyne-qlanzvpf fghql ercbegrq urer vf gung vg tvirf rapbhentvat fhccbeg gb gur ulcbgurfvf gung gur bofreirq nabznybhf nofbecgvba bs gur ngzbfcurer va gur fho-zvyyvzrger jniryratgu ertvba vf qhr gb ynetr 'yvdhvq' jngre pyhfgref." Guvf fghql gurersber fhcrefrqrf gur rneyvre zbyrphyne-zrpunavpf jbex onfrq ba frzv-evtvq zbqryf,'5*' ng yrnfg sbe ybj jnirahzoref sebz 9 gb 899 pz-'. Ubjrire, gur ertvba nebhaq 299 pz-' vf nyfb bs pbafvqrenoyr vagrerfg, naq urer gur ZZ erfhygf znl fgvyy or gur orfg thvqr gb gur fcrpgen craqvat n cebcre dhnaghz zbyrphyne-qlanzvpf vairfgvtngvba. Gur cerfrag fghql vf pyrneyl n svefg jbeq engure guna n ynfg nf sne nf haqrefgnaqvat gur cbffvoyl pbzcyrk ceb- prffrf vaibyirq va gur nabznybhf ngzbfcurevp nofbecgvba curabzran. </p>
      <p>Gur dhnagvgngvir nfcrpgf bs gur pbzcnevfba orgjrra gur pyhfgre zbqry naq bofreingvbaf, fgnegvat jvgu gur dhrfgvba bs pyhfgre fvmrf naq gur zrpunavfz ol juvpu ynetr pyhfgref ner perngrq haqre pbaqvgvbaf jura gurl ner gurezb- qlanzvpnyyl zrgnfgnoyr, erdhver shegure vairfgvtngvbaf. Ubjrire, vg vf qvssvphyg gb oryvrir gung gur oebnq srngherf bs gur pnyphyngrq fcrpgen qrcraq frafvgviryl ba gur nccebk- vzngvbaf vaibyirq, fhpu nf gur sbez bs gur cbgragvny, gur nffhzcgvba bs vagreany evtvqvgl rgp. </p>
      <p>Nzbat gur zber vagevth- vat bs gurfr oebnq srngherf ner gur irel uvtu vagrafvgl nofbec- gvba crnxf juvpu nccrne nf gur grzcrengher vf envfrq, naq gura qvfnccrne ntnva. Vg vf grzcgvat gb ertneq gurz nf glcvpny pbyyrpgvir aba-yvarne curabzran naq ynory gurz 'tvnag qvcbyr erfbanaprf '. -8.bW 9 8 7 6 5 gyCF Svt. 4. Cybg bs qvcbyr nhgbpbeeryngvba shapgvba O(g) ntnvafg gvzr (cf) sbe gur 87-zre (U,B),, ng 18.6 X sebz juvpu svt. 3 vf pnyphyngrq. Ersreraprf 8 U. N. Troovr, Culf. Eri., 8402, 892, 8845. 7 U. N. Troovr, J. W. Oheebhtuf, W. R. Uneevrf naq E. U. Pnzreba, Nfgebculf. W., 8413, 805,590. 6 U. N. Troovr, J. W. Oheebhtuf naq T. </p>
      <p>E. Oveq, Cebp. E. FBP. (Ybaqba), Fre. N, 8414,689,024. 5 N. Mnibql, E. W. Rzrel naq U. N. Troovr, Angher (Ybaqba), 8414,742,517. 0 E. N. Obuynaqre, U. N. Troovr naq T. J. S. Cneqbp, Angher (Ybaqba), 8429,773,802. 1 U. N. Troovr, C. Z. Xhua naq E. N. Obuynaqre, Angher (Ybaqba), 8429,771,28. 2 T. T. Tvzzrfgnq naq U. N. Troovr, W. Ngzbf. Gree. Culf., 8421, 63, 670. 3 C. U. Zbssng, E. N. Obuynaqre, J. E. ZpPenr naq U. N. Troovr, Angher (Ybaqba), 8422,714,121. 4 T. T. Tvzzrfgnq, E. U. Jner, E. N. Obuynaqre naq U. N. Troovr, Nfgebculf. W., 8422, 783, 688. 89 Q. G. Yyrjryyla Wbarf, E. W. Xavtug naq U. N. Troovr, Angher (Ybaqba),8423,725,322. 88 U. N. Troovr, Angher (Ybaqba), 8437,7%, 577. 87 C. Qvnf Ynypnpn, A. W. P. Cnpxunz naq U. N. Troovr, Masenerq Culf., 8435,75562. 86 P. G. E. Jvyfba, Genaf. E. FBP.(Ybaqba), Fre. N, 8342, 834, 710; Cuvybf. Genaf. E. FBP.(Ybaqba), Cneg N, 8344,847,596; 846,734. 85 V. C. Ohssrl naq J. Olref Oebja, Purz. Culf. Yrgg., 8435, 894, 04. 80 V. C. Ohssrl, J. Olref Oebja naq U. N. Troovr, Purz. Culf. Yrgg., 8433, 853, 738. 81 V. C. Ohssrl, Cu.Q. Gurfvf (Havirefvgl bs Znapurfgre, 8433). 82 Z. C. Nyyra naq Q. W. Gvyqrfyrl, Pbzchgre Fvzhyngvba bs Yvdhvqf (Pyneraqba Cerff, Bksbeq, 8432). 83 9. Zngfhbxn, R. Pyrzragv naq L. Lbfuvzvar, W. Purz. Culf., 8421,18, 051. 84 C. Y. Z. Cyhzzre naq G. F. Pura, W. Culf. Purz., 8436, 32, 5849. 79 Q. Svapunz, PPCF Arjfyrggre, 8438,7, 1. Cncre 4/96103W; Erprvirq 70gu Nhthfg, 8434  </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Culf. Eri.</title>
          <year>8402</year>
          <volumeno>892</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8845</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. W.</fname>
            <surname>Oheebhtuf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. R.</fname>
            <surname>Uneevrf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. U.</fname>
            <surname>Pnzreba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Nfgebculf. W.</title>
          <year>8413</year>
          <volumeno>805</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>590</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. W.</fname>
            <surname>Oheebhtuf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. E.</fname>
            <surname>Oveq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cebp. E. Fbp. (Ybaqba), Fre. N</title>
          <year>8414</year>
          <volumeno>689</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>024</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Mnibql</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. W.</fname>
            <surname>Rzrel</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8414</year>
          <volumeno>742</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>517</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. N.</fname>
            <surname>Obuynaqre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. J. S.</fname>
            <surname>Cneqbp</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8429</year>
          <volumeno>773</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>802</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Xhua</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. N.</fname>
            <surname>Obuynaqre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8429</year>
          <volumeno>771</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>28</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. T.</fname>
            <surname>Tvzzrfgnq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Ngzbf. Gree. Culf.</title>
          <year>8421</year>
          <volumeno>63</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>670</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. U.</fname>
            <surname>Zbssng</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. N.</fname>
            <surname>Obuynaqre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. E.</fname>
            <surname>ZpPenr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8422</year>
          <volumeno>714</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>121</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. T.</fname>
            <surname>Tvzzrfgnq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. U.</fname>
            <surname>Jner</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. N.</fname>
            <surname>Obuynaqre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Nfgebculf. W.</title>
          <year>8422</year>
          <volumeno>783</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>688</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. G.</fname>
            <surname>Yyrjryyla Wbarf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. W.</fname>
            <surname>Xavtug</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8423</year>
          <volumeno>725</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>322</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit11">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher (Ybaqba)</title>
          <year>8437</year>
          <volumeno>741</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>577</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit12">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Qvnf Ynypnpn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. W. P.</fname>
            <surname>Cnpxunz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vasenerq Culf.</title>
          <year>8435</year>
          <volumeno>75</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>562</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit13">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. G. E.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyfba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Genaf. E. Fbp. (Ybaqba), Fre. N</title>
          <year>8342</year>
          <volumeno>834</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>710</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. G. E.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyfba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cuvybf. Genaf. E. Fbp. (Ybaqba), Cneg N</title>
          <year>8344</year>
          <volumeno>847</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>596</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. G. E.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyfba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cuvybf. Genaf. E. Fbp. (Ybaqba), Cneg N</title>
          <year>8344</year>
          <volumeno>846</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>734</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit14">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V. C.</fname>
            <surname>Ohssrl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Olref Oebja</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Culf. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8435</year>
          <volumeno>894</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>04</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit15">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V. C.</fname>
            <surname>Ohssrl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Olref Oebja</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. N.</fname>
            <surname>Troovr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Culf. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <volumeno>853</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>738</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit16">
        <citation type="thesis"><citauth><fname>V. C.</fname><surname>Ohssrl</surname></citauth>, <it>Cu.Q. Gurfvf</it>(<citpub>Havirefvgl bs Znapurfgre</citpub>, <year>8433</year>).</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit17">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>Z. C.</fname><surname>Nyyra</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>Q. W.</fname><surname>Gvyqrfyrl</surname></citauth>, <title>Pbzchgre Fvzhyngvba bs Yvdhvqf</title>(<citpub>Pyneraqba Cerff</citpub>, <pubplace>Bksbeq</pubplace>, <year>8432</year>).</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit18">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>B.</fname>
            <surname>Zngfhbxn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R.</fname>
            <surname>Pyrzragv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Lbfuvzvar</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Culf.</title>
          <year>8421</year>
          <volumeno>18</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>051</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit19">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. Y. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Cyhzzre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. F.</fname>
            <surname>Pura</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Culf. Purz.</title>
          <year>8436</year>
          <volumeno>32</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5849</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit20">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q.</fname>
            <surname>Svapunz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>PPC0 Arjfyrggre</title>
          <year>8438</year>
          <volumeno>7</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
