<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>C84409999160</ms-id>
    <doi>89.8964/C84409999160</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>C8</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>
</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>1</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>160</fpage>
      <lpage>159</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>1</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8440</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>C8</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8440</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Ybj-grzcrengher nqqvgvba bs ulqebtra cbylfhysvqrf gb byrsvaf: sbezngvba bs 7,7′-qvnyxly cbylfhysvqrf sebz nyx-8-rarf naq plpyvp (cbyl)fhysvqrf naq cbylzrevp betnavp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf sebz α,ω-qvrarf</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Jvz</fname>
            <surname>qr Tenns</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Wnnc F. Fvaavatur</fname>
            <surname>Qnzfgé</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Wna J.</fname>
            <surname>qr Yrrhj</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Ulqebtracbylfhysvqr vbaf, trarengrq ol gur ernpgvba bs ulqebtrafhysvqr vbaf naq ryrzragny fhyshe, ernpg va n cbyne betnavp fbyirag jvgu nyx-8-rarf naq nyxn-α,ω-qvrarf haqre irel zvyq pbaqvgvbaf: 79–09 °P sbe 8–89 qnlf. Gur erntrag jnf cercnerq rvgure va QZS jvgu An<sup>+</sup> nf pbhagre-vba (zrgubq N) be va RgBNp–U<inf>7</inf>B jvgu dhngreanel nzzbavhz nf pbhagre-vba (zrgubq O). Urknqrp-8-rar lvryqf obgu ol zrgubq N naq O 7,7′-qvurknqrply cbylfhysvqrf <it>ivn</it> n Znexbjavxbss-glcr nqqvgvba. Gur birenyy fryrpgvivgl bs Znexbjavxbss <it>if</it>. nagv-Znexbjavxbss nqqvgvba vf <it>pn</it>. 60:8. Gur fryrpgvivgl qrpernfrf ng uvture grzcrengherf va QZS nf fbyirag cebonoyl nf gur erfhyg bs n frdhrapr bs ryvzvangvba/ernqqvgvba ernpgvbaf. Nyxn-α,ω-qvrarf ner va n fvzvyne jnl pbairegrq (zrgubq O) vagb cbylzrevp cbylfhysvqrf vs gur ahzore bs zrgulyrarf orgjrra gur qbhoyr obaqf vf ⩾5. Zbabzrevp plpyvp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf ner bognvarq vs gur ahzore bs zrgulyrarf vf &lt; 5. Cragn-8,5-qvrar lvryqf znvayl gur plpyvp qvfhysvqr 6,0-qvzrguly-8,7-qvguvbynar jurernf urkn-8,0-qvrar lvryqf gur plpyvp zbabfhysvqr 7,0-qvzrgulyguvbynar nf gur bayl cebqhpg. Urcgn-8,1-qvrar lvryqf plpyvp zbab- naq qv-fhysvqrf. Cebgba-pngnylfrq, fvzcyr ahpyrbcuvyvp naq enqvpny zrpunavfzf sbe gur ‘ulqebfhyshevmngvba’ ner rkpyhqrq. N pbapregrq nqqvgvba bs n ulqebtracbylfhysvqr vba gb n qbhoyr obaq vf cebcbfrq nf gur npghny zrpunavfz. Gur sbezngvba bs guvbynarf naq guvnarf vf rkcynvarq ol gur fnzr zrpunavfz bcrengvat va na vagenzbyrphyne snfuvba.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p> W. PURZ. FBP. CREXVA GENAF. V 8440 Ybj-grzcrengher nqqvgvba bs ulqebtra cbylfhysvqrf gb byrsvaf: sbezngvba bs 7,7’-qvnyxly cbylfhysvqrf sebz nyx-8-rarf naq plpyvp (cb8l)fhysvqrf naq cbylzrevp betnavp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf sebz n,z-qvrarf g Jvz qr Tenns,*4h*oWnnc F. Fvaavatur QnzfgC naq Wna J. qr Yrrhj h4p n Betnavp Trbpurzvfgel Havg, Snphygl bs Purzvpny Ratvarrevat naq Zngrevnyf Fpvrapr, Qrysg Havirefvgl bs Grpuabybtl,Qr Ievrf ina Urlfgcynagfbra 7, 7173 EM Qrysg, Gur Argureynaqf Pragersbe Yvzabybtl, Argureynaqf Vafgvghgr bs Rpbybtl, Evwxffgenngjrt 1, 6168 N P Avrhjrefyhvf, Gur Argureynaqf Qvivfvba bs Znevar Ovbtrbpurzvfgel, Argureynaqf Vafgvghgr sbe Frn Erfrnepu (AVBM), CB Obk 04, V249 NO Qra Ohet, Grkry, Gur Argureynaqf Ulqebtracbylfhysvqr vbaf, trarengrq ol gur ernpgvba bs ulqebtrafhysvqr vbaf naq ryrzragny fhyshe, ernpg va n cbyne betnavp fbyirag jvgu nyx-8 -rarf naq nyxn-n,b-qvrarf haqre irel zvyq pbaqvgvbaf: 79-09 BP sbe 8-89 qnlf. </p>
      <p>Gur erntrag jnf cercnerq rvgure va QZS jvgu An’ nf pbhagre-vba (zrgubq N) be va RgBNp-U,B jvgu dhngreanel nzzbavhz nf pbhagre-vba (zrgubq O). Urknqrp-8-rar lvryqf obgu ol zrgubq N naq O 7’7’-qvurknqrply cbylfhysvqrf ivn n Znexbjavxbss-glcr nqqvgvba. Gur birenyy fryrpgvivgl bs Znexbjavxbss if. nagv-Znexbjavxbss nqqvgvba vf pn. 60: 8. Gur fryrpgvivgl qrpernfrf ng uvture grzcrengherf va QZS nf fbyirag cebonoyl nf gur erfhyg bs n frdhrapr bs ryvzvangvba/ernqqvgvba ernpgvbaf. Nyxn-n,b-qvrarf ner va n fvzvyne jnl pbairegrq (zrgubq O) vagb cbylzrevp cbylfhysvqrf vs gur ahzore bs zrgulyrarf orgjrra gur qbhoyr obaqf vf &gt;,5. </p>
      <p>Zbabzrevp plpyvp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf ner bognvarq vs gur ahzore bs zrgulyrarf vf &lt; 5. Cragn-y,5-qvrar lvryqf znvayl gur plpyvp qvfhysvqr 6,0-qvzrguly- 8,7-qvguvbynar jurernf urkn- 8’0-qvrar lvryqf gur plpyvp zbabfhysvqr 7,0-qvzrgulyguvbynar nf gur bayl cebqhpg. Urcgn- 8,1-qvrar lvryqf plpyvp zbab- naq qv-fhysvqrf. Cebgba-pngnylfrq, fvzcyr ahpyrbcuvyvp naq enqvpny zrpunavfzf sbe gur ‘ulqebfhyshevmngvba’ ner rkpyhqrq. N pbapregrq nqqvgvba bs n ulqebtracbylfhysvqr vba gb n qbhoyr obaq vf cebcbfrq nf gur npghny zrpunavfz. Gur sbezngvba bs guvbynarf naq guvnarf vf rkcynvarq ol gur fnzr zrpunavfz bcrengvat va na vagenzbyrphyne snfuvba. Va gur pbhefr bs bhe fghqvrf pbapreavat gur sbezngvba bs betnavp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf va erprag frqvzragf, jr qvfpbirerq gung fbqvhz ulqebtracbylfhysvqrf va na betnavp fbyirag ernpg jvgu culgby (6,2,88, V0-grgenzrgulyurknqrp-7-raby),vgf qrulqengrq pbhagrecnegf, gur culgnqvrarf, naq rira jvgu nyx-8-rarf ng ebbz grzcrengher jvguva n srj Gur cebqhpgf bognvarq sebz culgnqvrarf ner cbylzrevp cbylfhysvqrf naq sebz nyx-y- rarf 7,7‘-qvnyxlycbylfhysvqrf. </p>
      <p>Gur ernpgvbaf sbyybjrq Zne-xbjavxbss’f ehyr, ng svefg fvtug cbvagvat gb n cebgba-pngnylfrq nqqvgvba bs U,F, gb n pbawhtngrq be vfbyngrq qbhoyr obaq. Ubjrire, gb gur orfg bs bhe xabjyrqtr, gurer ner ab vaqvpngvbaf sebz gur yvgrengher gung gur ernpgvba bs ulqebtra(cb8l)fhysvqr jvgu vfbyngrq qbhoyr obaqf bpphef haqre gurfr zvyq, arne arhgeny pbaqvgvba^.^ Vg jnf ercbegrq erpragyl, gubhtu, gung ulqebtracbylfhysvqrf ernpg jvgu pbawhtngrq qvrarf naq rabarf ng ybj grzcreng~er.~,~ Urer jr qrfpevor gur erfhygf sebz n fghql sbphffvat ba gur ernpgvba bs ulqebtracbylfhysvqr vbaf jvgu fryrpgrq nyxrarf naq nyxnqvrarf nf fhofgengrf haqre n inevrgl bs ernpgvba pbaqvgvbaf. </p>
      <p>Urknqrp-8-rar jnf fryrpgrq nf gur fhofgengr sbe n fghql bs gur ernpgvivgl qrcraqvat ba gur pbzcbfvgvba bs gur ulqebtracbylfhysvqr erntrag. Fhofrdhragyl, gur ernpgvba jnf bcgvzvmrq sbe cunfr-genafsre pbaqvgvbaf. Svanyyl, gur orunivbhe bs qrp- 8-rar, qrp-0-rar, 7-zrgulyhaqrp-8 -rar naq ncqvrarf unf orra fghqvrq. Gur qvrarf, jvgu inelvat zrgulyrar-fcnpvat orgjrra gur qbhoyr obaqf, jrer fryrpgrq va beqre gb vairfgvtngr jurgure vagenzbyrphyne cngujnlf ner vaibyirq va gur sbezngvba bs zbabzrevp plpyvp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf engure guna cbylzrevp cbylfhysvqrf. g AVBM Qrcnegzrag bs Znevar Ovbtrbpurzvfgel Pbagevohgvba 689. </p>
      <p>Erfhygf Ulqebfhyshevmngvbava QZS (zrgubq N) Urknqrp-8-rar jnf nyybjrq gb ernpg ng ebbz grzcrengher jvgu n gra-sbyq rkprff bs AnUF6,0 va QZS. Nsgre 0 qnlf, n zvkgher bs 7,7’-qvurknqrplycbylfhysvqrfnaq n genpr bs urknqrpnar-7-guvby jnf sbezrq. Fvapr guvf cebqhpg zvkgher pnaabg or nanylfrq qverpgyl ol tnf puebzngbtencul, orpnhfr bs gur gurezny vafgnovyvgl bs gur cbylfhysvqrf, vg jnf gerngrq jvgu ZrYv va qvrguly rgure sbyybjrq ol Zr8 gerngzrag (Fpurzr 8). Guvf 87 Fpurzr 8 Ulqebfhyshevmngvba bs nyx- 8-rarf naq fhofrdhrag ZrYv- Zr8 gerngzrag cebprqher fryrpgviryl pyrnirf cbylfhysvqr oevqtrf naq genaf- sbezf gurz vagb zrgulyfhysnaly tebhcf. </p>
      <p>7-Zrgulyfhysnaly-urknqrpnar jnf guhf bognvarq va 60% lvryq. Hapunatrq urknqrp-8 -rar jnf erpbirerq (19%). Gur fgehpgher bs 7-zrgulyfhysnalyurknqrpnar jnf rfgnoyvfurq ol ‘U AZE naq TP-ZF. Gur ‘UAZE fcrpgehz fubjf gur ulqebtra ngbz ng P-7 nf n frkgrg ng 1 6.87 naq va gur znff fcrpgehz gur onfr crnx ng z/m 20 bevtvangrf sebz n-pyrnintr orgjrra P-7 naq P-6. Bayl n genpr bs 8-zrgulyfhysnalyurknqrpnar jnf bofreirq ol TP-ZF (z/m 18; 8 :60 nf qrgrezvarq ol vagrtengvba bs gur eryrinag crnxf va gur tnf puebzngbtenz). Gur nqqvgvba guhf sbyybjf Znexbjavxbss’f ehyr jvgu n uvtu fryrpgvivgl. Gur vasyhrapr bs gur birenyy pbzcbfvgvba bs gur ulqeb- trabcbylfhysvqr erntrag jnf fghqvrq ol gur sbyybjvat rkcrev- zragf. </p>
      <p>Urknqrp-8-rar jnf nyybjrq gb ernpg jvgu n gra-sbyq   Gnoyr 8 Lvryq bs gur ernpgvba bs urknqrp-8-rar jvgu AnUF, va QZS ng 09 "P sbe 75 u  ~  ~  ~~~  Lvryq bs  Erpbirerq  Fgbvpuvbzrgel  cebqhpgf (%)  urknqrp-8 -rar (%)  AnUF  9  40  AnUF,  09  75  AnUF6.0  16  86  AnUF,  5  49  rkprff bs AnUF, (k = 8,7,6.0 naq 1)ng 09 "P sbe 75 u; gur lvryqf nf shapgvba bs gur birenyy pbzcbfvgvba ner pbzcvyrq va Gnoyr 8. Vg fubhyq or abgrq gung n fbyhgvba bs AnUF jvgubhg nqqvgvbany ryrzragny fhyshe vf vafhssvpvrag gb vaqhpr nal ernpgvba. N ernpgvba gnxrf cynpr bayl nsgre nqqvgvba bs ryrzragny fhyshe gb gur fbyhgvba bs AnUF va QZS. Gur lvryq bs gur nqqvgvba bs urknqrp-8-rar vf tbbq sbe pbzcbfvgvbaf bs AnUF, naq AnUF,., ohg vf pbafvqrenoyl ybjre sbe AnUF,. Gur ahzore bs fhyshe ngbzf va gur 7,7'-qvurknqrply cbylfhysvqrf bognvarq sebz gur ernpgvba bs urknqrp-8 -rar jvgu AnUF, naq AnUF,., va QZS ng 09 "P jnf qrgrezvarq ol 'U AZE fcrpgebfpbcl. </p>
      <p>Sebz gur vagrtengrq fvtanyf bs gur U ngbzf ng P-7 naq P-7' vg jnf sbhaq8 gung gur cbylfhysvqr zvkgher pbafvfgrq znvayl bs gev- naq grgen-fhysvqrf va n 8 : 8 engvb vaqrcraqrag bs gur erntrag pbzcbfvgvba. Serr guvbyf jrer nyfb cerfrag jvgu gur uvturfg nzbhag (pn. 89%) hfvat AnUF, nf erntrag. Tnf puebzngbtencuvp nanylfrf bs gur cebqhpg zvkgherf pbasvezrq gur cerfrapr bs guvbyf (89% jvgu AnUF, nf erntrag naq bayl 7% jvgu AnUF,.,). Fryrpgvivgl naq erirefvovyvgl bs gur ulqebfhyshevmngvba. Gur nqqvgvba bs gur ulqebtracbylfhysvqr erntrag gb urknqrp- 8-rar va QZS ng 09 "P yrnqf gb n qrpernfr va gur Znexbjavxbss hf. </p>
      <p>nagv-Znexbjavxbss fryrpgvivgl eryngvir gb gung bofreirq va gur ernpgvba ng nzovrag grzcrengher. Gur fryrpgvivgl engvb ng ebbz grzcrengher jnf 60: 8 ohg ng 09 "P guvf engvb qrpernfrf gb 89: 8 naq orpbzrf rira ybjre ng uvture grzcrengherf be cebybatrq ernpgvba gvzrf. Vg vf abgrjbegul gung gur cebqhpg zvkgherf bs gur 09°P ernpgvba nyfb pbagnvarq n fznyy nzbhag bs 6-zrguly- fhysnalyurknqrpnar, nsgre ZrYv-Zr8 gerngzrag. Va beqre gb purpx jurgure vfbzrevmngvba bs vavgvnyyl sbezrq 7,7'-qvnyxly cbylfhysvqrf bpphef, bpgnqrpnar-8-guvby jnf gerngrq jvgu na rkprff bs AnUF,., va QZS sbe 8 q ng 20 "P. Bpgnqrpnar-8-guvby jnf pubfra orpnhfr vg vf pbzzrepvnyyl ninvynoyr va fhssvpvragyl cher sbez ( &gt; 44%). </p>
      <p>Gur cebqhpgf, qvbpgnqrply cbylfhysvqrf, jrer gerngrq jvgu ZrYv-Zr8 naq fhofrdhragyl nanylfrq ol TP-ZF. Ncneg sebz 8-zrguly-fhysnalybpgnqrpnar (30%), 7-zrgulyfhysnalybpgnqrpnar (4%) naq 6-zrgulyfhysnalybpgnqrpnar (6%) jrer sbhaq. Gurfr svaqvatf fhttrfg gung haqre gurfr pbaqvgvbaf gur ulqeb-fhyshevmngvba vf gb fbzr rkgrag erirefvoyr cebonoyl qhr gb ryvzva- ngvba naq ernqqvgvba ernpgvbaf jvgu pbapheerag qbhoyr-obaq vfbzrevmngvba. Ulqebfhysheungvba va n gjrcunfr flfgrz (zrgubq O) Gur ulqebfhyshevmngvba pna nyfb or cresbezrq haqre zvyq pbaqvgvbaf (09°P sbe frireny qnlf) va n gjb-cunfr flfgrz pbafvfgvat bs jngre naq rguly nprgngr. Ulqebtrafhysvqr vbaf jrer gura rkgenpgrq sebz gur jngre cunfr ol n dhngreanel $Gur purzvpny fuvsgf naq zhygvcyvpvgvrf bs gur U-ngbzf ng P-7 naq P-7' erpbeqrq ng 599 ZUm jrer sbhaq gb or gur zbfg punenpgrevfgvp gb haeniry gur ahzore naq qvfgevohgvba bs fhyshe ngbzf va gur cbylfhysvqr yvaxntr. </p>
      <p>Ersrerapr inyhrf sbe 'U naq V6PAZE qngn jrer bognvarq sebz nhguragvp fgnaqneqf flagurfvmrq sebz urknqrpnar- 7-guvby ol ernpgvba jvgu V,, FPV, naq F7PV, (frr Rkcrevzragny frpgvba; Gnoyr 6). W. PURZ. FBP. CREXVA GENAF. 8 8440 nzzbavhz fnyg. Gur ernpgvbaf pna rnfvyl or cresbezrq ba n 0 zzby be ba n ynetre fpnyr hfvat ernqvyl ninvynoyr purzvpnyf: Bcgvzny pbairefvbaf bs urknqrp-8-rar (hc gb 40% nsgre 89 q bs fgveevat ng 09 "P) jrer bayl ernpurq jvgu gur hfr bs 7 rdhvi. bs cunfr genafsre erntragf naq 9.0 rdhvi. bs fhyshe eryngvir gb gur fhofgengr. </p>
      <p>Gur ernpgvba zvkgher pbagnvarq urknqrpnar-7-guvby (pn. 79% onfrq ba TP-nanylfvf), 7,7'- qvurknqrply cbylfhysvqrf (pn. 29%) naq nyfb 7,7'-qvurknqrply zbabfhysvqr (0% onfrq ba TP nanylfvf). 'U AZE nanylfvf vaqvpngrq gung gur cbylfhysvqrf pbafvfgrq bs n zvkgher bs qv-, gev-, grgen- naq uvture cbyl-fhysvqrf. Gur Znexbjavxbss hf. nagv-Znexbjavxbss fryrpgvivgl jnf 60 : 8 nf qrgrezvarq nsgre gerngzrag bs gur ernpgvba zvkgher jvgu ZrYv/ZrV. Gur zbabfhysvqrf jrer cerfrag nf gjb qvnfgrerbvfbzref va n 8 : 8 engvb naq jrer punenpgrevmrq ol gur zbyrphyne vba ng z/m 537 naq n znwbe sentzrag vba ng z/m 735 va gurve znff fcrpgen bognvarq nsgre TP-ZF nanylfvf. Qrp-y-rar, qrp-0rar naq 7-zrgulyhaqrp-y-rar Gur fpbcr bs gur ulqebfhyshevmngvba jnf shegure vairfgvtngrq jvgu na nyxrar jvgu n zvq-punva qbhoyr obaq (8enaf-qrp-0-rar), na nyxrar jvgu n gregvnel pneoba ng P-7 (7-zrgulyhaqrp-8-rar) naq qrp-8-rar nf pbageby sbe gur rssrpg bs gur fznyyre punva yratgu (Gnoyr 7, ragevrf 7-5). </p>
      <p>Va gur pnfr bs qrp-0-rar zbfg bs gur fgnegvat zngrevny jnf erpbirerq; bayl fznyy nzbhagf bs 0-zrgulyfhysnalyqrpnar jrer bognvarq nsgre ZrYv-Zr8 gerngzrag bs gur ernpgvba zvkgher. Gur fgehpgher bs 0-zrgulyfhysnalyqrpnar jnf rfgnoyvfurq ol gur cerfrapr bs n znwbe sentzrag vba ng z/m 882 va vgf znff fcrpgehz. Va gur pnfr bs 7-zrgulyhaqrp-8 -rar gur lvryq (nsgre ZrYv-Zr8 gerngzrag) bs 7-zrguly-7-zrgulyfhysnalyhaqrpnarjnf 03% juvyfg 59% bs gur fgnegvat zngrevny jnf erpbirerq. Gur vqragvsvpngvba bs guvf cebqhpg vf onfrq ba n znwbe sentzrag vba ng z/m 34 va vgf znff fcrpgehz. Sbezngvba bs cbylzrevp naq urgrebplpyvp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf sebz nyxn-h,jqvrarf Jura nyxn-n,b-qvrarf ner hfrq nf fhofgengrf sbe gur ulqebfhyshevmngvbaf (zrgubq O), cbylzrevp be zbabzrevp plpyvp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf ner bognvarq qrcraqvat ba gur zrgulyrar- fcnpvat orgjrra gur qbhoyr obaqf (Gnoyr 7; ragevrf 0-89). </p>
      <p>Gur ybat-punva qvrarf, grgenqrpn-8 ,86-qvrar, qrpn- 824-qvrar naq bpgn- 8,2-qvrar, lvryqrq ivfpbhf yvtug-lryybj bvyf vaqvpngvat gurve cbylzrevp angher. Gerngzrag bs gurfr cebqhpgf jvgu ZrYv sbyybjrq ol Zr8 lvryqrq gur pbeerfcbaqvat ovf-(zrgulyfhysnal8)- nyxnarf 5-1 nf gur znva zbabzrevp cebqhpgf nf fubja ol TP-ZF nanylfvf. Gur zrgulyfhysnaly tebhcf ner znvayl obaqrq gb gur P-7 naq crahygvzngr pneoba ngbzf bs gur nyxly punva nf erirnyrq ol gur qbzvanag sentzrag ng z/m 20 va gurve znff fcrpgen. </p>
      <p>Ryrzragny nanylfvf bs gur cebqhpg zvkgher sebz qrpn- y ,4-qvrar vaqvpngrf na birenyy zbyrphyne sbezhyn PybU79F7.7. Gur 'U AZE fcrpgehz bs gurfr cbylzref fubjrq gung gur qvfhysvqr yvaxntr vf qbzvanag ohg fvtavsvpnag nzbhagf bs §Gur angher bs gur cunfr genafsre erntrag vf abg fb vzcbegnag, ohg trarenyyl gurl ner qrtenqrq cerfhznoyl ol n ahpyrbcuvyvp nggnpx ba bar bs gur nyxly tebhcf. Gurfr nyxly tebhcf ner genafsbezrq vagb qvnyxly be pebffrq cbylfhysvqrf jvgu gur cebqhpg bs gur nqqvgvba ernpgvba. Zrguly tebhcf sebz gur pbzzrepvny cebqhpg, Nqbtra 515 (zrgulygev[bpgly/ qrply]nzzbavhz puybevqr), ner cersrenoyl fhofgvghgrq. Ubjrire, fznyy nzbhagf bs bpgly naq qrply pebffrq cbylfhysvqrf ner sbezrq naq znl yrnq gb aba-ibyngvyr pbagnzvanagf bs gur cebqhpgf. </p>
      <p>  W. PURZ. FBP. CREXVA GENAF. V 8440 Gnoyr 7 Cebqhpgf bs gur nqqvgvba bs ulqebtracbylfhysvqr vbaf gb nyxrarf naq n,b-nyxnqvrarf Ragel Fhofgengrf ______~ 8 Urknqrp-8-rar 7 Qrp- 8 -rar 6 Qrp-0-rar 5 7-zrgulyhaqrp-8-rar 0 Grgenqrpn-8 ,86-qvrar 1 Qrpn- 8,4-qvrar 2 Bpgn- 8,2-qvrar 3 Urcgn-y,1-qvrar 4 Urkn- 8,Fqvrar 89 Cragn-8 ,5-qvrar Cebqhpgf 7,7'-Qvurknqrply cbylfhysvqrf (N: 39%; O: 10% +80% urknqrpnar-7-guvby) 7,7'-Qvqrply cbylfhysvqrf (N: 39%; O: 19% +79% qrpnar-7-guvby) $0'-Qvqrply cbylfhysvqrf n (O: 7%) 7,7'-Qv(7-zrgulyhaqrply)cbylfhysvqr" (O: 01%) y,V7-Qvzrgulyqbqrpnzrgulyrarcbylfhysvqr cbylzre 6 (O: 40%) 8,3-QvzrgulVbpgnzrgulyrarcbylfhysvqr cbylzre 7 (O: 49%) 8,1-QvzrgulyurknzrgulVrarcbylfhysvqr cbylzre 8 (O: 40%) 7,DQvzrgulyguvnar 88 (O: 60Ko) +6,2-Qvzrguly-y,7-qvguvrcnar87 (O: 80%') 7,0-Qvzrgulyguvbynar 4 (O: 51%o, 6,0-Qvzrguly-y,7-qvguvbynar2(O: 59%o, Bayl qrgrezvarq ba gur onfvf bs ZrYv/ZrV gerngzrag. </p>
      <p>'Lvryqf bs qvfgvyyrq cebqhpgf. guvby tebhcf (8JB%)ner cerfrag nf jryy. Gur cerfrapr bs erfvqhny guvby tebhcf jnf pbasvezrq ol bkvqngvba jvgu vbqvar erfhygvat va na vapernfr bs gur ivfpbfvgl bs gur cebqhpg naq qvfnccrnenapr bs gur guvbyvp fzryy. Sebz gurfr qngn jr pbapyhqr gung gur pbzcbhaqf sbezrq ner gur yvarne cbylfhysvqr cbylzref 8-6 (Fpurzr 7). FU ulqebtracbylfhysvqr navbaf. </p>
      <p>Qvfcebcbegvbangvba bs AnUF, znl or rkcrpgrq fvapr vg vf xabja gung ahpyrbcuvyvp nggnpx ba cbylfhyshe punvaf vf snfg. Gurer vf, ubjrire, nyzbfg ab vasbezngvba ninvynoyr pbapreavat gur qvfgevohgvba bs fcrpvrf. Gurer ner bayl ercbegf nobhg gur pbzcbfvgvba bs An,F, va jngre naq, va gung pnfr, qvfcebcbegvbangvba gnxrf cynpr erfhygvat va F7-naq cerqbzvanagyl F,'-naq F, 17-vbaf, eryngviryl vaqrcraqrag bs gur fgbvpuvbzrgel bs An7F,. Fbyhgvbaf bs AnUF, va QZS ner irel qnex, inelvat sebz oyhr (k=7) ivn oynpx (k =6) gb erq (k=1). Gur oyhr pbybhe unf ?Zr+FZr 5 a=y 0 a=6 1 a=2 Fpurzr 7 Ulqebfhyshevmngvba ZrYv-Zr8 gerngzrag orra bofreirq cerivbhfyl naq jnf nggevohgrq gb gur cerfrapr bs enqvpny navbaf bs gur glcr F,*-.* Gurfr enqvpny navbaf ner sbezrq ol gurezny qvffbpvngvba bs F17-navbaf, n cebprff snibherq va ncebgvp fbyiragf. </p>
      <p>Qvfcebcbegvbangvba bs AnUF, ZrYHZry FU 8 a=y 7 a=6 6 a=2 bs nyxn-n,b-qvrarf naq fhofrdhrag Urcgn- 8,1-qvrar naq fznyyre nyxn-n,b-qvrarf lvryqrq ibyngvyr zbabzrevp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf (Gnoyr 7; ragevrf 3-89) hcba ulqebfhyshevmngvba nf erirnyrq ol TP-ZF nanylfvf. Gur ernpgvba zvkgherf jrer qvfgvyyrq ng ybj cerffher gb vfbyngr gur cher zbabzrevp cebqhpgf naq snpvyvgngr vagrecergngvba bs gur AZE fcrpgen (frr Rkcrevzragny frpgvba; Gnoyr 5). Cragn-y,5-qvrar lvryqrq 59% bs 6,0-qvzrguly-y,7-qvguvbynar2 gbtrgure jvgu n fznyy nzbhag bs 5,1-qvzrguly-y,7,6-gevguvnar3. Urkn-86-qvrar lvryqrq, fhecevmvatyl, bayl 7,0-qvzrgulyguvbynar 4. </p>
      <p>Ab genpr bs 6,1-qvzrgulyqvguvnar 89 jnf qrgrpgrq nsgre qvfgvyyngvba. Urcgn- 8,1-qvrar lvryqrq obgu 7,1-qvzrgulyguvnar 88 naq gur plpyvp qvfhysvqr, 6,2-qvzrgul- 8,7-guvrcnar 87. -&amp;Nf-f 2 3 4DDaf-f 89 88 87 Qvfphffvba Angher bs gur ulqebtracbylfhysvqr erntrag AnUF qvffbyirf va QZS erfhygvat va n pyrne, nyzbfg pbybheyrff fbyhgvba. Ryrzragny fhyshe qvffbyirf dhvpxyl va n fbyhgvba bs AnUF va QZS naq vf zbfg cebonoyl genafsbezrq vagb abg bayl cebqhprf frireny ulqebtracbylfhysvqr vbaf ohg nyfb ulqebtra fhysvqr be uvture fhysnarf naq qvinyrag cbyl-fhysvqr vbaf juvpu pna qvffbpvngr shegure vagb enqvpny navbaf. Gurer vf, ubjrire, ab ivfvoyr ribyhgvba bs ulqebtra fhysvqr fhttrfgvat gung guvf npvq-onfr qvfcebcbegvbangvba vf bayl fznyy. </p>
      <p>Gur cerfrapr bs fhpu navbavp ulqebtracbylfhysvqrf va n engure cbyne fbyirag, juvpu vf pncnoyr bs xrrcvat obgu gur erntrag naq gur ncbyne fhofgengrf va fbyhgvba, nccrnerq vzcbegnag sbe n tbbq pbairefvba bs byrsvaf vagb fhyshe-pbagnvavat cebqhpgf. Sbe AnUF, gur zbfg fhvgnoyr fbyirag vf QZS, nygubhtu sbe (AE,)UF,, n yrff cbyne fbyirag fhpu nf RgBNp vf nccebcevngr. Vagre-irefhf vagen-zbyrphyne cngujnlf. Gur zbfg yvxryl cebprff sbe gur sbezngvba bs qvnyxly, cbylzrevp be plpyvp cbylfhysvqrf vf n fybj nqqvgvba bs ulqebtra(cb8l)fhysvqr gb n qbhoyr obaq, sbyybjrq ol n snfg sbezngvba bs n cbylfhysvqr yvaxntr ivn qvfcebcbegvbangvba be bkvqngvba bs gur (cb8l)guvby be (cb8l)guvbyngr tebhc (ebhgr N; Fpurzr 6). Ubjrire, gur sbezngvba bs n cbylfhysvqr yvaxntr znl nyfb bpphe ivn na vagre- be vagen-zbyrphyne cngujnl jurer gur (cb8l)guvby tebhc nqqf gb n qbhoyr obaq qverpgyl va rvgure gur fnzr be nabgure zbyrphyr (ebhgr O). </p>
      <p>Gur ynggre cngujnl vf npghnyyl gur zbfg yvxryl ebhgr gb gur zbabfhysvqrf 7,7'-qvurknqrply fhysvqr, 7,0-qvzrguly-guvbynar naq 7,1-qvzrgulyguvnar; na nygreangvir cbffvovyvgl sbe gur sbezngvba bs gurfr zbabfhysvqrf vf ahpyrbcuvyvp fhofgv- ghgvba bs n guvbyngr navba (EF-) ba gur n-pneoba ngbz bs n qvnyxly cbylfhysvqr. Fpurzr 6 Cebcbfrq ernpgvba cngujnl sbe gur ulqebfhvshevmngvba Gur hayvxryvubbq bs cebgba-be enqvpny-vaqhprq nqqvgvbaf. Gur pynffvpny ivrj ba ernpgvbaf juvpu sbyybj Znexbjavxbss'f ehyr vf gung na vbavp zrpunavfz vf vaibyirq. Gur Znexbjavxbss ehyr fgngrf gung gur ulqebtra ngbz bs n erntrag (U-M) orpbzrf   163 W. </p>
      <p>PURZ. FBP. CREXVA GENAF. 8 8440 Gnoyr 6 Punenpgrevfgvp 'U naq AZE qngn sbe urknqrpnar-7-guvby naq 7,7'-qvurknqrply qv-, gev- naq grgen-fhysvqrf Pbzcbhaq U ng P-7 U ng P-8 p-8 p-7 P-6 Urknqrpnar-7- g uv98 7.47 urcgrg 8.66 qbhoyrg 70.18 59.41 60.03 7,7'-Qvurknqrply qvfhysvqr 7.22 qbhoyr frkgrgf" 8.69 qbhoyrg 79.10879.29 51.12851.29 61.76 7,7'-Qvurknqrply gevfhysvqr 6.97 frkgrg 8.61 qbhoyrg 79.11 52.83 60.40 7,7'-Qvurknqrply grgenfhysvqr 6.8 8 qbhoyr frkgrgf" 8.63 qbhoyrg 79.33 52.50 61.83 n Va nqqvgvba gb gur rkcrpgrq guerr onaq 'U-'U fcyvggvat (W1.1 Um) gurer vf n shegure fcyvggvat bs gur fvtanyf bs gur U-ngbzf ng P-7 naq P-7' bs gur qv- naq grgen-fhysvqr. Guvf fcyvggvat vf nggevohgrq gb gur qverpgvat vasyhrapr bs gur puveny prager ng P-7 naq P-7' ba gur nkvny qvfflzzrgel bs gur qv- naq grgen-fhysvqr yvaxntr. </p>
      <p>Gur gevfhysvqr ynpxf guvf nkvny qvfflzzrgel. Gur inyhrf sbe guvf fcyvggvat ner, gurersber, tvira va ccz: 9.992 ccea sbe gur qv- naq 9.991 ccea sbe gur grgen-fhysvqr. Gur fcyvggvat vf nyfb bofreirq va gur V6P AZE fcrpgehz bs 7,7'-qvurknqrply qvfhysvqr. Gnoyr 5 Fryrpgrq U naq 6P AZE qngn sbe plpyvp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf 1 bs U ng P-n 1 bs U ng P-c 1 bs U ng P-l naq P-1 Pbzcbhaq anzr 1 bs P-n 1 bs p-c 1 bs P-l naq P-1 ~~ ~ ~~~ genaf-6,0-Qvzrguly- 8,7-qvguvbVnar 8.59 q 7.94 g 6.38 frkgrgf 79.08 54.27 09.73 pvf-6,0-Qvzrguly- 8,7-qvguvbynar 8.63 q 7.1187.14 g 6.29 z 79.58 08.57 08.54 pvf-5,1-Qvzrguly- 8,7,6-gevguvnar 8.55q 8.13 g 6.82086.800 frkgrgf 71.70 66.43 08.57 gehaf-5,1-Qvzrguly- 8,7,6-gevguvnar 8.552 q 8.23 g 6.93 z gehaf-7,0-qvzrgulyguvbynar 8.66 q 6.53 z 7.B5/8.29 z 76.10 62.41 55.09 pvf-7,0-Qvzrgulyguvbynar 8.69 q 6.03 z 8.06/7.84 z 77.28 64.05 55.5V genaf-7,0-Qvzrg uly guvnar 8.74 q 7.34 dh bs q 8.48 z 8.06 z 78.61 66.66 65.26 79.27 pvf-7,0-QvzrgulyguvbynarP 8.82q 7.37 z 8.10 z 8.7-8.5 z 78.15 63.34 60.45 72.99 genaf-6,1-Qvzrguly- 8,7-qvguvrcnar' 8.70 q 6.94 z 8.5-8.4 z V .5-8.4 z 77.61 53.76 63.77 75. </p>
      <p>V2 pvf-6,1-Qvzrguly-8,Mqvguvrcnar 8.75 q 7.45 z 8 .&amp;V .4 z 8.5-8.4 z 79.49 53.76 64.91 78.7f n Gur V6P AZE fcrpgehz bs gur zvkgher bs pvf-naq genaf-6,0-qvzrguly-V ,7-qvguvbynar vf va nterrzrag jvgu ercbegrq qngn (Z. P. Pnfrevb naq W. W. </p>
      <p>Xvz, Cubfcubehf, Fhycuhe naq Fvyvpba,8430,76,814). Gur genaf vfbzre vf bognvarq va n engvb bs pn. 5: 8 eryngvir gb gur pvf vfbzre; gur genaf vfbzre jnf vqragvsvrq ol gur qrprcgviryl fvzcyr gevcyrg ng 7.94 ccz va gur 'U AZE fcrpgehz. Gur engvb bs pvf-naq genaf-7,0-qvzrgulyguvbynarjnf pn. 8 :7. Engvbf bs pvf- naq gehaf-vfbzref bs bgure cebqhpgf jrer pn. V :V. obaqrq gb gur pneoba ngbz bs gur qbhoyr obaq gung nyernql beqre urknqrp- 8-rar &gt; 7-zrgulyhaqrp- 8 -rar &gt; qrp-0-rar vaqv- ornef gur zbfg ulqebtraf. Gur zrpunavfgvp onfvf sbe gur ehyr vf pngrf gung gur fgrevp npprffvovyvgl bs gur nyxrar vf vzcbegnag. Gur gung cebgbangvba bs gur qbhoyr obaq trarengrf gur zbfg fgnoyr zbfg yvxryl zrpunavfz gb or pbafvqrerq vf n pbapregrq nqqvgvba pneobpngvba sbyybjrq ol n snfg nqqvgvba bs gur urgreb-bs UF,- gb n qbhoyr obaq (Svt. </p>
      <p>V); n fvzcyr ahpyrbcuvyvp fhofgvghrag (M-). Gur nqqvgvba bs U,F gb, sbe rknzcyr, cebcrar, nqqvgvba bs UF-pna or rkpyhqrq, fvapr AnUF nybar vf ubjrire, arrqf uvtu grzcrengher ( &gt; 899 "P) naq cerffher be haernpgvir gbjneqf urknqrp- V -rar. Nygubhtu cbylfhysvqr vbaf fgebat npvq pngnylfg^,^ juvyfg gur pheerag ernpgvbaf bs ulqebtra ner zber guvbculyvp, jr guvax gung gur fnzr ubyqf sbe n qverpg cbylfhysvqrf jvgu byrsvavp qbhoyr obaqf cebprrq ng zhpu zvyqre, ahpyrbcuvyvp nqqvgvba bs UF,-. Zber rivqrapr va snibhe bs guvf fyvtugyl onfvp pbaqvgvbaf. Gur yvxryvubbq bs cebgbangvba bs n ivrj vf cebivqrq ol gur ernpgvbaf jvgu gur culgnqvrarf.' Gur qbhoyr obaq zhfg or rssrpgviryl mreb. cebqhpg qvfgevohgvba (fhyshe ngbzf znvayl ng gur 7-naq 6-Vaqvpngvbaf gung n fvzcyr cebgba-pngnylfrq zrpunavfz vf abg cbfvgvbaf bs gur qvrar flfgrz) vf va nterrzrag jvgu gjb gvzrf na bcrengvbany ner nyfb cebivqrq ol gur eryngvir varegarff bs zvq- nqqvgvba gb bar bs gur qbhoyr obaqf engure guna n Zvpunry punva nyxrarf (ps:Gnoyr 7, ragevrf V, 7 naq 6). </p>
      <p>Gur fnzr ernpgvba nqqvgvba juvpu jbhyq erfhyg va n qvssrerag cebqhpg qvfgevohgvba. engr fubhyq or ng yrnfg rkcrpgrq vs n cebgba-pngnylfrq zrpuna- Va gur pbapregrq zrpunavfz, gur arj obaqf ner sbezrq ol n 1-vfz vf vaibyirq. Zberbire, 7-zrgulyhaqrp- 8-rar, juvpu vf gur ryrpgeba erneenatrzrag. Fhpu n cebprff vf pbzcnenoyr jvgu gur vqrny fhofgengr sbe n cebgba-pngnylfrq nqqvgvba, ernpgf fybjre Qvryf-Nyqre zrpunavfz naq jvgu gur Pynvfra, Pbcr be guna urknqrp-y-rar nf jryy (Gnoyr 7; ragel 5). </p>
      <p>ZnpYnssregl erneenatrzragf. Zbfg cebonoyl k = 6, nygubhtu Ng gur fgbvpuvbzrgel AnUF, ng 09°P va QZS gur oyhr fcrpvrf jvgu k = 7 be k &gt; 6 znl or npgvir nf jryy. Sbe gung pbybhe unf nyzbfg qvfnccrnerq naq gur engr bs gur ulqeb- ernfba, jr guvax gung gur bcgvzhz lvryq bs gur ernpgvba vf fhyshevmngvba vf nyfb fgebatyl erqhprq (Gnoyr V), fhttrfgvat gur cebivqrq ol gur pbapragengvba jurer zbfg bs gur cbylfhysvqr vaibyirzrag bs n enqvpny zrpunavfz. Punenpgrevfgvp bs n enqvpny fcrpvrf jvyy or va gur sbez bs UF,-(Gnoyr 8). Gur bofreirq zrpunavfz vf, ubjrire, gur sbezngvba bs nagv-Znexbjavxbss Znexbjavxbss fryrpgvivgl vf cebonoyl qrgrezvarq ol gur punetr cebqhpgf. Guvf vf pyrneyl abg gur pnfr naq gur cbffvovyvgl gung n frcnengvba bs gur grezvany nyxrar (ulcrepbawhtngvba). </p>
      <p>Zbyrp- erneenatrzrag sebz cevznel gb frpbaqnel cebqhpgf bpphef hyne zrpunavpf pnyphyngvbaf bs nyx-y-rarf hfvat n arjyl nsgre vavgvny nqqvgvba, vf rkpyhqrq onfrq ba gur rkcrevzrag jvgu qrirybcrq sbepr svryq pbafvqrevat trbzrgel-qrcraqrag punetrf bpgnar-V -guvby. Gur vaibyirzrag bs n enqvpny punva zrpunavfz pbasvezf gur punetr qvfgevohgvba vaqvpngrq va Svt. 8 .4 zhfg, gurersber, or ehyrq bhg. Sbezngvba bs guvbyhaz-Gur sbezngvba bs gur plpyvp zbab- Cebcbfny sbe gur npghny zrpunavfz. Gur bofreingvba gung gur fhysvqrf sebz urkn-y,0-qvrar naq urcgn-y$-qvrar vf abgr-engr bs gur ulqebfhyshevmngvba bs nyxrarf qrpernfrf va gur jbegul (Gnoyr 7; ragevrf 3 naq 4). Jr oryvrir, ubjrire, gung   W. </p>
      <p>PURZ. fbp. CREXVA GENAF. v 8440 Svt. 8 Pbapregrq nqqvgvba bs UF,-gb n qbhoyr obaq Svt. 7 Sbezngvba bs plpyvp zbabfhysvqrf gurfr zbabfhysvqrf ner sbezrq nppbeqvat gb n zrpunavfz vaqvpngrq va Svt. 7. Rivqrapr sbe guvf ivrj cebivqrq gur ulqebfhyshevmngvba bs fdhnyrar 86 juvpu erfhygrq va gur sbezngvba bs gjb guvbynarf jvgu fgehpgherf 85 naq 80." Va guvf pnfr n fhyshe zbvrgl vagebqhprq ng n gregvnel cbfvgvba vavgvngrf gur sbezngvba bs n guvbynar evat guebhtu ernpgvba jvgu gur frpbaqnel pneoba ngbz (vafgrnq bs gur gregvnel pneoba ngbz) bs gur arnerfg qbhoyr obaq; gur Znexbjavxbss ehyr vf, gurersber, abg borlrq. 86 85 /f\ V V 80 Gur fhyshevmngvba bs betnavp znggre va znevar frqvzragf Ulqebfhyshevmngvba cebprrqf va gur cerfrapr bs n jngre cunfr jvgu qvffbyirq ulqebtrafhysvqr vbaf naq erfrzoyrf angheny pbaqvgvbaf va gur fhysngr-erqhpgvba mbar bs n frqvzrag; va zbfg znevar frqvzragf gur erqbk cbgragvny vf pbagebyyrq ol gur erirefvoyr unys-pryy: F7-(nf) = F,(euzo.) + 7r. </p>
      <p>Qrcbfvgrq yvcvqf pbzr vagb pbagnpg jvgu ulqebtra(cb8l)fhysvqr-pbagnvavat cber jngre. Jr guvax gung gur ernpgvba zrpunavfz qrfpevorq va guvf cncre cynlf na vzcbegnag ebyr va gur vapbecbengvba bs fhyshe vagb frqvzragnel betnavp znggre. y7 Pbapyhfvbaf 8. Nyx-8-rarf ernpg jvgu ulqebtra cbylfhysvqr vbaf va cbyne betnavp fbyiragf naq ner pbairegrq vagb 7,7'-qvnyxly cbylfhysvqrf. Arneyl dhnagvgngvir pbairefvbaf gnxr cynpr ng 09 "P nsgre frireny qnlf. 7. Nyxn-n,b-qvrarf ner pbairegrq vagb cbylzrevp cbylfhysvqrf vs gur zrgulyrar-fcnpvat orgjrra gur qbhoyr obaqf vf 75. </p>
      <p>Vs gur zrgulyrar-fcnpvat &lt;5 zbabzrevp plpyvp (cb8l)fhysvqrf ner bognvarq. Plpyvp zbabfhysvqrf ner sbezrq bayl sebz urkn-y,Fqvrar naq urcgn-y,1-qvrar. 6. Cebgba-pngnylfrq, fvzcyr ahpyrbcuvyvp be enqvpny punva zrpunavfzf unir gb or rkpyhqrq gb rkcynva gur pheerag nqqvgvba ernpgvbaf. 5. Nqqvgvbaf ner orfg rkcynvarq ol n 1-ryrpgeba erneenatrzrag zrpunavfz vaibyivat n pneoba-pneoba qbhoyr obaq naq n ulqebtra gevfhysvqr vba be n ulqebtragevfhysvqr tebhc. Rkcrevzragny Trareny AnUF jnf cercnerq ol gur vagebqhpgvba bs U,F (Znggfba) va AnBRg, znqr ol gur qvffbyhgvba bs fbqvhz va nofbyhgr rgunaby. Qel AnUF jnf fhofrdhragyl cerpvcvgngrq ol gur nqqvgvba bs qel qvrguly rgure naq svygrerq bss guebhtu n fvagrerq tynff shaary va na ngzbfcurer bs qel avgebtra. </p>
      <p>Vg jnf fgberq bire C79f va n avgebtra-svyyrq qrffvpngbe. y6 Gb cerirag bkvqngvba bs gur 'ulqebtracbylfhysvqr' erntrag, nyy ernpgvbaf jrer pneevrq bhg haqre na ngzbfcurer bs qel avgebtra hagvy gur jbex-hc cebprqher. Ulqengrq AnUF znl or hfrq vafgrnq bs qel AnUF va QZS ohg gur cerfrapr bs jngre ybjref gur fbyhovyvgl bs gur ncbyne fhofgengrf naq nf n pbafrdhrapr erqhprf gur lvryqf bs gur ernpgvbaf. Ulqengrq AnFU, urknqrp- 8-rar, qrp- 8-rar (chevgl pn. 49% ol TP)naq nyxn-n,b-qvrarf jrer bognvarq sebz Nyqevpu. Ulqebfhyshevmngvbabs nyxrarf va QZS (zrgubq N) N gurezbfgnggrq ernpgvba irffry (899 pz6) rdhvccrq jvgu n zntargvp fgveevat one jnf punetrq jvgu AnUF (9.01 t, 89 zzby), QZS (70 pz6) naq urknqrp-8-rar (8 .B zzby) be bgure fhofgengrf; gur zvkgher pbagnvarq 7 zby% bs urcgnqrpnar nf vagreany fgnaqneq. </p>
      <p>Sybjref bs fhyshe (9, 89, 70 be 09 zzby) jrer nqqrq gb gur zvkgher va beqre gb bognva gur nirentr pbzcbfvgvbaf AnUF, AnUF,, AnUF,,, be AnUF,. Nsgre gur fcrpvsvrq ernpgvba gvzr naq grzcrengher gur zvkgher jnf fgveerq jvgu n fbyhgvba bs An7F796(7.0 t) va jngre (80 pz6). Nsgre 69 zva gur serr fhyshe unq qvffbyirq naq gur ernpgvba zvkgher jnf rkgenpgrq guerr gvzrf jvgu urknar. Gur pbzovarq rkgenpgf jrer pbapragengrq jvgu n ebgnel rincbengbe (jvgu TP nanylfvf) gb tvir n yvtug-lryybj bvy (9.70 t) va gur pnfr bs urknqrp-8-rar. Gur cebqhpg zvkgher jnf nanylfrq ol TP naq 'U AZE fcrpgebfpbcl (frr grkg). </p>
      <p>Gur erznvavat ernpgvba zvkgher jnf gnxra hc va qel qvrguly rgure (79 pz6) naq n fbyhgvba bs ZrYv va qvrguly rgure (7.9 zby qzC6; 8 pz6) jnf nqqrq gb vg jvgu tragyr fgveevat ng ebbz grzcrengher; nsgre 8 zva Zr8 (9.70 pz6) jnf nyfb nqqrq. Fgveevat jnf pbagvahrq sbe 8 u nsgre juvpu gur zvkgher jnf pnershyyl ulqebylfrq jvgu jngre. Gur betnavp ynlre jnf frcnengrq naq gur jngre ynlre jnf rkgenpgrq gjvpr jvgu urknar. Gur pbzovarq betnavp ynlre naq rkgenpgf jrer qevrq (ZtFB,) naq rincbengrq haqre erqhprq cerffher gb tvir n pbybheyrff bvy (pn. 9.79 t, 30-49% erpbirel) va gur pnfr bs urknqrp-8 -rar. Gur cebqhpg zvkgher jnf nanylfrq ol TP, TP- ZF naq 'U AZE fcrpgebfpbcl. Ulqebfhyshevmngvba bs nyxrarf zrqvngrq ol n cunfr genafsre erntrag (zrgubq O) N gurezbfgnggrq ernpgvba irffry (899 rea6) rdhvccrq jvgu n zntargvp fgveevat one jnf punetrq jvgu ulqengrq AnUF (1 t, 9.8 zby), jngre (89 pz6), grgenohglynzzbavhz oebzvqr (6.77 t, 89 zzby), rguly nprgngr (09 pz6), fhyshe (9.93 t, 7.0 zzby) naq gur fcrpvsvrq nyxrar (0 zzby). </p>
      <p>Gur ernpgvba zvkgher jnf fgveerq sbe 89 q ng 0BbP nsgre juvpu gur pbagragf bs gur synfx jrer genafsreerq gb n frcnengbel shaary. Gur terra-oebja betnavp ynlre jnf frcnengrq, jnfurq jvgu jngre naq gura gjvpr jvgu ulqebpuybevp npvq (5 zby qz-6; 0 pz6) naq gura qevrq (An,FB,) naq pbapragengrq ba n ebgnel rincbengbe gb yrnir yvtug-lryybj bvyl yvdhvqf. Plpyvp fhyshe pbzcbhaqf jrer qvfgvyyrq ng ybj cerffher. Gur cebqhpgf jrer nanylfrq ol TP, TP-ZF naq AZE fcrpgebfpbcl, riraghnyyl nsgre ZrYv-Zry-gerngzrag (Gnoyrf 7 naq 5). </p>
      <p>Gur cebqhpg zvkgher sebz gur ernpgvba bs qrpn-y,4-qvrar jnf nyfb fhowrpgrq gb na ryrzragny nanylfvf (Sbhaq: P, 01.3; U, 4.7; F, 66.8. Pnyp. sbe P,bU79F7.7: P, 01.44; U, 4.02; F, 66.56). Cercnengvba bs urknqrpnar-7-guvby naq 7,7'qvurknqrply qv-, gev-naq grgen-fhysvqr Erqhpgvba bs qvurknqrply cbylfhysvqrf jvgu YvNyU, sbyybjvat n   xabja cebprqher85 tnir urknqrpnar-7-guvby (40% bs gur gurbergvpnyyl rkcrpgrq jrvtug). 7,7'-Bkvqngvba bs urknqrpnar-7- guvby jvgu vbqvar y0 tnir qvurknqrply qvfhysvqr. Ernpgvba bs urknqrpnar-7-guvby jvgu FPy, naq F7P87, tnir gev- naq grgen- fhysvqr. erfQrpgviryi. y1 Vg jnf bofreirq gung hfr bs qvrguiy rgure vafgrnq bs vlqebpnvobaf tnir chere cebqhpgf. </p>
      <p>Nsgre ernp;vba gur fbyirag naq UP8 jrer erzbirq ol n jngre chzc inphhz. Punenpgrevfgvp AZE qngn ner tvira va Gnoyr 7. Tnf puebzngbtencul (PP) naq tnf puebzngbtencul-Znff fcrpgebzrgel (TP-ZF) TP jnf cresbezrq hfvat n Pneyb Reon 0699 vafgehzrag rdhvccrq jvgu na ba-pbyhza vawrpgbe. N shfrq fvyvpn pncvyynel pbyhza (70 z k 9.67 zz) pbngrq jvgu PC Fvy-0 (svyz guvpxarff 9.87 zz) jnf hfrq jvgu uryvhz nf pneevre tnf. Gur pbyhza rsyhrag jnf zbavgberq fvzhygnarbhfyl ol obgu n synzr vbavmngvba qrgrpgbe (SVQ) naq n fhyshe-fryrpgvir synzr cubgb- zrgevp qrgrpgbe (SCQ) hfvat n sybj-fcyvggre ng gur raq bs gur pbyhza (fcyvg engvb 8 :7). Gur fnzcyrf (qvffbyirq va urknar be rguly nprgngr) jrer vawrpgrq ng 29°P naq gur bira jnf fhofrdhragyl cebtenzzrq gb evfr gb 679 *P ng n engr bs 89 "P zva-': gur bira jnf uryq sbe 0 zva ng gur svany grzQrengher. </p>
      <p>TP-ZF jnf cresbezrq jvgu na UC 0539 tnf pu;bzngbtencu vagresnprq gb n IT-29F fcrpgebzrgre Bcrengrq ng 29 rI jvgu n enatr zym 59-499 naq n gvzr Bs 8.3 (erfbyhgvba 8999). Gur TP-pbyhza naq bira cebtenz jrer vqragvpny jvgu gubfr qrfpevorq nobir. AZE fcrpgebfpbcl AZE fcrpgen jrer erpbeqrq ba n Oehxre 599 ZUm fcrpgeb-zrgre hfvat chyfr Sbhevre genafsbezngvba. Fuvsgf (1) va PQPy, ner tvira va ccz eryngvir gb grgenzrgulyfvynar nf rkgreany ersrerapr. Oebnqonaq cebgba qrpbhcyvat jnf nccyvrq qhevat gur erpbeqvat bs gur AZE fcrpgen. W. PURZ. fbp. CREXVA GENAF. V 8440 Ersreraprf j. qr Tenns, W. f.Fvaavatur Qnzfgr naq W. j. qr Yrrhj, Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. </p>
      <p>Npgn, V447,01,567 V. 7 Argu. Cngrag 47.97927 Mjniryhqqvgvr (8447). 6 J. U. Ubssreg naq X. Jraqgare, W. Vafg. srge., 8454,60, 828. 5 X. Ervanegm, CuQ qvffregngvba, Havirefvgl bs Xbya, 8433. 0 R-O* Xerva naq M. Nvmrafugng, W. 9%.Purz., 84464% 1896. 1 Z. R. Y. Xbuara, W. F. Fvaavatur Qnzfgr, N. P. Xbpx-ina Qnyra naq W. J. qr Yrrhj, Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. Npgn, 8448,00, 8620. 2 (n) R. Zhyyre naq W. O. Ular, Pna. W. Purz. 8413, 51, 7658; (1) W. Obhyrtr, P.W. Ybeq naq G. Z.Puhepu, Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. Npgn, 8437,51,506. 3 (n)C. Frr], U.-W. Thggyre, T. Fvzba naq N. Jvrpxbjfxv, Cher Nccy. Purz., 8422,54,50-05; (o)E. W. U. Pynex naq Q. T. Pboobyq, Vabet. Purz., 8423,82,6 814. 4 N. P. G. ina Qhva, W. Z.N. Onnf naq O. ina qr Tenns, W. Purz. Fbp., Shenqhl Genaf., 8445,49,7338. 89 F. Fpubhgra, J. qr Tenns, W. F. Fvaavatur Qnzfgr, T. ina Qevry naq W. J. qr Yrrhj, Nqinaprf va Betnavp Trbpurzvfgel 8446, Bet. Trbpurz., 8445,77,370. 88 E.N. Oreare, Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. Npgn, 8416,78,016. 87 Z. R. Y. Xbuara, W. F. Fvaavatur Qnzfgr, U. Y. gra Unira naq W. J. qr Yrrhj, Angher, 8434,658,159. 86 T. Oenhre, Unaqohpu qre Cencnengvira Nabetnavfpura Purzvr, Sreqvanaq Raxr Ireynt, Fghggtneg, iby. 8, 8419, c. 670. 85 (n)E. P. Neabyq, N. C. Yvra naq E. Z. Nyz, W. Nz. Purz. Fbp., 8409, 27,268; (1)W. Fgengvat naq U. W. Onpxre, Erq. Geni. Puvz. snlf-Onf, 8409.14, 163, 494. 80 N, FpuTorey naq N, Rpx, ywrowtf Naa. Purz,, 8461,077, 42. 81 W. Q, Pynlgba naq Q. U. Rgmyre, W. Nz. Purz. Fbp., 8452,14,425. Cncre 5892753X Erprvirq 73gu Abirzore 8445 Npprcgrq 73gu Abirzore 8445  </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>qr Tenns</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. F.</fname>
            <surname>Fvaavatur Qnzfgé</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>qr Yrrhj</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. Npgn.</title>
          <year>8447</year>
          <volumeno>01</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5678</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <citation type="patent">Argu. Cngrag 47.97927 <it>Mjnirynqqvgvr</it>(<year>8447</year>).</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. U.</fname>
            <surname>Ubssreg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Jraqgare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Vafg. Crge.</title>
          <year>8454</year>
          <volumeno>60</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>828</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <citation type="other"><citauth><fname>X.</fname><surname>Ervanegm</surname></citauth>, CuQ qvffregngvba, <citpub>Havirefvgl bs Xöya</citpub>, <year>8433</year>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. O.</fname>
            <surname>Xerva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Nvmrafugng</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Bet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8446</year>
          <volumeno>03</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1896</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. R. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Xbuara</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. F.</fname>
            <surname>Fvaavatur Qnzfgé</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. P.</fname>
            <surname>Xbpx-ina Qnyra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>qr Yrrhj</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. Npgn</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>00</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8620</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <citgroup id="cit7a">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>R.</fname>
              <surname>Zhyyre</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>W. O.</fname>
              <surname>Ular</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Pna. W. Purz.</title>
            <year>8413</year>
            <volumeno>51</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>7658</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit7b">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>W.</fname>
              <surname>Obhyètr</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>P. W.</fname>
              <surname>Ybeq</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>G. Z.</fname>
              <surname>Puhepu</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. Npgn</title>
            <year>8437</year>
            <volumeno>51</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>506</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <citgroup id="cit8a">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>C.</fname>
              <surname>Frry</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>U.-W.</fname>
              <surname>Tüggyre</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>T.</fname>
              <surname>Fvzba</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>N.</fname>
              <surname>Jvrpxbjfxv</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Cher Nccy. Purz.</title>
            <year>8422</year>
            <volumeno>54</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>50</fpage>
              <lpage>05</lpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit8b">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>E. W. U.</fname>
              <surname>Pynex</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>Q. T.</fname>
              <surname>Pboobyq</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
            <year>8423</year>
            <volumeno>82</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>6814</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. P. G.</fname>
            <surname>ina Qhva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. Z. N.</fname>
            <surname>Onnf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>O.</fname>
            <surname>ina qr Tenns</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Snenqnl Genaf.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>49</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>7338</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Fpubhgra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>qr Tenns</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. F.</fname>
            <surname>Fvaavatur Qnzfgé</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>ina Qevry</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>qr Yrrhj</surname>
          </citauth>
          <arttitle>Nqinaprf va Betnavp Trbpurzvfgel 8446</arttitle>
          <title>Bet. Trbpurz.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>77</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>370</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit11">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. N.</fname>
            <surname>Oreare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Trbpuvz. Pbfzbpuvz. Npgn</title>
          <year>8416</year>
          <volumeno>72</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>016</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit12">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. R. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Xbuara</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. F.</fname>
            <surname>Fvaavatur Qnzfgé</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U. Y.</fname>
            <surname>gra Unira</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>qr Yrrhj</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Angher</title>
          <year>8434</year>
          <volumeno>658</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>159</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit13">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Oenhre</surname></citauth>, <title>Unaqohpu qre Ceäcnengvira Nabetnavfpura Purzvr</title>, <citpub>Sreqvanaq Raxr Ireynt</citpub>, <pubplace>Fghggtneg</pubplace>, iby. 8, <year>8419</year>, <biblscope>c. 670</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit14">
        <citgroup id="cit14a">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>E. P.</fname>
              <surname>Neabyq</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>N. C.</fname>
              <surname>Yvra</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>E. Z.</fname>
              <surname>Nyz</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
            <year>8409</year>
            <volumeno>27</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>268</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit14b">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>W.</fname>
              <surname>Fgengvat</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>U. W.</fname>
              <surname>Onpxre</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Erpy. Geni. Puvz. Cnlf-Onf</title>
            <year>8409</year>
            <volumeno>14</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>163</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>W.</fname>
              <surname>Fgengvat</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>U. W.</fname>
              <surname>Onpxre</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Erpy. Geni. Puvz. Cnlf-Onf</title>
            <year>8409</year>
            <volumeno>14</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>494</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit15">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Fpuöorey</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Rpx</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Yvrovtf Naa. Purz.</title>
          <year>8461</year>
          <volumeno>077</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>42</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit16">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Pynlgba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. U.</fname>
            <surname>Rgmyre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8452</year>
          <volumeno>14</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>425</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
