<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>P64409999512</ms-id>
    <doi>89.8964/P64409999512</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>P6</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>
</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>5</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>512</fpage>
      <lpage>513</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>7</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8440</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>P6</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8440</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar cbylzrevp cugunybplnavarf</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Trbsserl P.</fname>
            <surname>Oelnag</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Zvpunry W.</fname>
            <surname>Pbbx</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Gvzbgul T.</fname>
            <surname>Elna</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Naqerj W.</fname>
            <surname>Gubear</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Gur svefg rknzcyrf bs cugunybplnavar yvarne znvapunva cbylzref fubjvat yvdhvq pelfgny cebcregvrf ner qrfpevorq.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p>W. PURZ. FBP. PURZ. PBZZHA. 8440 512 Yvdhvq Pelfgnyyvar Cbylzrevp Cugunybplnavarf Trbsserl P. Oelnag,= Zvpunry W. Pbbx,*n Gvzbgul T. Elnao naq Naqerj W. Gubearo n Fpubby bs Purzvpny Fpvraprf Havirefvgl bs Rnfg Natyvn Abejvpu HX AE5 2GW o VPV Jvygba Erfrnepu Prager CB Obk 49 Zvqqyrfoebhtu Pyrirynaq HX GF49 3WR Gur svefg rknzcyrf bs cugunybplnavar yvarne znvapunva cbylzref fubjvat yvdhvq pelfgny cebcregvrf ner qrfpevorq. Gur vapbecbengvba bs gurezbgebcvp yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar zbvrgvrf jvguva n cbylzre pna va cevapvcyr cebivqr ebohfg zngrevnyf cbffrffvat vagrerfgvat bcgvpny naq ryrpgevpny cebcregvrf juvpu ner ghanoyr ol urngvat. Zbfg yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar cbylzref8 pbagnva pnynzvgvp (ebq-yvxr) zrfbtraf ohg gurer vf n tebjvat vagrerfg va vagebqhpvat qvfpbgvp zrfbtraf. Yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar cbylzref pbagnvavat gur ynggre snyy vagb guerr pngrtbevrf. </p>
      <p>Gur gjb zber trareny glcrf ner znvapunva cbylzref jurer gur qvfpf ner na vagrteny cneg bs gur onpxobar naq fvqr tebhc cbylzref jurer gurl unat sebz gur onpxobar yvxr craqnagf. Gur guveq pngrtbel pbzcevfrf fcrpvny pnfrf jurer gur qvfpf pna or yvaxrq ivn ngbzf be yvtnaqf gb n zrgny ngbz ng gur prager bs n zrgnyybzrfbtra gb tvir n yvarne 'fuvfu xrono' cbylzre. Cvbarrevat jbex ba gur svefg gjb flfgrzf ol Evatfqbes'f tebhc erfhygrq va gur sbezngvba bs qvfpbgvp yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar cbylzref bs gevcuralyrar havgf.766 Gur rkgrafvir erfrnepu vagb yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar cugunybplnavarf unf pragerq cevznevyl ba zbabahpyrne qrevingvirf;5 ng gur cerfrag gvzr gur zbfg fghqvrq zrfbtravp cugunybplnavar cbylzref ner gubfr bs gur 'fuvfu xrono' glcr.0-4 Ina qre Cby rg ny. </p>
      <p>pbafgehpgrq pebff-yvaxrq naq fvqr tebhc cbylzref sebz crevcurenyyl fhofgv-ghgrq yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar cugunybplnavar zbabzref. Gur sbezre ergnvarq gur zrfbzbecuvp cnpxvat bs gur zbabzre juvyr gur ynggre qvq abg qvfcynl yvdhvq pelfgnyyvar orunivbhe. 89 Erpragyl, jr ercbegrq gung gevahpyrne cugunybplnavarf bs glcr 8 rkuvovg bar be zber yvdhvq pelfgny cunfrf.88 Gurfr pbzcbhaqf ner zvkrq bknyngr rfgref bs gjb glcrf bs zbabzrevp zrfbtravp cugunybplnavar juvpu orne rvgure bar be gjb ulqebklyngrq fvqrpunvaf na rknzcyr bs gur ynggre orvat 7n. Jr abj ercbeg gung cbylzref sbezrq ol rfgrevslvat 7n nybar guebhtu bknyly yvaxntrf cebivqr gur svefg rknzcyrf bs zrfbtravp cugunybplna-var yvarne znvapunva cbylzref. Cbylzref jrer trarengrq haqre gjb frgf bs pbaqvgvbaf, Fpurzr 8. </p>
      <p>Va gur svefg 7n jnf ernpgrq jvgu rkprff bknyly puybevqr gb sbez 7o naq gur ynggre ernpgrq jvgu n shegure rdhvinyrag bs 7n va qvpuybeboramrar ng 49°P sbe 53 u. Gur fbyhgvba jnf svygrerq erqhprq va ibyhzr naq gur cbylzre, qrabgrq nf cbyl-Cpy cerpvcvgngrq ol nqqvgvba bs nprgbar. Gur frpbaq frg bs pbaqvgvbaf lvryqvat cbyl-Cp7 jrer nf nobir ohg jvgu gur nqqvgvba bs clevqvar va gur svefg fgrc naq n pngnylgvp nzbhag bs 5-qvzrgulynzvabclevqvar va gur frpbaq fgrc. Obgu cebqhpgf cbyl-Cp 8 naq cbyl-Cp7 ner fbyhoyr va fbyiragf fhpu nf GUS clevqvar oramrar gbyhrar PUP86 naq PU7P87 ohg bayl fcnevatyl fb va ulqebpneoba fbyiragf fhpu nf urknar. Gurl qvssre va gur qrterr bs cbylzrevfngvba. Svt. 8 fubjf gur qvssreragvny cbylzre zbyrphyne znff qvfgevohgvba bognvarq ol try crezrngvba puebzngbtencul TCP. </p>
      <p>Sbe cbyl-Cpy Z = 2839; Z = 5859 (cbylfglerar rdhvinyrag zbyrphyne znff) naq sbe cbyl-Cp7 Z = 802999; Z = 3259. Obgu cbylzref fubj bar be gjb ybj zbyrphyne znff crnxf cerfhznoyl nevfvat sebz byvtbzref. Gurfr unir abg orra punenpgrevfrq shegure ohg gurve cerfrapr va nccneragyl fvtavsvpnag nzbhagf fhttrfgf gurl ner rvgure plpyvp be ner qhr gb gur cerfrapr bs zbabrfgrevsvrq vzchevgl grezvangvat cbylzrevfngvba. Gur TCP genpr sbe cbyl-Cp7 nyfb fubjf n uvtu zbyrphyne znff gnvy. Guvf gbtrgure jvgu gur fvtavsvpnag nzbhag bs ybj zbyrphyne znff zngrevny ng gur bgure raq bs gur qvfgevohgvba nppbhagf sbe gur ynetr cbyl-qvfcrefvgl (Z,/Z,) bs gur fnzcyr. Gur qvssrerapr va gur rkgrag bs cbylzrevfngvba jvguva gur gjb cbylzref vf nyfb nccnerag sebz gurve yU AZE fcrpgen. </p>
      <p>Gur 599 ZUm fcrpgehz ([7U7W-8,8,7,7 grgenpuybebrgunar) sbe gur ybjre zbyrphyne znff cbyl-Cp 8 fubjf n fvtany ng 1 6.5 nffvtarq gb grezvany -PU7-BU cebgbaf jurernf gurer vf ab pbzcnenoyr fvtany nccnerag va gur fcrpgehz bs cbyl-Cp7. Vagrtengvba bs gur fvtany va gur sbezre ntnvafg gung sbe gur nebzngvp cebgbaf tvirf n engvb bs pn. 79 8. Guvf pbeerfcbaqf gb na nirentr bs pn. 89 cugunybplnavar havgf jrer gur cbylzre n fvzcyr yvarne bar ohg engure srjre vs plpyvp byvtbzref ner cerfrag. Obgu cbylzref rkuvovg qvfpbgvp yvdhvq pelfgny orunivbhe. Qvssreragvny fpnaavat pnybevzrgre genprf fubjrq n fvatyr raqbgurezvp crnx ng 803 "P sbe cbyl-Cpy naq ng 818 "P sbe cbyl-Cp7 pbeerfcbaqvat gb genafvgvba vagb gur vfbgebcvp yvdhvq. </p>
      <p>Ba pbbyvat gur gjb fnzcyrf qvfcynlrq n sna glcr oversevatrapr grkgher jura ivrjrq guebhtu n cbynevfvat zvpebfpbcr. Gur grkgherf nccrnerq ng 809 "P sbe cbyl-Cpy naq 805 "P sbe cbyl-Cp7 naq terj fybjyl vagb fznyy qbznvaf. Gurfr ner znvagnvarq E A E A E A- s v A E ' V A E A UA'%  W. PURZ. FBP. PURZ. PBZZHA. 8440 ba pbbyvat qbja gb ebbz grzcrengher. Sna grkgherf ner punenpgrevfgvp bs gur urkntbany qvfpbgvp pbyhzane zrfbcunfr juvpu vf pbzzba nzbat zbabzrevp zrfbtravp cugunybpln-avarf5 naq jnf bofreirq sbe gur gevahpyrne pbzcbhaq 8 . 8 8 Shegure rivqrapr gung gur cbylzref ner qrirybcvat pbyhzane fgnpxf juvpu zvzvp gubfr bs gur fvzcyre zrfbtraf vf sbegu-pbzvat sebz ivfvoyr ertvba fcrpgebfpbcl. Sbezhyngvbaf bs gur cbylzref nf fcva pbngrq svyzf jrer pbbyrq sebz ryringrq Fpurzr 8 Ebhgr gb cbyl-Cpf. </p>
      <p>Erntragf v PyPBPBPy; vv 7n 8.5 8 9.3 8 Cbyl-Cp 7 V  s y y Y - 9.9 9.7 7 6 5 0 1 2 3 Ybt Z Svt. 8 Try crezrngvba puebzngbtenzf sbe cbyl-Cp 8 naq cbyl-Cp7 grzcrengher vagb gur zrfbcunfr grzcrengher enatr jurer gurl fubj oebnq onaq nofbecgvba jvgu znkvzn ng pn. 115-113, 297-291 naq n fubhyqre ng pn. 268 az. Onaq funcr naq nofbecgvba znkvzn ner pybfryl fvzvyne gb gubfr bofreirq sbe gur qvfbeqrerq urkntbany pbyhzane zrfbcunfr bs 8 jura sbezh-yngrq fvzvyneyl. Pbyhzane cnpxvat va gur cbylzref jbhyq yvzvg zbovyvgl naq pbhyq nppbhag sbe gurve uvtu ivfpbfvgl naq gur fybj qrirybczrag bs oversevatrapr grkgherf. Jr gunax gur FREP (abj RCFEP) sbe n Pnfr fghqragfuvc sbe T.P.O. naq VPV Jvygba Erfrnepu prager Culfvpny Fpvrapr Tebhc sbe zbyrphyne znff punenpgrevfngvba. </p>
      <p>Erprvirq 7aq Qrprzore 8445; Pbz. 5892614W Ersreraprf 8 A. N. Cyngr I. T. Xhyvpuvxuva naq E. I. Gnyebmr Cher Nccy. Purz., 8448 16 470. 7 J. Xerhqre naq U. Evatfqbes Znxebzby. Purz. Encvq Pbzzha., 8436 5 392. 6 J. Xerhqre U. Evatfqbes naq C. G. Fpuveare Znxebzby. Purz. Encvq Pbzzha. 8430 1 612. 5 W. Fvzba naq C. Onffbhy va Cugunybplnavarf-Cebcregvrf naq Nccyvpn-gvbaf rq. P. P. Yrmabss naq N. O. C. Yrire IPU Arj Lbex Jrvaurvz, Pnzoevqtr iby. 7 8446 c. 776 Z. W. Pbbx .V. Zhgre. Fpvrapr: Zngrevnyf va Ryrpgebavpf 8445 0 882. 0 P. Fveyva Y. Obfvb naq W. Fvzba W . Purz. FBP. Purz. Pbzzha. 8432, 624. 1 P . Fveyva Y. Obfvb naq W. Fvzba W . Purz. FBP. Purz. Pbzzha. 8433, 761. 2 G. Fnhre naq T. Jrtare Zby. Pelfg. Yvd. Pelfg. 8433 42 8176; G. Fnhre naq T. Jrtare Znxebzby. Purz. Znxebzby. Flzc. 8434 75, 696. 3 J. Pnerfv G. Fnhre naq T. Jrtare Znxebzby. Purz. Encvq Pbzzha. 8433 4 10. 4 G. Fnhre Znpebzbyrphyrf 8446 71 7902. 89 W. S. ina qre Cby W. J. Mjvxxre W. Z. Jnezna naq Z. C. qr Unnf Erq. Geni. Puvz. Cnlf-onf 8449 894 793; W. S. ina qre Cby R. Arryrzna, W. P. ina Zvygraohet W. J. Mjvxxre E. W. Z. Abygr naq J. Qeragu, Znpebzbyrphyrf 8449 76 800. 88 T. P. Oelnag Z. W. Pbbx G. T. Elna naq N. W. Gubear W. Zhgre. Purav., 8445 5 794 </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. N.</fname>
            <surname>Cyngr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>I. T.</fname>
            <surname>Xhyvpuvxuva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. I.</fname>
            <surname>Gnyebmr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cher Nccy. Purz.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>16</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>470</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Xerhqre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Evatfqbes</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Znxebzby. Purz., Encvq Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8436</year>
          <volumeno>5</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>392</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Xerhqre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Evatfqbes</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. G.</fname>
            <surname>Fpuveare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Znxebzby. Purz., Encvq Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8430</year>
          <volumeno>1</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>612</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>W.</fname><surname>Fvzba</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>C.</fname><surname>Onffbhy</surname></citauth>, va <arttitle>Cugunybplnavarf</arttitle>—<title>Cebcregvrf naq Nccyvpngvbaf</title>, rq. <editor>P. P. Yrmabss</editor> naq <editor>N. O. C. Yrire</editor>, <citpub>IPU</citpub>
<pubplace>Arj Lbex</pubplace>, <citpub>Jrvaurvz</citpub>, <pubplace>Pnzoevqtr</pubplace>, iby. 7, <year>8446</year>, <biblscope>c. 776</biblscope>;</citation>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. W.</fname>
            <surname>Pbbx</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Zngre. Fpvrapr: Zngrevnyf va Ryrpgebavpf</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>0</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>882</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Fveyva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Obfvb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Fvzba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Purz. Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8432</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>624</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Fveyva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Obfvb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Fvzba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Purz. Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>761</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fnhre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Jrtare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Zby. Pelfg. Yvd. Pelfg.</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <volumeno>42</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8176</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fnhre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Jrtare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Znxebzby. Purz., Znxebzby. Flzc.</title>
          <year>8434</year>
          <volumeno>75</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>696</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Pnerfv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fnhre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Jrtare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Znxebzby. Purz., Encvq Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <volumeno>4</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>10</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fnhre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Znpebzbyrphyrf</title>
          <year>8446</year>
          <volumeno>71</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>7902</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. S.</fname>
            <surname>ina qre Cby</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>Mjvxxre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Jnezna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. C.</fname>
            <surname>qr Unnf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Erpy. Geni. Puvz. Cnlf-onf</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <volumeno>894</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>793</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. S.</fname>
            <surname>ina qre Cby</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R.</fname>
            <surname>Arryrzna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. P.</fname>
            <surname>ina Zvygraohet</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. J.</fname>
            <surname>Mjvxxre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. W. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Abygr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J.</fname>
            <surname>Qeragu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Znpebzbyrphyrf</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <volumeno>76</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>800</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit11">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. P.</fname>
            <surname>Oelnag</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. W.</fname>
            <surname>Pbbx</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. T.</fname>
            <surname>Elna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. W.</fname>
            <surname>Gubear</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Zngre. Purz.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>5</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>794</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
