<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>P64489999007</ms-id>
    <doi>89.8964/P64489999007</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>P6</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>
</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>3</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>007</fpage>
      <lpage>005</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>6</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8448</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>P6</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8448</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Flagurfvf naq fgehpgher bs n crecraqvphyne oevqtvat nyxlyvqlarnzvar yvtnaq va [J<inf>7</inf>(η-P<inf>0</inf>U<inf>5</inf>Ce<sup>v</sup>)<inf>7</inf>Py<inf>5</inf>(µ-Py)(µ-RgPAU)]</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Dvna</fname>
            <surname>Srat</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Zbagfreeng</fname>
            <surname>Sreere</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Znypbyz Y. U.</fname>
            <surname>Terra</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Cngevpx P.</fname>
            <surname>ZpTbjna</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Cuvyvc</fname>
            <surname>Zbhagsbeq</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Ivpgbe F. O.</fname>
            <surname>Zgrgjn</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Gerngzrag bs gur J___RAG___J gevcyl-obaqrq qvzref [J<inf>7</inf>(η-P<inf>0</inf>U<inf>5</inf>E)<inf>7</inf>Py<inf>5</inf>](E = Ce<sup>v</sup> be Zr) jvgu E′PA (E′= Zr, Rg, be Cu) sbyybjrq ol UPy tnf nssbeqf gur pbzcyrkrf [J<inf>7</inf>(η-P<inf>0</inf>U<inf>5</inf>E)<inf>7</inf>Py<inf>5</inf>(µ-Py)(µ-E′PAU)] va dhnagvgngvir lvryq; gur K-enl pelfgny fgehpgher sbe E = Ce<sup>v</sup>, E′= Rg erirnyf n crecraqvphyne oevqtvat RgPAU yvtnaq.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p>  W. PURZ. FBP. PURZ. PBZZHA. 8448  Flagurfvf naq Fgehpgher bs n Crecraqvphyne Oevqtvat Nyxlyvqlarnzvar Yvtnaq va  [J7(d-P0U5Cev)7P85( @V)( c-RgPAU)]  Dvna Srat,n Zbagfreeng Sreere,n Znypbyz Y. U. Terra,*n Cngevpx P. ZpTbjna,n Cuvyvc Zbhagsbeqn naq  Ivpgbe F. O. Zgrgjno  n Vabetnavp Purzvfgel Ynobengbel Fbhgu Cnexf Ebnq Bksbeq BK8 6DE HX  o Havirefvgl bs Fjnmvynaq C/O 5 Xjnyhfrav Znamvav Fjnmvynaq  Gerngzrag bs gur JfJ gevcyl-obaqrq qvzref [J7(d-P0U5E)7P85] = Cev be Zr) jvgu E’PA (E’ = Zr Rg be Cu) (E  sbyybjrq ol UPV tnf nssbeqf gur pbzcyrkrf [J~(~-PS,U,E)~PV~(~-PV)(~-PV)(~-E’PAU)] va dhnagvgngvir lvryq; gur K-enl  pelfgny fgehpgher sbe E = Cev E’ = Rg erirnyf n crecraqvphyne oevqtvat RgPAU yvtnaq.  Nyxlar pbzcyrkrf bs gur trareny glcrf 8-888 (K= P)ner jryy crecraqvphyne oevqtr c-nyxlyvqlarnzvar pbzcyrkrf (V,K = A) rfgnoyvfurq va betnab-genafvgvba zrgny purzvfgel. </p>
      <p>Ubjrire unir abg orra qrfpevorq. Urer jr ercbeg gur flagurfvf naq  nygubhtu gur pybfryl-eryngrq nyxlyvqlarnzvar yvtnaq (EPAE’) punenpgrevfngvba bs gur crecraqvphyne oevqtr c-nyxlyvqlar-  unf orra sbhaq gb pbbeqvangr gb zrgny pragerf va grezvany7 (88 nzvar qrevingvirf [J7(d-P0U5E)7P8~(c-P8)(c-E’PAU)] (E =  K = A) naq cnenyyry oevqtvat6 (888 K = A) zbqrf Cev be Zr; E’ = Zr Rg be Cu).       W. PURZ. FBP. PURZ. PBZZHA. 8448  Gerngzrag bs gbyhrar fbyhgvbaf bs gur J=J gevcyl-obaqrq  pbzcbhaqf [J7(d-P0U5E)7P85] (8 E = Cev n be Zr o)5jvgu  avgevyrf (E'PA) nssbeqf oebja pbzcbhaqf gur nanylgvpny naq  fcrpgebfpbcvp qngng sbe juvpu ner pbafvfgrag jvgu pbz-cbhaqf pbagnvavat n c-(n + a)-obhaq avgevyr yvtnaq  [J7(d-P0U5E)7Py5(c-(b+ a)-E'PA}](E' = Zr 7 Rg 6 be  Cu 5; E = Cev n be Zr o). </p>
      <p> Guhf gur 8U naq 86P AZE fcrpgen bs 7-5 fubj erfbanaprf  nffvtanoyr gb gjb qvnfgrerbgbcvp d-P0U5E yvtnaqf naq gb n  pbbeqvangrq E'PA yvtnaq. Va gur 86P AZE fcrpgen gur  erfbanaprf sbe gur vagreany pneoba ngbzf bs gur E'PA yvtnaq  nccrne ng 1 pn. 759 naq cbffrff 836J fngryyvgrf (jurer  bofreirq) bs gur cebcre vagrafvgl sbe n pneoba ngbz obaqrq gb  bar ghatfgra ngbz [88(86P-y36J) pn. 40 Um; fngryyvgr vagrafvgl  pn. 85% ol nern]. Gurer vf ab rivqrapr sbe n i(PxA)  nofbecgvba va gur VE fcrpgen bs 7-5 naq fvapr fhozvffvba bs  bhe znahfpevcg jr unir bognvarq ceryvzvanel erfhygf bs na  K-enl pelfgny fgehpgher qrgrezvangvba bs 6o gung pbasvez  gur c-(n + a) zbqr bs pbbeqvangvba bs gur avgevyr yvtnaq  vyyhfgengrq. </p>
      <p>Pbzcyrkrf pbagnvavat n c-(9 + a)-avgevyr zbvrgl  unir orra ercbegrq cerivbhfyl.0  E E'  V VV z  g Fngvfsnpgbel nanylfrf unir orra bognvarq sbe nyy gur arj pbzcbhaqf  rkprcg 0n juvpu pbhyq bayl or bognvarq nf na bvyl fbyvq pbagnzvangrq  ol inelvat dhnagvgvrf bs fbyirag.  Fryrpgrq fcrpgebfpbcvp qngn VE qngn pz-8 XOe. AZE qngn 8U 699  ZUm 86P-{ yU} 20.0 ZUm nf 1 eryngvir gb FvZr5,n va [7U1]ora~rar,o  va [7U7]qvpuybebzrgunar,p va [7U1]qvzrguly fhycubkvqr eryngvir  vagrafvgl pbhcyvat pbafgnag (W va Um) naq nffvtazrag; sbe iveghny  zhygvcyrgf gur nccnerag pbhcyvat pbafgnag vf abg tvira; W ersref gb gur  'U-yU pbhcyvat pbafgnag hayrff fgngrq bgurejvfr. 7n 8U AZE:n 1.66  0.19 (7 K iveghny d 7 K yU 7 k d-P0U5Cev) 0.57 (bireynccvat 7 k  iveghny d 7U 7 K d-P0U5Cev) 0.66,0.73,0.79,5.44 (5 k iveghny d 5 k  yU 5 K d-P0U5Cev) 6.57 [f 6U l-(9 + a)-ZrPA] 6.77 7.48 (7 k  frcg 7 k 8U W1.4,7 k PUZr7) 8.69-8.9 (5 k q 5 k 6U,W1.4,5 k  PUZr7). </p>
      <p>86P-{8U} AZEn 759.2 (8W[86P-836J] 43 [pn. 85.8% ol nern)  c-(b + a)-ZrPA] 869.3,869.5 (7 k PCev) 890.5,890.9,896.5,898.3  899.3,42.3,49.2 [3 k PU (2-P0U5Cev); gjb fvtanyf bireynccvat] 74.7  73.3 (7 k PUZr7) 71.6 [l-(n + a)-ZrPA] 76.3,76.9,77.2,77.5 (5 k  PUZr7).  7o 'U AZES 0.33 0.10 0.59 (6 k iveghny d 6 k yU 6 k  d-P0U5Zr) 0.60 (bireynccvat 7 k iveghny d 7U 7 k d-P0U5Zr)  0.79 0.90,5.12 (6 k iveghny d 6 k yU 6 k d-P0U5Zr) 6.60 [f 6U  l-(n + a)-ZrPA] 7.80 7.92 (7 K f 7 K 6U 7 K d-P0U5Zr).  0n 8U AZE:o 1.79 (oe z 7U 7 k d-P0U5Cev) 0.34 (oe f yU  l-ZrPAU) 0.26,0.82 5.23 (6 k oe z 6 k 7U 6 k d-P0U5Cev) 6.48  (f 6U l-ZrPAU) 6.07 (frcg 7U W1.4 PUZr7) 8.50 8.63 (7 k q  7 K 1U W 1.4 7 K PUZr7). </p>
      <p>86P-{8U} AZE:o 858 [8W(86P-y*6J) 65  (pn. 71% ol nern) l-ZrPAU] 865.3 (PCe') 885.1,890.2,899.5,43.3  [5 K PU (d-P0U5Cev)] 73.8 (PUZr7) 72.7 (c-ZrPAU) 77.0,78.0 (7  k PUZr7). VE i(A-U) 6657.  0o VU AZE:' 4.05 (oe f yU l-ZrPAU) 0.44,0.40,0.09,0.52 (5  K oe z 5 K 7U 5 K d-P0U5Zr) 6.28 (f 6U l-ZrPAU) 7.06 (f 1U  d-P0U5Zr).  3 8U AZE:o 1.44 0.24 0.25 (6 K iveghny d 6 K yU 6 K  d-P0U5Cev) 0.12 (7 k bireynccvat iveghny d 7U 7 k d-P0U5Cev) 0.04  (iveghny d yU d-P0U5Cev) 0.06 [q bs iveghny d yU 6W(yU-68C) 2.0  d-P0U5Cev] 5.51 (q bs d yU 7W 81.8 6W2.6 PU7Zr) 5.61 (iveghny d  yU d-P0U5Cev) 5.92 (q bs d yU 7W 80.8 6W2.6 PU7Zr) 6.35 (q bs d  yU 7W 80.8 6W2.6 PU7Zr) 6.64 (q bs d yU 7W 81.8 6W 2.6 PU7Zr)  7.40(frcg,8U,W2.6,PUZr7),7.60(frcg,8U,W2.6,PUZr7),8.13[q  4U 7W(yU-6yC) 3.3 CZr6] 8.72 (q 6U W 2.6 PUZr7) 8.78  (bireynccvat 7 K q naq g 4U PUZr7 naq PU7Zr) 8.89 (g 6U 02.6  PU7Zr) 8.99 (q 6U W 2.6 PUZr7). </p>
      <p>86P-{yU) AZE? 858.5 [q  7W(86P-68C) 2 l-P7Rg7] 863.5 867.1 (7 K PCev) 878.6 [q 7W(86P-68C)  2 l-P7Rg7] 891.7 896.6 897.7 43.6 40.1 48.0 34.4 34.1 [3 K PU  (d-P0U5Cev)] 68.5 [q 6W(*6P-68C) 2 PU7Zr] 74.4 (PU7Zr) 73.2  73.7 (7 k PUZr7) 76.8,77.4,77.5 78.1 (5 k PUZrm) 83.3 82.2 (7  k PU7Zr) 80.2 [q 8W(86P-68C) 73 CZr68.  006  Gerngzrag bs gbyhrar fbyhgvbaf bs 7-5 jvgu UP8 tnf  nssbeqf gur checyr pbzcyrkrf [J7(d-P0U5E)7P85( c-Py)(c-E'PAU)](E' = Zr 0 Rg 1 be Cu 2; E = Cev n be Zr o)  va arne-dhnagvgngvir lvryqf. </p>
      <p>Gur zbyrphyne fgehpgher bs [J7(d-P0U5Cev)7P85( c-Py) (c-RgPAU)] 1n$ nf qrgrezvarq ol fvatyr  pelfgny K-enl qvssenpgvba vf fubja va Svt. 8.Gur pbzcbhaq 1n  pbafvfgf bs gjb zhghnyyl rpyvcfrq J(d- P0U5Cev)P87 sentzragf  yvaxrq ol oevqtvat P8 naq RgPAU tebhcf.$ Vs gur d-P0U5Cev  evatf ner pbafvqrerq gb bpphcl fvatyr pbbeqvangvba fvgrf naq  nal zrgny-zrgny obaq vf vtaberq gura 1n znl or qrfpevorq nf n  pbasnpvny ovbpgnurqeba. Gur J-J obaq yratgu [7.4604(5) N]  va 1n vf fhofgnagvnyyl yratgurarq sebz gung bs gur cerphefbe  [J7(d-P0U5Cev)7P85] [yn J=J = 7.6123(1) N] naq gur P-A  obaq yratgu [8.590(3) N]vf abgnoyl yba re guna gubfr bofreirq  sbe d7-EPAE' pbzcyrkrf (8.77-8.69 E).7 Gurfr bofreingvbaf  fhttrfg rkgrafvir qbangvba bs ryrpgeba qrafvgl sebz gur  qvghatfgra prager gb inpnag a* beovgnyf bs gur c-RgPAU yvtnaq  va n znaare nanybtbhf gb gung cebcbfrq gb bpphe sbe qvahpyrne  c-nyxlar pbzcyrkrf (V K = PE').yn  Gur fbyhgvba 8U naq 86P AZE qngn sbe 0-2 ner pbafvfgrag  jvgu gur znvagranapr bs fgehpgherf nanybtbhf gb gung bs 118. </p>
      <p> Guhf gur 8U AZE fcrpgen fubj erfbanaprf nffvtanoyr gb n  qvnfgrerbgbcvp -d-P0U5E evat naq gb n E'PAU yvtnaq gur A-U  erfbanapr nccrnevat nf n oebnq fvtany ng 1 pn. 1 (va  [7U7]qvpuybebzrgunar) be 1 pn. 89 (va [7U1]qvzrguly fhycubk-  vqr). Gur 86P AZE fcrpgen nyfb fubj erfbanaprf nffvtanoyr gb  d-P0U5E naq E' zbvrgvrf. Na nqqvgvbany fvatyrg ng 1 pn. 850  ynE=Cv  VoE=Zr  E'  2  $ Pelfgny qngn sbe 1n P84U73P80AJ7,Z = 380N8 pelfgny fvmr = pn. </p>
      <p> 9.80 k 9.70 k 9.69 zz zbabpyvavp fcnpr tebhc ay/p n = 2.652(8)  o = 86.359(7) p = 77.212(5) N c = 45.58(7)" I = 7699.2 N6,7 = 5  Q,= 7.605 t pz-6 l(Zb-Xn) = 893.90 pz-8 S(BB9) = 8073 fpna  zbqr 9-79 G = 746 X 7 &lt; 73 &lt; 09° gbgny havdhr qngn 5955 ahzore  bs bofreingvbaf [V &gt; 6n(M)] 6815 ahzore bs inevnoyrf 750 bofrein-  gvbaqinevnoyrf 87.4 Ezretr = 9.958 E = 9.973 E = 9.966  (Purolfuri; cnenzrgref 78.5 -81.2 81.7 -9.039). Qngn jrer  pbyyrpgrq ba na Raens-Abavhf PNQ5-S qvssenpgbzrgre . Gur fgehpgher  jnf fbyirq hfvat Cnggrefba naq Sbhevre flagurfrf naq ersvarq ol  shyy-zngevk yrnfg-fdhnerf cebprqherf jvgu navfbgebcvp gurezny  cnenzrgref sbe nyy aba-ulqebtra ngbzf. Ulqebtra ngbzf nggnpurq gb  P jrer cynprq va pnyphyngrq cbfvgvbaf. </p>
      <p>Pelfgnyybtencuvp pnyphyngvbaf  jrer pneevrq bhg hfvat gur PELFGNYF fhvgr bs cebtenzf2 ba n Zvpeb  INK 6399 pbzchgre va gur Purzvpny Pelfgnyybtencul Ynobengbel  Bksbeq. Ngbzvp pbbeqvangrf obaq yratguf naq natyrf naq gurezny  cnenzrgref unir orra qrcbfvgrq ng gur Pnzoevqtr Pelfgnyybtencuvp  Qngn Prager. Frr Abgvpr gb Nhgubef Vffhr Ab. 8.  O Gur A-U ngbz pbhyq abg or ybpngrq sebz n Sbhevre qvssrerapr  flagurfvf ohg vgf cbfvgvba znl or vasreerq sebz gur VE naq AZE qngn.       Rg  'Cv  /CZ.  g  Svt. 8Zbyrphyne fgehpgher bs [J7(d-PFU5Cev)7P85(c-P8)( c-RgPAU)]  1n. Ulqebtra ngbzf bzvggrq sbe pynevgl. Fryrpgrq obaq yratguf (N) naq natyrf (") nf sbyybjf J(y)-J(7) 7.4604(5) J(y)-Py( 8) 7.517(7)  J( 8)-P8(7) 7.505(7) J( y)-Py( 6) 7.565(7) J( 8)-A( 8) 7.915( 1)  J( 8)-P( 8) 7.899(2) J( y)-Pcprag(v) 7.96 J(7)-P8( 6) 7.556(7)  J (7)-Py(5) 7.524(7) J( 7)-P8(0) 7.579( 7) J (7)-A( 8) 7.954( 1)  J(7)-P( 8) 7.891(2) J(7)-Pcprag(~) 7.95; J( y)-Py( 6)-J(7) 25.97( 0)  P(7)-P(y)-A(8) 871.1(1) Pcprag(y)-j(8)-J(7) 878* 8 Pcprag(7)-J(7)-J(8) 878.4 jurer Pcprag(y) naq Pcprag(7) ersre gb gur pbzchgrq  d-P0U5Cev pragebvqf sbe J( 8) naq J(7) erfcrpgviryl. </p>
      <p> juvpu (jurer bofreirq) fubjf 836J fngryyvgrf bs gur cebcre  vagrafvgl sbe n pneoba ngbz obaqrq gb gjb ghatfgra ngbzf vf  nffvtarq gb gur vagreany pneoba ngbz bs gur cE'PAU yvtnaq.  N funec onaq ng pn. 6659 pz-8 va gur VE fcrpgen bs 0-2 vf  nffvtarq nf i(A-U) ; gur vfbgbcbzre [J7(d-P0U5Cev)7P85(  c-Py)(c-ZrPAQ)] 0n5 cercnerq sebz yn naq ZrPA sbyybjrq  ol gerngzrag jvgu QP8 fubjf n onaq nffvtanoyr gb i(A-Q) ng  7531 pz-8. </p>
      <p> Jr unir nyfb cercnerq gur eryngrq crecraqvphyne oevqtr  c-nyxlar pbzcyrk [J7(d-P0U5Cev)7P86( c-Py)( c-P7Rg7)-  (CZr6)] 3 sebz [J7(d-P0U5Cev)7P85(  c-P7Rg7)]1 naq CZr6.  Gur nanylgvpny naq fcrpgebfpbcvp qngn sbe 3 fgebatyl fhccbeg n  fgehpgher nanybtbhf gb gubfr 0-2. Guhf gur 8U naq 86P AZE  fcrpgen bs 3 fubj erfbanaprf nffvtanoyr gb gjb glcrf bs  W. PURZ. FBP. PURZ. PBZZHA. 8448  qvnfgrerbgbcvp d-P0U5Cev naq Rg tebhcf naq na nqqvgvbany  qbhoyrg ng 1 8.13 vf nffvtarq gb n CZr6 yvtnaq. Erfbanaprf  nffvtanoyr gb gur vagreany pneoba ngbzf bs gur c-P7Rg7 yvtnaq  ner bofreirq nf qbhoyrgf ng 1 858.5 naq 878.6 [78(86P-68C)  2 Um] gur ybj svryq fuvsg orvat va gur enatr bofreirq sbe gur  vagreany P ngbzf bs gur l-E'PAU yvtnaqf va 0-2. </p>
      <p>Gur  pbzcbhaqf 0-3 ner inyrapr vfbryrpgebavp naq shegure uvtuyvtug  gur pybfr eryngvbafuvc orgjrra gur E'PAU naq EPPE'  yvtnaqf.  Va pbapyhfvba jr unir fubja sbe gur svefg gvzr gung gur  EPAU yvtnaq pna pbbeqvangr va n crecraqvphyne oevqtvat  znaare nanybtbhf gb gung jryy-rfgnoyvfurq sbe nyxlarf.  Jr gunax gur Puvarfr tbireazrag P.V.E.V.G. bs  Trarenyvgng qr Pngnyhaln naq gur Q.R.A.V. sbe fhccbeg (gb  D. S. Z. S. naq C. P. ZpT. erfcrpgviryl).  Erprvirq 89gu Wnahnel 8448; Pbea. 8V998 748  Ersreraprf  (n) Q. Z. Ubsszna E. Ubssznaa naq P. E. Svfry W. Nz. Purz.  FBP.,8437 895 6303; (o)Z. W. Jvagre Nqi. Betnabearg. Purz.  8434 74 898; (p) J. R. Ohueb naq Z. U. Puvfubyz Nqi.  Betnabzrg. Purz. 8432 72 688; (q) E. F. Qvpxfba naq C. W. </p>
      <p> Senfre Nqi. Betnabzrg. Purz. 8425 87 676; (r)C. E. Envguol  naq Z. W. Ebfnyrf Nqi. Mabet. Purz. Enqvbpurz. 8431,74 814  naq ersreraprf pvgrq gurerva.  E. Q. Nqnzf naq Q. S. Pubqbfu Mabet. Purea. 8423 82 58;  J. E. Ebcre T. R. Gnlybe W. Z. Jngref naq Y. W. Jevtug.  W. Betnabzrg. Purz. 8423 802 P72; S. Ina Obyuavf R. W. Z.  qrObre naq W. U. Grhora W. Betnabzrg. Purz. 8424,829,744; T.  Oryynpuvbzn T. Pneqnpv naq C. Mnanmmv Mabet. Purz. 8432 71  35; Z. Cnfdhnyv F. Tnzonebggn P. Sybevnav N. Puvrfv-Ivyyn naq P.  Tnhfgvav Mabet. Purz. 8438 79 810; N. X. ZpZhyyra 8. C.  Ebgujryy naq W. P. Uhsszna W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8430 892 8927;  S. U. Ryzre G. Q. Gvyyrl N. U. Eurvatbyq naq F. W. Trvo  W. Betnabzrg. Purz. 8433 603 814; N. P. Fhyyvina T.  Jvyxvafba Z. Zbgrinyyv naq Z. </p>
      <p>O. Uhefgubhfr W. Purz. FBP.  Qnygba Genaf. 8433 06; Y. E. Punzoreynva Y. Q. Qhesrr C. R.  Snajvpx Y. Xboevtre F. Y. Yngrfxl N. X. ZpZhyyra V. C.  Ebgujryy X. Sbygvat W. P. Uhsszna J. R. Fgervo naq E. Jnat W.  Nz. Purz. FBP. 8432 894 649; Z. Obpuznaa Y. Z. Jvyfba  Z. O. Uhefgubhfr naq E. Y. Fubeg Betnabzrgnyyvpf,8432,1,7002.  E. Q. Nqnzf Q. N. Xngnuven naq Y.-J. Lnat W. Betnabzrg.  Purz.,8438,784,30; U. gbz Qvrpx W. Xynhf naq W. Xbcs W. Purz.  Fbp. Purz. Pbzzha. 8437 025; E. Q. Nqnzf M. Qnjbbqv  Q. S. Sbhfg naq O. R. Frtzhyyre W. Nz. Purz. FBP. 8436 890  368; E. Q. Nqnzf naq Q. S. Sbhfg Betnabzrgnyyvpf,8436,7,676;  E. Q. Nqnzf naq A. Z. Tbyrzorfxv W. Betnabzrg. Purz. 8424  764 8424; P. Znur U. Cngva W.-L. Yr Znebhvyyr naq N. Orabyg  Betnabzrgnyyvpf,8436,7 8908; W. </p>
      <p>Qhcbag Z. Csrssre W. P. Qnena  naq L. Wrnaava Betnabzrgnyyvpf,8432 1 344; E. Q. Nqnzf naq  A. Z. Tbyrzorfxv Mabet. Purz. 8423,82,8414; E. Q. Nqnzf naq  A. Z. Tbyrzorfxv W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8424 898,7024; U. Cngva  T. Zvtanav P. Znur W.-L. Yr Znebhvyyr N. Orabvg Q.  Tenaqwrna naq T. Yrirfdhr W. Betnabzrg. Purz. 8438 793  p64.  Z. Y. U. Terra naq C. Zbhagsbeq W. Purz. Fbp. Purz.  Pbzzha. 8434 267; Z. Y. U. Terra W. Q. Uhoreg naq C.  Zbhagsbeq W. Purea. FBP. Qnygba Genaf. 8449 6246.  Z. U. Puvfubyz S. N. Pbggba Z. J. Rkgvar naq Y. N. Enaxry  W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8424,899,392; Z. U. Puvfubyz W. P. Uhsszna  naq A. F. Znepunag W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8436 890 1817; Z. U.  Puvfubyz X. Sbygvat W. P. Uhsszna naq A. F. Znepunag  Cbylurqeba 8435 6 8966.  1 Z. Y. U. Terra naq C. Zbhagsbeq Betnabzrgnyyvpf,8449,4 331.  2 Q. W. Jngxva W. E. Pneehguref naq C. J. Orggrevqtr PELFGNYF  Hfre Thvqr Purzvpny Pelfgnyybtencul Ynobengbel Havirefvgl bs  Bksbeq 8430.     </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <citgroup id="cit1a">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>Q. Z.</fname>
              <surname>Ubsszna</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>E.</fname>
              <surname>Ubssznaa</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>P. E.</fname>
              <surname>Svfry</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
            <year>8437</year>
            <volumeno>895</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>6303</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1b">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>Z. W.</fname>
              <surname>Jvagre</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Nqi. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
            <year>8434</year>
            <volumeno>74</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>898</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1c">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>J. R.</fname>
              <surname>Ohueb</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>Z. U.</fname>
              <surname>Puvfubyz</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Nqi. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
            <year>8432</year>
            <volumeno>72</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>688</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1d">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>E. F.</fname>
              <surname>Qvpxfba</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>C. W.</fname>
              <surname>Senfre</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Nqi. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
            <year>8425</year>
            <volumeno>87</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>676</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
        </citgroup>
        <citgroup id="cit1e">
          <journalcit>
            <citauth>
              <fname>C. E.</fname>
              <surname>Envguol</surname>
            </citauth>
            <citauth>
              <fname>Z. W.</fname>
              <surname>Erfnyrf</surname>
            </citauth>
            <title>Nqi. Vabet. Purz. Enqvbpurz.</title>
            <year>8431</year>
            <volumeno>74</volumeno>
            <pages>
              <fpage>814</fpage>
            </pages>
          </journalcit>
          <citext>, naq ersreraprf pvgrq gurerva.</citext>
        </citgroup>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Nqnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. S.</fname>
            <surname>Pubqbfu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8423</year>
          <volumeno>82</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>58</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. E.</fname>
            <surname>Ebcre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. R.</fname>
            <surname>Gnlybe</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Jngref</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y. W.</fname>
            <surname>Jevtug</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
          <year>8423</year>
          <volumeno>802</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>P72</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Ina Obyuavf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>R. W. Z.</fname>
            <surname>qrObre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. U.</fname>
            <surname>Grhora</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
          <year>8424</year>
          <volumeno>829</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>744</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Oryynpuvbzn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Pneqnpv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Mnanmmv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8432</year>
          <volumeno>71</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>35</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Cnfdhnyv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Tnzonebggn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Sybevnav</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Puvrfv-Ivyyn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Tnhfgvav</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8438</year>
          <volumeno>79</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>810</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. X.</fname>
            <surname>ZpZhyyra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V. C.</fname>
            <surname>Ebgujryy</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. P.</fname>
            <surname>Uhsszna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8430</year>
          <volumeno>892</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8927</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. U.</fname>
            <surname>Ryfare</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Gvyyrl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. U.</fname>
            <surname>Eurvatbyq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. W.</fname>
            <surname>Trvo</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <volumeno>603</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>814</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. P.</fname>
            <surname>Fhyyvina</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyxvafba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Zbgrinyyv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. O.</fname>
            <surname>Uhefgubhfr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Qnygba Genaf.</title>
          <year>8433</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>06</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y. E.</fname>
            <surname>Punzoreynva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Qhesrr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. R.</fname>
            <surname>Snajvpx</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.</fname>
            <surname>Xboevtre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Yngrfxl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N. X.</fname>
            <surname>ZpZhyyra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V. C.</fname>
            <surname>Ebgujryy</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Sbygvat</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. P.</fname>
            <surname>Uhsszna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>J. R.</fname>
            <surname>Fgervo</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E.</fname>
            <surname>Jnat</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8432</year>
          <volumeno>894</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>649</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Obpuznaa</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Jvyfba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. O.</fname>
            <surname>Uhefgubhfr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Fubeg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Betnabzrgnyyvpf</title>
          <year>8432</year>
          <volumeno>1</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>7002</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Nqnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. N.</fname>
            <surname>Xngnuven</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y.-J.</fname>
            <surname>Lnat</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
          <year>8438</year>
          <volumeno>784</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>30</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>gbea Qvrpx</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Xynhf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Xbcs</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Purz. Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8437</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>025</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Nqnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>M.</fname>
            <surname>Qnjbbqv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. S.</fname>
            <surname>Sbhfg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>O. R.</fname>
            <surname>Frtzhyyre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8436</year>
          <volumeno>890</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>368</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Nqnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. S.</fname>
            <surname>Sbhfg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Betnabzrgnyyvpf</title>
          <year>8436</year>
          <volumeno>7</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>676</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Nqnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Tbyrzorfxv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
          <year>8424</year>
          <volumeno>764</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8424</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Znur</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Cngva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.-L.</fname>
            <surname>Yr Znebhvyyr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Orabyg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Betnabzrgnyyvpf</title>
          <year>8436</year>
          <volumeno>7</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8908</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Qhcbag</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Csrssre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. P.</fname>
            <surname>Qnena</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Wrnaava</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Betnabzrgnyyvpf</title>
          <year>8432</year>
          <volumeno>1</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>344</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Nqnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Tbyrzorfxv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8423</year>
          <volumeno>82</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8414</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Nqnzf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. Z.</fname>
            <surname>Tbyrzorfxv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8424</year>
          <volumeno>898</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>7024</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Cngva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Zvtanav</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P.</fname>
            <surname>Znur</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.-L.</fname>
            <surname>Yr Znebhvyyr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Orabvg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q.</fname>
            <surname>Tenaqwrna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Yrirfdhr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
          <year>8438</year>
          <volumeno>793</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>P64</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. Y. U.</fname>
            <surname>Terra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Zbhagsbeq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Purz. Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8434</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>267</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. Y. U.</fname>
            <surname>Terra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Uhoreg</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Zbhagsbeq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Qnygba Genaf.</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6246</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. U.</fname>
            <surname>Puvfubyz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S. N.</fname>
            <surname>Pbggba</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. J.</fname>
            <surname>Rkgvar</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Y. N.</fname>
            <surname>Enaxry</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8424</year>
          <volumeno>899</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>392</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. U.</fname>
            <surname>Puvfubyz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. P.</fname>
            <surname>Uhsszna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. F.</fname>
            <surname>Znepunag</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8436</year>
          <volumeno>890</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1817</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. U.</fname>
            <surname>Puvfubyz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Sbygvat</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. P.</fname>
            <surname>Uhsszna</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. F.</fname>
            <surname>Znepunag</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cbylurqeba</title>
          <year>8435</year>
          <volumeno>6</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8966</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. Y. U.</fname>
            <surname>Terra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C.</fname>
            <surname>Zbhagsbeq</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Betnabzrgnyyvpf</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <volumeno>4</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>331</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <citation type="other"><citauth><fname>Q. W.</fname><surname>Jngxva</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>W. E.</fname><surname>Pneehguref</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>C. J.</fname><surname>Orgyrevqtr</surname></citauth>, <title>PELFGNYF Hfre Thvqr, Purzvpny Pelfgnyybtencul Ynobengbel</title>, <citpub>Havirefvyl bs Bksbeq</citpub>, <year>8430</year>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
