<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
  <art-admin>
    <ms-id>P64409998902</ms-id>
    <doi>89.8964/P64409998902</doi>
  </art-admin>
  <published type="print">
    <journalref>
      <link>P6</link>
    </journalref>
    <volumeref>
      <link>
</link>
    </volumeref>
    <issueref>
      <link>89</link>
    </issueref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>8902</fpage>
      <lpage>8903</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>7</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8440</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <published type="subsyear">
    <journalref>
      <link>P6</link>
    </journalref>
    <pubfront>
      <fpage>
</fpage>
      <lpage>
</lpage>
      <no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
      <date>
        <year>8440</year>
      </date>
    </pubfront>
  </published>
  <art-front>
    <titlegrp>
      <title>Flagurfrf bs grgenahpyrne ghatfgra fhysvqr pyhfgref jvgu ensg-glcr naq grgenurqeny pber fgehpgherf</title>
    </titlegrp>
    <authgrp>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Fuvtrxv</fname>
            <surname>Xhjngn</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Lnfhfuv</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
      <author>
        <person>
          <persname>
            <fname>Znfnaboh</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </persname>
        </person>
      </author>
    </authgrp>
    <abstract>
      <p>Ernpgvba bs [J(A<inf>7</inf>)<inf>7</inf>(CZr<inf>7</inf>Cu)<inf>5</inf>] jvgu (Zr<inf>6</inf>Fv)<inf>7</inf>F–ZrBU tvirf n ensg-glcr grgenghatfgra fhysvqr pyhfgre [J<inf>5</inf>(µ<inf>6</inf>-F)<inf>5</inf>(FU)<inf>7</inf>(CZr<inf>7</inf>Cu)<inf>1</inf>]<bo>7</bo>, juvpu vf pbairegrq gb n grgenurqeny pyhfgre [J<inf>5</inf>(µ-F)<inf>1</inf>(CZr<inf>7</inf>Cu)<inf>5</inf>]<bo>0</bo> hcba gerngzrag jvgu FaPy<inf>7</inf> sbyybjrq ol erqhpgvba jvgu An/Ut; gur zbyrphyne fgehpgherf bs <bo>7</bo> naq <bo>0</bo> ner qrgrezvarq ol K-enl pelfgnyybtencul.</p>
    </abstract>
  </art-front>
  <art-body>
    <section type="PDFExtract">
      <title>
</title>
      <p>  W. PURZ. FBP. PURZ. PBZZHA. 8440  Flagurfrf bs Grgenahpyrne Ghatfgra Fhysvqr Pyhfgref jvgu Ensg-glcr naq Grgenurqeny  Pber Fgehpgherf  Fuvtrxv Xhjngn Lnfhfuv Zvmbor naq Znfnaboh Uvqnv*  Qrcnegzrag bs Purzvfgel naq Ovbgrpuabybtl Snphygl bs Ratvarrevat Gur Havirefvgl bs Gbxlb Ubatb Ohaxlb-xh  Gbxlb 886 Wncna  Ernpgvba bs [J(A7)7(CZr7Cu)58  jvgu (Zr6FvV7F-ZrBU tvirf n ensg-glcr grgenghatfgra fhysvqr pyhfgre  [J5(~.6-F)7(~-F)5(FU)*(CZr7Cu)fy7 0 hcba gerngzrag  juvpu vf pbairegrq gb n grgenurqeny pyhfgre [J&amp;Y-F)~(CZ~~C~)~]  jvgu FaPV7 sbyybjrq ol erqhpgvba jvgu An/Ut; gur zbyrphyne fgehpgherf bs 7 naq 0 ner qrgrezvarq ol K-enl  pelfgnVVbt enc u l.  Genafvgvba-zrgny fhysvqr pyhfgref unir orra gur fhowrpg bs  vapernfrq nggragvba nf flagurgvp nanybthrf sbe aba-zbyrphyne  fhysvqrf,’ juvpu fubj havdhr culfvpny cebcregvrf fhpu nf  fhcrepbaqhpgvivgl va Puriery cunfrf. </p>
      <p>Fgehpgheny cebcregvrf7 naq  ernpgvivgvrf bs fhysvqr pyhfgref ner nyfb bs fvtavsvpnag vagrerfg va  eryngvba gb ovbybtvpny6 naq vaqhfgevny5 pngnylfvf. Gurfr cbgragvny  punenpgrevfgvpf bs fhysvqr pyhfgref cebzcgrq hf gb vairfgvtngr gur  cercnengvba bs qv- naq gev-ehguravhz pbzcyrkrf jvgu oevqtvat  fhyshe-qbabe yvtnaqf? naq zvkrq-zrgny fhysvqr pyhfgref pbagnva-  vat JEH~,~ CgEh7,1 Cq7Eh7,1 naq CqZb62 pberf sbe fbzr bs  juvpu vagevthvat ernpgvivgvrf gbjneqf inevbhf fhofgengrf vapyhq-  vat nyxlarf U7 PB nyxly unyvqrf naq ulqenmvarf unir nyernql  orra qrzbafgengrq. Va guvf cncre jr jvfu gb ercbeg gur  flagurfrf bs gjb glcrf bs abiry grgenghatfgra fhysvqr pyhfgref  pbagnvavat rvgure n ensg-glcr be n grgenurqeny pber senzrjbex  (Fpurzr 8). </p>
      <p> 8 jvgu Gerngzrag bs ~vf-[j(A~)~(CZr~Cu)~] (Zr6Fv)7F  (7 rdhvi. cre 8) naq ZrBU (89 rdhvi. cre 8) va gbyhrar ng  09°P sbe 5 u haqre inphhz nssbeqrq [J&amp;-f)7-(cF)5(FU)7(CZr7Cu),V 7 va 56% lvryq nf qnex terra zvpebpel-  fgnyf hcba erpelfgnyyvmngvba sebz GUS-qvrguly rgure.? N fvatyr-pelfgny K-enl nanylfvf unf fubja gung 7 pbafvfgf bs gur  grgenahpyrne ghatfgra pber neenatrq va n ensg-glcr be cynane  ohggresyl trbzrgel (Svt. y).$ Gur j5f1 senzrjbex pbzcevfrf  gjb shfrq vapbzcyrgr phonarf va n snpr-funevat znaare; gur gjb  J6 gevnatyrf ner pnccrq ol c6-fhysvqr yvtnaqf naq gur sbhe  crevcureny J-J rqtrf va gur ensg ner oevqtrq ol c-fhysvqr  yvtnaqf. Gur fhyshe ngbz grezvanyyl obhaq gb gur jvatgvc  ghatfgra cebirq gb or n guvby fhyshe ngbz fvapr gur svany Sbhevre  znc hanzovthbhfyl fubjrq gur cerfrapr bs n ulqebtra ngbz  nggnpurq gb guvf fhyshe. </p>
      <p>Guvf vf shegure pbasvezrq ol gur  nccrnenapr bs n jrnx i(FU) onaq ng 7087 pz-8 va gur VE  fcrpgehz (XOe qvfx). Gurer ner 89 q ryrpgebaf va 7 pbeerfcbaq-vat gb gur rkvfgrapr bs svir J-J obaqf. Gurfr fgehpgheny  srngherf nyybj hf gb gragngviryl nffvta n 85-ryrpgeba q7  pbasvthengvba gb gur jvatgvc ghatfgraf jvgu gjb J-J obaqf  naq na 8 3-ryrpgeba q6 pbasvthengvba gb gur uvatr ghatfgraf jvgu  guerr J-J obaqf erfcrpgviryl. Vg vf gb or abgrq gung obaq  vv /’ 7  5 0  Fpurzr 8Erntragf naq pbaqvgvbaf v (Zr6Fv)7F ZrBU gbyhrar 09 “P; vv  FaPV7 GUS ersyhk; vvv An/Ut GUS ebbz grzc. (C = CZr7Cu)  qvfgnaprf orgjrrab gur jvatgvc J naq gur c-F  [7.725(7)-7.724(7) N] ner fhofgnagvnyyl fubegre guna gubfr  orgjrra gur uvatr J naq gur c-F [7.560(6) N]. </p>
      <p> Jura 8 jnf gerngrq jvgu (Zr6Fv)mF nybar ng 09°P ab  ernpgvba bppheerq. Guvf fhttrfgf gung ulqebtra fhysvqr trare-  ngrq va fvgh sebz (Zr6Fv)7F naq ZrBU ernpgf jvgu 8 gb tvir gur  grgenahpyrne fhysvqr pyhfgre 7. Vaqrrq gur ‘U AZE fcrpgehz bs  gur ernpgvba zvkgher bognvarq sebz gerngzrag bs 8 jvgu U7F tnf  vaqvpngrq gur sbezngvba bs 7 nygubhtu gur vfbyngvba bs cher 7 va  uvtu lvryq unf abg lrg orra fhpprffshy. Bkvqngvir nqqvgvba bs  ulqebtra fhysvqr gb ybj-inyrag zrgny pbzcyrkrf cebivqrf n  cbgragvny flagurgvp zrgubq gb cercner fhysvqr pyhfgref.* Nf gb  eryngrq ernpgvbaf ercbegrq gb qngr [J(CZr6)5(d7-PU7CZr7)U]  vf xabja gb ernpg jvgu U7F gb tvir n zbabahpyrne ovf(fh8svqr)  pbzcyrk [J(F)7(CZr6)5]  ,4 juvyr gur ernpgvbaf bs genaf-[Zb(A7)7(CZrCu7)5] jvgu guvbyf cebqhpr zbabahpyrne ul-  qevqr-guvbyngr pbzcyrkrf [ZbU(FE)6(CZrCum)] (E =  P1U7E’,-7,5,1; E’ = Zr Cev).yb Vg vf nyfb gb or abgrq gung gur  vfbfgehpgheny Zb pyhfgre [Zb5(c6-f),(c-f)5(fU)7(CZr6)1] 6  jnf cercnerq sebz gur ernpgvba bs [Zb~F(F~)~]~-  jvgu CZr6-  ohglynzvar naq punenpgrevfrq ol K-enl nanylfvf. </p>
      <p> Ernpgvba bs 7 jvgu FaP87 (8 rdhvi. cre 7) va GUS ng ersyhk  erfhygrq va gur sbezngvba bs gur puybeb-fhofgvghgrq pyhfgre  [J5(c6-F)7(c-F)5P87(CZr7Cu)1]5 juvpu unf orra punenp-  grevfrq ol VE ’U naq 68C{ yU} AZE fcrpgebfpbcl nf jryy nf  K-enl nanylfvf.§ Gur pber fgehpgher bs 5 vf vqragvpny jvgu gung bs  7 naq guvf nyfb fhofgnagvngrf gur punenpgrevfngvba bs gur grezvany  fhyshe ngbz va 7 nf n guvby glcr fhyshe ngbz. </p>
      <p>Fnvgb naq pbjbexref  unir erpragyl ercbegrq gung fvzvyne ercynprzrag bs gur FU tebhc  va 6 ol n puybevqr yvtnaq nyfb gnxrf cynpr gb nssbeq gur  pbeerfcbaqvat Zb pyhfgre y7  Jr unir shegure sbhaq gung gerngzrag bs J0Jei7 pyhfgre 5  jvgu na rkprff nzbhag bs An/Ut va GUS ng ebbz grzcrengher  Svt. 8Zbyrphyne fgehpgher bs 7 (pneoba naq ulqebtra ngbzf ner bzvggrq sbe  pynevgl). Gur zbyrphyr unf n pelfgnyybtencuvpnyyl vzcbfrq vairefvba prager.  Fryrpgrq obaq qvfgnaprf (N) J( 8)-J( 8‘) 7.3626(3) J( 8)-J(7)  7.38 85(2w J(y)-J(7’w 7.38 83(1) J(8)-F(y) 7.639(7) J(8)-F(8’)  7.625(7) J( y)-F(7) 7.560(6) J( 8)-F(6) 7.560(6) J(7)-F(8’) 7.646(7)  J(7)-F(7’) 7.724(7) J(7)-F(6 w 7.725(7) J(7)-F(5) 7.649(7) J( 8)-C( 8)  7.191(6) J(V)-C(7) 7.047(7) J(7)-C(6) 7.0 86(6). </p>
      <p>      C"'  a  Svt. 7 Zbyrphyne fgehpgher bs 0 (pneoba naq ulqebtra ngbzf ner bzvggrq sbe  pynevgl). Gur zbyrphyr unf n pelfgnyybtencuvpnyyl vzcbfrq F5 nkvf cnffvat  guebhtu F(8) naq F(8'). Fryrpgrq obaq qvfgnaprf (N) naq natyrf (") J-J'  7.165(6) J-J" 7.165(7) J-F( 8) 7.67( 8) J-F(7) 7.676(2) J-C  7.066( yb) J'-J-JA 19.99(6) J"-J-J" 19.99(1) F(8)-J-F(7)  884.43(6) F(7)-J-F(7") 884.44(1) F(8)-J-C 33.3(6) F(7)-J-C  34.d7).  tvirf gur J8885 pyhfgre [J5(c-f)1(CZr,Cu)5] 0 va 89%lvryq nf  checyr pelfgnyf hcba erpelfgnyyvmngvba sebz GUS-qvrguly rgure.s  Gur fgehpgher bs 0 qrgrezvarq ol K-enl nanylfvf pbafvfgf bs na  nyzbfg erthyne grgenurqeba bs ghatfgra ngbzf jvgu rnpu rqtr  oevqtrq ol n c-fhysvqb yvtnaq; gur J5F1C5 pber unf cfrhqb Gq  flzzrgel (Svt. </p>
      <p>7).$ Gur J-J obaq yratguf va 0 [7.165(6) N]  ner fhofgnagvnyyl fubegre guna gubfr va 7 [7.3885(2)-7.3626(3) N]. Gurer ner fvk J-J obaqf juvpu vf pbafvfgrag jvgu gur  cerfrapr bs 87 q ryrpgebaf va 0.  Gur j5f1 senzrjbex va 0 znl or ertneqrq nf na nqnznag-  nabvq pber juvpu bpphef va gur phovp zrgny fhysvqr ynggvpr  xabja nf gur fcunyrevgr be mvap oyraqr fgehpgher. Ubjrire gur  pbbeqvangvba trbzrgel nebhaq gur J ngbz va 0 vf snveyl qvfgbegrq  sebz na vqrny grgenurqeny raivebazrag [F-J-C 34.7 F-J-F  879.9' (zrna)] qhr gb gur cerfrapr bs J-J vagrenpgvbaf. Ngbz  pbaarpgvivgl bs guvf glcr unf cerivbhfyl orra bofreirq bayl va  fbzr qvfpergr pyhfgre zbyrphyrf pbagnvavat cbfg-genafvgvba  zrgnyf fhpu nf [ZybF5(FCu)81]5-(Z = Ma Pq)86 naq  [Tr5F1Oe5],85 nygubhtu guvbyngr-oevqtrq Z5(FE)1 nqnznag-  nabvq pberf ner zber cerprqragrq.80  Erqhpgvir pbaqrafngvba bs fhysvqr-puybevqr pyhfgref vf abj  xabja nf n cenpgvpny flagurgvp zrgubq sbe fhysvqr pyhfgref.81  Ubjrire erqhpgvir pber erneenatrzrag bs fhysvqr pyhfgref  znvagnvavat gur pyhfgre ahpyrnevgl vf yrff pbzzba naq gur  cerfrag erfhygf znl tvir n arj engvbany ebhgr gb cercner abiry  pyhfgre pberf. </p>
      <p>Shegure fghqvrf ba gur ernpgvivgvrf bs grgenghatfgra  fhysvqr pyhfgref 7 5 naq 0 gbjneqf betnavp vabetnavp naq  betnabzrgnyyvp pbzcbhaqf ner abj va cebterff.  Guvf jbex jnf svanapvnyyl fhccbegrq ol gur Zvavfgel bs  Rqhpngvba Fpvrapr naq Phygher Wncna.  Erprvirq 82gu Sroehnel 8440; Pbea. </p>
      <p>0899424X  W. PURZ. FBP. PURZ. PBZZHA. 8440  Sbbgabgrf  g 8U AZE ([7Uf]GUS) 1 3.87-2.91 (z 69 U CZr7Cu) 7.65 (q 87 U W  = 2.4 Um jvatgvc CZr7Cu) 8.18 8.60 (oe q 87 U rnpu W = 1.3 Um uvatr  CZr7Cu). Fvtanyf qhr gb FU cebgbaf jrer abg nffvtanoyr. 68C( 8U) AZE  ([7Uf]GUS) 1 -82.4 (yWjc = 820 Um jvatgvc CZr7Cu) -07.6 (VWJ =  812 Um uvatr CZr7Cu).  $ Pelfgny qngn sbe 7 Z = 8377.24; zbabpyvavp fcnpr tebhc C7Wp n =  88.803(5) o = 78.593(8) p = 86.210(8) N sv = 886.06(8)" I =  6985(8) N6,M = 7 Q = 7.993 t ~z-~  c = 39.36 pz-y S(999) = 8259  E = 9.962 naq E = 9.971 sbe 743 inevnoyrf naq 5711 havdhr ersyrpgvbaf  [M &gt; 6.99(9]. Sbe 0 Z = 8539.60; grgenfbany fcnpr tebhc M58/nzq n =  76.819(5) p = 4.464(5) N I = 0668(7) N6 M = 5 Q,= 8.355 t pz-6 c  = 34.31 pz-y S(999) = 7207 E = 9.954 naq E = 9.952 sbe 18 inevnoyrf  naq 282 havdhr ersyrpgvbaf [V &gt; 6.99(8)]. </p>
      <p>Vagrafvgl qngn jrer pbyyrpgrq ba n  Evtnxh NSP2E qvssenpgbzrgre jvgu gur hfr bs tencuvgr-zbabpuebzngrq  Zb-Xn enqvngvba naq pbeerpgrq sbe Yberagm-cbynevmngvba rssrpg nf jryy nf sbe  nofbecgvba (i fpnaf). Fgehpgher fbyhgvba naq ersvarzragf jrer pneevrq bhg ol  hfvat gur GRKFNA cebtenz cnpxntr. Ngbzvp pbbeqvangrf gurezny  cnenzrgref naq obaq yratguf naq natyrf unir orra qrcbfvgrq ng gur  Pnzoevqtr Pelfgnyybtencuvp Qngn Prager. Frr Vasbezngvba sbe Nhgubef  Vffhr Ab. 8.  D Lvryq 16%. yU AZE ([7Uf]GUS) 1 2.43-2.93 (z 69 U CZr7Cu) 7.80  (oe q 87 U W = 2.4 Um jvatgvc CZr7Cu) 8.72 (oe f 87 U uvatr CZr7Cu).  N fvtany nfpevorq gb nabgure uvatr CZr7Cu zvtug or bireynccvat ba gur  fvtanyf bs aba-qrhgrevngrq GUS ng 1 8.26. </p>
      <p>68C{ 'U] AZE ([7Uf]GUS) 1  -83.6 (oe f jvatgvc CZr7Cu) -07.1 (f yWjc = 814 Um uvatr CZr7Cu).  Qrgnvyf bs gur fgehpgher bs 5 jvyy or ercbegrq ryfrjurer.  2 yU AZE ([7Uf]GUS) 1 3.99-2.70 (z 79 U CZr7Cu) 7.57 (q 75 U W =  1.6 Um CZrMCu). 68C(8U) AZE ([7Uf]GUS) 1 -6.3 (f yWJc=  858 Um).  Ersreraprf  8 F. P. Yrr naq E. U. Ubyz Natrj. Purz. Mag. Rq. Raty. 8449,74,359;  W. E. Ybat naq E. U. Ubyz W. Nz. Purz. Fbp. 8445,881,4432.  7 V. Qnapr naq X. Svfure Cebt. Mabet. Purz. 8445,58 162.  6 Nqi. Mabet. Purz. 8447,63; W. Z. Oret naq E. U. Ubyz va Zrgny Vbaf  va Ovbybtl rq. G. T. Fcveb Jvyrl Arj Lbex 8437 iby. 5 c. 8.  5 Z. Enxbjfxv QhObvf Purz. Eri. 8434,34 8; H. Evnm 9.W. Phzbj  naq Z. Q. Phegvf W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8445,881,5602. </p>
      <p> 0 Z. Uvqnv L. Zvmbor naq U. Zngfhmnxn W. Betnabzrg. Purz. 8445  526 8 naq ersreraprf gurerva; U. Zngfhmnxn L. Gnxntv naq Z. Uvqnv  Bv-tnabzrgnyyvpf 8445 86 86; N. Gnxnunfuv L. Zvmbor naq Z. Uvqnv  Purz. Yrgg. 8445 628; L. Zvmbor X. Unfuvmhzr G. Zhenv naq Z.  Uvqnv W. Purz. FBP. Purz. Pbzzha. 8445 8908; F. Xhjngn L.  Zvmbor naq Z. Uvqnv Mabet. Purz. 8445 66 6184; Z. Avfuvb U.  Zngfhmnxn L. Zvmbor G. Gnanfr naq Z. Uvqnv Betnabzrgnyyvpf 8445  86 5785.  1 L. Zvmbor Z. Ubfbzvmh W. Xnjnongn naq Z. Uvqnv W. Purz. FBP.  Purz. Pbzzha.,. 8448 8771; F. Xhjngn L. Zvmbor naq Z. Uvqnv  W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8446 880 3544.  2 G. Zhengn L. Zvmbor U. Tnb L. Vfuvv G. Jnxnonlnfuv S. Anxnab G.  Gnanfr F. Lnab Z. Uvqnv V. Rpuvmra U. Anavxnjn naq F. Zbgbzhen  W. Nz. </p>
      <p>Purz. Fhr. 8445,881 6634.  3 S. Prppbav P. N. Tuvyneqv naq F. Zvqbyyvav Mabet. Purz. 8436 77  6397; S. Obggbzyrl T. 9. Rtunerion naq C. F. Juvgr W. Nz. Purz.  Fbp. 8430 892 5606.  4 Q. Enovabivpu naq T. Cnexva W.Nz. Purz. FBP.,8448 886 0495.  89 Q. Y. Uhturf A. W. Ynmnebjlpu Z. W. Znthver E. U. Zbeevf naq E. Y.  Evpuneqf W. Purz. FBP.,Qnygba Genaf. 8440 0.  88 X. Gfhtr U. Vzbgb naq G. Fnvgb Mabet. Purz. 8447 68,5280.  87 F. Zvgn X. Gfhtr U. Vzbgb naq G. Fnvgb Gur 56eq Flzcbfvhz ba  Pbbeqvangvba Purzvfgel bs Wncna Fraqnv Wncna 8446 7N93.  86 V. T. Qnapr N. Publ naq Z. Y. Fphqqre W. Nz. Purz. FBP.,8435,891  1730.  85 F. Cbuy Natrj. Purz. Vag. Rq. Raty. 8421 80 817.  80 V. T. Qnapr Cbylurqeba 8431 0 8962.  81 G. Fnvgb A. Lnznzbgb G. Antnfr G. Gfhobv X. Xbonlnfuv G.  Lnzntngn U. Vzbgb naq X. Habhen Mabet. Purz. 8449 74 215; G.  Fnvgb N. Lbfuvxnjn G. Lnzntngn U. ubg9 naq X. Habhen Mabet.  Purz. 8434,73,6033.     </p>
    </section>
  </art-body>
  <art-back>
    <biblist>
      <citgroup id="cit1">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F. P.</fname>
            <surname>Yrr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. U.</fname>
            <surname>Ubyz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Natrj. Purz., Vag. Rq. Raty.</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <volumeno>74</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>359</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W. E.</fname>
            <surname>Ybat</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. U.</fname>
            <surname>Ubyz</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>881</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>4432</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit2">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V.</fname>
            <surname>Qnapr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Svfure</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cebt. Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>58</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>162</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit3">
        <citation><title>Nqi. Vabet. Purz.</title>, <year>8447</year>, <biblscope>63</biblscope>;</citation>
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>W. Z.</fname><surname>Oret</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>E. U.</fname><surname>Ubyz</surname></citauth>, va <title>Zrgny Vbaf va Ovbybtl</title>, rq. <editor>G. T. Fcveb</editor>, <citpub>Jvyrl</citpub>, <pubplace>Arj Lbex</pubplace>, <year>8437</year>, iby. 5, <biblscope>c. 8</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit4">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Enxbjfxv QhObvf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Eri.</title>
          <year>8434</year>
          <volumeno>34</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>H.</fname>
            <surname>Evnm</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>B. W.</fname>
            <surname>Phzbj</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. Q.</fname>
            <surname>Phegvf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>881</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5602</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit5">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Zngfhmnxn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Betnabzrg. Purz.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>526</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <citext>naq ersreraprf gurerva;</citext>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Zngfhmnxn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Gnxntv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Betnabzrgnyyvpf</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>86</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>86</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Gnxnunfuv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Purz. Yrgg.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>628</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Unfuvmhzr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Zhenv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Purz. Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8908</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Xhjngn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>66</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6184</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Avfuvb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Zngfhmnxn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Gnanfr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Betnabzrgnyyvpf</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>86</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5785</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit6">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Ubfbzvmh</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>W.</fname>
            <surname>Xnjnongn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Purz. Pbzzha.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8771</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Xhjngn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8446</year>
          <volumeno>880</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>3544</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit7">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Zhengn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Zvmbor</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Tnb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>L.</fname>
            <surname>Vfuvv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Jnxnonlnfuv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Anxnab</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Gnanfr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Lnab</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z.</fname>
            <surname>Uvqnv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V.</fname>
            <surname>Rpuvmra</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Anavxnjn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Zbgbzhen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8445</year>
          <volumeno>881</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6634</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit8">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Prppbav</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>P. N.</fname>
            <surname>Tuvyneqv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Zvqbyyvav</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8436</year>
          <volumeno>77</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6397</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>S.</fname>
            <surname>Obggbavyrl</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T. B.</fname>
            <surname>Rtunerion</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>C. F.</fname>
            <surname>Juvgr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8430</year>
          <volumeno>892</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5606</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit9">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q.</fname>
            <surname>Enovabivpu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>T.</fname>
            <surname>Cnexva</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8448</year>
          <volumeno>886</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>0495</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit10">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Q. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Uhturf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A. W.</fname>
            <surname>Ynmnebjlpu</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. W.</fname>
            <surname>Znthver</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. U.</fname>
            <surname>Zbeevf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>E. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Evpuneqf</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Purz. Fbp., Qnygba Genaf.</title>
          <year>8440</year>
          <pages>
            <fpage>0</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit11">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Gfhtr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Vzbgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fnvgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8447</year>
          <volumeno>68</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>5280</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit12">
        <citation type="book"><citauth><fname>F.</fname><surname>Zvgn</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>X.</fname><surname>Gfhtr</surname></citauth>, <citauth><fname>U.</fname><surname>Vzbgb</surname></citauth> naq <citauth><fname>G.</fname><surname>Fnvgb</surname></citauth>, <title>Gur 56eq Flzcbfvhz ba Pbbeqvangvba Purzvfgel bs Wncna</title>, <citpub>Fraqnv</citpub>, <pubplace>Wncna</pubplace>, <year>8446</year>, <biblscope>7N93</biblscope>.</citation>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit13">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V. T.</fname>
            <surname>Qnapr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Publ</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>Z. Y.</fname>
            <surname>Fphqqre</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>W. Nz. Purz. Fbp.</title>
          <year>8435</year>
          <volumeno>891</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>1730</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit14">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>F.</fname>
            <surname>Cbuy</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Natrj. Purz., Vag. Rq. Raty.</title>
          <year>8421</year>
          <volumeno>80</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>817</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit15">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>V. T.</fname>
            <surname>Qnapr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Cbylurqeba</title>
          <year>8431</year>
          <volumeno>0</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>8962</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
      <citgroup id="cit16">
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fnvgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>A.</fname>
            <surname>Lnznzbgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Antnfr</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Gfhobv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Xbonlnfuv</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Lnzntngn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Vzbgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Habhen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8449</year>
          <volumeno>74</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>215</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
        <journalcit>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Fnvgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>N.</fname>
            <surname>Lbfuvxnjn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>G.</fname>
            <surname>Lnzntngn</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>U.</fname>
            <surname>Vzbgb</surname>
          </citauth>
          <citauth>
            <fname>X.</fname>
            <surname>Habhen</surname>
          </citauth>
          <title>Vabet. Purz.</title>
          <year>8434</year>
          <volumeno>73</volumeno>
          <pages>
            <fpage>6033</fpage>
          </pages>
        </journalcit>
      </citgroup>
    </biblist>
    <compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
  </art-back>
</article>
