<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article artid="psst179521">
  <article-metadata>
    <jnl-data jnlid="psst">
      <jnl-fullname>Cynfzn Fbheprf Fpvrapr naq Grpuabybtl</jnl-fullname>
      <jnl-abbreviation>Cynfzn Fbheprf Fpv. Grpuaby.</jnl-abbreviation>
      <jnl-shortname>CFFG</jnl-shortname>
      <jnl-issn>9416-9707</jnl-issn>
      <jnl-coden>CFGRRH</jnl-coden>
      <jnl-imprint>Vafgvghgr bs Culfvpf Choyvfuvat</jnl-imprint>
      <jnl-web-address>fgnpxf.vbc.bet/CFFG</jnl-web-address>
    </jnl-data>
    <volume-data>
      <year-publication>7995</year-publication>
      <volume-number>86</volume-number>
    </volume-data>
    <issue-data>
      <issue-number>6</issue-number>
      <coverdate>Nhthfg 7995</coverdate>
    </issue-data>
    <article-data>
      <article-type type="paper" sort="regular"/>
      <type-number type="paper" artnum="002">7</type-number>
      <article-number>824078</article-number>
      <first-page>628</first-page>
      <last-page>625</last-page>
      <length>5</length>
      <pii>F9416-9707(95)24078-6</pii>
      <doi>89.8933/9416-9707/86/6/997</doi>
      <copyright>7995 VBC Choyvfuvat Ygq</copyright>
      <ccc>9416-9707/95/969628+95$69.99</ccc>
      <printed>Cevagrq va gur HX</printed>
      <features colour="none" mmedia="no" suppdata="no"/>
    </article-data>
  </article-metadata>
  <header>
    <title-group>
      <title lang="english">Pneoba vba vzcynagngvba ba gvgnavhz sbe GvP sbezngvba hfvat n qrafr cynfzn sbphf qrivpr</title>
      <short-title>Pneoba vba vzcynagngvba</short-title>
      <ej-title>Pneoba vba vzcynagngvba</ej-title>
    </title-group>
    <author-group>
      <author address="psst179521ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Ehol</first-names>
        <second-name>Thcgn</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="psst179521ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Z C</first-names>
        <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
      </author>
    </author-group>
    <address-group>
      <address id="psst179521ad1" showid="no" alt="no" type="academic"><orgname>Qrcnegzrag bs Culfvpf naq Nfgebculfvpf, Havirefvgl bs Qryuv</orgname>, Qryuv-889992, <country>Vaqvn</country></address>
    </address-group>
    <history received="11 January 2004" online="13 May 2004"/>
    <abstract-group>
      <abstract lang="english">
        <heading>Nofgenpg</heading>
        <p indent="no" type="new-line">Va guvf cncre, jr ercbeg gvgnavhz pneovqr sbezngvba ba n gvgnavhz zrgny fhofgengr ol hfvat n 6.6 xW Zngure-glcr qrafr cynfzn sbphf (QCS) qrivpr rdhvccrq jvgu n tencuvgr pneoba fbhepr. Gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr vf vafregrq sebz gur gbc bs gur cynfzn punzore naq vf veenqvngrq ol netba naq pneoba vbaf cebqhprq va zhygvcyr fubgf bs QCS. K-enl qvssenpgvba fcrpgen bs gur ynlre sbezrq ba gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr jvgu 89, 80, 79, 70 naq 69 fubgf ng n glcvpny qvfgnapr bs 7.0 pz sebz gur gbc bs gur nabqr fubj crnxf pbeerfcbaqvat zbfgyl gb gvgnavhz pneovqr. Gur fhesnpr zbecubybtl naq uneqarff bs gur ynlre sbezrq unir orra vairfgvtngrq hfvat n fpnaavat ryrpgeba zvpebfpbcr naq n Xabbc zvpebuneqarff grfgre, erfcrpgviryl.</p>
      </abstract>
    </abstract-group>
  </header>
  <body numbering="bysection" refstyle="numeric" toc="no">
    <sec-level1 id="psst179521s1" label="1" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Vagebqhpgvba</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Gvgnavhz pneovqr vf jvqryl hfrq nf n uneq naq jrne-erfvfgnag pbngvat va svryqf fhpu nf zrgnyyhetl, nrebanhgvpf, ryrpgebavpf naq zrqvpvar va beqre gb qrpernfr jrne va n inevrgl bs pbzcbaragf. Gvgnavhz pneovqr pbngvat qrcbfvgvba unf orra cresbezrq ol vba ornz fchggrevat [<cite linkend="psst179521bib01" show="author" override="no">8</cite>], purzvpny incbhe qrcbfvgvba [<cite linkend="psst179521bib02" show="author" override="no">7</cite>], pngubqvp nep cynfzn qrcbfvgvba [<cite linkend="psst179521bib03" show="author" override="no">6</cite>], chyfrq ynfre noyngvba [<cite linkend="psst179521bib04" show="author" override="no">5</cite>] naq chyfrq ryrpgebqr fhesnpvat [<cite linkend="psst179521bib05" show="author" override="no">0</cite>]. Gur cebcregvrf bs gur pbngvat qrcraq gb fbzr rkgrag hcba gur grpuavdhrf bs qrcbfvgvba naq gur qrcbfvgvba cnenzrgref.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Vbaf bs qrafr cynfzn sbphf (QCS) unir orra hfrq sbe gur cunfr punatr bs zngrevnyf va guva svyz sbez [<cite linkend="psst179521bib06" range="bib6,bib7,bib8,bib9,bib10" show="author" override="no">1–89</cite>] naq sbe guva svyz qrcbfvgvba [<cite linkend="psst179521bib11" range="bib11,bib12,bib13,bib14,bib15" show="author" override="no">88–80</cite>] va gur Cynfzn Erfrnepu Ynobengbel bs gur Havirefvgl bs Qryuv sbe gur svefg gvzr va gur jbeyq. Gur QCS qrivpr vf n fvzcyr naq eryngviryl pbfg rssrpgvir qrivpr gung znxrf hfr bs n frys-trarengrq zntargvp svryq sbe pbzcerffvat gur cynfznf gb irel uvtu ahzore qrafvgvrf (∼89<sup>70</sup>–89<sup>71</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>) naq uvtu grzcrengher (8–7 xrI). Vg nyfb npgf nf n fbhepr bs uvtuyl raretrgvp uvtu syhrapr vbaf univat raretvrf va gur enatr bs 70 xrI–3 ZrI, k-enlf naq eryngvivfgvp ryrpgebaf.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va gur cerfrag jbex, jr ercbeg gvgnavhz pneovqr sbezngvba ba n gvgnavhz zrgny fhofgengr, ng ebbz grzcrengher, hfvat zhygvcyr QCS fubgf. Gur cebprff znxrf hfr bs pneoba vbaf rzvggrq ol urngvat bs tencuvgr ol gur uvtu grzcrengher sbphfrq cynfzn cebqhprq va n Zngure-glcr QCS qrivpr. Gur sbezngvba bs gur gvgnavhz pneovqr ynlre jnf pbasvezrq ol k-enl qvssenpgvba (KEQ) fcrpgen. Gur fhesnpr zbecubybtl jnf rknzvarq hfvat n fpnaavat ryrpgeba zvpebfpbcr (FRZ) naq gur uneqarff bs gur GvP ynlre jnf zrnfherq ol n Xabbc zvpebuneqarff grfgre.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="psst179521s2" label="2" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Rkcrevzragny frg-hc</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Gur fpurzngvp bs gur QCS qrivpr hfrq va guvf cncre sbe gvgnavhz pneovqr sbezngvba ba gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr vf fubja va svther <figref linkend="psst179521fig01" override="no">8</figref>. Vg pbafvfgf bs n 6.6 xW Zngure-glcr sbphf jvgu n zbqvsvrq nabqr qrfvta naq n cebivfvba sbe vafregvat gur fhofgengr sebz gur gbc bs gur sbphf punzore. Gur sbphf vf cbjrerq ol n fvatyr 69 µs, 80 xI raretl fgbentr pncnpvgbe, qvfpunetrq ol n snfg fjvgpuvat flfgrz. Gur flfgrzf bs gur QCS qrivpr pbafvfg bs (n) n sbphf punzore pbafvfgvat bs n pbnkvny nffrzoyl bs ryrpgebqrf jvgu bar ubyybj nabqr fheebhaqrq ol fvk flzzrgevpnyyl cynprq pngubqr ebqf; (o) n uvtu ibygntr cbjre fhccyl gb punetr gur pncnpvgbe; (p) gur fcnex tnc nf n snfg fjvgpuvat qrivpr sbe qvfpunetvat gur pncnpvgbe guebhtu gur ryrpgebqrf vafvqr gur sbphf punzore; naq (q) gur gevttrevat ryrpgebavpf gb npgvingr gur fcnex tnc fjvgpuvat. Gur cynfzn punzore vf svyyrq jvgu netba tnf ng n cerffher bs 39 Cn. Gur tnf oernxqbja bpphef npebff gur vafhyngbe frcnengvat gur nabqr naq gur pngubqrf, jvgu gur qbzvanag pbzcbarag bs gur ryrpgevp pheerag qrafvgl orvat qverpgrq nkvnyyl qbjajneqf. Gur nkvnyyl qbjajneq pheerag qrafvgl nybat jvgu gur nmvzhguny zntargvp svryq tvirf evfr gb n enqvnyyl bhgjneq Yberagm sbepr fvzvyne gb na vairefr cvapu. Gur qlanzvpf gura ragref gur nkvny nppryrengvba cunfr. Gur pheerag furngu unf nkvny naq qbzvanag enqvny pbzcbaragf va guvf cunfr. Gur enqvny pbzcbarag bs gur pheerag furngu nybat jvgu gur nmvzhguny pbzcbarag bs gur zntargvp svryq tvirf evfr gb gur nkvny pbzcbarag bs gur Yberagm sbepr, juvpu vf erfcbafvoyr sbe gur nppryrengvba bs gur pheerag furngu gbjneqf gur gbc bs gur nabqr. Bapr vg ernpurf gur gbc bs gur nabqr, gur qlanzvpf ragref gur enqvny pbyyncfr cunfr. Bjvat gb n qbzvanag nkvnyyl hcjneq pbzcbarag bs gur pheerag qrafvgl naq gur nmvzhguny zntargvp svryq gurer nevfrf n enqvnyyl vajneq Yberagm sbepr. Gurersber gur pheerag furngu pbyyncfrf gb tvir evfr gb n guva pbyhza bs qrafr uvtu grzcrengher cynfzn jvgu n cbvagrq fgehpgher ng gur obggbz nf jryy nf ng gur gbc naq jvgu n ohytr ng gur prager, nybat gur iregvpny nkvf. Gur enqvny pbyyncfr cunfr pna or qvivqrq vagb svir fho-cunfrf, anzryl gur pbzcerffvba cunfr, irel qrafr cunfr, dhvrfprag cunfr, hafgnoyr cunfr naq qrpnl cunfr. N guva plyvaqevpny pbyhza bs rkgerzryl ubg naq qrafr cynfzn sbezrq ng gur raq bs gur irel qrafr cunfr fgnegf gb qvfehcg orpnhfr bs gur trarengvba bs n ybpny uvtu ryrpgevp svryq pnhfrq ol gur tebjgu bs <italic>z</italic> = 9 vafgnovyvgvrf qhevat gur hafgnoyr cunfr. Guvf qvfehcgvba svanyyl erfhygf va nppryrengvba bs ryrpgebaf gbjneqf gur obggbz bs gur nabqr naq bs uvtuyl raretrgvp vbaf va gur bccbfvgr qverpgvba, gbjneqf gur gbc bs gur punzore. N tencuvgr qvfp bs qvnzrgre 80 zz naq guvpxarff 0 zz vf vafregrq vafvqr gur gbc bs gur ubyybj nabqr. N plyvaqevpny oenff ebq juvpu unf n fhofgengr ubyqre nggnpurq gb bar raq vf vafregrq sebz gur gbc cyngr bs gur cynfzn sbphf punzore. Gur oenff ebq pna or zbirq hc naq qbja nybat gur nabqr nkvf fb gung gur fhofgengr pna or nqwhfgrq gb qvssrerag urvtugf sebz gur gbc bs gur nabqr. Nabgure oenff ebq jvgu na nyhzvavhz fuhggre nggnpurq gb bar raq vf nyfb vafregrq sebz gur gbc bs gur cynfzn sbphf punzore. Gur fuhggre vf cynprq orgjrra gur gbc bs gur nabqr naq gur fhofgengr gb nibvq gur aba-sbphfrq vbaf sebz uvggvat gur fhofgengr. N funec crnx va gur ibygntr cebor fvtany ba gur bfpvyybfpbcr vaqvpngrf n tbbq sbphfvat.
<figure id="psst179521fig01" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig01.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig01.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="psst179521fc01" label="Figure 1" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Fpurzngvp bs gur rkcrevzragny frg-hc (uvtu ibygntr chyfr genafsbezre (UICG), uvtu ibygntr FPE (UIFPE) naq ybj ibygntr FPE (YIFPE)).</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gvgnavhz fhofgengrf 89 zz × 89 zz × 7 zz va fvmr ner zrpunavpnyyl cbyvfurq jvgu n znahny cbyvfuvat znpuvar. Gur fhofgengr vf uryq ntnvafg furrgf bs fvyvpba pneovqr rzrel cncre bs fhpprffvir tevg fvmrf fgnegvat sebz 879 gb 7999 sbe 0 zva rnpu. Gur fhofgengr vf pyrnarq jvgu oramrar naq nypbuby naq zbhagrq ba gur fhofgengr ubyqre vafvqr gur QCS punzore. Nsgre n srj fubgf jr ner noyr gb trg n funec crnx va gur ibygntr cebor fvtany, juvpu vf qvfcynlrq ba gur bfpvyybfpbcr (Grxgebavk GQF 235 Qvtvgny Fgbentr Bfpvyybfpbcr). Nsgre tbbq sbphfvat vf npuvrirq gur fuhggre vf erzbirq naq gur fhofgengr vf fhowrpgrq gb zhygvcyr fubgf bs vbaf bs QCS. Gur fhofgengr qvfgnapr vf znvagnvarq ng 7.0 pz nobir gur gbc bs gur nabqr naq fhowrpgrq gb 89, 80, 79, 70 naq 69 QCS fubgf. Gur ynlre sbezrq vf punenpgrevmrq hfvat n tenmvat-natyr KEQ (Cuvyvcf CJ-6289). Gur ynlre vf nanylfrq sbe gur sbezrq fhesnpr zbecubybtl hfvat n WRBY, WFZ-8359 FRZ. Gur uneqarff bs gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr nf jryy nf gur fhofgengr jvgu 89, 80, 79, 70 naq 69 fubgf bs pneoba vbaf vf zrnfherq ol n Xabbc zvpebuneqarff grfgre (Jbycreg I-grfgbe IGQ-87).</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="psst179521s3" label="3" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Erfhygf naq qvfphffvba</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Ivfhny vafcrpgvba bs gur ynlre sbezrq fubjf n qnex terl pbybherq fhesnpr jvgu n fvyire gbhpu, veerfcrpgvir bs gur ahzore bs fubgf. Gur nqurfvba bs gur ynlre sbezrq ba gur fhofgengr, purpxrq dhnyvgngviryl ol gur cva fpengpu grfg, vf sbhaq gb or tbbq, naq vf vaqrcraqrag bs gur ahzore bs fubgf. Gur KEQ fcrpgehz bs gur fhofgengr nf fubja va svther <figref linkend="psst179521fig02" override="no">7(<italic>n</italic>)</figref> unf crnxf ng 7___RAG___ rdhny gb 60.86°, 63.09°, 59.75°, 06.86°, 29.16° naq 21.82°. Gurfr crnxf pbeerfcbaq gb vagrecynane fcnpvat bs 7.050 Å (899), 7.659 Å (997), 7.764 Å (898), 8.277 Å (897), 8.667 Å (896) naq 8.709 Å (887), erfcrpgviryl. Gur KEQ fcrpgehz bs gur ynlre sbezrq ba gvgnavhz jvgu 89 QCS fubgf vf fubja va svther <figref linkend="psst179521fig02" override="no">7(<italic>o</italic>)</figref>. Guvf svther fubjf crnxf ng 7___RAG___ rdhny gb 60.4°, 58.38°, 19.45° naq 27.36°, pbeerfcbaqvat gb vagrecynane fcnpvat bs 7.544 Å (888), 7.856 Å (799), 8.549 Å (779) naq 8.715 Å (688), erfcrpgviryl, va nqqvgvba gb gur gvgnavhz crnxf. Gur bofreirq crnx inyhrf ng 7___RAG___ rdhny gb 60.4°, 58.38°, 19.45° naq 27.36° vaqvpngr gur cerfrapr bs gur gvgnavhz pneovqr ynlre ba gur fhofgengr. Gur KEQ fcrpgehz bs gur ynlre sbezrq jvgu 80 QCS fubgf fubjf gur fnzr crnxf nf bofreirq jvgu 89 QCS fubgf, jvgu na vapernfr va vagrafvgl bs gur gvgnavhz pneovqr crnxf naq n qrpernfr va vagrafvgl bs gur gvgnavhz crnxf. Gur KEQ fcrpgen bs gur ynlref sbezrq jvgu 79, 70 naq 69 QCS fubgf ner sbhaq gb unir gur fnzr gvgnavhz pneovqr crnxf nf bofreirq jvgu 89 be 80 QCS fubgf. Ntnva, gurve vagrafvgl vapernfrf jvgu na vapernfr va gur ahzore bs fubgf. Gur KEQ fcrpgehz bs gur svyz qrcbfvgrq jvgu 69 QCS fubgf vf fubja va svther <figref linkend="psst179521fig02" override="no">7(<italic>p</italic>)</figref>. Bayl guerr gvgnavhz crnxf pbeerfcbaqvat gb inyhrf bs 7___RAG___ rdhny gb 60.86°, 63.09° naq 59.75° ner bofreirq, jvgu vagrafvgvrf qrpernfvat jvgu na vapernfr va gur ahzore bs fubgf, jurernf gur erfg bs gur gvgnavhz crnxf ner dhrapurq sbe nyy gur ynlref sbezrq jvgu 79, 70 naq 69 fubgf. Gur vapernfr va vagrafvgl bs gur gvgnavhz pneovqr crnxf jvgu vapernfvat ahzore bs fubgf naq nyfb gur cerfrapr bs fbzr crnxf bs gvgnavhz jubfr vagrafvgvrf qrpernfr jvgu vapernfvat ahzore bs fubgf vzcyvrf gung gurer vf haernpgrq gvgnavhz jura gur ahzore bs QCS fubgf vf yrffre.
<figure id="psst179521fig02" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig02.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig02.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="psst179521fc02" label="Figure 2" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">KEQ Fcrpgehz bs (<italic>n</italic>) gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr, (<italic>o</italic>) gur ynlre sbezrq ba gvgnavhz fhofgengr jvgu 89 QCS fubgf naq (<italic>p</italic>) gur ynlre sbezrq ba gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr jvgu 69 QCS fubgf.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur tenva fvmr bs GvP unf orra pnyphyngrq sebz k-enl qngn hfvat Fpureere'f rdhngvba <italic>Q</italic> = λ/(βpbf___RAG___), jurer <italic>Q</italic> vf nirentr tenva qvnzrgre, λ vf gur jniryratgu bs k-enl hfrq, β vf shyy jvqgu ng unys znkvzn va enqvnaf naq ___RAG___ vf natyr bs qvssenpgvba. Gur nirentr tenva qvnzrgre sbe gur GvP ynlre sbezrq jvgu 89 QCS fubgf vf sbhaq gb or 50 az, 61 az, 61 az naq 05 az sbe 7___RAG___ inyhrf 60.4°, 58.38°, 19.45° naq 27.36°, erfcrpgviryl. Sbe gur GvP ynlre sbezrq jvgu 69 QCS fubgf, gur tenva qvnzrgre vf sbhaq gb or 07 az, 61 az, 61 az naq 11 az pbeerfcbaqvat gb 7___RAG___ inyhrf 60.4°, 58.38°, 19.45° naq 27.36°, erfcrpgviryl. Gur nirentr tenva fvmr sbe gur GvP ynlre sbezrq fubjf n fznyy vapernfr jvgu gur vapernfr va gur ahzore bs fubgf.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur sbezngvba bs gvgnavhz pneovqr ba gur gvgnavhz znl or haqrefgbbq va gur sbyybjvat jnl. Gur uvtu grzcrengher bs gur sbphfrq cynfzn ng gur gbc bs gur nabqr erfhygf va gur cebqhpgvba bs pneoba incbhe sebz tencuvgr, juvpu fhofrdhragyl orpbzrf shyyl vbavmrq. Gur netba vbaf va gur sbphfrq cynfzn nybat jvgu pneoba vbaf zbir hcjneqf va n sbhagnva-yvxr fgehpgher qhr gb <italic>z</italic> = 9 vafgnovyvgl naq uvg gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr. Gur netba vbaf eryrnfr gvgnavhz vbaf. Fvapr netba vf vareg, netba vbaf qb abg ernpg jvgu gvgnavhz vbaf naq gur pneoba vbaf ng gur obggbz bs gur sbhagnva-yvxr fgehpgher pbzovar jvgu gvgnavhz vbaf gb sbez GvP, juvpu erqrcbfvgf nf n pbng bs gvgnavhz pneovqr ba gvgnavhz. Va guvf cebprff, fbzr gvgnavhz vbaf ner yrsg haernpgrq. Nf gur ahzore bs fubgf vf vapernfrq, gur cebprff bs eryrnfr bs gvgnavhz vbaf vf ercrngrq, gurfr pbzovar jvgu gur pneoba vbaf gb sbez gvgnavhz pneovqr naq nf fhpu gur haernpgrq gvgnavhz pbagrag va gur svyz erqhprf naq gur gvgnavhz pneovqr pbagrag vapernfrf. Guvf vf nyfb fhccbegrq ol gur KEQ erfhygf.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Svtherf <figref linkend="psst179521fig03" override="no">6(<italic>n</italic>) naq (<italic>o</italic>)</figref> ner FRZ zvpebtencuf bs gur GvP ynlref sbezrq ba gvgnavhz fhofgengr hfvat 79 naq 69 fubgf bs QCS. Gur fhesnpr zbecubybtl erirnyf gung gur GvP ynlre unf fznyy fvmrq tenvaf. Gur nirentr tenva fvmrf sebz gur FRZ zvpebtencuf, sbe gur GvP ynlref sbezrq jvgu 79 naq 69 fubgf ner sbhaq gb or bs gur beqre bs 59–19 az naq 09–49 az, erfcrpgviryl. Guvf enatr bs inyhrf sbe tenva fvmr vf va pybfr nterrzrag jvgu KEQ rfgvzngrf.
<figure id="psst179521fig03" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig03.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig03.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="psst179521fc03" label="Figure 3" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">FRZ zvpebtencu bs gur GvP ynlre sbezrq ba gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr jvgu (<italic>n</italic>) 79 QCS fubgf naq (<italic>o</italic>) 69 QCS fubgf.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur zvpebuneqarff bs gur fhofgengr naq gur GvP ynlre sbezrq jvgu qvssrerag ahzoref bs QCS fubgf unf nyfb orra zrnfherq ol hfvat n Xabbc zvpebuneqarff grfgre jvgu n ybnq bs 899 t. Svther <figref linkend="psst179521fig04" override="no">5</figref> fubjf gur inevngvba bs zvpebuneqarff sbe gur GvP ynlre sbezrq ba gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr, jvgu na vapernfvat ahzore bs QCS fubgf. Gur zvpebuneqarff inyhrf cybggrq ner gur nirentr inyhrf, juvpu ner pnyphyngrq ol ubzbtrarbhfyl qvfgevohgvat sbhe vaqragf npebff rnpu svyz. Gur zvpebuneqarff vapernfrf fybjyl sbe 89 naq 80 fubgf. Fhofrdhragyl vg evfrf noehcgyl sbe 79 fubgf naq gura fybjyl vapernfrf sbe 70 fubgf. Gur inyhr bs zvpebuneqarff sbe gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr vf zrnfherq nf 734 xt zz<sup>−7</sup> naq nggnvaf gur inyhr 7255 xt zz<sup>−7</sup> sbe gur GvP ynlre sbezrq jvgu 70 fubgf. Guvf inevngvba znl or qhr gb gur sbyybjvat gjb ernfbaf. Gur GvP ynlre sbezrq jvgu n ybjre ahzore bs fubgf unf zber haernpgrq gvgnavhz pbagrag, nf vf nyfb rivqrag sebz KEQ qngn, naq nf fhpu gur ybjre zrnfherq zvpebuneqarff inyhr vf qhr gb gur gvgnavhz pneovqr ynlre nf jryy nf haernpgrq gvgnavhz. Sbe n uvture ahzore bs fubgf gur haernpgrq gvgnavhz va gur GvP ynlre sbezrq erqhprf naq hygvzngryl orpbzrf artyvtvoyl fznyy sbe 70 fubgf, naq gurersber zvpebuneqarff ernpurf n inyhr juvpu pbeerfcbaqf gb n uvtu inyhr sbe gvgnavhz pneovqr. Zberbire, gur ybnq znl or erfcbafvoyr sbe oevatvat nobhg gur fhofgengr rssrpg va gur zvpebuneqarff zrnfherzrag naq gur fhofgengr rssrpg jvyy erqhpr jvgu vapernfvat guvpxarff bs gur GvP ynlre sbezrq.
<figure id="psst179521fig04" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig04.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/psst179521fig04.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="psst179521fc04" label="Figure 4" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Inevngvba bs Xabbc zvpebuneqarff bs gur GvP ynlre sbezrq ba gur gvgnavhz fhofgengr jvgu vapernfvat ahzore bs QCS fubgf.</p></caption></figure></p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="psst179521s4" label="4" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Pbapyhfvba</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Jr unir fhpprffshyyl sbezrq gvgnavhz pneovqr ba n gvgnavhz fhofgengr ol pneoba vba vzcynagngvba, hfvat n QCS qrivpr svyyrq jvgu netba tnf ng 39 Cn naq n tencuvgr qvfp vafregrq vafvqr vgf ubyybj nabqr, juvpu vf pbasvezrq ol KEQ fcrpgen. Zvpebuneqarff zrnfherzragf vaqvpngr n ernfbanoyl uneq gvgnavhz pneovqr ynlre ba gur fhofgengr.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <acknowledgment>
      <heading>Npxabjyrqtzrag</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">ET gunaxf gur Pbhapvy bs Fpvragvsvp naq Vaqhfgevny Erfrnepu, Vaqvn, sbe gur njneq bs n fravbe erfrnepu sryybjfuvc.</p>
    </acknowledgment>
  </body>
  <back>
    <references>
      <heading>Ersreraprf</heading>
      <reference-list type="numeric">
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib01" num="1">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ur</second-name>
              <first-names>Z</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Yv</second-name>
              <first-names>J M</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Yv</second-name>
              <first-names>U Q</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8445</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Zngre. Erf.</jnl-title>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <pages>7600</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib02" num="2">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Rebtyh</second-name>
              <first-names>F</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Tnyybaf</second-name>
              <first-names>O</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8440</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Zngre. Fpv.</jnl-title>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <pages>8205</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib03" num="3">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnapvryrwxb</second-name>
              <first-names>Z</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cerpug</second-name>
              <first-names>J</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pmlmavrjxfv</second-name>
              <first-names>N</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8444</year>
          <jnl-title>Inpphz</jnl-title>
          <volume>06</volume>
          <pages>02</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib04" num="4">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Nyrffvb</second-name>
              <first-names>Y Q</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fnyiv</second-name>
              <first-names>N Z</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Grtuvy</second-name>
              <first-names>E</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Anebgn</second-name>
              <first-names>I</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fnagntngn</second-name>
              <first-names>N</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Oeharggv</second-name>
              <first-names>O</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Sreeb</second-name>
              <first-names>Q</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Qr</second-name>
              <first-names>T</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Znevn</second-name>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8443</year>
          <jnl-title>Nccy. Fhes. Fpv.</jnl-title>
          <volume>865</volume>
          <pages>06</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib05" num="5">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Nttnejny</second-name>
              <first-names>N</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Qnubger</second-name>
              <first-names>A O</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8444</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Zngre. Rat. Cresbez.</jnl-title>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <pages>524</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib06" num="6">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Enjng</second-name>
              <first-names>E F</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Gnaqba</second-name>
              <first-names>F</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Znafvatu</second-name>
              <first-names>N</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8446</year>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Eri.</jnl-title>
          <part>O</part>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>5303</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib07" num="7">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fntne</second-name>
              <first-names>E</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8446</year>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <part>N</part>
          <volume>836</volume>
          <pages>794</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib08" num="8">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Zbunagl</second-name>
              <first-names>F E</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Naancbbeav</second-name>
              <first-names>F</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Enjng</second-name>
              <first-names>E F</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8441</year>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <part>N</part>
          <volume>780</volume>
          <pages>16</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib09" num="9">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Nttnejny</second-name>
              <first-names>C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Naancbbeav</second-name>
              <first-names>F</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Enjng</second-name>
              <first-names>E F</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Punhuna</second-name>
              <first-names>C</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8442</year>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <part>N</part>
          <volume>768</volume>
          <pages>565</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib10" num="10">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Nttnejny</second-name>
              <first-names>C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Qurre</second-name>
              <first-names>C A</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnqznanona</second-name>
              <first-names>I C A</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Thcgn</second-name>
              <first-names>N</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8444</year>
          <jnl-title>Culfvpn</jnl-title>
          <part>P</part>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <pages>32</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib11" num="11">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Puunln</second-name>
              <first-names>E X</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Enjng</second-name>
              <first-names>E F</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8442</year>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <part>N</part>
          <volume>771</volume>
          <pages>787</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib12" num="12">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Puunln</second-name>
              <first-names>E X</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Enjng</second-name>
              <first-names>E F</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8443</year>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <part>N</part>
          <volume>764</volume>
          <pages>894</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <misc-ref id="psst179521bib13" num="13">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ebl</second-name>
              <first-names>F</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Puunln</second-name>
              <first-names>E X</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <misc-text>CNG/6.81.84/43919/43</misc-text>
          <source>Angvbany Erfrnepu Qrirybczrag Pbecbengvba, Vaqvn</source>
        </misc-ref>
        <conf-ref id="psst179521bib14" num="14">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fevinfgnin</second-name>
              <first-names>Z C</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Thcgn</second-name>
              <first-names>E</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8444</year>
          <conf-title>Nqinaprf va Nccyvrq Cynfzn Fpvrapr: Cebp. Vag. Flzc. ba Nccyvrq Cynfzn Fpvrapr '44</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Bfnxn</conf-place>
          <volume>iby 7</volume>
          <editors order="normal">
            <author type="normal" corres="no">
              <first-names>N</first-names>
              <second-name>Xbonlnfuv</second-name>
            </author>
            <author type="normal" corres="no">
              <first-names>A Z</first-names>
              <second-name>Tubavrz</second-name>
            </author>
          </editors>
          <publication>
            <publisher>Vafgvghgr bs Nccyvrq Cynfzn Fpvrapr</publisher>
          </publication>
          <pages>c 818</pages>
        </conf-ref>
        <misc-ref id="psst179521bib15" num="15">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Puunln</second-name>
              <first-names>E X</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7999</year>
          <thesis>CuQ Gurfvf</thesis>
          <source>Havirefvgl bs Qryuv</source>
        </misc-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib16" num="16">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Zngure</second-name>
              <first-names>W J</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8415</year>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Syhvqf</jnl-title>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <pages>0</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="psst179521bib17" num="17">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Yrr</second-name>
              <first-names>F</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8433</year>
          <jnl-title>Nz. W. Culf.</jnl-title>
          <volume>01</volume>
          <pages>17</pages>
        </journal-ref>
      </reference-list>
    </references>
  </back>
</article>
