<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "http://ej.iop.org/dtd/iopv1_4_7a.dtd">
<article artid="ppcf207268">
  <article-metadata>
    <jnl-data jnlid="ppcf">
      <jnl-fullname>Plasma Physics and Controlled Fusion</jnl-fullname>
      <jnl-abbreviation>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-abbreviation>
      <jnl-shortname>PPCF</jnl-shortname>
      <jnl-issn>0741-3335</jnl-issn>
      <jnl-coden>PLPHBZ</jnl-coden>
      <jnl-imprint>Institute of Physics Publishing</jnl-imprint>
      <jnl-web-address>stacks.iop.org/PPCF</jnl-web-address>
    </jnl-data>
    <volume-data>
      <year-publication>2006</year-publication>
      <volume-number>48</volume-number>
    </volume-data>
    <issue-data>
      <issue-number>4</issue-number>
      <coverdate>April 2006</coverdate>
    </issue-data>
    <article-data>
      <article-type type="paper" sort="special"/>
      <type-number type="paper" artnum="S06">6</type-number>
      <article-number>207268</article-number>
      <first-page>S75</first-page>
      <last-page>S86</last-page>
      <length>12</length>
      <pii>S0741-3335(06)07268-X</pii>
      <doi>10.1088/0741-3335/48/4/S06</doi>
      <copyright>2006 IOP Publishing Ltd</copyright>
      <ccc>0741-3335/06/040075+12$30.00</ccc>
      <printed>Printed in the UK</printed>
      <features colour="none" mmedia="no" suppdata="no"/>
    </article-data>
  </article-metadata>
  <header>
    <title-group>
      <title>The interplay between Reynolds stress and zonal flows: direct numerical simulation as a bridge between theory and experiment</title>
      <short-title>Reynolds stress and zonal flows</short-title>
      <ej-title>Reynolds stress and zonal flows</ej-title>
    </title-group>
    <author-group>
      <author address="ppcf207268ad1" email="ppcf207268ea1">
        <first-names>M</first-names>
        <second-name>Vergote</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="ppcf207268ad1">
        <first-names>M</first-names>
        <second-name>Van Schoor</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="ppcf207268ad1">
        <first-names>Y</first-names>
        <second-name>Xu</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="ppcf207268ad1">
        <first-names>S</first-names>
        <second-name>Jachmich</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="ppcf207268ad1">
        <first-names>R</first-names>
        <second-name>Weynants</second-name>
      </author>
    </author-group>
    <address-group>
      <address id="ppcf207268ad1" showid="no"><orgname>Laboratoire de physique des plasmas—Laboratorium voor Plasmafysica, Association ‘Euratom-Etat Belge’—Associatie ‘Euratom-Belgische Staat’, Ecole Royale Militaire—Koninklijke Militaire School</orgname>, Avenue de la Renaissance 30—Renaissancelaan 30, B-1000 Brussels, <country>Belgium</country> (Partner in Trilateral Euregio Cluster).</address>
      <e-address id="ppcf207268ea1">
        <email mailto="maarten.vergote@rma.ac.be">maarten.vergote@rma.ac.be</email>
      </e-address>
    </address-group>
    <history received="2 September 2005" finalform="22 November 2005" online="20 March 2006"/>
    <abstract-group>
      <abstract>
        <heading>Abstract</heading>
        <p indent="no">We describe the results of a measurement campaign on the CASTOR tokamak where the drive of flows and zonal flows by Reynolds stress was investigated by means of a dual probe head system allowing us to measure the properties of the electrostatic turbulence and the rotation velocities at the same location and at the same moment. We compare these experimental results with a turbulence model linked to a one dimensional fluid model describing the electrostatic turbulence and its influence on the background flow. The turbulence is simulated locally on the basis of the Hasegawa–Wakatani equations, completed with magnetic inhomogeneity terms. In the fluid model the toroidal geometry is correctly taken into account, while various sources and sinks like viscosity, interaction with neutrals, Reynolds stress and electric current induced by biasing are included. The good agreement of the predicted flow with the measured one demonstrates that in a pure cylindrical geometry the modelled strength of Reynolds stress acceleration of flow is overestimated.</p>
      </abstract>
    </abstract-group>
    <classifications>
      <class-codes scheme="pacs" print="no">
        <code>52.35.Ra</code>
      </class-codes>
    </classifications>
  </header>
  <body numbering="bysection">
    <sec-level1 id="ppcf207268s1" label="1">
      <heading>Introduction</heading>
      <p indent="no">In magnetized plasmas it is often found that the cross-field transport exceeds by far the expected (neo) classical diffusive transport due to collisions. This ‘anomalous’ transport dramatically reduces the confinement and is due to turbulence, driven by various sources such as density or temperature gradients and curvature [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib01">1</cite>]. For the successful exploitation of a fusion reactor, the understanding of the nature of the turbulence as well as the study of strategies to control and/or reduce it are therefore of major importance.</p>
      <p>Sheared flows which rip the convective cells apart have long been invoked as a major control mechanism to quench the turbulence. Such flows can be established by various means such as electrode biasing [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib02">2</cite>] and neutral beam injection [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib03">3</cite>] and show the direct impact of background poloidal and toroidal rotation on the turbulence [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib04">4</cite>]. The turbulence however also influences the background flows via the so-called Reynolds stress as was first put forward by Diamond in search of a mechanism to explain L- to H-mode transition. This inverse phenomenon has been studied both on the theoretical [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib05">5</cite>] and on the experimental side [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib06">6</cite>].</p>
      <p>Nonlinear interaction, the agent behind Reynolds stress, is also at the basis of the self-organization of the turbulence. Zonal flows, defined as large scale poloidally-extended coherent structures (<italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> &lt; <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub>, but <italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> nonzero), can, for example, quench smaller scale turbulence, a phenomenon that, because of the self-similar nature of the turbulence, can be expected to be active on different spatial scales.</p>
      <p>As the pioneering work in this domain by Xu [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib06">6</cite>] was impeded by a lack of precise quantitative measurements of the poloidal rotation in HT-6M, we now aim at further documenting the interaction between the background flow and turbulence via Reynolds stress by comparing the results of a dedicated experimental campaign on the CASTOR tokamak to the predictions of theoretical models describing the turbulence and the behaviour of the background flow. In addition we investigate the role of Reynolds stress in the self-organization and behaviour of the turbulence.</p>
      <p>By means of a manipulator, inserted at the top of the machine, and holding a Gundestrup probe to measure the rotation velocities, as well as a dedicated Reynolds stress probe (RS-probe, see figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig01">1</figref>) [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib07">7</cite>] we were able to measure the background flow and the turbulence properties simultaneously and at the same location. Different shots then allowed us to establish radial profiles. We investigated Ohmic plasmas as well as scenarios where rotation is driven by electrode biasing.
<figure id="ppcf207268fig01" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig01.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig01.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc01" label="Figure 1"><p indent="no">Schematic drawing of the experimental set-up at CASTOR.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>On the other hand, we built an electrostatic turbulence code based on the Hasegawa–Wakatani equations (HWE) [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib08">8</cite>] in two-dimensional (2D) (<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>), extended with magnetic inhomogeneity (these terms are commonly called curvature terms), so that the rectangular grid (<italic>x</italic>, <italic>y</italic>) could be mapped on a 2D (<italic>r</italic>, ___ENT___) domain. First of all, we confront this model with the experimentally measured turbulence and make an extensive comparison between the code simulations and the experiment.</p>
      <p>Then we study the influence of the turbulence on the background flow by means of a one-dimensional (1D) fluid model which describes the poloidal acceleration of the plasma due to a gradient in Reynolds stress and electrode biasing. Various damping mechanisms such as bulk viscosity and drag due to neutral particles are also included. Furthermore, compared with previous work [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib05">5</cite>], the curvature is correctly taken into account, giving rise to the neoclassical factor 1 + 2<italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup> in certain terms [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib07">7</cite>]. For this model we need the surface averaged gradient of the Reynolds stress, a quantity that can be computed only if the poloidal dependence of the turbulence is known. As we have no experimental clue, we use the extended HWE model to establish the poloidal dependence by direct numerical simulation. We thus obtain a model function that can be used to compute the flux surface average. The model is then used to study the experimentally obtained rotation.</p>
      <p>Finally we comment on the role the Reynolds stress plays in the creation of zonal flows and show experimental evidence.</p>
      <p>The remaining part of this paper is organized as follows. We start in section <secref linkend="ppcf207268s2">2</secref> by presenting our simulations based on the set of the extended HWE, which has been validated by the measured data taken at CASTOR and furthermore lead to a model function describing the poloidal dependence of the strength of the Reynolds stress. In section <secref linkend="ppcf207268s3">3</secref>, the 1D fluid model, which includes this Reynolds stress term, is explained and is compared as well with the experimental observations at HT-6M and CASTOR. In section <secref linkend="ppcf207268s4">4</secref> conclusions are drawn.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="ppcf207268s2" label="2">
      <heading>Turbulence modelling</heading>
      <p indent="no">The turbulence model is established to simulate the data taken in CASTOR with the experimental set-up described in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib07">7</cite>] and depicted in figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig01">1</figref>. Under the assumption of electrostatic turbulence the velocity fluctuations are related to the potential fluctuations (
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\bvsim} =({1}/{B^2})(\vec{\hbox{\bit B}} \times \vec{\bnabla} \phisim) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in001.gif"/></inline-eqn>), so that density and potential fluctuations, monitored at the different pins of the probe allow us to compute basic quantities such as correlation time and lengths, the turbulence driven particle flux (
<inline-eqn><?TeX \Gamma = \langle \nsim {\vsim_{\,r}} \rangle_{\tau} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in002.gif"/></inline-eqn> with 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \langle x \rangle_{\tau} = {1}/{\tau}\int_{t}^{{t} + \tau} x\,\rmd t ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in003.gif"/></inline-eqn>) and the components of the Reynolds stress, (
<inline-eqn><?TeX RS = \langle {\vsim_{\,r}} {\vsim_{\,\theta}} \rangle_{\tau} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in004.gif"/></inline-eqn>), that we need for later modelling.</p>
      <p>The simplest model that allows us to describe this experiment is the Hasegawa–Wakatani model [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib08">8</cite>], to which we added curvature terms [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib09">9</cite>] in view of a study of the poloidal dependence of the turbulence:
<display-eqn id="ppcf207268eq001" eqnnum="1"><?TeX \[
\begin{equation}
\left({\frac{\partial }{\partial t'}} -[\phi',]\right)\nabla'^2_\perp
\phi' = C_1 (\phi'- n') + C_2 \nabla'^2_\perp (\nabla'^2_\perp \phi
')- {\mathcal{K'}}(n'),\end{equation}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268de001.gif"/></display-eqn>
<display-eqn id="ppcf207268eq002" eqnnum="2"><?TeX \[
\begin{equation}
\left({\frac{\partial }{\partial t'}} -[\phi',]\right) n' = C_1
 ( \phi' - n') + {\frac{\partial \phi'}{\partial y'}}
\kappa + C_2 \nabla'^2_\perp n' + {\mathcal{K'}}(\phi'- n').\end{equation}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268de002.gif"/></display-eqn>
The primes denote dimensionless quantities (radial dimension, <italic>x</italic>′ = <italic>x</italic>/ρ<sub><italic>s</italic></sub>, perpendicular distance, <italic>y</italic>′ = <italic>y</italic>/ρ<sub><italic>s</italic></sub>, parallel coordinate, <italic>z</italic>′, time, <italic>t</italic>′ = ω<sub>ci</sub><italic>t</italic>, density <italic>n</italic>′ = ≁/<italic>n</italic><sub>0</sub> and potential ___ENT___′ = <italic>e</italic>___ENT___<italic>sim</italic>/<italic>T</italic>) with ρ<sub><italic>s</italic></sub> the ion Larmor radius at electron temperature and ω<sub>ci</sub> the ion cyclotron frequency. The Poisson brackets 
<inline-eqn><?TeX [f,g] = \vec{\hbox{\bit u}}_z \cdot \vec{\bnabla} f \times \vec{\bnabla} g ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in005.gif"/></inline-eqn> constitute the nonlinear part of the HWE. We also added a particle diffusion in the electron continuity equation to increase the stability during the numerical calculations [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib10">10</cite>].</p>
      <p>The magnetic field inhomogeneity depends on the poloidal angle through the curvature operator 
<inline-eqn><?TeX {\mathcal{K'}} (f) =\omega_B (\sin \theta {({\partial }/{\partial x'})} + \cos \theta {({\partial }/{\partial y'})}) f ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in006.gif"/></inline-eqn>, with ω<sub><italic>B</italic></sub> = (2ρ<sub><italic>s</italic></sub>/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) and <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> the major radius. There is no effect of magnetic field shear included in the model, or equivalently the safety factor <italic>q</italic> is constant over the computational domain. The adiabaticity coefficient of the electron response is abbreviated 
<inline-eqn><?TeX C_1=({T_{e} \sigma_z}/{e^2 \omega_{\rm ci} n_{0}}) k_z^2 ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in007.gif"/></inline-eqn> (with σ<sub><italic>z</italic></sub> the electron conductivity in the parallel direction) and the kinematic ion shear viscosity, μ = η<sub>1</sub>/<italic>n</italic><sub>0</sub>/<italic>M</italic><sub>i</sub> [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib11">11</cite>], is introduced by 
<inline-eqn><?TeX C_2={\mu}/{\omega_{\rm ci}\rho_s^2} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in008.gif"/></inline-eqn>.</p>
      <p>The normalized driving background density gradient is introduced via κ = − ∂ (ln <italic>n</italic><sub>0</sub>)/∂<italic>x</italic>′, and determines 
<inline-eqn><?TeX k_z^2 ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in009.gif"/></inline-eqn> through the assumption of maximum growth rate. Therefore we write the dispersion relation of the set HWE by neglecting the viscosity (<italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> = 0) and the curvature terms (ω<sub><italic>B</italic></sub> = 0):
<display-eqn id="ppcf207268ueq001"><?TeX \[
\begin{equation*}\omega^2 + \rmi \omega b - \rmi b \omega_1 =0,\end{equation*}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268ude001.gif"/></display-eqn>
in which ω<sub>1</sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub> κ/(1 + <italic>k</italic><sup>2</sup>) and <italic>b</italic> = <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub>(1 + <italic>k</italic><sup>2</sup>)/<italic>k</italic><sup>2</sup>. We rather find <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub> ≈ <italic>k</italic><sup>2</sup> <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub> (∂(ln<italic>n</italic><sub>0</sub>)/∂<italic>x</italic>′)/(1 + <italic>k</italic><sup>2</sup>)<sup>2</sup> instead of the quadruple of this value as reported in the original paper. We derived the exact solution (<italic>b</italic> ≈ ω<sub>1</sub>, as is obtained as well in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib12">12</cite>]) and did not approximate the final condition, 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \omega=\case{1}{2}(-\rmi b + \rmi b \sqrt{1-4\rmi \omega_1 /b}) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in010.gif"/></inline-eqn>, as is done in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib08">8</cite>]. These values for the parallel wavenumber (or equivalently <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub>) result in increased levels of fluctuations, leading to more realistic values when compared with the experiment.</p>
      <p>The evolution of the dynamical equations (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq001">1</eqnref>) and (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq002">2</eqnref>) is computed locally by a pseudospectral code on a rectangular grid of 33 × 33 with periodic boundary conditions. As the computational domain is sufficiently restricted in radial as well as in poloidal extent, all coefficients can be considered constant on the domain. The real space between two different grid points is smaller than half a gyro radius: in all calculations we used as grid spacing, ρ<sub><italic>s</italic></sub>/2.1 (for typical values, see the next section), so that the maximum dimensionless wavenumber is 2.1 π in both directions. Wavenumbers in a modulus larger than 2 π are artificially damped by a hyperviscosity [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib13">13</cite>]. The time-stepping algorithm is based on a predictor–corrector scheme.</p>
      <sec-level2 id="ppcf207268s2-1" label="2.1">
        <heading>Confrontation with experimental data</heading>
        <p indent="no">To compare with the data taken at CASTOR and reported in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib07">7</cite>], we put 3 ‘probe pins’ in the grid (33 × 33 points = 8 × 8 mm in real units) at the same relative position as the pins of the real probe used in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib07">7</cite>] (at the top of the poloidal section, see figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig01">1</figref>). We simulated the self consistent evolution of turbulence on the basis of equations (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq001">1</eqnref>) and (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq002">2</eqnref>) and sampled the signals at the same frequency as during the experiment (1 MHz). The coefficients are computed according to the edge parameters of CASTOR (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> ≈ 20 eV, <italic>n</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> = 1 × 10<sup>19</sup> m<sup>−3</sup>, ∇<italic>n</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> = −5 × 10<sup>20</sup> m<sup>−4</sup> and <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.40 m, <italic>a</italic> = 0.085 m, <italic>B</italic><sub><italic>T</italic></sub> = 1.3 T), leading to ρ<sub><italic>s</italic></sub> ≈ 0.4 mm, ω<sub>ci</sub> = 1.2 × 10<sup>8</sup> rad s<sup>−1</sup>, κ = −0.02, <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub> ∈ −0.005, …, 0.005, <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> = 1.2 × 10<sup>−4</sup> and ω<sub><italic>B</italic></sub> = 2 × 10<sup>−3</sup>. These values are at the low end of the spectrum of the cases treated in the original paper [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib08">8</cite>].</p>
        <p>We can now compare the simulated and the experimental signals. First, we study the correlation properties of the fluctuations. The data analysis of the signals coming from the real experiment and from the virtual probe pins on the grid are both made in the laboratory frame. In our simulation model, there is no background electric field and thus no corresponding 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\hbox{\bit E}} \times \vec{\hbox{\bit B}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in011.gif"/></inline-eqn> drift. To correctly identify the correlation properties of the turbulence and also make the comparison significant, we choose the radial position of the probe to be the one where the radial electric field 
<inline-eqn><?TeX (|\vec{\hbox{\bit E}}_r|) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in012.gif"/></inline-eqn> measured on CASTOR is minimum so that the 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\hbox{\bit E}}_r \times \vec{\hbox{\bit B}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in013.gif"/></inline-eqn> flow-effect on the turbulence correlation is negligible.</p>
        <p>The correlation time obtained for both signals is of the order of <italic>T</italic><sub>corr</sub> ≈ 5–6 µs, as can be seen in figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig02">2</figref>, which depicts the e-folding time of the normalized autocorrelation function of the sampled potential fluctuations (
<inline-eqn><?TeX R(\Delta t)=1/N \sum_{j=1}^{N-\Delta t}{{\phisim} (j + \Delta t)\cdot {\phisim}(j)} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in014.gif"/></inline-eqn>, with the time lag Δ<italic>t</italic> a multiple of the sample period), obtained by simulation (dotted line) and by measurement (full line). This function can be computed in each point of the simulation grid and for all the measurement points of the probe. Here we have represented only one typical curve. Similar values have been found for other locations and other probe-pins. A correlation time of the same order was reported by Hron in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib14">14</cite>].
<figure id="ppcf207268fig02" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig02.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig02.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc02" label="Figure 2"><p indent="no">Auto-correlation function for the potential fluctuations by simulation and on CASTOR (<italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.88). Note that these curves refer to a simulation and to experimental data with respect to the laboratory frame.</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>Next we compare the fluctuation levels of ___ENT___<italic>sim</italic> and the Reynolds stress (
<inline-eqn><?TeX RS = \langle {\vsim_{\,r}} {\vsim_{\,\theta}} \rangle_{\tau} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in004.gif"/></inline-eqn>, which is actually a zero-delay cross-correlation function between two fluctuating quantities, 
<inline-eqn><?TeX {\vsim_{\,r}} = - (1/B) ({\Delta {\phisim}}/{r \Delta \theta}) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in015.gif"/></inline-eqn> and 
<inline-eqn><?TeX {\vsim_{\,\theta}} = (1/B) ({\Delta {\phisim}}/{ \Delta r}) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in016.gif"/></inline-eqn>, shown in figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig03">3</figref>). It is clear that the simulated fluctuation levels are somewhat lower than experimentally observed (a factor of three for the raw data, a factor of five for the Reynolds stress). This discrepancy can be partially explained by the assumption of homogeneous temperature in the model as discussed in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib15">15</cite>].
<figure id="ppcf207268fig03" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig03.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig03.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc03" label="Figure 3"><p indent="no">Top: floating potential fluctuations (dimensionless) at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.97 in CASTOR (<italic>a</italic>) and simulated (<italic>b</italic>). Bottom: time-averaged value (––––: rapid fluctuations with a boxcar window of 10 µs; ······: slow fluctuations with one of 100 µs) of Reynolds stress at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.97 in CASTOR (<italic>c</italic>) and from simulation (<italic>d</italic>).</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>Plotting the time trace of the spectrally defined, instantaneous radial diffusion coefficient 
<inline-eqn><?TeX D = -{\langle \nsim {\vsim_{\,r}}\rangle}/{\nabla n} = -\rmi ({T}/{eB_{0}})(\sum_{k} n'_k \phi'^\ast _k k_y)/{({\partial {n'}}/{\partial x'})} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in017.gif"/></inline-eqn> for a simulation at ___ENT___ = 0 (outboard, see figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig04">4</figref>, chosen for reasons of clarity), we remark a phenomenon of intermittency [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib16">16</cite>]. The horizontal line on the bottom plot of figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig04">4</figref> represents the rms-value of the complete time sequence (<italic>D</italic><sub>rms</sub> = 1.61). Moments during which <italic>D</italic> is temporarily higher than this value can be identified as strong bursts with high particle loss (‘high activity’), in opposition to the ‘quiet’ periods.
<figure id="ppcf207268fig04" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig04.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig04.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc04" label="Figure 4"><p indent="no">Simulation at outboard (___ENT___ = 0). Top: instantaneous values of Reynolds stress (RS) (m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−2</sup>). Bottom: instantaneous turbulence driven diffusion coefficient (D) (m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>).</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>The rms-value at ___ENT___ = 0 is more than twice the value of the same quantity for a simulation at ___ENT___ = π/2 (see figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig07">7</figref>) and agrees well with the real experimentally observed anomalous particle diffusion (for CASTOR is the experimental value of <italic>D</italic> of the order of unity, expressed in metres square per second).</p>
        <p>During the ‘quiet’ periods we also see that the radial diffusion is strongly reduced (by a factor of 3 to the mean value, <italic>D</italic><sub>mean</sub> ≈ 0.9 m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>). Interestingly, the periods of strong diffusion seem to be accompanied by more Reynolds stress activity (instantaneous values, derived from a spectral ensemble average, represented as 
<inline-eqn><?TeX RS = \langle {\vsim_{\,r}} {\vsim_{\,\theta}}\rangle ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in018.gif"/></inline-eqn>), and vice versa. This means that the Reynolds stress and the turbulence driven diffusion coefficient are closely related. We are investigating this relationship more profoundly to clarify the link.</p>
        <p>The intermittent behaviour of the turbulence can be further analysed by way of the standard <italic>k</italic>-spectrum (figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig05">5</figref>). The figure depicts the <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> spectra at a certain moment (instantaneous) during the simulation, which falls in a situation of ‘high activity’ (figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig05">5(<italic>a</italic>)</figref>) or within a ‘quiet’ (figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig05">5(<italic>b</italic>)</figref>) window. We always see that a structure with <italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> &lt; <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> is present during the quiet periods. This structure is not present during the periods of high ‘activity’.
<figure id="ppcf207268fig05" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig05.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig05.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc05" label="Figure 5"><p indent="no">Instantaneous wavenumber-spectra for the potential fluctuations during (<italic>a</italic>) a turbulent situation (‘high activity’); (<italic>b</italic>) a possible ‘zonal flow’ (‘quiet’) situation.</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>A possible interpretation is that a zonal flow develops and that it temporarily quenches the turbulent ‘activity’. With the restrictions on the grid size, the condition for a zonal flow is rather difficult to verify on the wavenumber-spectrum (see peaks A and B on figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig05">5(<italic>b</italic>)</figref>).</p>
        <p>A simple snapshot of the grid (not shown in this paper, see [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib17">17</cite>]) at a moment where the turbulence is saturated reveals that the density and the potential fluctuations are out of phase. Furthermore, the density fluctuations always incorporate more small scale (turbulent) structures than the potential fluctuations. A typical cross-correlation coefficient between <italic>n</italic>′ and ___ENT___′ is ≈0.15, compared with ≈0.2–0.35 experimentally (depending on minor radius).</p>
        <p>A further cross-check of the code can be done by looking at the wavenumber–frequency spectrum shown in figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig06">6</figref>, derived from ohmical CASTOR data by the experimental two-point correlation technique, as proposed in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib18">18</cite>].
<figure id="ppcf207268fig06" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig06.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig06.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc06" label="Figure 6"><p indent="no">Wavenumber-frequency spectrum <italic>S</italic>(<italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub>, <italic>f</italic>) from CASTOR ((<italic>a</italic>) at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.97, (<italic>b</italic>) at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.88) and (<italic>c</italic>) from simulation. The ion diamagnetic direction is represented here in the positive direction.</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>The experiment (figures <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig06">6(<italic>a</italic>) and (<italic>b</italic>)</figref>) reveals a phase velocity, 
<inline-eqn><?TeX v^\ast_{\rm ph} = \omega / k ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in019.gif"/></inline-eqn>, of the order of 5 km s<sup>−1</sup> (at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.97) and −2 km s<sup>−1</sup> (at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.88) in the ion and electron diamagnetic direction, respectively, while the simulation gives <italic>v</italic><sub>ph</sub> = −2 km s<sup>−1</sup> (figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig06">6(<italic>c</italic>)</figref>). In the simulation, <italic>v</italic><sub>ph</sub> is only driven by the pressure gradient (
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\bnabla} p ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in020.gif"/></inline-eqn>) as there is no background radial electric field (
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\hbox{\bit E}}_r ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in021.gif"/></inline-eqn>) set in the code. Experimentally, 
<inline-eqn><?TeX v^\ast_{\rm ph} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in022.gif"/></inline-eqn> is related to both the 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\hbox{\bit E}}_r \times \vec{\hbox{\bit B}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in013.gif"/></inline-eqn> drift and the 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\bnabla} p \times \vec{\hbox{\bit B}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in023.gif"/></inline-eqn> velocity. Therefore, we compare the simulation result with figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig06">6(<italic>b</italic>)</figref>, made at <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.88 on CASTOR, where 
<inline-eqn><?TeX |\vec{\hbox{\bit E}}_r| ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in024.gif"/></inline-eqn> is minimal. The 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\bnabla} p \times \vec{\hbox{\bit B}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in023.gif"/></inline-eqn>-velocity in the edge in CASTOR is of the order of 1 km s<sup>−1</sup>, while the simulated 
<inline-eqn><?TeX v^\ast_{\rm ph} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in022.gif"/></inline-eqn> is twice as large as this
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\bnabla} p \times \vec{\hbox{\bit B}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in023.gif"/></inline-eqn> velocity and both in the electron diamagnetic direction as expected from the drift wave turbulence. At the location of <italic>r</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 0.97, the calculated 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\hbox{\bit E}}_r \times \vec{\hbox{\bit B}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in013.gif"/></inline-eqn> flow is around 4 km s<sup>−1</sup> (in the ion diamagnetic direction) and dominates clearly the phase velocity of the fluctuations in CASTOR at that position. This situation confirms studies in other tokamaks, as reported in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib19">19</cite>].</p>
      </sec-level2>
      <sec-level2 id="ppcf207268s2-2" label="2.2">
        <heading>Poloidal dependence of the Reynolds stress and the diffusion coefficient</heading>
        <p indent="no">We are now ready to analyse the dependence of the different quantities on the poloidal angle (___ENT___ = 0 at the low field side). Two effects have to be taken into account. Firstly the parameter <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> depends on <italic>B</italic>, so that it varies with ___ENT___. The same is true for the reference value used in the definition of the dimensionless parameters. Secondly the curvature operator 
<inline-eqn><?TeX {\mathcal{K'}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in025.gif"/></inline-eqn> depends explicitly on ___ENT___. In figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig07">7</figref> we show the computed rms-value of the Reynolds stress and the (in time) averaged diffusion coefficient. The time-window, over which the average is taken, is situated in the saturated regime and spans over several milliseconds. As can be seen, the curvature amplifies the effect that the normalization has on the fluctuations (comparison is represented for Reynolds stress only).
<figure id="ppcf207268fig07" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig07.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig07.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc07" label="Figure 7"><p indent="no">Reynolds stress (○: with curvature; ▿: without curvature) and diffusion coefficient (⋄) as a function of the poloidal angle of the centre of the domain. A curve of the form <italic>RS</italic><sub>HFS</sub>(1 + <italic>b</italic> cos<sup>2</sup>(___ENT___/2)) is fitted to the data.</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>Beside the exceptional outcome of the simulation at ___ENT___ = 0, one can fit the dependence of the Reynolds stress on ___ENT___ by a function of the form, <italic>RS</italic>(___ENT___) = <italic>RS</italic><sub>HFS</sub>(1 + <italic>b</italic> cos<sup>2</sup>(___ENT___/2)). The measurements being taken at the top of the tokamak (___ENT___ = π/2), we would then postulate the link, <italic>RS</italic><sub>EXP</sub> = <italic>RS</italic><sub>HFS</sub>(1+ (<italic>b</italic>/2)), between the model and experiment. <italic>RS</italic><sub>HFS</sub> = <italic>RS</italic><sub>___ENT___=π</sub> is the multiplying constant, approximately one tenth of the maximal value of the Reynolds stress close to the outboard plane, and <italic>b</italic> = 9 consequently. Checking numerically the flux-surface-average of the represented simulated points in figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig07">7</figref> against the flux-surface-average obtained with the proposed function, we see a difference of the order of 15%. We will thus use this model function when the flux surface averaged Reynolds stress is needed. Concerning the diffusion coefficient, we see—as expected—that the turbulent activity is stronger at the low field side of a tokamak.</p>
      </sec-level2>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="ppcf207268s3" label="3">
      <heading>The interaction between turbulence and background flow</heading>
      <p indent="no">We now come to the possible influence the turbulence has on the background flow. As demonstrated by Xu in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib06">6</cite>], in certain circumstances, the Reynolds stress can drive background flow. In this section we wish to further analyse this possibility and corroborate it by the CASTOR experiments.</p>
      <p>We start from the Braginskii equations [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib11">11</cite>] and follow the method originally proposed by Reynolds and used by Peeters [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib20">20</cite>], writing the fluid velocity 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{{\bit v}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in026.gif"/></inline-eqn> and the density <italic>n</italic> as a mean plus a fluctuating part (
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{{\bit v}} = \underline{\mathop{\vec{\bit v}}} + \vec{\bvsim} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in027.gif"/></inline-eqn>, <italic>n</italic> = <underline>n</underline> + ≁). The mean is defined as a time-average, <underline>x</underline> = ⟨<italic>x</italic>⟩<sub>τ</sub>, with the timescale of averaging τ large compared with the timescale of the fluctuations but short with respect to any macroscopical timescale. 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\hbox{\bit U}} = \underline{\vec{\bit v}} +(\underline{\mathop{\nsim \vec{\bvsim}}}/{\underline{n}}) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in028.gif"/></inline-eqn> is called the total velocity and transforms the total momentum equation in the form (higher order terms in fluctuations are neglected)
<display-eqn id="ppcf207268eq003" eqnnum="3"><?TeX \[
\begin{equation}
 \fl m \frac{\partial }{\partial t}
{(\underline{n}\ \, \vec{\!\!\hbox{\bit U}}\,)} + m
\vec{\bnabla}\cdot (\underline{n}\ \, \vec{\!\!\hbox{\bit U}}
\ \, \vec{\!\!\hbox{\bit U}}\,) + m \vec{\bnabla}\cdot (\underline{n}\,
\underline{\vec{\bvsim}\vec{\bvsim}}) +
\underline{\vec{\bnabla}\cdot\ \vec{\vec{\!\!\hbox{\bit P}}}} =
\underline{\vec{\hbox{\bit J}}}\times
\vec{\hbox{\bit B}} - m(\underline{n} \nu^\ast)\ \, \vec{\!\hbox{\bit 
U}},\end{equation}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268de003.gif"/></display-eqn>
in which 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\bnabla}\cdot (\underline{n}\,\underline{\vec{\bvsim}\vec{\bvsim}}) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in029.gif"/></inline-eqn> is the Reynolds stress term and 
<inline-eqn><?TeX m(\underline{n} \nu^\ast)\vec{\!\hbox{\bit U}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in030.gif"/></inline-eqn> is the neutral friction force with <underline>n</underline> ν<sup>*</sup> = <underline>n</underline> (<italic>n</italic><sub>neutrals</sub> ⟨σ · <italic>v</italic>⟩), the neutral friction coefficient [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib21">21</cite>]. The other symbols have their usual meaning.</p>
      <p>With the same definition, it is possible to write the continuity equation in the form, 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \partial_t \underline{n}+\vec{\bnabla}\cdot (\underline{n} \vec{\hbox{\bit U}})=0 ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in031.gif"/></inline-eqn>. Expressing this equation in toroidal coordinates ((<italic>r</italic>, ___ENT___, υ), denoting the radial, poloidal and toroidal coordinates, respectively), and restricting the model to a circular poloidal cross-section as in CASTOR, one can define the flux-surface-averaged poloidal rotation, ⟨<italic>U</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub>⟩<sub>flux</sub> = (<italic>F</italic>(<italic>r</italic>)/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>), and write the poloidal velocity as <italic>U</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> = (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>/<italic>R</italic>)(<italic>F</italic>(<italic>r</italic>)/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>), where use is made of the flux surface average operation, defined as 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \langle X\rangle_{\rm flux} = ({1}/{2\pi R_0 2\pi r})\int_{\varphi}\int_{\theta} X r\,\rmd \theta R\, {\rmd} \varphi = ({1}/{2\pi R_0})\int_{\theta} X R\,\rmd \theta ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in032.gif"/></inline-eqn>, and where <italic>R</italic> = <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> + <italic>r</italic> cos ___ENT___.</p>
      <p>The turbulence is supposed to be electrostatic [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib08">8</cite>], so that 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \vec{\bvsim} =({1}/{B^2})(\vec{\hbox{\bit B}} \times \vec{\bnabla} \phisim) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in001.gif"/></inline-eqn> lies in the perpendicular plane. An important consequence of this statement is that 
<inline-eqn><?TeX {{\vsim}_{\parallel}} = 0 ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in033.gif"/></inline-eqn>, so that 
<inline-eqn><?TeX {{\vsim}_{\varphi}} = -\Theta {{\vsim}_{\theta}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in034.gif"/></inline-eqn> (Θ = tan α, with α the pitch of the magnetic field). This results finally in a rather simple form for the Reynolds stress terms in the toroidal and parallel components of equation (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq003">3</eqnref>). It is easy to show that one can write the complete Reynolds stress tensor in function of the covariance between the two fluctuating velocities (
<inline-eqn><?TeX RS = \underline{{{\vsim}_{\,r}}\, {{\vsim}_{\,\theta}}} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in035.gif"/></inline-eqn>, commonly called the Reynolds stress) and of the two variances 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \underline{{\vsim}_{r}^2} \simeq \underline{(-\nabla_\theta {\phisim}/B)^2} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in036.gif"/></inline-eqn> and 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \underline{{\vsim}_{\theta}^2} \simeq \underline{(\nabla_r {\phisim}/B)^2} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in037.gif"/></inline-eqn>.</p>
      <p>Taking the divergence of this tensor, and projecting equation (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq003">3</eqnref>) on the toroidal and parallel direction, we can write an equation for <italic>F</italic>(<italic>r</italic>), or—equivalently—the flux-surface-averaged poloidal velocity [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib22" range="bib22,bib23,bib24">22–24</cite>]. As we only wish to model a narrow radial layer we take the safety factor <italic>q</italic> to be constant. With a poloidal dependence for the Reynolds stress established in the previous section, we find
<display-eqn id="ppcf207268eq004" eqnnum="4"><?TeX \[
\begin{eqnarray}
 \fl {\frac{\partial }{\partial
t}}\left(\frac{F(r)}{R_0} \right)= - \frac{B_{0}}{\underline{n}
m(1+2q^2)} \langle{J_r}\rangle_{\rm flux} - \frac{1}{\underline{n}
(1+2q^2)}\frac{1}{r} \frac{\partial }{\partial r}\left(r
\underline{n} \left(1+\frac{b}{2}\right) (\underline{{{\vsim}_{r}} {\vsim}_{\theta}})_{\rm HFS}\right)\nonumber\\
\ms - \nu
^\ast \frac{F(r)}{R_0} - \frac{1}{\underline{n} \Theta m B_0
(1+2q^2)}C \left({\frac{F(r)}{R_0}}-U_{\rm Neo}\right).\end{eqnarray}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268de004.gif"/></display-eqn>
In this equation, the convection has been neglected and the viscosity is reduced to 
<inline-eqn><?TeX \langle \vec{\hbox{\bit B}}\cdot \vec{\bnabla}\cdot \vec{\vec{\bpi}}\rangle_{\rm flux}= ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in038.gif"/></inline-eqn><italic>C</italic> · ((<italic>F</italic>(<italic>r</italic>)/<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) − <italic>U</italic><sub>Neo</sub>), where for the collisional regime 
<inline-eqn><?TeX C= B_{0}\case{3}{2}({\Theta \eta_{0}}/{R_{0}^2}) ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in039.gif"/></inline-eqn> and <italic>U</italic><sub>Neo</sub> = (−2.1/<italic>Z</italic> <italic>e</italic> <italic>B</italic><sub>0</sub>)(∂<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>/∂<italic>r</italic>) [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib22">22</cite>].</p>
      <p>When comparing this equation with the form proposed by Diamond in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib05">5</cite>] (
<inline-eqn><?TeX \partial_t \langle {V_\theta} \rangle = \langle \partial_r (\tilde{V}_r \tilde{V}_\theta)\rangle ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268in040.gif"/></inline-eqn>) and also used in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib06">6</cite>], the most conspicuous difference, apart from the presence of additional source and sink terms, is the presence of the neo-classical factor (1 + 2<italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup>). This factor importantly reduces the influence of the Reynolds stress with respect to the prediction of [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib05">5</cite>] as it is of the order of 10–100 in the edge of a tokamak. The poloidal dependence of the Reynolds stress does not compensate this factor. It is also clear that a poloidal dependence of the form <italic>f</italic>(___ENT___) = <italic>RS</italic><sub>HFS</sub>(1 + <italic>b</italic> cos<sup>2</sup>(___ENT___/2)) does not lead to a different result compared with a homogeneous distribution of the Reynolds stress as previously used in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib07">7</cite>]. It is noteworthy to mention the importance of the place where the fluctuation measurements are taken. A measurement at the top of the tokamak is a good approximation for the flux-surface-average of the Reynolds stress.</p>
      <sec-level2 id="ppcf207268s3-1" label="3.1">
        <heading>Confronting the model with data taken at CASTOR and HT-6M</heading>
        <p indent="no">To investigate the possible role of Reynolds stress in driving rotation, a quite promising campaign was held at HT-6M by Xu <italic>et al</italic> and reported in [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib06">6</cite>]. Turbulence was imposed by a turbulent heating (TH) pulse, creating temporarily very steep gradients in the Reynolds stress strength. The drawbacks of this campaign, however, were the uncertainty about the absolute magnitude of the poloidal velocity and the possibility that the TH pulse induces not only electrostatic turbulence in the edge. Indeed, imposing a TH pulse could result also in a non-negligible electromagnetic component of the turbulence (Maxwell stresses). The eventual conclusion, based on an analysis using the model of [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib05">5</cite>] was however that the Reynolds stress was responsible for the observed rotation.</p>
        <p>To further corroborate these conclusions and to validate our model (equation (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq004">4</eqnref>)), where the additional effect of the neoclassical factor is present, we will now further analyse the obtained CASTOR data. Ohmic shots in an hydrogen-plasma were performed with machine parameters as mentioned above, but with high <italic>q</italic>-values (<italic>q</italic> = 15) to stress in particular the effect of <italic>q</italic> in the equation (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq004">4</eqnref>). We limit our analysis to Ohmic shots, since our turbulence code assumes a fixed background density profile, prohibiting any transition-inducing scenario. Moreover, during the biasing phase itself, the Reynolds stress influence is completely overwhelmed by the biasing-induced radial current torque (see also [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib07">7</cite>]).</p>
        <p>Figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig08">8</figref> shows a typical radial profile of the Reynolds stress and its gradient for such an Ohmic scenario. The full line is the radial derivative of the different markers, being the average of all individual measurements of the Reynolds stress at that radius. The error-bars on the plots are obtained by comparing several reproducible shots. The Reynolds stress is of the same order of the one measured in HT-6M [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib06">6</cite>], but the gradient is less pronounced and the error-bars are more important. The gradient develops a few millimetres inside the separatrix; the error-bars in this region are also the largest.
<figure id="ppcf207268fig08" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig08.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig08.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc08" label="Figure 8"><p indent="no">Top: a snapshot of Reynolds stress measurements by the two different triplets (123) and (345), at <italic>t</italic> = 12.9 ms. Bottom: radial gradient of Reynolds stress in Ohmic discharges</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>To check the prediction of our 1D fluid model, we apply the measured Reynolds stresses in equation (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq004">4</eqnref>) and obtain the results shown in figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig09">9</figref>, using the real values of <italic>q</italic>, η<sub>0</sub> and <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> and supposing a neutral density of 10<sup>16</sup> m<sup>−3</sup> everywhere. Note that figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig08">8</figref> only shows a snapshot of the Reynolds stress, while figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig09">9</figref> uses the different actual successive values of the Reynolds stresses between 12 and 13 ms to compute the poloidal velocity profile as a function of time. Because the plasma is during these Ohmic shots in a rather stationary state, no appreciable difference exists between these snapshots of the Reynolds stress.
<figure id="ppcf207268fig09" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig09.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/ppcf207268fig09.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="ppcf207268fc09" label="Figure 9"><p indent="no">Poloidal velocities, simulated by equation (<eqnref linkend="ppcf207268eq004">4</eqnref>), starting from the measured profile at <italic>t</italic> = 12 ms with the real <italic>q</italic>-values and with the mean gradient derived from shot to shot.</p></caption></figure></p>
        <p>We see a clear damping of the flow close to the separatrix and an acceleration of the flow further inside. This acceleration can only be due to the Reynolds stress. Moreover, to obtain this result we took the real value of <italic>q</italic> (in CASTOR the shots were done at a large <italic>q</italic>(<italic>a</italic>) ≃ 15) and used the successive profiles from figure <figref linkend="ppcf207268fig08">8</figref> at the subsequent times. If <italic>q</italic> is taken equal to zero (reducing our model to a cylindrical approximation), we obtain accelerations that are two orders of magnitude too high and which cannot be damped by increasing the neutral density as then the damping close to the separatrix would be far too high, so that the flows would be reduced to zero over the simulated length of time. This is not experimentally observed, so we tend to conclude that the factor of 1+2<italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup> seems to be justified in this case.</p>
        <p>A rather severe consequence of this reasoning is that we do not believe that gradients in electrostatic Reynolds stress, in the amount that they are present (and measurable with Langmuir probes) on different tokamaks [<cite linkend="ppcf207268bib25">25</cite>], can be solely responsible for a macroscopic poloidal <italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> = 0 acceleration. Our model confirms that a radial gradient in the Reynolds stress is indeed a driving term, capable of sustaining a certain poloidal velocity in the steady state, but—on the other hand—its raw strength is divided by the factor 1 + 2<italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup> with respect to driving the flux-surface-averaged poloidal velocity. However, this conclusion on the <italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> = 0 component does not impede the Reynolds stress's local drive of a zonal flow.</p>
      </sec-level2>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="ppcf207268s4" label="4">
      <heading>Conclusion</heading>
      <p indent="no">Our turbulence model leads to relevant results with respect to the measurements made at the edge in CASTOR. Although the level of the fluctuations is slightly too low (one order of magnitude for the Reynolds stress), the correlation time and the turbulence driven diffusion coefficient can be simulated in accordance with the experimentally observed values. Besides this, the simulations show an intermittent behaviour of the turbulence, as is found as well on CASTOR. The model predicts the (temporary) existence of zonal flows in the saturated state of the turbulence, during which the anomalous diffusion is reduced.</p>
      <p>The extension of this comparison with the experiment towards the full poloidal cross section leads to a model function that we used in the 1D fluid description to compute the flux-surface-averaged influence of the Reynolds stress.</p>
      <p>From our 1D fluid description, we conclude that the driving force, coming from the electrostatic Reynolds stresses, is divided by 1 + 2<italic>q</italic><sup>2</sup> for what concerns the <italic>k</italic><sub>___ENT___</sub> = 0 component of the poloidal velocity. The comparison between the model and the experiment (Ohmic regime) confirms the driving capabilities of a gradient in the Reynolds stress profile. Nevertheless, the factor makes it hard to believe that gradients in the electrostatic Reynolds stress, in the amount that they are measured in the edge of present tokamaks, can be solely responsible for the major poloidal acceleration in the edge, invoking a steady shear layer and consequently a L- to H-mode transition.</p>
    </sec-level1>
  </body>
  <back>
    <references>
      <heading>References</heading>
      <reference-list type="numeric">
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib01" num="1">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Wootton</second-name>
              <first-names>A</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1990</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Fluids</jnl-title>
          <part>B</part>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <pages>2879</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib02" num="2">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Weynants</second-name>
              <first-names>R R</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1993</year>
          <conf-title>20th EPS Conf. on Controlled Fusion and Plasma Physics (Lisbon, Portugal, 26–30 July 1993)</conf-title>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <pages>B177</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib03" num="3">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Burrell</second-name>
              <first-names>K</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1994</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <pages>1536</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib04" num="4">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Jachmich</second-name>
              <first-names>S</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1998</year>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <pages>1105</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib05" num="5">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Diamond</second-name>
              <first-names>P H</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1991</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Fluids</jnl-title>
          <part>B</part>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <pages>1626</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib06" num="6">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Xu</second-name>
              <first-names>Y H</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2000</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <pages>3867</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib07" num="7">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Vergote</second-name>
              <first-names>M</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2005</year>
          <jnl-title>Czech J. Phys.</jnl-title>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <pages>389</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib08" num="8">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Wakatani</second-name>
              <first-names>M</first-names>
            </au>
            <au>
              <second-name>Hasegawa</second-name>
              <first-names>A</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1984</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Fluids</jnl-title>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <pages>611</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib09" num="9">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Scott</second-name>
              <first-names>B</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2001</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <pages>447</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib10" num="10">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Naulin</second-name>
              <first-names>V</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2004</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <part>A</part>
          <volume>321</volume>
          <pages>355</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib11" num="11">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Braginskii</second-name>
              <first-names>S I</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1965</year>
          <art-title>Transport processes in a plasma</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Rev. Plasma Phys.</jnl-title>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <pages>205</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <book-ref id="ppcf207268bib12" num="12">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Kadomtsev</second-name>
              <first-names>B B</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1965</year>
          <book-title>Plasma Turbulence</book-title>
          <publication>
            <place>London</place>
            <publisher>Academic</publisher>
          </publication>
        </book-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib13" num="13">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Smith</second-name>
              <first-names>S A</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1997</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <pages>978</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="ppcf207268bib14" num="14">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Hron</second-name>
              <first-names>M</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2003</year>
          <conf-title>30th EPS Conf. on Controlled Fusion and Plasma Physics</conf-title>
          <conf-place>St Petersburg, Russia, 7–11 July 2003</conf-place>
          <volume>vol 27A</volume>
          <pages>P1-1.172</pages>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib15" num="15">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Scott</second-name>
              <first-names>B</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2003</year>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <pages>A385</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib16" num="16">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Duran</second-name>
              <first-names>I</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2000</year>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <part>B</part>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <pages>1693</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="ppcf207268bib17" num="17">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Vergote</second-name>
              <first-names>M</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2005</year>
          <conf-title>32nd EPS Conf. on Controlled Fusion and Plasma Physics</conf-title>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib18" num="18">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Beall</second-name>
              <first-names>J M</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1982</year>
          <jnl-title>J. Appl. Phys.</jnl-title>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <pages>3933</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib19" num="19">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Ritz Ch</second-name>
              <first-names>P</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1984</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Fluids</jnl-title>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <pages>2956</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib20" num="20">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Peeters</second-name>
              <first-names>A G</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1998</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <pages>763</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <book-ref id="ppcf207268bib21" num="21">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Harrison</second-name>
              <first-names>M</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1986</year>
          <book-title>Physics of Plasma-wall Interactions in Controlled Fusion</book-title>
          <series>NATO ASI of Ser.
<volume>vol B 131</volume></series>
          <publication>
            <place>New York</place>
            <publisher>Plenum</publisher>
          </publication>
        </book-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib22" num="22">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Cornelis</second-name>
              <first-names>J</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1994</year>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <pages>171</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib23" num="23">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Boozer</second-name>
              <first-names>A</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1976</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Fluids</jnl-title>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <pages>149</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <book-ref id="ppcf207268bib24" num="24">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Balescu</second-name>
              <first-names>R</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1988</year>
          <book-title>Transport Processes in Plasmas</book-title>
          <publication>
            <place>Amsterdam</place>
            <publisher>North-Holland</publisher>
          </publication>
        </book-ref>
        <journal-ref id="ppcf207268bib25" num="25">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Hidalgo</second-name>
              <first-names>C</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1999</year>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <pages>2203</pages>
        </journal-ref>
      </reference-list>
    </references>
  </back>
</article>
