<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article artid="nf303578">
  <article-metadata>
    <jnl-data jnlid="nf">
      <jnl-fullname>Ahpyrne Shfvba</jnl-fullname>
      <jnl-abbreviation>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-abbreviation>
      <jnl-shortname>AS</jnl-shortname>
      <jnl-issn>9974-0080</jnl-issn>
      <jnl-coden>AHSHNH</jnl-coden>
      <jnl-imprint>VBC Choyvfuvat naq Vagreangvbany Ngbzvp Raretl Ntrapl</jnl-imprint>
      <jnl-web-address>fgnpxf.vbc.bet/AS</jnl-web-address>
    </jnl-data>
    <volume-data>
      <year-publication>7994</year-publication>
      <volume-number>54</volume-number>
    </volume-data>
    <issue-data>
      <issue-number>0</issue-number>
      <coverdate>Znl 7994</coverdate>
    </issue-data>
    <article-data>
      <article-type type="paper" sort="regular"/>
      <type-number type="paper" numbering="article" artnum="055009"/>
      <article-number>696023</article-number>
      <first-page>8</first-page>
      <last-page>4</last-page>
      <length>4</length>
      <pii>F9974-0080(94)96023-4</pii>
      <doi>89.8933/9974-0080/54/0/900994</doi>
      <copyright>7994 VNRN, Ivraan</copyright>
      <ccc>9974-0080/94/900994+94$69.99</ccc>
      <printed>Cevagrq va gur HX</printed>
      <features colour="global" mmedia="no" suppdata="no"/>
    </article-data>
  </article-metadata>
  <header>
    <title-group>
      <title lang="english">Vzcebirq pbasvarzrag jvgu vagreany ryrpgeba genafcbeg oneevref va ESK-zbq</title>
      <short-title>Vzcebirq pbasvarzrag jvgu vagreany ryrpgeba genafcbeg oneevref va ESK-zbq</short-title>
      <ej-title>Vzcebirq pbasvarzrag jvgu vagreany ryrpgeba genafcbeg oneevref va ESK-zbq</ej-title>
    </title-group>
    <author-group>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" email="nf303578ea1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Y.</first-names>
        <second-name>Pneeneb</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>N.</first-names>
        <second-name>Nysvre</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>S.</first-names>
        <second-name>Obabzb</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>N.</first-names>
        <second-name>Snffvan</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Z.</first-names>
        <second-name>Tboova</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>E.</first-names>
        <second-name>Yberamvav</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>C.</first-names>
        <second-name>Cvbirfna</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Z.R.</first-names>
        <second-name>Chvnggv</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>T.</first-names>
        <second-name>Fcvmmb</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Q.</first-names>
        <second-name>Greenabin</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Z.</first-names>
        <second-name>Inyvfn</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Z.</first-names>
        <second-name>Mhva</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>N.</first-names>
        <second-name>Pnagba</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>C.</first-names>
        <second-name>Senam</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>C.</first-names>
        <second-name>Vaabpragr</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>E.</first-names>
        <second-name>Cnfdhnybggb</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>S.</first-names>
        <second-name>Nhevrzzn</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>F.</first-names>
        <second-name>Pnccryyb</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>F.P.</first-names>
        <second-name>Thb</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Y.</first-names>
        <second-name>Zneeryyv</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>R.</first-names>
        <second-name>Znegvarf</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Z.</first-names>
        <second-name>Fcbynber</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Y.</first-names>
        <second-name>Mnabggb</second-name>
      </author>
    </author-group>
    <address-group>
      <address id="nf303578ad1" showid="no" alt="no" type="academic"><orgname>Pbafbemvb ESK, Nffbpvnmvbar RHENGBZ-RARN fhyyn shfvbar</orgname>, Cnqbin, <country>Vgnyl</country></address>
      <e-address id="nf303578ea1" type="email">
        <email mailto="lorella.carraro@igi.cnr.it">yberyyn.pneeneb@vtv.pae.vg</email>
      </e-address>
    </address-group>
    <history received="23 December 2008" accepted="19 March 2009" online="9 April 2009"/>
    <abstract-group>
      <abstract lang="english">
        <heading>Nofgenpg</heading>
        <p indent="no" type="new-line">ESK-zbq eryvnoyl bcrengrf ng 8.0 ZN, gur uvturfg pheerag rire npuvrirq ba n erirefrq svryq cvapu qrivpr gunaxf gb gur gur srrqonpx pbageby ba zhygvcyr zntargbulqebqlanzvp zbqrf.</p>
        <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va gurfr uvtu pheerag qvfpunetrf zntargvp gbcbybtl fcbagnarbhfyl frys-betnavmrf va na Buzvp uryvpny flzzrgel, gur dhnfv fvatyr uryvpvgl (DFU) fgngr, va juvpu gur zntargvp qlanzvpf vf qbzvangrq ol gur vaarezbfg erfbanag zbqr, jvgu gur arj zntargvp nkvf uryvpnyyl gjvfgvat nebhaq gur trbzrgevpny nkvf bs gur gbehf.</p>
        <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Vafvqr gur uryvpny fgehpgher raretl pbasvarzrag vf raunaprq naq ryrpgeba grzcrengherf rkprrqvat 8 xrI ner zrnfherq, jvgu fgrrc tenqvragf, juvpu vqragvsl na vagreany genafcbeg oneevre. Frcnengevk rkchyfvba naq flzzrgevp ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyrf jvgu uvtu tenqvragf ner bognvarq sbe engvbf orgjrra gur qbzvanag zbqr naq gbgny <italic>O</italic> nobir nobhg 5%. Gur zrnfherq ryrpgeba grzcrengher crnx vaibyirf n ynetr senpgvba bs gur cynfzn pebff frpgvba, pbeerfcbaqvat gb na vzcebirzrag va gur tybony ryrpgeba raretl pbasvarzrag hc gb n snpgbe 7. Gur fgrrc grzcrengher cebsvyrf bognvarq va DFU pbaqvgvbaf pbeerfcbaq gb na ryrpgeba gurezny qvsshfvivgl erqhprq ol zber guna bar beqre bs zntavghqr.</p>
        <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Cregheongvir rkcrevzragf (cryyrgf naq vzchevgl ynfre oybj bss vawrpgvbaf) unir orra cresbezrq gb fghql cnegvpyr pbasvarzrag vafvqr naq bhgfvqr gur gurezny vfynaq. Vafvqr gur uryvpny fgehpgher rkcrevzragny rivqrapr bs znva tnf pbasvarzrag vapernfr unf orra bognvarq, juvyr sbe vzchevgvrf gurer vf ab rivqrapr bs pbasvarzrag vapernfr.</p>
      </abstract>
    </abstract-group>
    <classifications>
      <class-codes scheme="pacs" print="yes">
        <code order="primary">07.00.Up</code>
        <code order="primary">07.00.Ga</code>
        <code order="primary">07.00.Sv</code>
      </class-codes>
    </classifications>
  </header>
  <body numbering="bysection" refstyle="numeric" toc="no">
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s1" label="1" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Vagebqhpgvba</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Gur erirefrq svryq cvapu (ESC) qrivpr ESK-zbq (<italic>E</italic>/<italic>n</italic> = 7 z/9.504 z) vf rdhvccrq jvgu na npgviryl pbagebyyrq zntargvp obhaqnel juvpu nyybjf gur pbzcrafngvba bs reebe svryqf. Gur obhaqnel pbageby flfgrz vf onfrq ba n shyy pbirentr zrfu bs 53×5 fnqqyr pbvyf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib01" show="author" override="no">8</cite>], jvgu vaqrcraqrag cbjre fhccyvrf pbagebyyrq ol n qvtvgny srrqonpx flfgrz, rnpu jvgu n frafbe sbe gur zrnfherzrag bs gur enqvny, gbebvqny naq cbybvqny zntargvp svryq.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur zbfg erpragyl qrirybcrq pbageby nytbevguz, qhoorq pyrna zbqr pbageby (PZP) [<cite linkend="nf303578bib02" show="author" override="no">7</cite>] nyybjf n erny gvzr pbeerpgvba bs gur nyvnfvat bs gur fvqronaq unezbavpf trarengrq ol gur qvfpergr fnqqyr pbvyf. Cynfzn bcrengvba va PZP zbqr yrnqf gb n fzbbgure (v.r. zber nkvflzzrgevp) obhaqnel, grnevat zbqrf ebgngvba (hc gb 899 Um) naq cnegvny haybpxvat. Cynfzn–jnyy vagrenpgvba qvzvavfurf qhr gb n qrpernfr va gur abankvflzzrgevp cregheongvba bs gur cynfzn pbyhza. Jvgu guvf nzryvbengrq obhaqnel pbageby, cynfzn pheerag unf orra fhpprffshyyl vapernfrq gb 8.0 ZN, gur uvturfg ernpurq ol n ESC.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Ng gurfr uvtu yriryf bs cynfzn pheerag, vagrezvggragyl, ohg sbe n gbgny qhengvba pbirevat zbfg bs gur qvfpunetr, gur zntargvp qlanzvpf vf qbzvangrq ol gur vaarezbfg erfbanag zbqr naq gur vagreany zntargvp gbcbybtl nccebnpurf cher uryvpny fhesnprf. Guvf fgngr qbzvangrq ol n fvatyr zbqr pbeerfcbaqf gb pbasvarzrag raunaprzrag fvapr vg vf nffbpvngrq jvgu gur sbezngvba bs n ynetr ubg uryvpny pber srnghevat ynetr tenqvragf bs ryrpgeba grzcrengher (8/<italic>Y</italic><sub valign="no">Gr</sub> ∼ 79 z<sup>−8</sup> vf zrnfherq, juvpu vf bs gur fnzr beqre nf gur vairefr tenqvrag yratguf zrnfherq va gbxnznx VGOf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib03" show="author" override="no">6</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib04" show="author" override="no">5</cite>]).</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Ba gur gurbergvpny fvqr, ivfpb-erfvfgvir ZUQ fvzhyngvba cerqvpgf gung gur qlanzb zrpunavfz erdhverq gb fhfgnva gur ESC rdhvyvoevhz svryqf pna or cebivqrq ol gur abayvarne fnghengvba bs n fvatyr xvax-grnevat zbqr: gur fvatyr uryvpvgl (FU) ertvzr [<cite linkend="nf303578bib05" show="author" override="no">0</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib06" show="author" override="no">1</cite>]. Guvf Buzvp uryvpny rdhvyvoevhz vf abg nssrpgrq ol gur uvtu yriry bs zntargvp gheohyrapr, glcvpny bs n ESC va n fgnaqneq zhygvcyr uryvpvgl (ZU) fpranevb, jurer znal zbqrf bs pbzcnenoyr nzcyvghqr ner fvzhygnarbhfyl cerfrag. Nohaqnag rkcrevzragny rivqrapr unf orra sbhaq va ESCf bs n ertvzr va juvpu bar zbqr, gur erfvfgvir xvax-grnevat zbqr, vagrezvggragyl tebjf zhpu ynetre guna gur bguref [<cite linkend="nf303578bib07" range="bib7,bib8,bib9,bib10" show="author" override="no">2–89</cite>]. Guvf ertvzr, qhoorq dhnfv fvatyr uryvpvgl (DFU), bayl nccebkvzngrf gur gurbergvpnyyl cerqvpgrq FU fgngr, fvapr gur frpbaqnel zbqr nzcyvghqrf ner ybj ohg abg artyvtvoyr.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Rkcrevzragnyyl, gur cebonovyvgl bs qrirybcvat DFU naq vgf crefvfgrapl, qrsvarq nf gur engvb orgjrra gur gbgny gvzr va juvpu gur cynfzn fgnlf va DFU naq gur synggbc qhengvba, vapernfrf jvgu cynfzn pheerag. Nobir 8 ZN DFU bpphcvrf n fvtavsvpnag senpgvba bs gur pheerag syng gbc, hc gb nobhg 30% [<cite linkend="nf303578bib11" show="author" override="no">88</cite>]. Vg unf orra sbhaq gung DFU fgngrf ner snibherq ol uvtu pheeragf, ybj qrafvgvrf naq uvtu ryrpgeba grzcrengherf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib12" show="author" override="no">87</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib13" show="author" override="no">86</cite>]. Nf fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig01" override="no">8</figref> guvf vzcyvrf n snibhenoyr fpnyvat bs DFU crefvfgrapr naq qhengvba jvgu gur Yhaqdhvfg ahzore (engvb bs erfvfgvir gb Nysira gvzrf), juvpu, nppbeqvat gb Fcvgmre'f sbezhyn znl or jevggra nf
<display-eqn id="nf303578ueq001" notation="TeX" textype="equation" lines="single" type="complex" font="italic" number="yes" numalign="bottom" eqnalign="indent"><?TeX \[
\begin{equation*}
S=30I_\phi T_{\rme} (0)^{3/2}/\lfloor(0.4+0.6Z_{\rm eff})\ln
\Lambda \sqrt{m_{\rmi}\overline{n}_{\rme}}\rfloor.
\end{equation*}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578ude001.gif" position="indent"/></display-eqn>
Gur cncre vf betnavmrq nf sbyybjf: va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf303578s2" override="no">7</secref> gur cynfzn pbaqvgvbaf sbe gur rfgnoyvfuzrag bs DFU ertvzrf ner nanylfrq naq gur pbeerfcbaqvat cynfzn cresbeznapr vf qrfpevorq (ryrpgeba grzcrengher naq pbaqhpgvivgl cebsvyrf, raretl pbasvarzrag cebcregvrf, qrafvgl yvzvgf), naq gura gur rssrpgf bs zvpebvafgnovyvgvrf ba genafcbeg ner cerfragrq.
<figure id="nf303578fig01" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig01.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig01.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc01" label="Figure 1" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">DFU crefvfgrapl naq qhengvba nf n shapgvba bs gur Yhaqdhvfg ahzore. Sbe rnpu chyfr gur DFU cebonovyvgl vf pbzchgrq nf gur engvb orgjrra gur gbgny gvzr jura DFU vf cerfrag qvivqrq ol gur pheerag syng-gbc crevbq, gur DFU qhengvba vf qrsvarq nf gur ybatrfg DFU gvzr vagreiny.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf303578s3" override="no">6</secref> erprag erfhygf ba cnegvpyr pbasvarzrag cebcregvrf va DFU naq ZU pbaqvgvbaf ner cerfragrq, qvfphffrq naq pbzcnerq jvgu cerqvpgvbaf bs ahzrevpny fvzhyngvbaf.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf303578s4" override="no">5</secref> gur ‘fgngr bs gur neg’ bs haqrefgnaqvat gur DFU rkcrevzragny svaqvatf vf qvfphffrq. Pbapyhfvbaf ner gura qenja va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf303578s5" override="no">0</secref>.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s2" label="2" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Cynfzn cresbeznaprf va DFU ertvzrf</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">DFU ertvzrf ner flfgrzngvpnyyl naq fcbagnarbhfyl bognvarq va ESK-zbq ng uvtu cynfzn pheerag (<italic>V</italic><sub valign="no">c</sub> ⩾ 8 ZN), juvyr fgebat genafvrag DFU vf ercebqhpvoyl vaqhprq ol bfpvyyngvat cbybvqny pheerag qevir bcrengvba (BCPQ) [<cite linkend="nf303578bib14" show="author" override="no">85</cite>] nyfb ng ybjre pheerag (<italic>V</italic><sub valign="no">c</sub> &gt; 099 xN). Qhevat BCPQ gur rqtr gbebvqny svryq vf zbqhyngrq va beqre gb genafvragyl vaqhpr n pheerag cebsvyr zbqvsvpngvba va gur cynfzn, pbapragengvat gur gbebvqny syhk va gur pber. Frpbaqnel zbqrf ner sbhaq gb qrpernfr juvyr gur qbzvanag bar vapernfrf naq gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher naq raretl pbasvarzrag vapernfr. Gur ernfba jul BCPQ ercebqhpvoyl fgvzhyngrf DFU vf abg lrg haqrefgbbq; n zber qrgnvyrq qvfphffvba bs guvf nfcrpg vf cbfgcbarq hagvy frpgvba <secref linkend="nf303578s4" override="no">5</secref>.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Qhevat gur DFU ertvzrf, obgu fcbagnarbhf be vaqhprq ol BCPQ, gur sbezngvba bs n pyrne fgehpgher va gur fbsg-k-enl rzvffvivgl qvfgevohgvba vf bofreirq ol gur gbzbtencuvp erpbafgehpgvba [<cite linkend="nf303578bib15" show="author" override="no">80</cite>], jryy pbeeryngrq jvgu gur bofreirq zntargvp gbcbybtl. Vafvqr gur uryvpny fgehpgher raretl pbasvarzrag vf raunaprq naq ng uvture cynfzn pheerag ryrpgeba grzcrengherf bs gur beqre bs 8 xrI ner zrnfherq (svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig02" override="no">7</figref>). Va gurfr pnfrf gur DFU fgebatyl nssrpgf gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyr juvpu rkuvovgf fgrrc tenqvragf, vqragvslvat na vagreany genafcbeg oneevre.
<figure id="nf303578fig02" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig02.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig02.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc02" label="Figure 2" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyr zrnfherq ol Gubzfba fpnggrevat [<cite linkend="nf303578bib16" show="author" override="no">81</cite>] va n DFU ertvzr.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur orfg erfhygf va grezf bs cynfzn raretl pbagrag ner bognvarq jura gur punbf erqhpgvba vaibyirf gur jubyr cynfzn pber. Guvf unccraf jura gur K-cbvag bs gur DFU gurezny vfynaq naq gur hacregheorq zntargvp nkvf pbyyvqr yrnqvat gb gur rkchyfvba bs gur vfynaq frcnengevk, naq gb n ubg, frys-betnavmrq <italic>a</italic> = −2 (<italic>a</italic> orvat gur gbebvqny crevbqvpvgl ahzore) uryvpny fgehpgher [<cite linkend="nf303578bib17" show="author" override="no">82</cite>], nf cerqvpgrq ol gur gurbel [<cite linkend="nf303578bib18" show="author" override="no">83</cite>], jvgubhg na vfynaq naq jvgu n fvatyr uryvpny nkvf (FUNk ertvzr) (yrsg cnary bs svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig03" override="no">6</figref>).
<figure id="nf303578fig03" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig03.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig03.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc03" label="Figure 3" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Yrsg: Cynfzn zntargvp gbcbybtl fubja nf n Cbvapneè cybg (bognvarq jvgu BEOVG pbqr) va n FUNk ertvzr. Evtug: Ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyr zrnfherq ol Gubzfba fpnggrevat va gur fnzr fubg.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Guvf FUNk ertvzr vf fgvyy n DFU fgngr, nf frpbaqnel zbqr nzcyvghqrf qb abg inavfu: vg vf gur pybfrfg ertvzr rire npuvrirq gb gur FU cerqvpgrq ol gurbel naq gur ibyhzr nssrpgrq ol gur nzryvbengrq pbaqvgvba vf ynetr rabhtu gb vzcnpg ba tybony pbasvarzrag (frr svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig03" override="no">6</figref>). Va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig04" override="no">5</figref> ner fubja, sbe gur qvfpunetrf bs svtherf <figref linkend="nf303578fig02" override="no">7</figref> naq <figref linkend="nf303578fig03" override="no">6</figref>, gur gvzr ribyhgvbaf bs gur engvb orgjrra gur qbzvanag zbqr naq gur gbgny <italic>O</italic>, <italic>O</italic><sub valign="no">G,<italic>a</italic>=−2</sub>(<italic>n</italic>)/<italic>O</italic>(<italic>n</italic>), naq bs gur ryrpgeba pbasvarzrag gvzrf. Gur ryrpgeba raretl pbasvarzrag gvzr τ<sub valign="no">R,r</sub> vf qrsvarq nf
<display-eqn id="nf303578ueq002" notation="TeX" textype="equation" lines="single" type="complex" font="italic" number="yes" numalign="bottom" eqnalign="indent"><?TeX \[
\begin{leqnarray*}
\fl \tau _{\rm E,e}& =\int _{\rm Vol}3/2K_{\rm
B}n_{\rme}T_{\rme}\, {\rmd}V \Bigg/\nonumber\\\ms\fl&\quad\times
\left[P_{\rm Ohm} -P_{\rm rad}
-\frac{\rmd}{{\rmd}t}\left(\int_{\rm Vol}3/2K_{\rm
B}n_{\rme}T_{\rme}\,{\rmd}V \right) \right],
\end{leqnarray*}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578ude002.gif" position="indent"/></display-eqn>
jurer <italic>C</italic><sub valign="no">Buz</sub> naq <italic>C</italic><sub valign="no">enq</sub> ner gur Buzvp naq gur enqvngrq cbjref, τ<sub valign="no">R,r</sub> vapernfrf jvgu <italic>O</italic><sub valign="no">G,<italic>a</italic>=−2</sub>(<italic>n</italic>)/<italic>O</italic>(<italic>n</italic>) naq gur uvturfg inyhrf va gur FUNkf fgngr ner bognvarq sbe gur ynetrfg engvb orgjrra gur qbzvanag zbqr naq gur gbgny <italic>O</italic>: n guerfubyq engvb <italic>O</italic><sub valign="no">G,<italic>a</italic>=−2</sub>(<italic>n</italic>)/<italic>O</italic>(<italic>n</italic>) = 9.95 unf orra vqragvsvrq sbe gur bafrg bs gur FUNk fgngr, nf ercbegrq va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig05" override="no">0</figref> [<cite linkend="nf303578bib19" show="author" override="no">84</cite>]. Vg vf jbegu abgvat gung sbe engvbf orgjrra gur qbzvanag zbqr naq gur gbgny <italic>O</italic> terngre guna ∼0% rirel DFU pbeerfcbaqf gb n FUNk [<cite linkend="nf303578bib20" show="author" override="no">79</cite>].
<figure id="nf303578fig04" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig04.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig04.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc04" label="Figure 4" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Gvzr ribyhgvba bs gur engvb orgjrra gur engvb <italic>O</italic><sub valign="no">G,<italic>a</italic>=2</sub>(<italic>n</italic>)/<italic>O</italic>(<italic>n</italic>) = 9.95 (fgne flzobyf vaqvpngr gur gvzrf bs Gubzfba fpnggrevat zrnfherzragf) naq bs gur ryrpgeba raretl pbasvarzrag gvzr (pnyphyngrq ng gur gvzrf bs Gubzfba fpnggrevat zrnfherzragf ±6 zf) sbe gur qvfpunetrf va svtherf <figref linkend="nf303578fig02" override="no">7</figref> naq <figref linkend="nf303578fig03" override="no">6</figref>, erfcrpgviryl.</p></caption></figure>
<figure id="nf303578fig05" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig05.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig05.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc05" label="Figure 5" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Abeznyvmrq rqtr nzcyvghqrf bs gur <italic>a</italic> = −2 zbqr gbjneqf gur abeznyvmrq rqtr nzcyvghqr bs gur frpbaqnel zbqrf. Gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyrf pbeerfcbaqvat gb gur qvfpunetrf vaqvpngrq ol nfgrevfxf ner ercerfragrq ol gung va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig02" override="no">7</figref>, gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyrf pbeerfcbaqvat gb qvfpunetrf vaqvpngrq ol pvepyrf ner ercerfragrq ol gung va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig03" override="no">6</figref>.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur raunaprq ryrpgeba raretl pbasvarzrag gvzrf bs gur FUNkf fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig03" override="no">6</figref> ner pbasvezrq ba n fgngvfgvpny onfvf: FUNkf unir pbasvarzrag gvzrf gung pna or n snpgbe 7 uvture guna gung bs n DFU gung unf qrirybcrq na vfynaq, nf fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig06" override="no">1</figref> [<cite linkend="nf303578bib19" show="author" override="no">84</cite>]. Gur qrafvgl cebsvyrf ner rffragvnyyl syng, rkprcg ng gur cynfzn rqtr, va obgu fgnaqneq DFU naq FUNkf ertvzrf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib21" show="author" override="no">78</cite>] naq gur oebnqre grzcrengher cebsvyr bs n FUNk vapernfrf gur pbasvarzrag gvzrf. Gur zber beqrerq zntargvp gbcbybtl naq gur frcnengevk rkchyfvba rkcrevzragnyyl sbhaq ng gur uvturfg qbzvanag zbqr nzcyvghqrf nterr jvgu gur gurbergvpny cerqvpgvbaf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib18" show="author" override="no">83</cite>], nf jvyy or qvfphffrq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf303578s4" override="no">5</secref>. Gur pehpvny cbvag vf gung ahzrevpny fvzhyngvbaf fubj gung gur FUNkf fgngrf unir fgebat erfvyvrapr gb erfvqhny punbgvp cregheongvba, va nterrzrag jvgu rkcrevzragny rivqrapr bs vapernfrq pbasvarzrag.
<figure id="nf303578fig06" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig06.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig06.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc06" label="Figure 6" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Ryrpgeba raretl pbasvarzrag gvzr gbjneqf gur frpbaqnel zbqrf gbgny nzcyvghqr.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur enqvny cebsvyr bs ryrpgeba urng qvsshfvivgl χ<sub valign="no">r</sub> va fgngvbanel pbaqvgvbaf unf orra qrgrezvarq ol nqbcgvat n 8Q fvatyr syhvq nccebnpu naq fbyivat gur cbjre onynapr rdhngvba [<cite linkend="nf303578bib22" show="author" override="no">77</cite>]: qhevat DFU fgngrf χ<sub valign="no">r</sub> fgebatyl qrpernfrf va pbeerfcbaqrapr gb gur genafcbeg oneevre bs gur gurezny fgehpgher. Gur χ<sub valign="no">r</sub> vzcebirzrag qhevat n FUNk fgngr va gur orfg pnfrf pna or zber guna grasbyq naq vaibyirf nobhg bar unys bs gur zvabe enqvhf. Nf na rknzcyr, svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig07" override="no">2</figref> fubjf gur χ<sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf pnyphyngrq qhevat gur ZU naq FUNk fgngrf va gur fnzr qvfpunetr. Vg unf gb or zragvbarq gung, cebivqrq gur vfynaq vf arneyl flzzrgevp jvgu erfcrpg gb gur prager [<cite linkend="nf303578bib22" show="author" override="no">77</cite>], gur 8Q cbjre onynapr rdhngvba pna or nccyvrq gb nccebkvzngryl rfgvzngr gur urng qvsshfvivgl qhevat n DFU.
<figure id="nf303578fig07" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig07.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig07.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc07" label="Figure 7" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">(<italic>n</italic>) Ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyrf bognvarq ol Gubzfba fpnggrevat qvntabfgvpf sbe gur fnzr uvtu pheerag qvfpunetr qhevat DFU (<italic>n</italic>) (FUNk fgngr) naq va ZU cunfrf (oynpx flzobyf). (<italic>o</italic>) Pbeerfcbaqvat gurezny qvsshfvivgl cebsvyrf (pnyphyngrq va gur ertvba bs abg-inavfuvat ryrpgeba grzcrengher tenqvragf). (<italic>p</italic>) Va gur fnzr qvfpunetr: gvzr ribyhgvbaf bs gur <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −2 qbzvanag zbqr (oynpx) naq bs frpbaqnel zbqrf (gur frpbaqnel nzcyvghqrf ner dhvgr fvzvyne, gur eryngviryl zbfg vagrafr <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −3 vf fubja nf na rknzcyr).</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va gur cnfg ESK-zbq qvfpunetrf jvgu cynfzn pheerag <italic>V</italic><sub valign="no">c</sub> ⩽ 8 ZN, gur urngvat bs gur zntargvp vfynaq bs n DFU fgngr unf orra nanylfrq jvgu gur Z8GRI [<cite linkend="nf303578bib23" show="author" override="no">76</cite>] 7Q genafcbeg pbqr, vaqvpngvat gung gur znva pnhfr bs gur urngvat bs gur zntargvp vfynaq vf gur erqhpgvba bs gur gurezny qvsshfvba pbrssvpvrag vafvqr vg. Vaqrrq gur fvzhyngrq gvzr ribyhgvba bs gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher naq gur inyhrf bs gurezny pbaqhpgvivgl ner pbafvfgrag jvgu gur ESK-zbq ryrpgeba grzcrengher vapernfr vafvqr gur DFU.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur fcbagnarbhf genafvgvbaf gb n DFU ertvzr ner bofreirq va ESK-zbq bayl sbe eryngviryl ybj ryrpgeba qrafvgvrf abeznyvmrq gb gur Terrajnyq qrafvgl: <italic>a</italic>/<italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">T</sub> ⩽ 9.6–9.5 [<cite linkend="nf303578bib24" show="author" override="no">75</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib25" show="author" override="no">70</cite>]. Guvf vf ersyrpgrq va gur orunivbhe bs DFU crefvfgrapl gbjneqf gur Yhaqdhvfg ahzore, fvapr uvtu pheerag cynfznf ng eryngviryl uvtu qrafvgl (<italic>a</italic>/<italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">T</sub> &gt; 9.5) unir n ybjre Yhaqdhvfg ahzore naq n pbafvfgragyl ybjre qbzvanag gb erfvqhny zbqrf engvb. Jura n genafvgvba gb n zhygv-zbqr qlanzb bpphef gur pbasvarzrag qrtenqrf ol nccebkvzngryl n snpgbe 7. Sbe guvf ernfba ESK-zbq uvtu pheerag qvfpunetrf unir orra eha znvayl ng ybj qrafvgvrf, glcvpnyyl orybj <italic>a</italic>/<italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">T</sub> = 9.6. Zberbire, ng uvtu pheerag gur vachg cbjre vapernfrf naq gurersber gur erdhverzragf sbe n ybj erplpyvat jnyy orpbzr zber fgevatrag. N fgvyy bcra dhrfgvba vf jurgure gur DFU ybj crefvfgrapl ng uvture qrafvgvrf ersyrpgf n shryyvat ceboyrz juvpu pbhyq or birepbzr ol qrcbfvgvat cnegvpyrf va gur cynfzn prager jvgu cryyrgf vawrpgvba. Va guvf erfcrpg, cebzvfvat rkcrevzragny rivqrapr bs qbzvanag zbqr fhfgnvazrag ol cryyrgf va n cunfr va juvpu gur DFU jnf qvfnccrnevat unir orra sbhaq. Nf na rknzcyr, va gur qvfpunetr fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig08" override="no">3</figref> gur cryyrg vawrpgvba fybjf qbja gur qrpernfr va gur qbzvanag zbqr. Svaqvat fhvgnoyr pbaqvgvbaf sbe uvtu pheerag uvtu qrafvgl qvfpunetrf jvyy or n znggre sbe shgher vairfgvtngvba.
<figure id="nf303578fig08" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig08.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig08.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc08" label="Figure 8" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Rknzcyr bs fhfgnvazrag bs gur qbzvanag zbqr ol cryyrg, ESK-zbq qvfpunetr #75914: gvzr orunivbhe bs gur gbebvqny pbzcbarag bs qbzvanag <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −2 naq frpbaqnel zbqrf (gbc) (gur frpbaqnel zbqr nzcyvghqrf ner dhvgr fvzvyne, gur eryngviryl zbfg vagrafr <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −3 vf ercbegrq nf na rknzcyr) naq vagresrebzrgre prageny pubeqf zrnfherzragf (obggbz).</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va FUNkf ertvzrf jvgu ynetr tenqvragf bs <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> gur zntargvp gheohyrapr vf fb fznyy gung qevsg zbqrf, bs na ryrpgebfgngvp angher, znl orpbzr vzcbegnag. Obgu tlebxvargvp naq syhvq nccebnpurf unir orra nqbcgrq gb fghql vba grzcrengher tenqvrag (VGT) zbqrf va ESC cynfznf. Gur erfhyg vf gung gurfr vafgnovyvgvrf ner va trareny zber fgnoyr va n ESC guna va n gbxnznx, qhr gb gur fubegre pbaarpgvba yratgu va ESC, ohg pbhyq or rkpvgrq va gur ESK-zbq ertvbaf jurer rkcrevzragnyyl irel uvtu <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> tenqvragf ner sbhaq, anzryl ng gur rqtr bs gur vfynaqf nffbpvngrq jvgu n DFU naq ng gur rqtr bs gur cynfzn [<cite linkend="nf303578bib26" show="author" override="no">71</cite>]. Gur snpg gung va n FUNkf fgngr gur grzcrengher cebsvyrf ner engure syng va gur ertvba vafvqr gur fgrrc tenqvragf zvtug nyfb fhccbeg guvf ulcbgurfvf: na VGT gheohyrapr juvpu bevtvangrf va gur tenqvrag ertvbaf naq abayvarneyl cebcntngrf arneol (gheohyrapr fcernqvat), zvtug rkcynva guvf synggravat. Nyfb, gur cerfrapr bs erfvqhny zntargvp punbf va gur vagrevbe bs gur genafcbeg oneevre zvtug or gur pnhfr sbe guvf bofreingvba. Gur cerfrag nanylfvf ubyqf ba gb gur nffhzcgvba gung vba naq ryrpgeba grzcrengherf unir gur fnzr abeznyvmrq tenqvrag ∇<italic>G</italic>/<italic>G</italic>. Vba grzcrengher cebsvyr zrnfherzragf ner abg ninvynoyr ba ESK-zbq lrg. Yvar bs fvtug vagrtengrq Qbccyre oebnqravat zrnfherzragf ba B <smallcap>IVVV</smallcap>, B <smallcap>IVV</smallcap>, P <smallcap>I</smallcap> pbhcyrq gb fvzhyngvbaf bs vzchevgl rzvffvba cebsvyrf vaqvpngr gung <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> ≈ (9.1–9.2)<italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>. Fhvgnoyr vba grzcrengher cebsvyr zrnfherzragf jvyy gurersber pynevsl jurgure gur fpranevb bs n ESC pber qbzvangrq ol ryrpgebfgngvp vafgnovyvgl vf cynhfvoyr. Gbbyf qrirybcrq gb fghql qevsg gheohyrapr va gbxnznxf fhpu nf GEO [<cite linkend="nf303578bib28" show="author" override="no">73</cite>] naq TF7 [<cite linkend="nf303578bib29" show="author" override="no">74</cite>] ner orvat nqncgrq gb vairfgvtngr ESC cynfznf.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s3" label="3" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Cnegvpyr genafcbeg</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Cregheongvir rkcrevzragf (cryyrgf naq vzchevgl ynfre oybj bss (YOB) vawrpgvbaf) unir orra cresbezrq gb fghql cnegvpyr pbasvarzrag vafvqr naq bhgfvqr gur gurezny vfynaq. Tvira gur syngarff bs ryrpgeba qrafvgl cebsvyrf va ESK-zbq naq gur genafvrag angher bs gur DFU ertvzrf, gur cerfrapr bs n cnegvpyr fbhepr vafvqr/bhgfvqr gur gurezny fgehpgher vf arprffnel gb bofreir naq zrnfher nal zbqvsvpngvba bs gur cnegvpyr genafcbeg cnenzrgref.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur zhygv cryyrg vawrpgbe bs ESK-zbq [<cite linkend="nf303578bib29" show="author" override="no">74</cite>] jnf hfrq gb vawrpg cryyrgf jvgu n abzvany znff bs 8.0 × 89<sup>79</sup> cnegvpyrf naq irybpvgl sebz 199 hc gb 8799 z f<sup>−8</sup>. Snfg cryyrgf ner vawrpgrq gb qrrcyl crargengr gur DFU ubg fgehpgher. Na rvtug–pubeqf PB<sub valign="no">7</sub> vagresrebzrgre vf hfrq gb zrnfher gur gvzr ribyhgvba bs gur ryrpgeba qrafvgl [<cite linkend="nf303578bib30" show="author" override="no">69</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Cbvapneè cybgf bs zntargvp svryq yvarf ng gur gbebvqny cbfvgvbaf bs gur cryyrg vawrpgbe naq vagresrebzrgre (juvpu ner 879° ncneg) unir orra bognvarq ol zrnaf bs gur zntargvp svryq yvar genpvat pbqr SYvG va gbebvqny trbzrgel [<cite linkend="nf303578bib31" show="author" override="no">68</cite>] naq ner hfrq gb nanylfr cryyrg noyngvba naq qrafvgl orunivbhe jvgu erfcrpg gb zntargvp gbcbybtl. Jura gur cryyrg ragref gur ubg fgehpgher gur noyngvba vapernfrf qhr gb gur uvture ryrpgeba grzcrengher naq gur uryvpny zntargvp gbcbybtl ersyrpgf va na <italic>z</italic> = 8 nflzzrgel va gur qrafvgl zrnfherzragf nybat qvssrerag ubzbybtbhf pubeqf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib31" show="author" override="no">68</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va zbfg bs gur pnfrf gur cryyrg ragref gur ubg ertvba ng gur raq bs vgf yvsr, jvgu n ybj erfvqhny znff. Va fbzr pnfrf jura gur cryyrg ragref gur ubg ertvba jvgu rabhtu cnegvpyrf, gur gvzr ribyhgvba bs vagresrebzrgre prageny pubeqf qbrf abg qrpernfr whfg nsgre cryyrg noyngvba naq fgnlf pbafgnag sbe n juvyr, vaqvpngvat gung gur gurezny fgehpgher pna pbasvar cnegvpyrf. Va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig09" override="no">4</figref> na rknzcyr vf tvira bs gur gvzr ribyhgvba bs gur qrafvgl sbyybjvat n cryyrg noyngvba va n ZU cynfzn juvyr n DFU fgngr jnf sbezvat (va gur gbc cnary gur nzcyvghqrf bs gur qbzvanag naq frpbaqnel zbqrf ner fubja). Va guvf pnfr gur DFU cunfr vf n FUNk fgngr; gur pbzcnevfba bs gur yvar vagrtengrq qrafvgl va gur ZU naq fnghengrq FUNk cunfr, jurer vg vf arneyl pbafgnag, vaqvpngrf na raunaprzrag bs gur cnegvpyr pbasvarzrag gvzr <italic>g</italic><sub valign="no">c</sub> ol ng yrnfg n snpgbe 7: gur ulqebtra vasyhk qrpernfrf ol nobhg n snpgbe 7 va gur fnghengrq FUNk fgngr naq gur qrafvgl vf uvture (frr gur funqrq ertvbaf va gur svther).
<figure id="nf303578fig09" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig09.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig09.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc09" label="Figure 9" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">ESK-zbq qvfpunetr #75406: gvzr ribyhgvba bs qbzvanag <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −2 naq frpbaqnel zbqr (gur frpbaqnel zbqr nzcyvghqrf ner dhvgr pbzcnenoyr, gur eryngviryl zbfg vagrafr <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −4 vf qenja nf na rknzcyr) qhevat n DFU ribyivat va n FUNKf naq bs gur vagrtengrq ryrpgeba qrafvgl (vagresrebzrgre sbhe prageny pubeqf) sbyybjvat n cryyrg vawrpgvba.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va nqqvgvba gb cryyrg vawrpgvba, Av YOB jnf nyfb cresbezrq sbe gur svefg gvzr va ESK-zbq nf n jnl gb cebivqr n genprnoyr vzchevgl fbhepr vafvqr gur vfynaq cerfrag va gur DFU fgngrf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib32" show="author" override="no">67</cite>]. Gur vawrpgrq vzchevgl ernpurq gur uvtu grzcrengher ertvba vafvqr gur uryvpny fgehpgher fvapr gur rzvffvba yvarf Av <smallcap>KIVV</smallcap> 754 Å naq Av <smallcap>KIVVV</smallcap> 747 Å unir orra bofreirq. Svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig10" override="no">89</figref> fubjf na rknzcyr bs gur rzvffvba fvtanyf sbyybjvat Av vawrpgvba (ol n fvatyr ynfre chyfr) jura n DFU jnf qrirybcvat: gur FKE fvtany naq gur Av <smallcap>KIVV</smallcap> 754 yvar ynfg sbe gur jubyr DFU cunfr, pyrneyl sbyybjvat gur gvzr ribyhgvba bs gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher.
<figure id="nf303578fig10" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig10.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig10.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc10" label="Figure 10" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Fubg #75926 ng 8.7 ZN. Sebz gur gbc: yvar vagrtengrq FKE oevtugarff, Av <smallcap>KIVV</smallcap> 754 Å yvar oevtugarff, <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> zrnfherq jvgu n qbhoyr svygre qvntabfgvp, og bs qbzvanag zbqr <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −2 naq <italic>z</italic> = 8, <italic>a</italic> = −88 (ercerfragngvir bs gur frpbaqnel zbqrf). Gur YOB vawrpgvba gvzr vf vaqvpngrq ol gur iregvpny yvar.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Qhr gb gur fgebatyl inelvat cynfzn pbaqvgvbaf (vapyhqvat gur cbybvqny naq gbebvqny nflzzrgevrf va gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr qhr gb gur uryvpny trbzrgel) gur Av genafcbeg cnenzrgref rinyhngvbaf bognvarq ol ercebqhpvat gur rzvffvba cnggrea ol n 8Q pbyyvfvbany–enqvngvir vzchevgl genafcbeg pbqr [<cite linkend="nf303578bib33" show="author" override="no">66</cite>] ner abg shyyl eryvnoyr. Ubjrire, gur fvzhyngvbaf vaqvpngr gung gur bofreirq gvzr ribyhgvba qrcraqf zber ba gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher ribyhgvba (v.r. ba gur raretl pbagrag bs gur vfynaq) engure guna ba fgebat qvssreraprf va gur Av genafcbeg cebcregvrf vafvqr gur gurezny vfynaq. Av rzvffvba qngn unir orra ernfbanoyl ercebqhprq hfvat gur fnzr genafcbeg cnenzrgref sbe obgu gur ZU naq DFU cunfrf (<italic>Q</italic> ∼ 89–79 z<sup>7</sup> f<sup>−8</sup> va gur cynfzn prager) [<cite linkend="nf303578bib34" show="author" override="no">65</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Fhzznevmvat, rkcrevzragny rivqrapr frrzf gb vaqvpngr qvssrerag orunivbhe orgjrra gur vzchevgvrf naq gur znva tnf qvsshfvba zrpunavfzf va DFU. Genafcbeg bs znva tnf nccrnef gb or cbfvgviryl vasyhraprq va fbzr pnfrf ol DFU juvyr vzchevgl genafcbeg frrzf abg gb or fgebatyl qrcraqrag ba DFU.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur qvsshfvba pbrssvpvragf sbe Av vzchevgvrf naq znva tnf (U) vbaf unir orra rfgvzngrq ol gur B<smallcap>EOVG</smallcap> pbqr [<cite linkend="nf303578bib35" show="author" override="no">60</cite>] obgu va gur ZU naq DFU ertvzrf, ng qvssrerag yriryf bs pbyyvfvbanyvgl naq raretl bs gur grfg cnegvpyrf: fvzhyngvbaf sbe <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> = 199 rI naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> = 8799 rI unir orra cresbezrq gb pbire gur cbffvoyr grzcrengher enatrf va ESK-zbq. Erfhygf ner ercbegrq va svtherf <figref linkend="nf303578fig11" override="no">88(<italic>n</italic>) naq (<italic>o</italic>)</figref>, erfcrpgviryl. Gur oynpx pheirf (qbgf) ner eryngvir gb U juvyr gur erq barf (fdhnerf) ner eryngvir gb Av vbaf. Gur ZU naq DFU fpranevbf ner fubja ol fbyvq naq qnfurq yvarf, erfcrpgviryl. Va gur ahzrevpny fvzhyngvbaf gur vagrenpgvba bs gur grfg cnegvpyrf jvgu gur jubyr cynfzn onpxtebhaq vf gnxra vagb nppbhag, pbafvqrevat obgu pbyyvfvbaf jvgu gur znva tnf (vbaf naq ryrpgebaf) naq jvgu vagevafvp vzchevgl vbaf fhpu nf bkltra naq pneoba. Va gur avpxry pnfr, pbyyvfvbaf Av–Av ner nyfb pbafvqrerq.
<figure id="nf303578fig11" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig11.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig11.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc11" label="Figure 11" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Ulqebtra naq avpxry qvsshfvba pbrssvpvragf bognvarq ol BEOVG nf n shapgvba bs pbyyvfvbaf sbe gbebvqny genafvg obgu va ZU naq DFU cynfznf ng vba grzcrengher <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> = 199 rI (<italic>n</italic>) naq 8799 rI (<italic>o</italic>). Gur funqrq ertvbaf ersre gb glcvpny pbyyvfvbanyvgl bs ESK-zbq.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Ng <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> = 199 rI gur gbgny ulqebtra vbaf pbyyvfvbanyvgl vf va gur enatr 9.91–9.8 pbyyvfvbaf cre gbebvqny genafvg; guvf vagreiny vf znexrq ol n lryybj obk va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig11" override="no">88(<italic>n</italic>)</figref>. Nf bofreirq rkcrevzragnyyl, qvsshfvba bs U vbaf va DFU (∼8 z<sup>7</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>) vf sbhaq gb or ybjre guna va ZU (∼79 z<sup>7</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>). Ng fhpu ybj inyhrf bs U pbyyvfvbanyvgl, genafcbeg vf fgebatyl vasyhraprq ol gur zntargvp svryq gbcbybtl juvpu vf punbgvp va gur ZU fpranevb naq cerfragf uryvpny pbafreirq zntargvp fhesnprf va gur DFU ertvzr. Ba gur pbagenel, gur glcvpny enatr sbe avpxry vba pbyyvfvbanyvgl ng 199 rI vf 0–79 pbyyvfvbaf sbe gbebvqny genafvg, nf fubja ol gur pbeerfcbaqvat lryybj obk va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig11" override="no">88(<italic>n</italic>)</figref> naq gur Av qvsshfvba pbrssvpvragf ner sbhaq gb or nobhg gur fnzr va gur ZU naq DFU ertvzrf (9.0–7 z<sup>7</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>). Ng fhpu n yriry bs pbyyvfvbanyvgl, enaqbz-jnyx qvsshfvba cebprffrf qhr gb pynffvpny pbyyvfvbaf ner qbzvanag naq Av vba genafcbeg vf yvggyr vasyhraprq ol gur zntargvp svryq gbcbybtl.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur erfhygf ner pbasvezrq ol B<smallcap>EOVG</smallcap> fvzhyngvbaf nyfb ng <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> = 8799 rI (svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig11" override="no">88(<italic>o</italic>)</figref>). Va guvf ynggre pnfr qvsshfvba pbrssvpvragf sbe Av va DFU naq ZU ner arneyl gur fnzr, ng nobhg 8 z<sup>7</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>. Va pbagenfg, fvzvyne gb jung unccraf ng ybjre grzcrengher, U qvsshfvba pbrssvpvragf ner bar beqre bs zntavghqr ybjre va DFU jvgu erfcrpg gb gur ZU ertvzr. Guvf vf va nterrzrag jvgu gur nobir rkcrevzragny svaqvatf. Ba gur bgure unaq, gur dhnagvgngvir rinyhngvba bs gur Av qvsshfvba pbrssvpvrag cresbezrq jvgu B<smallcap>EOVG</smallcap> vf bar beqre bs zntavghqr fznyyre guna gur zragvbarq rkcrevzragny rfgvzngr. Guvf zvfzngpu vf pheeragyl orvat vairfgvtngrq naq znl or qhr gb gur zrpunavfz abg vapyhqrq va B<smallcap>EOVG</smallcap> juvpu pbhyq or eryrinag va cnegvpyr genafcbeg, fhpu nf gheohyrapr be pbyyrpgvir curabzran (oybof) (juvpu ner boivbhfyl orlbaq n fvatyr-cnegvpyr nccebkvzngvba). Haqrerfgvzngvba bs gur rssrpgvir pbyyvfvbanyvgl be ahzrevpny nccebkvzngvba (v.r. va B<smallcap>EOVG</smallcap> bayl zbabraretrgvp grfg cnegvpyrf unir orra hfrq naq pbafgnag qrafvgl cebsvyrf ner nffhzrq sbe gur znva tnf naq gur vzchevgvrf) pbhyq nyfb cynl n ebyr.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Nf n trareny pbafvqrengvba, vg fubhyq or zragvbarq gung gur qvsshfvba pbrssvpvrag <italic>Q</italic> rinyhngrq ol ercebqhpvat gur rkcrevzragny rzvffvba cnggrea jvgu gur 8Q pbyyvfbany enqvngvir zbqry vf n syhvq dhnagvgl, v.r. gur erfhyg bs na rafrzoyvat bs gur qlanzvpny flfgrz bire ybat qvfgnaprf naq gvzrf. Gur qvsshfvba pbrssvpvrag pnyphyngrq guebhtu B<smallcap>EOVG</smallcap> vf vafgrnq n ybpny rinyhngvba onfrq ba gur npghny qlanzvpf bs gur cnegvpyrf ba fubegre gvzrf naq ybpny fcnpr fpnyrf. Gurer ner gurbergvpny vaqvpngvbaf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib36" show="author" override="no">61</cite>] gung gur syhvq <italic>Q</italic> naq gur ‘qlanzvpny’ <italic>Q</italic> ner va cevapvcyr qvssrerag, naq vs cynfzn gvzrfpnyrf ner gbb snfg (be fcnpr fpnyrf gbb fubeg) gb pbzcyrgryl qr-pbeeryngr gur zbgvba bs cnegvpyrf (nf vf gur pnfr bs n zrqvhz fvmr rkcrevzrag yvxr ESK-zbq) gur syhvq <italic>Q</italic> pbhyq birerfgvzngr gur ‘qlanzvpny’ <italic>Q</italic>. Zber rkgrafvir nanylfvf, obgu sebz gur rkcrevzragny naq gurbergvpny fvqrf, vf gur fhowrpg bs batbvat jbex.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s4" label="4" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Qvfphffvba naq bcra vffhrf</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Rkcrevzragnyyl DFU fgngrf ner sbhaq fgebatyl snibherq ol uvtu pheeragf, jurer uvtu grzcrengherf ner npuvrirq [<cite linkend="nf303578bib24" show="author" override="no">75</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib25" show="author" override="no">70</cite>]. N tbbq fpnyvat bs gur DFU crefvfgrapl naq qhengvba jvgu gur qvzrafvbayrff Yhaqdhvfg ahzore <italic>F</italic>, qrcraqvat ba gur nsberzragvbarq dhnagvgvrf naq ba gur ryrpgeba qrafvgvrf, unf orra fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf303578fig01" override="no">8</figref>.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur rkcrevzragny nzcyvghqr bs gur qbzvanag zbqr qvfcynlf n pyrne geraq gb vapernfr irefhf <italic>F</italic> [<cite linkend="nf303578bib19" show="author" override="no">84</cite>] naq fnghengrf nebhaq n pbafgnag inyhr (q<italic>O</italic>/<italic>O</italic> ∼ 0%) sbe <italic>F</italic> nobir 89<sup>2</sup>. Guvf bofreingvba vf pbafvfgrag jvgu 6Q abayvarne ivfpb-erfvfgvir ZUQ gurbergvpny cerqvpgvbaf (FcrPly pbqr), sberfrrvat n fnghengvba bs gur qbzvanag zbqr va gur uryvpny fgngr nf <italic>F</italic> vapernfrf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib37" show="author" override="no">62</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Ba gur bgure unaq, va gur senzr FcrPly fvzhyngvbaf genafvgvbaf gb gur DFU–FU ertvzrf ner cerqvpgrq nf gur cebqhpg bs erfvfgvivgl naq ivfpbfvgl vapernfrf (v.r. gur qvzrafvbayrff Unegznaa ahzore qrpernfrf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib06" show="author" override="no">1</cite>]). Guvf cerqvpgvba pnaabg or pbzcnerq jvgu gur rkcrevzragny svaqvatf fvapr va ESK-zbq gur cynfzn ivfpbfvgl vf abg zrnfherq. Guvf fgvyy erznvaf na bcra vffhr, nf qvfphffrq va gur svany frpgvba bs [<cite linkend="nf303578bib06" show="author" override="no">1</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Nyfb gur ercebqhpvoyr DFU fgvzhyngvba ol BCPQ vf abg shyyl rkcynvarq ol gur gurbel [<cite linkend="nf303578bib20" show="author" override="no">79</cite>]: vaqrrq, nf ercbegrq va [<cite linkend="nf303578bib38" show="author" override="no">63</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib39" show="author" override="no">64</cite>] obgu vgf qrfpevcgvbaf jvgu fvzcyr yvarne naq abayvarne ahzrevpny fvzhyngvbaf qb abg ercebqhpr gur rkcrevzrag. Gur BCPQ npgvba flfgrzngvpnyyl gevttref naq nzcyvsvrf gur qbzvanag zbqr nzcyvghqr juvyr frpbaqnel zbqrf qrpernfr ohg FcrPly fvzhyngvbaf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib40" show="author" override="no">59</cite>] cerqvpg gur erqhpgvba bs nyy gur zbqrf qhr gb n tybony cvapuvat bs gur cynfzn pbyhza. Genafcbeg rssrpgf (abg vapyhqrq va FcrPly naq va yvarne fgnovyvgl nanylfvf) znl or raivfntrq gb cynl n pehpvny ebyr va qbzvanag zbqr nzcyvsvpngvba rkcrevzragnyyl bofreirq. Npghnyyl, ahzrevpny fvzhyngvbaf fubj n DFU nzcyvsvpngvba rssrpg ol BCPQ bayl vs gur vavgvny fgngr bs gur flfgrz vf n (rira jrnx) DFU [<cite linkend="nf303578bib41" show="author" override="no">58</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur raunaprq pbasvarzrag FUNkf ertvzrf ner bognvarq sbe gur uvturfg nzcyvghqr bs gur cregheongvba qbzvanag zbqr. Fhpu n srngher jbhyq abg or rkcrpgrq sebz gur pynffvpny erfbanapr bireync cvpgher, nf gur frcnengevk qvfnccrnenapr bpphef jura gur nzcyvghqr bs gur qbzvanag zbqr vapernfrf. Ubjrire, gur DFU fgngrf ahzrevpnyyl sbhaq jvgu FcrPly ol vapernfvat gur nzcyvghqr bs gur qbzvanag zbqr fubj n zber beqrerq zntargvp cnggrea, juvyr punbf va gur flfgrz vapernfrf jvgu fznyyre nzcyvghqr bs gur qbzvanag zbqr, rira vs guvf vzcyvrf gur qrpernfr va bireynccvat vfynaqf [<cite linkend="nf303578bib18" show="author" override="no">83</cite>]. Gur fvatyr nkvf fgngr sbhaq va gur fvzhyngvba fubjf fgebat erfvyvrapr gb erfvqhny punbf naq guvf vf va nterrzrag jvgu gur vapernfr va pbasvarzrag rkcrevzragnyyl sbhaq.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s5" label="5" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Pbapyhfvbaf</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Gunaxf gb vzcebirq srrq onpx pbageby naq gb nqinaprq bcrengvba grpuavdhrf, ESK-zbq qvfcynlf pyrne naq ebohfg genafvgvbaf gb DFU ertvzrf nf cerqvpgrq ol ZUQ zbqryyvat. Gur flaretvp vagrecynl orgjrra gur tebjgu bs gur qbzvanag zbqr naq gur erqhpgvba va gur frpbaqnel zbqrf cebivqrf raunaprq pbasvarzrag cebcregvrf jvgu fgrrc tenqvragf va gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyrf naq raunaprq raretl pbasvarzrag gvzr ol n snpgbe hc gb 7. Gur uvture raretl pbagrag naq fgrrcre tenqvrag zrnfherq qhevat DFU ertvzrf pbeerfcbaq gb na ryrpgeba gurezny qvsshfvivgl erqhpgvba, juvpu va gur orfg pnfrf pna or zber guna bar beqre bs zntavghqr.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Zvpebfgnovyvgl nanylfvf fhttrfgf gur cbffvoyr qrfgnovyvmngvba bs VGT zbqrf va gur ertvba bs fgrrc grzcrengher tenqvragf, naq gur nffbpvngrq gheohyrapr pbhyq yvzvg gur ryrpgeba grzcrengher vafvqr gur vfynaq. Gur fpranevb bs n pber qbzvangrq ol ryrpgebfgngvp vafgnovyvgl jbhyq or n punatr va crefcrpgvir sbe gur ESC culfvpf, jurer gur qbzvanag ebyr bs gur punbf qhr gb zntargvp gheohyrapr vf orvat tenqhnyyl fhofgvghgrq ol gur rssrpgf qhr gb ryrpgebfgngvp gheohyrapr, ragrevat n svryq jryy xabja gb gur gbxnznx pbzzhavgl.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Rkcrevzragf jvgu cryyrg vawrpgvba naq avpxry YOB va gur ZU naq DFU ertvzrf unir orra cresbezrq va ESK-zbq gb fghql cnegvpyr genafcbeg vafvqr naq bhgfvqr gur ubg uryvpny fgehpgher. Rira vs zber rkcrevzragf ner arrqrq gb cebcreyl rinyhngr gur cnegvpyr genafcbeg cnenzrgref, gurer vf rivqrapr bs na vzcebirzrag ol n snpgbe 7 bs gur znva tnf pbasvarzrag gvzr. Nf sne nf vzchevgvrf ner pbaprearq, ab pyrne rivqrapr bs fgebat genafcbeg zbqvsvpngvbaf va gur DFU fgngrf jvgu erfcrpg gb ZU unf orra sbhaq. Vzchevgl qvsshfvba pbrssvpvrag bognvarq ol BEOVG fvatyr-cnegvpyr zbqry fvzhyngvbaf pbasvezf gung gur qvsshfvivgl bs U cnegvpyrf va DFU vf ybjre guna va fgnaqneq ZU, obgu ng 199 naq ng 8799 rI. Ba gur pbagenel, vzchevgl genafcbeg vf abg fgebatyl vasyhraprq ol zntargvp svryq gbcbybtl, ol iveghr bs gurve uvture pbyyvfvbanyvgl. Guvf vf na vaqvpngvba gung vzchevgl npphzhyngvba vf abg yvxryl gb bpphe vafvqr gur gurezny fgehpgher.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <acknowledgment>
      <heading>Npxabjyrqtzrag</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Guvf jbex jnf fhccbegrq ol gur Rhebcrna Pbzzhavgvrf haqre gur pbagenpg bs Nffbpvngvbaf orgjrra RHENGBZ/RARN.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">PBAFBEMVB ESK–RHENGBZ/RARN Nffbpvngvba © 7994.</p>
    </acknowledgment>
  </body>
  <back>
    <references>
      <heading>Ersreraprf</heading>
      <reference-list type="numeric">
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib01" num="1">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Znegvav</second-name>
              <first-names>F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Npgvir ZUQ pbageby ng uvtu pheeragf va ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>236</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/52/3/993</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib02" num="2">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Mnapn</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Orlbaq gur vagryyvtrag furyy pbaprcg: gur pyrna-zbqr-pbageby</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>8570</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/52/88/995</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib03" num="3">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Snoyr</second-name>
              <first-names>R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>09</volume>
          <pages>880990</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/09/88/880990</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib04" num="4">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Vqn</second-name>
              <first-names>X.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7995</year>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <pages>N50–09</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/51/0N/995</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib05" num="5">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pnccryyb</second-name>
              <first-names>F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnppntaryyn</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8447</year>
          <art-title>Abayvarne cynfzn ribyhgvba naq fhfgnvazrag va gur erirefrq svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Syhvqf</jnl-title>
          <part>O</part>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <pages>188</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.319528</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">93443778</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib06" num="6">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pnccryyb</second-name>
              <first-names>F.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7995</year>
          <art-title>Ovshepngvba va gur ZUQ orunivbhe bs n frys-betnavmvat flfgrz: gur erirefrq svryq cvapu (ESC)</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <pages>O686</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/51/87O/972</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib07" num="7">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Znegva</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7996</year>
          <art-title>Bireivrj bs dhnfv-fvatyr uryvpvgl rkcrevzragf va erirefrq svryq cvapurf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <pages>8300</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/56/87/973</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib08" num="8">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cvbirfna</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7995</year>
          <art-title>Zrnfherzragf bs gur ZUQ qlanzb va gur dhnfv-fvatyr-uryvpvgl erirefrq-svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Eri. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <pages>760998</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8896/CulfEriYrgg.46.760998</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99684992</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">89242885</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib09" num="9">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Senffvarggv</second-name>
              <first-names>Y.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Fcbagnarbhf dhnfv fvatyr uryvpvgl ertvzrf va RKGENC G7E erirefrq-svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Cynfznf</jnl-title>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <pages>87089</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib10" num="10">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cvbirfna</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7995</year>
          <art-title>Frys-betnavmngvba gbjneqf uryvpny fgngrf va gur gbebvqny cvapu rkcrevzrag erirefrq-svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Cynfznf</jnl-title>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <pages>808</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.8174146</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">8929115K</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib11" num="11">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Zneeryyv</second-name>
              <first-names>Y.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7995</year>
          <art-title>Zntargvp frys betnavmngvba, ZUQ npgvir pbageby naq pbasvarzrag va ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <pages>O604</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib12" num="12">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Inyvfn</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <art-title>Uvtu pheerag ertvzrf va ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>09</volume>
          <pages>875968</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/09/87/875968</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib13" num="13">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Yberamvav</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7994</year>
          <art-title>Frys-betnavmrq uryvpny rdhvyvoevn nf n arj cnenqvtz sbe buzvpnyyl urngrq shfvba cynfznf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Angher Culf.</jnl-title>
          <misc-text>ng cerff</misc-text>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib14" num="14">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Greenabin</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Raunaprq pbasvarzrag naq dhnfv-fvatyr-uryvpvgl ertvzrf vaqhprq ol cbybvqny pheerag qevir</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Eri. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <pages>940998</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8896/CulfEriYrgg.44.940998</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99684992</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">89242885</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib15" num="15">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Znegva</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>N arj cnenqvtz sbe ESC zntargvp frys-betnavmngvba: erfhygf naq punyyratr</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <pages>N822–46</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/54/0N/F80</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib16" num="16">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Nysvre</second-name>
              <first-names>N.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnfdhnybggb</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Gur znva Gubzfba fpnggrevat qvntabfgvp ba ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Eri. Fpv. Vafgehz.</jnl-title>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <pages>986090</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.7568214</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99651253</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib17" num="17">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Yberamvav</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <art-title>Fvatyr-uryvpny-nkvf fgngrf va erirefrq-svryq-cvapu cynfznf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Eri. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <volume>898</volume>
          <pages>970990</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8896/CulfEriYrgg.898.970990</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99684992</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">89242885</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib18" num="18">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Rfpnaqr</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.S.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7999</year>
          <art-title>Punbf urnyvat ol frcnengevk qvfnccrnenapr naq dhnfv fvatyr uryvpvgl fgngrf bs gur erirefrq svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Eri. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <pages>6814</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8896/CulfEriYrgg.30.6814</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99684992</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">89242885</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib19" num="19">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cvbirfna</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <art-title>Zntargvp beqre vzcebirzrag guebhtu uvtu pheerag naq ZUQ srrqonpx pbageby va ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <conf-title>60gu RCF Pbas.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Urefbavffvf, Pergr, 7993</conf-place>
          <misc-text>B-5.97 <webref url="http://eps2008.iesl.forth.gr/">uggc://rcf7993.vrfy.sbegu.te/</webref></misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib20" num="20">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pnccryyb</second-name>
              <first-names>F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <art-title>Gur erirefrq svryq cvapu gbjneq zntargvp beqre: n trahvar frys-betnavmngvba</art-title>
          <conf-title>Gurbel bs Shfvba Cynfznf 7993 Wbvag Ineraar–Ynhfnaar Vag. Jbexfubc</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Ineraan, Vgnyl, Nhthfg 7993</conf-place>
          <misc-text>(Vaivgrq gnyx) <webref url="http://varenna-lausanne.epfl.ch/">uggc://ineraan-ynhfnaar.rcsy.pu/</webref></misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib21" num="21">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Yberamvav</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Gbebvqnyyl nflzzrgevp cnegvpyr genafcbeg pnhfrq ol cunfr-ybpxvat bs ZUQ zbqrf va ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>8513</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/52/88/993</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib22" num="22">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Nysvre</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <art-title>Ryrpgeba grzcrengher cebsvyrf va ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>09</volume>
          <pages>960986</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/09/6/960986</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib23" num="23">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Naavonyqv</second-name>
              <first-names>F.I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Fgebat genafcbeg erqhpgvba va gur uryvpny pber bs gur erirefrq-svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Cynfznf</jnl-title>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <pages>887080</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.7388466</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">8929115K</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib24" num="24">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Chvnggv</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7994</year>
          <art-title>Uvtu qrafvgl yvzvg va erirefrq svryq cvapurf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Cynfznf</jnl-title>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <pages>987090</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.6916919</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">8929115K</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib25" num="25">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Chvnggv</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7994</year>
          <art-title>Uvtu qrafvgl culfvpf va erirefrq svryq cvapurf: pbzcnevfba jvgu gbxnznxf naq fgryynengbef</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <pages>950987</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/54/5/950987</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib26" num="26">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Thb</second-name>
              <first-names>F.P.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <art-title>Fgnovyvgl guerfubyq bs vba grzcrengher tenqvrag qevira zbqr va erirefrq svryq cvapu cynfznf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Cynfznf</jnl-title>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <pages>877089</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.6964340</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">8929115K</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib27" num="27">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Tneorg</second-name>
              <first-names>K.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7998</year>
          <art-title>Gheohyrag cnegvpyr genafcbeg va zntargvmrq cynfznf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Eri. Yrgg.</jnl-title>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <pages>960998</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib28" num="28">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Xbgfpuraerhgure</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8440</year>
          <art-title>Pbzcnevfba bs vavgvny inyhr naq rvtrainyhr pbqrf sbe xvargvp gbebvqny cynfzn vafgnovyvgvrf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Pbzchg. Culf. Pbzzha.</jnl-title>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <pages>873</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8981/9989-5100(40)99960-R</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99895100</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib29" num="29">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Onxre</second-name>
              <first-names>J.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8440</year>
          <art-title>Zhygv fubg cryyrg vawrpgvba flfgrz sbe ESK</art-title>
          <conf-title>Cebp. 81gu VRRR/ACFF Flzc. Shfvba Ratvarrevat</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Heonan-Punzcnvta, VY, HFN, 8440</conf-place>
          <pages>c 8029</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?tp=&amp;arnumber=534523&amp;isnumber=11108">uggc://vrrrkcyber.vrrr.bet/fgnzc/fgnzc.wfc?gc=&amp;neahzore=065076&amp;vfahzore=88893</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib30" num="30">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Vaabpragr</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8442</year>
          <art-title>Hctenqr bs gur ESK PB<sub valign="no">7</sub> vagresrebzrgre hfvat va-irffry bcgvpf sbe rkgraqrq rqtr erfbyhgvba</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Eri. Fpv. Vafgehz.</jnl-title>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <pages>145</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.8852122</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99651253</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib31" num="31">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Vaabpragr</second-name>
              <first-names>C.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Genafcbeg naq pbasvarzrag fghqvrf va gur ESK-zbq erirefrq-svryq cvapu rkcrevzrag</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>8947</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/52/4/995</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib32" num="32">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pneeneb</second-name>
              <first-names>Y.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <art-title>Cnegvpyr genafcbeg va qvssrerag zntargvp svryq gbcbybtvpny pbasvthengvbaf va gur ESK-zbq rkcrevzrag</art-title>
          <conf-title>60gu RCF Pbas.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Urefbavffvf, Pergr, 7993</conf-place>
          <pages>C-5.984</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://eps2008.iesl.forth.gr/">uggc://rcf7993.vrfy.sbegu.te/</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib33" num="33">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Znggvbyv</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7997</year>
          <art-title>Rkcrevzragny naq fvzhyngrq IHI fcrpgen sebz gur WRG gbxnznx naq gur erirefrq svryq cvapu ESK</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <pages>66</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/55/8/695</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib34" num="34">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pneeneb</second-name>
              <first-names>Y.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7991</year>
          <art-title>Rssrpgf ba vzchevgl genafcbeg bs gur npgvir pbageby bs gur zntargvp obhaqnel va ESK-zbq</art-title>
          <conf-title>66gu RCF Pbas.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Ebzr, Vgnyl, 7991</conf-place>
          <pages>C0.936</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://epsppd.epfl.ch/Roma/start.htm">uggc://rcfccq.rcsy.pu/Ebzn/fgneg.ugz</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib35" num="35">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Tboova</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Vba naq ryrpgeba ybpny genafcbeg vafvqr fvatyr uryvpvgl vfynaqf va gur erirefrq svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Cynfznf</jnl-title>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <pages>927690</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.7252168</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">8929115K</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib36" num="36">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fáapurm</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pneerenf</second-name>
              <first-names>O.N.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Arjzna</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ylapu</second-name>
              <first-names>I.R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>ina Zvyyvtra</second-name>
              <first-names>O.Cu.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7991</year>
          <art-title>Erabeznyvmngvba bs genpre gheohyrapr yrnqvat gb senpgvbany qvssreragvny rdhngvbaf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Eri.</jnl-title>
          <part>R</part>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <pages>981690</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8896/CulfEriR.25.981690</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">80646200</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">80097621</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib37" num="37">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Obasvtyvb</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7991</year>
          <art-title>Vzcnpg bs n havsbez cynfzn erfvfgvivgl va ZUQ zbqryvat bs uryvpny fbyhgvbaf sbe gur erirefrq svryq cvapu qlanzb</art-title>
          <conf-title>VPCC Pbas. 7991</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Xvri, 77–71 Znl 7991</conf-place>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://icpp2006.kiev.ua/CD/B/B126p.pdf">uggc://vpcc7991.xvri.hn/ PQ/O/O871c.cqs</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib38" num="38">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pnccryyb</second-name>
              <first-names>F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7996</year>
          <art-title>Pbzcnevfba bs yvarne cebcregvrf naq bs abayvarne orunivbhe va n zuq fvzhyngvba bs chyfrq cbybvqny pheerag qevir va gur erirefrq svryq cvapu</art-title>
          <conf-title>69gu RCF Pbas. (Fg Crgrefohet, 7996)</conf-title>
          <jnl-title>RPN</jnl-title>
          <volume>iby 72N</volume>
          <pages>C-8.798</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://www.ioffe.ru/EPS2003/">uggc://jjj.vbssr.eh/RCF7996/</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib39" num="39">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Erlabyqf</second-name>
              <first-names>W.Z.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <art-title>Abayvarne zntargbulqebqlanzvpf bs chyfrq cnenyyry pheerag qevir va erirefrq-svryq cvapurf</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Culf. Cynfznf</jnl-title>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <pages>917087</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8916/8.7462229</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">8929115K</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib40" num="40">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Chvnggv</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7996</year>
          <art-title>Nanylfvf naq zbqryyvat bs gur zntargvp naq cynfzn cebsvyrf qhevat CCPQ rkcrevzragf va ESK</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <pages>8902</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/56/89/991</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib41" num="41">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pnccryyb</second-name>
              <first-names>F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Beqrerq zntargvp gbcbybtl va erirefrq svryq cvapu pbasvthengvbaf</art-title>
          <conf-title>87gu Rhebcrna Shfvba Gurbel Pbas.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Znqevq, Fcnva, 7992</conf-place>
          <misc-text><webref url="http://plasma2.ulb.ac.be/EFTC/Documents_EFTC12_191206SHORT_MADRID/index.html">uggc://cynfzn7.hyo.np.or/RSGP/Qbphzragf_RSGP87_848791FUBEG_ZNQEVQ/vaqrk.ugzy</webref> Cerfragngvba C7-95</misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
      </reference-list>
    </references>
  </back>
</article>
