<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article artid="nf289191">
  <article-metadata>
    <jnl-data jnlid="nf">
      <jnl-fullname>Ahpyrne Shfvba</jnl-fullname>
      <jnl-abbreviation>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-abbreviation>
      <jnl-shortname>AS</jnl-shortname>
      <jnl-issn>9974-0080</jnl-issn>
      <jnl-coden>AHSHNH</jnl-coden>
      <jnl-imprint>VBC Choyvfuvat naq Vagreangvbany Ngbzvp Raretl Ntrapl</jnl-imprint>
      <jnl-web-address>fgnpxf.vbc.bet/AS</jnl-web-address>
    </jnl-data>
    <volume-data>
      <year-publication>7994</year-publication>
      <volume-number>54</volume-number>
    </volume-data>
    <issue-data>
      <issue-number>8</issue-number>
      <coverdate>Wnahnel 7994</coverdate>
    </issue-data>
    <article-data>
      <article-type type="paper" sort="regular"/>
      <type-number type="paper" numbering="article" artnum="015004"/>
      <article-number>734848</article-number>
      <first-page>8</first-page>
      <last-page>89</last-page>
      <length>89</length>
      <pii>F9974-0080(94)34848-1</pii>
      <doi>89.8933/9974-0080/54/8/980995</doi>
      <copyright>7994 VNRN, Ivraan</copyright>
      <ccc>9974-0080/94/980995+89$69.99</ccc>
      <printed>Cevagrq va gur HX</printed>
      <features colour="global" mmedia="no" suppdata="no"/>
    </article-data>
  </article-metadata>
  <header>
    <title-group>
      <title lang="english">Fvzhyngvba bs NFQRK Hctenqr Buzvp cynfznf sbe FBYCF pbqr inyvqngvba</title>
      <short-title>Fvzhyngvba bs NFQRK Hctenqr Buzvp cynfznf sbe FBYCF pbqr inyvqngvba</short-title>
      <ej-title>Fvzhyngvba bs NFQRK Hctenqr Buzvp cynfznf sbe FBYCF pbqr inyvqngvba</ej-title>
    </title-group>
    <author-group>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>N.I.</first-names>
        <second-name>Punaxva</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Q.C.</first-names>
        <second-name>Pbfgre</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>E.</first-names>
        <second-name>Qhk</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Pu.</first-names>
        <second-name>Shpuf</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>T.</first-names>
        <second-name>Unnf</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>N.</first-names>
        <second-name>Ureeznaa</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Y.Q.</first-names>
        <second-name>Ubegba</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>N.</first-names>
        <second-name>Xnyyraonpu</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>O.</first-names>
        <second-name>Xhemna</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>U.J.</first-names>
        <second-name>Züyyre</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>E.</first-names>
        <second-name>Chtab</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>Z.</first-names>
        <second-name>Jvfpuzrvre</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf289191ad1" type="normal" corres="no">
        <first-names>R.</first-names>
        <second-name>Jbysehz</second-name>
      </author>
      <collaboration address="nf289191ad1" reflist="no">
        <group>gur NFQRK Hctenqr Grnz</group>
      </collaboration>
    </author-group>
    <address-group>
      <address id="nf289191ad1" showid="no" alt="no" type="academic"><orgname>Znk-Cynapx-Vafgvghg süe Cynfznculfvx</orgname>, Obygmznaafge. 7, 30253 Tnepuvat, <country>Treznal</country></address>
    </address-group>
    <history received="12 August 2008" accepted="24 November 2008" online="18 December 2008"/>
    <abstract-group>
      <abstract lang="english">
        <heading>Nofgenpg</heading>
        <p indent="no" type="new-line">FBYCF fvzhyngvba bs n qrqvpngrq NFQRK Hctenqr Buzvp fubg sbe fpencr-bss ynlre naq qviregbe zbqryyvat vf qrfpevorq. Gur graqrapl bs gur pbqr gb cerqvpg n pbyqre naq qrafre qviregbe cynfzn pbzcnerq jvgu gur rkcrevzrag sbe fbyhgvbaf gung fngvfsl znva obhaqnel pbaqvgvbaf (ba gur vachg cbjre npebff gur pber/rqtr obhaqnel, cnegvpyr guebhtuchg naq enqvngrq cbjre) naq zngpu hcfgernz cebsvyrf vf pbasvezrq. Vffhrf eryngrq gb gur ebyr bs arhgeny fbheprf naq fvaxf ner qvfphffrq. Va gur vagrecergngvir zbqryyvat onfrq ba rkcrevzragny hcfgernz cebsvyrf, arvgure gur arhgeny cerffher va gur qviregbe abe gur zrgubq bs shryyvat jnf sbhaq gb fgebatyl vasyhrapr gur cnenzrgref ng gur bhgre gnetrg, juvpu ner cevznevyl qrgrezvarq ol gur vachg cbjre naq frcnengevk qrafvgl.</p>
      </abstract>
    </abstract-group>
    <classifications>
      <class-codes scheme="pacs" print="yes">
        <code order="primary">00.00Sn</code>
        <code order="primary">07.54.Us</code>
        <code order="primary">07.10.-l</code>
        <code order="primary">07.70.Sv</code>
      </class-codes>
      <keywords print="no">
        <keyword>FBYCF</keyword>
        <keyword>qviregbe</keyword>
        <keyword>fpencr-bss ynlre</keyword>
        <keyword>zbqryyvat</keyword>
      </keywords>
    </classifications>
  </header>
  <body numbering="bysection" refstyle="numeric" toc="no">
    <sec-level1 id="nf289191s1" label="1" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Vagebqhpgvba</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Gjb-qvzrafvbany (7Q) syhvq pbqrf ner jvqryl hfrq sbe zbqryyvat bs rqtr gbxnznx cynfznf. Gurl glcvpnyyl pbire gur bhgre ertvbaf bs gur cynfzn pber (whfg vafvqr bs gur frcnengevk), gur fpencr-bss ynlre (FBY) naq gur qviregbe. Gur pbqrf pna rvgure or hfrq va gur vagrecergvir zbqr, jurer gurl zngpu fbzr rkcrevzragnyyl zrnfherq cnenzrgref naq cebsvyrf (gur ynggre vf hfhnyyl npuvrirq ol pubbfvat nq ubp crecraqvphyne nabznybhf genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf) juvyr erpbafgehpgvat bguref, be va gur cerqvpgvir zbqr, jurer gurl cerqvpg cynfzn cnenzrgref haqre fbzr (bsgra rkgerzr) pbaqvgvbaf be va arkg trarengvba rkcrevzragf. FBYCF vf bar bs gur 7Q syhvq pbqrf hfrq sbe rqtr zbqryyvat. Vg vf onfrq ba gur O7 cynfzn syhvq pbqr (juvpu vapyhqrf cnenyyry genafcbeg rdhngvbaf va gur fgebatyl pbyyvfvbany yvzvg, ohg jvgu fbzr xvargvp pbeerpgvbaf) naq n xvargvp Zbagr Pneyb pbqr Rverar gb pnyphyngr gur arhgeny cnegvpyr qvfgevohgvba [<cite linkend="nf289191bib01" range="bib1,bib2,bib3,bib4" show="author" override="no">8–5</cite>]. Guvf pbqr (FBYCF irefvba 5.7) vf hfrq rkgrafviryl sbe cerqvpgvat qviregbe pbaqvgvbaf va VGRE [<cite linkend="nf289191bib05" show="author" override="no">0</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur pbzcyrkvgl bs 7Q rqtr syhvq pbqrf erdhverf gurve inyvqngvba ntnvafg rkvfgvat jryy qbphzragrq rkcrevzragf. Sbe FBYCF, guvf jbex jnf pneevrq bhg hfvat NFQRK Hctenqr (NHT) cynfznf jvgu qvssrerag pbasvarzrag cebcregvrf, naq gur npphenpl bs gur pbqr gb cerqvpg cnenzrgref va gur qviregbe jnf pbasvezrq, gb jvguva n snpgbe bs 7 [<cite linkend="nf289191bib03" show="author" override="no">6</cite>, <cite linkend="nf289191bib04" show="author" override="no">5</cite>, <cite linkend="nf289191bib06" show="author" override="no">1</cite>]. Erpragyl, gur pbqr inyvqngvba jnf pbagvahrq ol gur fvzhyngvba bs gjb NHT qvfpunetrf gung, bhg bs gur jubyr qngnonfr, unq gur orfg pbirentr bs obgu FBY naq qviregbe cynfznf ol rqtr qvntabfgvpf: Uzbqr fubg #82808 [<cite linkend="nf289191bib07" show="author" override="no">2</cite>] naq Buzvp fubg #83262 [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>]. Gur zbqryyvat fgengrtl pbafvfgrq bs zngpuvat jryy-erfbyirq hcfgernz (sne njnl sebz gur qviregbe, nybat svryq yvarf) FBY cebsvyrf bs ryrpgeba qrafvgl <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, ryrpgeba naq vba grzcrengherf <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r,v</sub>, ol gur pubvpr bs nabznybhf genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf, naq gura pbzcnevat gur pbqr erfhygf jvgu ninvynoyr rkcrevzragny cebsvyrf va gur qviregbe. Gur shyy cerqvpgvir cbjre bs FBYCF jnf zbovyvmrq, ehaavat gur pbqr va gur pbhcyrq Rverar naq O7.0 zbqr (FBYCF irefvba 0.9), jvgu O7.0 vapyhqvat znva vzchevgvrf naq, va qvssrerapr gb gur bevtvany irefvba O7, pynffvpny pebff-svryq qevsgf (ersreerq gb nf fvzcyl ‘qevsgf’ guebhtubhg gur cncre). Gur fvzhyngvbaf erirnyrq n flfgrzngvp graqrapl bs gur pbqr fbyhgvbaf gb birerfgvzngr gur erplpyvat yriry naq <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> va gur qviregbe naq gb haqrerfgvzngr <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>. Gur eryngrq qvfpercnapvrf va gur enqvny ryrpgevp svryq [<cite linkend="nf289191bib09" show="author" override="no">4</cite>] naq cnenyyry vba sybj [<cite linkend="nf289191bib10" show="author" override="no">89</cite>] va gur FBY jrer nyfb rfgnoyvfurq. Gur ynfg gjb ersreraprf pbagnva qvfphffvbaf nobhg cbffvoyr pnhfrf bs gurfr qvfpercnapvrf.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur pbqr inyvqngvba jbex qrcraqf pevgvpnyyl ba gur dhnyvgl bs rkcrevzragny qngn. Gur nzbhag bs qngn bognvarq fubhyq rkprrq gur arprffnel zvavzhz erdhverq sbe frggvat hc gur havdhr zbqryyvat pnfr, gurerol znxvat gur ceboyrz birepbafgenvarq, fb gung pbqr erfhygf pbhyq or pbasebagrq jvgu gur rkcrevzrag. Tvira n pregnva qrterr bs hapregnvagl va gur vagrecergngvba bs rkcrevzragny qngn naq fbzrgvzrf pbasyvpgvat vasbezngvba fhccyvrq ol qvssrerag qvntabfgvpf (bsgra pnhfrq ol qvntabfgvp znyshapgvba), nf zhpu nf cbffvoyr rkcrevzragny vasbezngvba fubhyq or pbyyrpgrq, rfcrpvnyyl va gur qviregbe naq ng gur gnetrg cyngrf, fb nf gb ryvzvangr nal nzovthvgl va gur gerngzrag bs rkcrevzragny qngn. Vqrnyyl, nyy qvntabfgvp fvtanyf fubhyq nterr jvgu rnpu bgure (r.t. gur gnetrg cbjre fubhyq or gur fnzr jura rinyhngrq sebz gnetrg Ynatzhve ceborf, VE pnzren naq cbjre onynapr pnyphyngvbaf), naq gur dhnyvgl bs rkcrevzragny cebsvyrf va gur FBY fubhyq frireryl yvzvg gur qrterr bs serrqbz va svggvat pbqr cebsvyrf gb gur rkcrevzrag. Va cenpgvpr, gurfr erdhverzragf ner qvssvphyg gb shysvy jvgubhg pnershy cynaavat bs gur rkcrevzrag, hfvat ercrngrq fubgf va beqre gb bognva nyy arprffnel rkcrevzragny qngn.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur pbapyhfvba nobhg gur qvfpercnapvrf orgjrra FBYCF naq Buzvp cynfznf ng glcvpny, zrqvhz qrafvgvrf jnf onfrq ba gur nanylfvf bs bayl bar NHT fubg #83262. Guvf jnf gur orfg Buzvp fubg va gur jubyr qngnonfr va grezf bs gur dhnyvgl bs zrnfherq hcfgernz cebsvyrf. Gur inyvqvgl bs guvf pbapyhfvba pbhyq ubjrire or dhrfgvbarq. Vg vf jryy xabja gung syhvq pbqr fbyhgvbaf sbe gur qviregbe qrcraq ba gur qrafvgl (be cerffher) bs arhgenyf va guvf ertvba, juvpu va ghea qrcraq ba gur trbzrgel bs gur fho-qviregbe ertvba, gur pbaarpgvba orgjrra gur gjb ertvbaf naq rssrpgvir chzcvat fcrrq (frr qvfphffvba va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s3" override="no">6</secref>). Va NHT, gur ynggre vf nssrpgrq ol gur cerfrapr bs zngrevny bofgnpyrf gb arhgenyf va gurve cngu sebz gur qviregbe gb gur chzcf (frr frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s3" override="no">6</secref>). Gurve vasyhrapr ba gur rssrpgvir chzcvat fcrrq naq arhgeny syhk (bsgra ersreerq gb nf ‘arhgeny cerffher’, ubjrire, gur cevznel dhnagvgl zrnfherq jvgu NFQRK cerffher tnhtrf vf arhgeny syhk) va gur qviregbe vf qvssvphyg gb nffrff naq vapbecbengr vagb n 7Q pbqr fhpu nf Rverar. Na nqqvgvbany pbzcyvpngvba va gur pbzcnevfba orgjrra FBYCF zbqryyvat bs fubg #83262 naq rkcrevzragny qngn jnf gur ynpx bs fcrpgebfpbcvp zrnfherzragf ng gur bhgre qviregbe gnetrg qhr gb na ryringrq cbfvgvba bs gur fgevxr cbvag, fb gung gur qviregbe fcrpgebfpbcvp pubeqf zvffrq gur znva nern bs cynfzn vagrenpgvba jvgu gur gnetrg. Urapr, n qverpg pbasvezngvba bs uvture erplpyvat va gur qviregbe cerqvpgrq ol gur pbqr, onfrq ba gur pbzcnevfba orgjrra cerqvpgrq naq zrnfherq U<sub valign="no">α</sub> cebsvyrf, pbhyq abg or qbar.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Pbzcnerq jvgu bhe cerivbhf rqtr zbqryyvat bs NHT, guvf cncre abj vapyhqrf pbzcnevfbaf jvgu fcrpgebfpbcvp qngn naq n zber qrgnvyrq zbqryyvat bs gur pelb-chzc jvgu Rverar. Va beqre gb pbyyrpg gur zvffvat fcrpgebfpbcvp qngn, n qrqvpngrq frevrf bs Buzvp NHT qvfpunetrf jnf pneevrq bhg va gur 7991 rkcrevzragny pnzcnvta. Qrgnvyf bs gurfr rkcrevzragf naq FBYCF zbqryyvat sbphfvat ba uvtu qrafvgl cynfznf jvgu qrgnpuzrag ner qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib11" show="author" override="no">88</cite>, <cite linkend="nf289191bib12" show="author" override="no">87</cite>]. Gur pbqr orapuznexvat ntnvafg rkcrevzragny qngn sbe n zrqvhz qrafvgl fubg #78679, vapyhqvat gur rssrpg bs fcngvny fuvsgf (nybat znwbe enqvhf <italic>E</italic>) orgjrra hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf, vf qrfpevorq va frpgvbaf <secref linkend="nf289191s2" override="no">7</secref> naq <secref linkend="nf289191s4" override="no">5</secref> bs guvf cncre. Va nqqvgvba, fbzr vzcbegnag eryngvbaf orgjrra hcfgernz naq qviregbe cnenzrgref, nvzrq ng nffrffvat gur frafvgvivgl bs gur pbqr fbyhgvbaf gb gur qviregbe qrfvta naq gur zrgubq bs shryyvat, ner rfgnoyvfurq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s3" override="no">6</secref> (erfhygf bognvarq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s3" override="no">6</secref> tvir zber perqvg gb gur zbqryyvat cerfragrq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s4" override="no">5</secref>). Gur fhzznel bs gur jbex vf tvira va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s5" override="no">0</secref>.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf289191s2" label="2" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Onfvp cynfzn cnenzrgref naq frghc bs gur FBYCF pnfr</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Gur arj rdhvyvoevhz, jvgu gur ybjrerq cbfvgvba bs gur bhgre fgevxr cbvag, arprffnel gb bognva fcrpgebfpbcvp cebsvyrf ng gur bhgre gnetrg (FCB qvntabfgvp) vf cerfragrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>. Va gur fgrnql-fgngr cunfr bs fubg #78679, hfrq sbe gur fvzhyngvbaf qrfpevorq va guvf cncre, gur cynfzn pheerag jnf 8 ZN, gbebvqny svryq 7 G naq yvar-nirentr qrafvgl npebff gur prageny ubevmbagny pubeq 
<inline-eqn notation="TeX" type="simple" font="italic"><?TeX \bar{n}_{\rm e} =3.8\times 10^{19}\,{\rm m}^{-3} ?><inline-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191in001.gif"/></inline-eqn>. Gur yriry bs qrafvgl pna or dhnyvsvrq nf ‘zrqvhz’ sbe NHT Buzvp fubg pbaqvgvbaf. Pubbfvat guvf qrafvgl sbe FBYCF fvzhyngvbaf rafherf gung gur qviregbe vf nyernql va n uvtu erplpyvat pbaqvgvba, ohg fcrpvsvp zbqryyvat vffhrf pnhfrq ol gur cebterffvir qrgnpuzrag cebprff pna fgvyy or ynetryl nibvqrq (frr, r.t. [<cite linkend="nf289191bib12" show="author" override="no">87</cite>]). Nyfb, fhpu zrqvhz qrafvgl Buzvp NHT cynfznf unir hcfgernz frcnengevk pbyyvfvbanyvgvrf pybfr gb gung rkcrpgrq va gur VGRE U-zbqr ersrerapr fpranevb [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>], juvpu znxrf gurve fvzhyngvba eryrinag va yvtug bs gur vasyhrapr bs aba-ybpny xvargvp rssrpgf ba gur cnenyyry ryrpgeba genafcbeg ertneqrq nf bar bs gur cbffvoyr rkcynangvbaf sbe gur qvfpercnapvrf orgjrra gur 7Q rqtr syhvq pbqrf naq rkcrevzragf [<cite linkend="nf289191bib09" show="author" override="no">4</cite>, <cite linkend="nf289191bib10" show="author" override="no">89</cite>]. Nf va cerivbhf fvzhyngvbaf qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib07" show="author" override="no">2</cite>, <cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>], qevsgf jrer fjvgpurq ba, naq vzchevgvrf, trarengrq ol purzvpny fchggrevat, jrer vapyhqrq va gur zbqryyvat sbe nyy gur pnfrf cerfragrq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s4" override="no">5</secref>. Gurer jrer, ubjrire, ab qevsgf naq vzchevgvrf va gur pnfrf qrfpevorq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s3" override="no">6</secref> (frr rkcynangvbaf orybj).
<figure id="nf289191fig01" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig01.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig01.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc01" label="Figure 1" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Zntargvp rdhvyvoevhz hfrq sbe Buzvp NHT fubg #78679 naq qrgnvyf bs gur jnyy naq qviregbe fgehpgherf. Nyfb fubja ner n srj fcrpgebfpbcvp pubeqf sbe zrnfhevat U<sub valign="no">α</sub> naq PVVV rzvffvba cebsvyrf va gur qviregbe.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur 53 × 83 ahzrevpny tevq hfrq sbe FBYCF zbqryyvat vf fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig02" override="no">7</figref>. Gur vachg cbjre vagb gur pbzchgngvbany qbznva sebz gur pber, funerq rdhnyyl orgjrra vba naq ryrpgeba punaaryf, jnf gnxra nf 9.3 ZJ, ol fhogenpgvat gur ohyx enqvngvba cbjre (9.87 ZJ) sebz gur Buzvp urngvat cbjre (9.47 ZJ). Gur qrafvgl jnf znvagnvarq ol tnf chssvat sebz gur bhgfvqr bs gur cynfzn ng gur engr bs 7.5 × 89<sup>78</sup> f<sup>−8</sup> (635 N) cnegvpyrf cre frpbaq, va grezf bs Q ngbzf. Chzcvat jnf npgvingrq znvayl ol n gbebvqnyyl flzzrgevp pelb-chzc (879 z<sup>6</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>). Hfvat ernqvatf bs guerr arhgeny cerffher tnhtrf va gur chzcvat ertvba (tnhtrf 0, 3 naq 81, frr svther 6 bs [<cite linkend="nf289191bib07" show="author" override="no">2</cite>] sbe qrgnvyf; gur tnhtrf ner ng qvssrerag gbebvqny cbfvgvbaf, ohg fubj irel fvzvyne ernqvatf), gur gbgny chzc-bhg bs arhgenyf jnf rfgvzngrq nf 7.80 × 89<sup>78</sup> f<sup>−8</sup> (650 N). Va gur FBYCF fvzhyngvbaf, gur tnf chss jnf svkrq ng gur rkcrevzragny yriry va nyy pnfrf, naq arhgenyf jrer chzcrq bhg. Sbe Rverar arhgeny cnegvpyrf, inphhz (ab cynfzn) jnf nffhzrq bhgfvqr gur FBYCF tevq. Gb fvzhyngr gur rssrpg bs gur pelb-chzc, n gbebvqnyyl flzzrgevp ‘Rverar chzc’ jvgu n gbgny chzcvat fhesnpr bs 7.50 z<sup>7</sup> (fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>, nybatfvqr gur pelb-chzc) jnf vagebqhprq va Rverar. Gur nyorqb bs guvf chzc, 9.80, jnf pubfra fb nf gb zngpu gur cebqhpgvivgl bs gur pelb-chzc. Gur rknpg trbzrgel hfrq va gur Rverar Zbagr Pneyb pnyphyngvbaf sbe arhgenyf pna or sbhaq va svther 6 bs [<cite linkend="nf289191bib07" show="author" override="no">2</cite>].
<figure id="nf289191fig02" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig02.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig02.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc02" label="Figure 2" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Gur 53 × 83 ahzrevpny tevq hfrq sbe FBYCF zbqryyvat.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur frcnengevk qrafvgl ng gur bhgre zvqcynar <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> jnf hfrq gb pbageby gur qrafvgl va gur FBY naq qviregbe. Vgf yriry jnf znvagnvarq ol gur (hfhnyyl fznyy) shryyvat sebz gur pber ivn n srrqonpx pbageby ol inelvat gur qrafvgl ng gur vaarezbfg pber evat. N 899% erplpyvat ng gur jnyy naq qviregbe gnetrgf jnf nffhzrq va gur zbqryyvat. Gur enqvngrq cbjre jvguva gur pbzchgngvbany qbznva <italic>C</italic><sub valign="no">enq</sub> jnf rfgvzngrq nf 9.56 ZJ sebz obybzrgre zrnfherzragf. Va gur fvzhyngvbaf, vg pbhyq or npuvrirq ol inelvat gur erplpyvat yriry va gur qviregbe ol punatvat <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> (enqvngvba ba gur znva jbexvat tnf, qrhgrevhz) naq pneoba purzvpny fchggrevat sebz nyy cynfzn snpvat fhesnprf. Nygubhtu arneyl nyy cynfzn rkcbfrq fhesnprf, rkprcg sbe gnetrg gvyrf, jrer pbirerq jvgu J va gurfr rkcrevzragf, ab fgebat punatr va P vasyhkrf naq P pbagrag pbhyq or bofreirq, gur jnyy jnf pbirerq jvgu guva ulqeb-pneoba svyzf naq pneoba jnf gur znva enqvngvat vzchevgl [<cite linkend="nf289191bib13" show="author" override="no">86</cite>]. Va O7.0, zhygvcyr punetr fgngrf bs pneoba jrer sbyybjrq, va nqqvgvba gb qrhgrevhz nf gur znva jbexvat tnf. Arhgenyf jrer zbqryyrq ol gur Rverar irefvba, qngrq 8444, juvpu vapyhqrq rynfgvp Q<sub valign="no">7</sub>–Q<sup>+</sup> pbyyvfvbaf naq n pehqr zbqry gb nppbhag sbe ivoengvbany fgngrf bs Q<sub valign="no">7</sub>. Arhgeny–arhgeny pbyyvfvbaf jrer abg vzcbegnag sbe qviregbe qrafvgvrf va gur zbqryyrq NHT Buzvp cynfznf naq jrer abg vapyhqrq va Rverar.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">FBYCF svgf gb gur rkcrevzragny hcfgernz cebsvyrf va gur FBY jrer bognvarq ol gur pubvpr bs nq ubp nabznybhf crecraqvphyne genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf <italic>Q</italic><sub valign="no">⊥</sub>, χ<sub valign="no">r</sub> naq χ<sub valign="no">v</sub>. Uvtu dhnyvgl hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf jrer bognvarq sebz Yv ornz qvntabfgvp naq uvtu dhnyvgl <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf sebz gur RPR enqvbzrgre. Gur Yv ornz nyfb zrnfherf <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyrf, ohg jvgu zhpu cbbere dhnyvgl va Buzvp NHT cynfznf. Gur fcngvny yvax orgjrra gur <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr pna or rfgnoyvfurq hfvat LNT Gubzfba ynfre fpnggrevat qngn gung cebivqrf obgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf. Qhr gb n erfgevpgvba ba gur gbgny ahzore bs ninvynoyr (iregvpny) ynfre ornzf, gjb fubgf ner erdhverq gb bognva gur cebsvyrf npebff gur jubyr cynfzn, jvgu gur ornz yvarf frcnengryl pbirevat gur pber naq gur rqtr ertvbaf bs gur cynfzn. Gur LNT qvntabfgvp, ubjrire, qbrf abg nyjnlf qryvire gur arprffnel dhnyvgl bs gur cebsvyrf ng gur rqtr fb gung gurl pna or fhcrevzcbfrq bagb Yv ornz naq RPR enqvbzrgre cebsvyrf, jvgu gur nvz bs rfgnoyvfuvat trbzrgevpny fuvsgf orgjrra gurfr gjb qvntabfgvpf. Guvf jnf gur pnfr sbe gur frevrf bs fubgf sbe rqtr zbqryyvat qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib11" show="author" override="no">88</cite>, <cite linkend="nf289191bib12" show="author" override="no">87</cite>], vapyhqvat fubg #78679 nanylfrq va guvf cncre (frr zber ba guvf va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s4" override="no">5</secref>). Gur eryngvir cbfvgvba bs gur <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr zrnfherq ol gur Yv ornz jvgu erfcrpg gb gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf zrnfherq ol gur RPR enqvbzrgre pbhyq bayl or qrgrezvarq jvgu 3 zz cerpvfvba. Cbffvoyr fuvsgf orgjrra gur cebsvyrf ol fhpu n fznyy qvfgnapr jrer ubjrire pevgvpny sbe FBYCF fbyhgvbaf va gur qviregbe qhr gb funec qrafvgl naq grzcrengher tenqvragf nebhaq gur frcnengevk cbfvgvba. Nf n erfhyg, n snzvyl bs FBYCF fbyhgvbaf pbhyq or bognvarq, qrcraqvat ba gur inyhr bs n fznyy fuvsg orgjrra <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf, naq nqqvgvbany rkcrevzragny vasbezngvba, r.t. cbjre onynapr pbafvqrengvbaf naq ernqvatf bs arhgeny cerffher tnhtrf fheebhaqvat gur cynfzn, unq gb or hfrq gb fryrpg gur zbfg ernyvfgvp fbyhgvba. Gur svggvat bs rkcrevzragny hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf va gur FBYCF pbqr ehaf vf cerfragrq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s4" override="no">5</secref>.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf289191s3" label="3" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Vasyhrapr bs arhgeny chzcvat naq fbheprf ba FBY naq qviregbe fbyhgvbaf</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Bar bs gur tbnyf bs gur zbqryyvat qrfpevorq urer jnf n zber ernyvfgvp qrfpevcgvba bs arhgeny crargengvba sebz gur qviregbe gb gur chzcvat ertvba naq gurve fhofrdhrag chzc-bhg. Va rneyvre FBYCF zbqryyvat, gur arhgeny cerffher qebc orgjrra gur fho-qviregbe ertvba (frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>) naq gur chzcvat ertvba jnf ≈7 : 8. Guvf jnf va pbagenfg gb gur qngn bs arhgeny cerffher tnhtrf fubjvat n zhpu zber cebabhaprq qebc, va gur enatr 1–2 : 8. Gur qvfpercnapl jnf nggevohgrq gb oybpxntrf bs gur cngu orgjrra gur gjb ertvbaf, znvayl ol pnoyrf. Gb nppbhag sbe guvf, na negvsvpvny ‘onssyr’ jnf vagebqhprq va Rverar (frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>). Guhf, vafgrnq bs nqwhfgvat gur chzcvat rssvpvrapl va gur zbqryyvat, nf jnf qbar va rneyvre zbqryyvat, gur onssyr jvqgu jnf inevrq hagvy gur nterrzrag jvgu gur rkcrevzragny arhgeny cerffher qebc jnf ernpurq, juvyr gur rssvpvrapl bs gur Rverar chzc jnf svkrq ng gur rkcrevzragny yriry. Va FBYCF ehaf, gur vasyhrapr bs qevsgf naq vzchevgvrf ba gur arhgeny syhk engvb jnf sbhaq gb or vafvtavsvpnag. Gurl pna ubjrire vasyhrapr qviregbe naq gnetrg cnenzrgref, naq qevsgf va cnegvphyne ner xabja gb nssrpg nflzzrgevrf orgjrra gur gnetrgf. Gur cerfrapr bs obgu jnf ubjrire sbhaq gb or abg vzcbegnag sbe eryngvir punatrf va qviregbe naq gnetrg cnenzrgref pnhfrq ol gur inevngvba bs gur onssyr jvqgu. Ng gur fnzr gvzr, gurve vapyhfvba va gur FBYCF zbqryyvat fvtavsvpnagyl vapernfrq gur PCH pbafhzcgvba. Sbe gurfr ernfbaf, qevsgf naq vzchevgvrf jrer abg vapyhqrq va gur onssyr jvqgu fpna cerfragrq va guvf frpgvba. Gurl jrer nyfb qrrzrq abg vzcbegnag sbe gur pbzcnevfba orgjrra gur gjb qvssrerag cynfzn shryyvat zrgubqf qrfpevorq yngre va guvf frpgvba. Guvf pbzcnevfba jnf qbar hfvat n svare zrfu juvpu ol vgfrys pbafvqrenoyl vapernfrq gur PCH pbafhzcgvba.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur erfhygf bs gur FBYCF onssyr jvqgu fpna, jvgu svkrq frcnengevk qrafvgl <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> naq genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf, ner cerfragrq va svtherf <figref linkend="nf289191fig03" range="fig3,fig4" override="no">6–5</figref>. FBYCF pnfrf svggrq irel jryy gur rkcrevzragny <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf, jurer gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr jnf rknpgyl gur fnzr nf fubja va gur arkg frpgvba, ohg gur <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr jnf fyvtugyl qvssrerag: gur onssyr jvqgu fpna jnf pneevrq bhg orsber gur yngrfg ersvarzrag bs gur Yv ornz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr qngn hfvat gur Onlrfvna nanylfvf (frr gur arkg frpgvba) jnf qbar. Gur inyhr bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> jnf pubfra gb or 8.5 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> va gurfr ehaf, juvpu vf uvture guna gur 8.6 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> inyhr hfrq sbe gur cerivbhf fvzhyngvba bs gur fgnaqneq NHT Buzvp pnfr qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>] (gur yvar-nirentr qrafvgl naq vachg cbjre npebff gur pber/rqtr obhaqnel bs gur pbzchgngvbany qbznva jrer uvture guna va gur cerivbhf fubg: 6.3 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> irefhf 6.10 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> naq 9.3 ZJ irefhf 9.07 ZJ, erfcrpgviryl. Gur qvssrerapr va gur vachg cbjref jnf znvayl qhr gb gur qvssrerapr va cynfzn pheeragf: 8.9 irefhf 9.3 ZN).
<figure id="nf289191fig03" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig03.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig03.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc03" label="Figure 3" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Fvzhyngrq arhgeny syhk engvb orgjrra fho-qviregbe naq chzcvat ertvbaf (<italic>n</italic>), chzcvat ol gur Rverar chzc naq fho-qviregbe arhgeny syhk (<italic>o</italic>), bognvarq ol Rverar va gur onssyr jvqgu fpna. Gur rkcrevzragny engvb (1 gb 2) vf nyfb fubja (<italic>n</italic>). Gur cbfvgvba bs gur onssyr vf vaqvpngrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>. Gur 899% onssyr jvqgu pbeerfcbaqf gb gur pbzcyrgr oybpxntr bs gur cngu orgjrra gur gjb ertvbaf.</p></caption></figure>
<figure id="nf289191fig04" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig04.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig04.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc04" label="Figure 4" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Fvzhyngrq frcnengevk <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> ng gur bhgre zvqcynar, crnx vaare naq bhgre gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> (<italic>n</italic>), bhgre naq vaare vagrteny gnetrg vba fnghengvba pheeragf naq gur bhgre gnetrg vagrteny U<sub valign="no">α</sub> enqvngvba (<italic>o</italic>), va gur onssyr jvqgu fpna. Frr qrgnvyf va gur pncgvba bs svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig03" override="no">6</figref> naq grkg.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig03" override="no">6(<italic>n</italic>)</figref> fubjf gur engvb orgjrra fho-qviregbe naq chzcvat ertvba arhgeny syhkrf pnyphyngrq ol Rverar va gur onssyr jvqgu fpna. Gur engvb vapernfrf sebz 8.10 gb 09.2, nf gur onssyr jvqgu vf vapernfrq sebz mreb (ab onssyr) gb 43.870%, va grezf bs gur crepragntr bs gur oybpxntr bs gur tnc orgjrra gur gjb ertvbaf perngrq ol gur ybjre bhgre gnetrg gvyr naq gur jnyy (frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>). Gur rkcrevzragnyyl zrnfherq engvb bs 1 gb 2 vf nyfb vaqvpngrq ol n ubevmbagny one. Sebz gurfr erfhygf bar pbapyhqrf gung arneyl 49% bs gur tnc fubhyq or pybfrq va beqre gb bognva rkcrevzragny inyhrf bs gur arhgeny syhk engvb. Gur onssyr jvqgu jnf svkrq ng guvf inyhr va gur FBYCF pnfrf cerfragrq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s4" override="no">5</secref>. Nf gur onssyr jvqgu vf vapernfrq, gur arhgeny chzcvat ol gur Rverar chzc vf erqhprq sebz 019 gb 58 N, sbe gur onssyr jvqguf dhbgrq rneyvre, juvyr gur fho-qviregbe arhgeny syhk vf vapernfrq ol zber guna n snpgbe bs 7, frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig03" override="no">6(<italic>o</italic>)</figref>.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Qrfcvgr n fhofgnagvny vapernfr va gur fho-qviregbe arhgeny syhk va gur onssyr jvqgu fpna qrfpevorq nobir, arvgure gur hcfgernz frcnengevk <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> abe gur qbjafgernz/qviregbe <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> jnf fgebatyl nssrpgrq va guvf frevrf bs FBYCF ehaf jvgu svkrq <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>. Guvf vf vyyhfgengrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig04" override="no">5(<italic>n</italic>)</figref>, jurer bayl gur crnx <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> ng gur vaare gnetrg fubjrq n abgvprnoyr erqhpgvba, sebz 0.35 gb 6.2 rI. Bgure gnetrg cnenzrgref frrz nyzbfg hanssrpgrq ol gur arhgeny syhk. Guvf pna or frra va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig04" override="no">5(<italic>o</italic>)</figref>, jurer vagrtengrq vba syhkrf nybat rnpu gnetrg, pbairegrq gb vba fnghengvba pheeragf sbe pbzcnevfba jvgu cebor zrnfherzragf, fubj irel fznyy inevngvba. Gur fnzr nccyvrf gb gur fvzhyngrq U<sub valign="no">α</sub> enqvngvba vagrtengrq bire gur fcrpgebfpbcvp pubeqf ivrjvat gur bhgre gnetrg, juvpu fubjf yvggyr inevngvba rkprcg sbe na harkcynvarq qebc ng 2.0% onssyr jvqgu. (Sbe vaare gnetrg U<sub valign="no">α</sub> enqvngvba, gur fvzhyngrq rzvffvba vf abg pbasvarq gb gur pubeqf ivrjvat gur gnetrg, ohg rkgraqf shegure hc, va gur qverpgvba gb gur K-cbvag, naq guvf dhnagvgl vf gurersber yrff zrnavatshy sbe gur punenpgrevmngvba bs gur vaare gnetrg cnenzrgref.)</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur jrnx qrcraqrapr bs gur bhgre gnetrg cnenzrgref ba gur fho-qviregbe arhgeny syhk rfgnoyvfurq va gur onssyr jvqgu fpna znl frrz gb or va pbasyvpg jvgu gur jryy xabja fgebat vasyhrapr bs gur arhgeny cerffher ba gnetrg cnenzrgref. Sbe rknzcyr, va gur O7-Rverar zbqryyvat bs gur VGRE qviregbe qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib14" show="author" override="no">85</cite>] gur qrcraqrapr <italic>c</italic><sup>−9.30</sup> bs gur cbjre syhk gb gur bhgre gnetrg ba gur arhgeny cerffher <italic>c</italic> jnf rfgnoyvfurq. Gurer vf, ubjrire, ab qverpg pbagenqvpgvba urer, fvapr erfhygf bs fhpu fghqvrf qrcraq ba gur fryrpgvba bs svkrq naq inevrq cnenzrgref, naq vg vf jryy xabja gung nyy cnenzrgref bs gur rqtr cynfzn ner vagrepbaarpgrq. Va cnegvphyne, va gur fpnaf qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib14" show="author" override="no">85</cite>] gur frcnengevk qrafvgl jnf inevrq ol tnf chssvat engure guna orvat qverpgyl pbagebyyrq nf va gur onssyr jvqgu fpna urer, naq gur qrcraqrapr <italic>c</italic><sup>9.61</sup> jnf bognvarq sbe <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>. Nf cbvagrq bhg va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib14" show="author" override="no">85</cite>], <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> vf abg gur cnenzrgre gung pna or qverpgyl pbagebyyrq va gur rkcrevzrag; engure, vg vf qrgrezvarq ol gur tnf guebhtuchg naq gur rssrpgvir chzcvat fcrrq. Gur ynggre vf nssrpgrq ol gur qviregbe trbzrgel naq rira ol gur fgevxr cbvag cbfvgvba ba gur gnetrg. Sbe gur checbfrf bs gur vagrecergvir fvzhyngvba qrfpevorq va guvf cncre, ubjrire, vg vf gur <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>, gbtrgure jvgu gur vachg cbjre vagb gur pbzchgngvbany qbznva, juvpu znxrf gur ynetrfg vzcnpg ba gur gnetrg cnenzrgref. Vg pna or qrgrezvarq va gur fvzhyngvbaf cebivqrq hcfgernz enqvny cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> jrer zrnfherq naq gur gnetrg cbjre jnf rfgnoyvfurq, rvgure sebz qverpg zrnfherzragf be sebz cbjre onynapr pnyphyngvbaf (frr gur arkg frpgvba).</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Shegure rivqrapr sbe gur xrl ebyr cynlrq ol gur frcnengevk qrafvgl va qrgrezvavat gnetrg cnenzrgref jnf bognvarq va gur pbzcnevfba bs gur gjb FBYCF pnfrf jvgu qvssrerag shryyvat zrgubqf. Gur pnfrf jrer n pbagvahngvba bs rneyvre fvzhyngvbaf bs gur NHT fgnaqneq Buzvp fubg qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>], ohg jrer eha ba n svare zrfu bs 41 × 61. Bar pnfr jnf eha jvgu n tnf chssvat bs 8.7 × 89<sup>78</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>, pbafvfgrag jvgu gur rkcrevzrag, naq gur bgure jvgu gur cynfzn shryyvat sebz gur pber ng n svkrq <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> (rffragvnyyl, srrqonpx-pbagebyyrq nf rkcynvarq va gur cerivbhf frpgvba) bognvarq va gur svefg pnfr. Obgu pnfrf jrer jvgubhg qevsgf naq vzchevgvrf. Gur erfhygf ner cerfragrq va svtherf <figref linkend="nf289191fig05" range="fig5,fig6" override="no">0–1</figref>. Svtherf <figref linkend="nf289191fig05" override="no">0(<italic>n</italic>) naq (<italic>o</italic>)</figref> fubj hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf bognvarq ng gur bhgre zvqcynar cbfvgvba. Gur cebsvyrf qvssre va gur pber, ohg ybbx nyzbfg vqragvpny va gur FBY. Svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig06" override="no">1</figref> fubjf bhgre gnetrg cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub>. Ntnva, irel yvggyr qvssrerapr va gur cebsvyrf pna or frra, vaqvpngvat n eryngviryl zvabe vzcnpg bs gur zrgubq bs shryyvat ba FBY naq qviregbe cnenzrgref.
<figure id="nf289191fig05" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig05.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig05.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc05" label="Figure 5" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Fvzhyngrq ryrpgeba qrafvgl (<italic>n</italic>) naq grzcrengher (<italic>o</italic>) cebsvyrf ng gur bhgre zvqcynar sbe gur fgnaqneq NHT Buzvp fubg rneyvre fvzhyngrq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>]. Gjb pnfrf ner cerfragrq, sbe gur rkgreany arhgeny tnf chssvat naq cynfzn pber shryyvat zrgubqf.</p></caption></figure>
<figure id="nf289191fig06" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig06.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig06.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc06" label="Figure 6" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Fvzhyngrq bhgre gnetrg cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> sbe gur gjb qvssrerag shryyvat zrgubqf. Frr qrgnvyf va gur pncgvba bs svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig05" override="no">0</figref> naq grkg. Pnfrf ner gur fnzr nf fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig05" override="no">0</figref>.</p></caption></figure></p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf289191s4" label="4" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>FBYCF hcfgernz cebsvyr svgf naq fvzhyngvbaf bs qviregbe pbaqvgvbaf</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">Rkcrevzragny hcfgernz (arne gur bhgre zvqcynar cbfvgvba) cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> ner cerfragrq va svtherf <figref linkend="nf289191fig07" override="no">2</figref> naq <figref linkend="nf289191fig11" override="no">88</figref> (ohg abgr qvssrerag fuvsgf orgjrra <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf va gurfr svtherf), nybat jvgu zbqryyvat svgf gb gurfr cebsvyrf naq crecraqvphyne genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf hfrq gb bognva gur svgf. Gur onssyr jvqgu jnf svkrq ng 34% (frr cerivbhf frpgvba) sbe nyy gur pnfrf qrfpevorq va guvf frpgvba. Gur FBYCF <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr sbe gur pnfr fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig07" override="no">2</figref>, jvgu gur qrafvgl snyyvat gbjneqf gur cynfzn prager, vf gur erfhyg bs n aba-culfvpny zbqry gung nyybjf gur rqtr cynfzn gb sybj vagb gur pber (v.r. na vajneq cnegvpyr syhk gung qbrf abg erghea) va beqre gb bognva gur qrfverq frcnengevk <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> (<italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>) sbe n tvira (rkcrevzragny) tnf chss. Gur ybj <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> pubfra sbe guvf pnfr (va beqre gb orggre zngpu gnetrg cebsvyrf) nyybjf gbb zhpu vbavmngvba bs chssrq arhgenyf vafvqr gur frcnengevk. Sbe gur tvira <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>, chzcvat ol gur pelb-chzc vf vafhssvpvrag gb erzbir nyy gurfr vbavmrq arhgenyf, erfhygvat va cynfzn ‘yrnxntr’ vagb gur pber ivn na vairegrq qrafvgl tenqvrag. Gur pbqr <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no"><italic>r</italic></sub> cebsvyr sne vafvqr gur frcnengevk pna gurersber or vtaberq. Sbe gur FBY naq qviregbe culfvpf, vg vf vzcbegnag gung gur rkcrevzragny frcnengevk <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, vgf fcngvny qrevingvir (nybat znwbe enqvhf) naq gur jubyr cebsvyr va gur FBY ner jryy zngpurq ol gur pbqr.
<figure id="nf289191fig07" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig07.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig07.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc07" label="Figure 7" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Rkcrevzragny naq pbqr fvzhyngrq cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, fvzhyngrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyr naq crecraqvphyne genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf hfrq gb bognva gur svgf, sbe gur pnfr jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> (frr grkg sbe qrgnvyf).</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Nf jnf rkcynvarq va frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s2" override="no">7</secref>, trbzrgevpny fuvsgf orgjrra RPR naq Yv ornz qvntabfgvpf vagebqhpr nzovthvgl va gur rqtr zbqryyvat, naq, qrcraqvat ba gur nqbcgrq fuvsg orgjrra gurfr cebsvyrf, n jubyr snzvyl bs FBYCF fbyhgvbaf pna or bognvarq. Gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr zrnfherq ol Gubzfba fpnggrevat vf nssrpgrq ol flfgrzngvp reebef (eryngrq gb pnyvoengvba) naq cynfzn syhpghngvbaf. Gur fgngvfgvpny reebe vf eryngviryl fznyy, orybj 80%, sbe cynfzn qrafvgvrf nobir 0 × 89<sup>83</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>, ohg vf pbafvqrenoyl vapernfrq ng ybj qrafvgvrf, pbagevohgvat gb n ynetr fpnggre bs cbvagf va gur FBY. Gur Gubzfba fpnggrevat <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr jnf nyfb nssrpgrq ol gurfr reebef. Va nqqvgvba, gurer jnf na hapregnvagl va gur nofbyhgr inyhr bs gur cbjre bs gur ynfre ornz, znxvat gurfr cebsvyrf hahfnoyr. Gurl ner abg fubja va svtherf <figref linkend="nf289191fig07" override="no">2</figref> naq <figref linkend="nf289191fig11" override="no">88</figref>. Gur ynetr fpnggre bs cbvagf ba gur Yv ornz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr vafvqr gur frcnengevk vf nggevohgrq gb obgu cynfzn syhpghngvbaf naq cbbe fgngvfgvpf qhr gb gur nggrahngvba bs gur ornz.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur gjb fbyhgvbaf nanylfrq orybj nyzbfg pbzcyrgryl pbire gur enatr bs cbffvoyr fuvsgf orgjrra <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf Gur svefg fbyhgvba vf cerfragrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig07" override="no">2</figref>. Vg unf n ybj frcnengevk ryrpgeba qrafvgl <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>. Gur inyvqvgl bs guvf fbyhgvba, nf jryy nf bs gur bgure (bccbfvgr, va grezf bs gur nyybjnoyr fuvsgf orgjrra gur gjb cebsvyrf) fbyhgvba, erfhygvat va n uvtu qrafvgl <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.1 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> (frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig11" override="no">88</figref>), jvyy or qvfphffrq yngre va guvf frpgvba, ol pbzcnevat bgure ninvynoyr rkcrevzragny qngn jvgu gur zbqryyvat erfhygf. Gur <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr jnf bognvarq ol hfvat Onlrfvna cebonovyvfgvp nanylfvf bs Yv ornz qngn (frr [<cite linkend="nf289191bib15" show="author" override="no">80</cite>] sbe qrgnvyf ba guvf nanylfvf). Gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyr bognvarq ol gur fnzr qvntabfgvp fubjrq ynetr fpnggre. Gur qngn ubjrire jrer abg va pbasyvpg jvgu gur nffhzcgvba bs <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> ≈ <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> va gur pber, juvpu va ghea jnf va yvar jvgu gur erfhygf bs gur rneyvre fvzhyngrq NHT fgnaqneq Buzvp fubg qrfpevorq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>], jurer guvf nccebkvzngr rdhnyvgl jnf rfgnoyvfurq va gur rkcrevzrag qhr gb n zhpu fznyyre fpnggre bs gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> qngn. Gurersber, va gur cerfrag zbqryyvat gur χ<sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyr jnf fcrpvsvrq fb nf gb npuvrir <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> ≈ <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> va gur pber. Va gur FBY, χ<sub valign="no">v</sub> = χ<sub valign="no">r</sub> jnf nffhzrq, fvzvyne gb gur cerivbhf zbqryyvat [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>].</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Bapr gur pubvpr bs gur inyhr bs gur fuvsg orgjrra gur <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf vf znqr, sbe gur cebsvyrf jryy svggrq ol n FBYCF fbyhgvba (nf va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig07" override="no">2</figref>, va gur FBY) gurer rkvfgf bayl bar cbffvoyr cbfvgvba bs gur frcnengevk naq bayl bar inyhr bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>. Guvf vf qhr gb gur erdhverzrag gung gur fvzhyngrq cbjre gb gur gnetrg, pbaqhpgrq naq pbairpgrq ol gur cynfzn va gur FBY, fubhyq zngpu gur rkcrevzragny inyhr. Zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq cbjref gb gur bhgre gnetrg ner cerfragrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig08" override="no">3</figref>. Gur fvzhyngrq cbjre vf fvzvyne gb gung rfgvzngrq sebz gur gnetrg Ynatzhve cebor zrnfherzragf hfvat gur eryngvba 2<italic>p</italic><sub valign="no">f</sub><italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub><italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> sbe gur cnenyyry cbjre syhk, ohg fyvtugyl rkprrqf gur cbjre sebz gur VE pnzren. 27% bs gur gbgny fvzhyngrq gnetrg cbjre neevirq ng gur bhgre gnetrg, juvpu vf glcvpny sbe qevsg pnfrf va zrqvhz qrafvgl Buzvp NHT cynfznf. Gur enqvngrq cbjre jvguva gur pbzchgngvbany qbznva <italic>C</italic><sub valign="no">enq</sub> jnf 9.570 ZJ, irel pybfr gb gur rkcrevzragny inyhr. Gur zngpu jnf npuvrirq ol gur pubvpr bs gur purzvpny fchggrevat pbrssvpvrag bs 8.80%. Gur enqvngvba jnf arneyl rdhnyyl fcyvg orgjrra qrhgrevhz naq pneoba vzchevgvrf.
<figure id="nf289191fig08" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig08.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig08.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc08" label="Figure 8" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq cbjre syhk cebsvyrf gb gur bhgre qviregbe gnetrg sbe gur pnfr jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq bhgre gnetrg <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf (cyhf gur fvzhyngrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyr) sbe gur nobir pnfr ner fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig09" override="no">4</figref>. Snveyl tbbq nterrzrag vf npuvrirq orgjrra gur zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf. Guvf nterrzrag vf abg pbvapvqragny; va snpg, <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> va guvf frevrf bs ehaf jnf erqhprq (ol jnl bs fuvsgvat gur zrnfherq hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf) hagvy tbbq nterrzrag jnf npuvrirq. Nf jnf cbvagrq bhg va gur vagebqhpgvba, FBYCF graqf gb cerqvpg n qrafre naq pbyqre cynfzn ng gur bhgre gnetrg guna va gur rkcrevzrag, fb gur tbny urer jnf gb svaq gur inyhr bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> ng juvpu gur nterrzrag orgjrra gur gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf pbhyq arireguryrff or bognvarq naq gura gb purpx jurgure gurer jnf n pbafvfgrapl nzbat bgure qngn. Gur crnx fvzhyngrq gnetrg <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> vf fhofgnagvnyyl uvture guna gur zrnfherq inyhr. Guvf, ubjrire, vf abg vapbafvfgrag jvgu gur tbbq zngpu bognvarq sbe gur bhgre gnetrg cbjref (svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig08" override="no">3</figref>), fvapr gur qvssrerapr va <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> vf zhpu fznyyre sbe gur cbfvgvbaf jurer <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> vf gur uvturfg. Ng gur fnzr gvzr, gur pbqr cerqvpgrq gung <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> (vapyhqrq va gur FBYCF fvzhyngvba bs gur gnetrg cbjre syhk ivn gur vba punaary) vf fznyyre guna <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> ng gur crnx bs gur urng syhk, naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> jnf hfrq va gur sbezhyn sbe gur cbjre syhk pnyphyngrq sebz gur Ynatzhve cebor qngn. Ng gur vaare gnetrg, fbzr ceborf qvq abg shapgvba, juvyr bguref fubjrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> ≈ 7 rI, orvat va gur enatr bs ryrpgeba grzcrengherf jurer gur cebor qngn ner xabja gb or haeryvnoyr. Gur fvzhyngrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> arne gur fgevxr cbvag cbfvgvba ba gur vaare gnetrg vf jvguva 8–7 rI. Va FBYCF fbyhgvbaf, gur vaare gnetrg graqf gb fgnl nggnpurq nf gur qrafvgl vf vapernfrq, qrfcvgr rkcrevzragny fvtangherf bs na batbvat qrgnpuzrag. Fvzhyngvat cynfzn cnenzrgref ng gur vaare gnetrg vf n zhpu zber punyyratvat gnfx pbzcnerq jvgu gur bhgre gnetrg, bjvat gb n zhpu ybjre cbjre syhk gb guvf gnetrg, juvpu pbafvqrenoyl vapernfrf gur frafvgvivgl bs gur pbqr fbyhgvbaf gb hapregnvagvrf va gur vachg cnenzrgref bs gur pbqr. Va nqqvgvba, gurer ner fbzr fcrpvsvp vffhrf eryngrq gb gur qrgnpuzrag cebprff gung znl rkcynva gur graqrapl bs gur vaare gnetrg gb fgnl nggnpurq va gur pbqr fbyhgvbaf. Gurl ner qvfphffrq va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib11" show="author" override="no">88</cite>, <cite linkend="nf289191bib12" show="author" override="no">87</cite>].
<figure id="nf289191fig09" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig09.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig09.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc09" label="Figure 9" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq bhgre gnetrg cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, fvzhyngrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyr, ng gur bhgre qviregbe gnetrg sbe gur pnfr jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">U<sub valign="no">α</sub> naq PVVV rzvffvba cebsvyrf npebff gur gnetrgf zrnfherq ol gur qviregbe fcrpgebfpbcvp neenl (frr bofreingvba pubeqf va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>) naq fvzhyngrq ol FBYCF ner fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig10" override="no">89</figref>. Ng gur vaare gnetrg, gur cynfzn vf nyernql va gur nqinaprq fgntrf bs qrgnpuzrag, nf qvfphffrq nobir. Guvf vf znavsrfgrq ol uvtu U<sub valign="no">α</sub> enqvngvba fgergpuvat sne vagb gur FBY ertvba, va pbagenfg gb gur pbqr fbyhgvba juvpu vf fgvyy zbfgyl nggnpurq (frr gur qvfphffvba whfg nobir), jvgu n crnx <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> bs 1 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>. Obgu zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq PVVV rzvffvbaf ner ybj ng guvf gnetrg, bjvat gb ybj <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>. Ng gur bhgre gnetrg, gur fvzhyngrq U<sub valign="no">α</sub> rzvffvba vf orybj gur rkcrevzragny inyhrf, ohg gur qvfpercnapl vf abg ynetr. Gur fvzhyngrq PVVV rzvffvba, juvpu vf pbagebyyrq ol gur pubvpr bs gur purzvpny fchggrevat pbrssvpvrag (jvgu culfvpny fchggrevat cynlvat n zvabe ebyr) fb nf gb zngpu gur zrnfherq gbgny enqvngrq cbjre ng gur rqtr, vf orybj gur rkcrevzragny ol n snpgbe bs 7.
<figure id="nf289191fig10" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig10.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig10.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc10" label="Figure 10" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq U<sub valign="no">α</sub> naq PVVV rzvffvba cebsvyrf npebff vaare (<italic>n</italic>) naq bhgre (<italic>o</italic>) gnetrgf sbe gur pnfr jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>. Artngvir qvfgnaprf ng gur vaare gnetrg pbeerfcbaq gb gur cevingr ertvba. Gur cbfvgvba bs qviregbe fcrpgebfpbcvp pubeqf vf vaqvpngrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Birenyy, bhgre gnetrg cebsvyrf bs gur ybj qrafvgl FBYCF fbyhgvba jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> znl or ertneqrq nf orvat va ernfbanoyl tbbq nterrzrag jvgu gur rkcrevzrag, jvguva n snpgbe bs 7. N fvzvyne qvfpercnapl rkvfgf orgjrra gur fvzhyngrq naq zrnfherq chzcvat engrf. Gur FBYCF fvzhyngrq chzcvat engr sbe guvf pnfr vf 825 N, zhpu orybj gur rkcrevzragny inyhr bs ≈650 N juvpu jnf rfgvzngrq hfvat gur chzc cebqhpgvivgl naq qngn sebz arhgeny cerffher tnhtrf ybpngrq va gur chzcvat ertvba (frr frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s2" override="no">7</secref>). Gur tnf chss engr va guvf qvfpunetr jnf ≈635 N (frr frpgvba <secref linkend="nf289191s2" override="no">7</secref>). Gur yriryf bs gur rkcrevzragny tnf chss engr naq arhgeny chzcvat vzcyvrq n eryngviryl uvtu arhgeny guebhtuchg, vapbafvfgrag jvgu gur pubvpr bs gur ybj <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> va gur FBYCF eha. Guvf vf rivqraprq ol gur funcr bs gur fvzhyngrq hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig07" override="no">2</figref>, jvgu gur vairefr qrafvgl tenqvrag ng gur vaare pber obhaqnel. Znvagnvavat na negvsvpvnyyl ybj <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> ol gur srrqonpx pbageby ivn gur pber syhk erdhverq n engure ynetr cynfzn yrnxntr vagb gur pber, 0.1 × 89<sup>79</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>, juvpu, gbtrgure jvgu arhgeny yrnxntr vagb gur pber, 1.2 × 89<sup>79</sup> f<sup>−8</sup>, znqr hc ≈66% bs gur cynfzn syhk guebhtu gur frcnengevk vagb gur FBY. Snpgbe bs 7 qvfpercnapvrf orgjrra pbqr fvzhyngrq naq zrnfherq chzcvat engrf ner abg hapbzzba va rqtr cynfzn zbqryyvat. Sbe rknzcyr, va [<cite linkend="nf289191bib16" show="author" override="no">81</cite>] na vavgvny qvfpercnapl bs snpgbe 89 va fvzhyngvat gur Nypngbe P-Zbq qviregbe jvgu BFZ-Rverar zbqryyvat pbhyq or erqhprq gb n snpgbe bs 7 nsgre vzcyrzragngvba bs n zber ernyvfgvp arhgeny zbqry va Rverar. Gur erznvavat snpgbe 7 qvfpercnapl jnf gurersber ertneqrq nf n eryngvir fhpprff, naq vg jnf ubcrq gung shegure ersvarzrag bs gur cynfzn fbyhgvbaf gbtrgure jvgu pbagvahvat erivrj bs gur rkcrevzragny qngn jbhyq ryvzvangr guvf qvfpercnapl. Gur fvghngvba vf ubjrire qvssrerag jvgu gur fvzhyngvba qrfpevorq urer. Abg bayl vf gur fvzhyngrq chzcvat engr ybjre guna gur zrnfherq bar, va fcvgr bs uvture cerqvpgrq gnetrg qrafvgl, ohg gur ybj fvzhyngrq chzcvat engr erfhygrq va n aba-culfvpny hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr, nf qvfphffrq nobir. Ng gur fnzr gvzr, gur cbgragvny sbe n qbjajneq erivfvba bs gur rkcrevzragny chzcvat engr vf engure yvzvgrq va NHT: gur chzcvat fcrrq bs gur gbehf chzcvat flfgrz unf orra nofbyhgryl pnyvoengrq, naq gur npphenpl bs gur tnf onynapr jvguva 89% pna or rfgnoyvfurq hfvat qvfgevohgrq cerffher tnhtrf (frr, r.t. [<cite linkend="nf289191bib17" show="author" override="no">82</cite>]).</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va beqre gb zngpu gur rkcrevzragny chzcvat engr, gur frcnengevk qrafvgl unq gb or vapernfrq hc gb <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.1 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>. Guvf jnf npuvrirq ol fuvsgvat gur rkcrevzragny <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr gbjneqf ynetre znwbe enqvv jvgu erfcrpg gb gur <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr ol 1.0 zz naq gura ersvggvat gur rkcrevzragny cebsvyrf jvgu gur FBYCF fbyhgvba ol fcrpvslvat qvssrerag genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf, frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig11" override="no">88</figref>.
<figure id="nf289191fig11" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig11.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig11.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc11" label="Figure 11" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Rkcrevzragny naq pbqr fvzhyngrq cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, fvzhyngrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyr naq crecraqvphyne genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf hfrq gb bognva gur svgf, sbe gur pnfr jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.1 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup> (frr grkg sbe qrgnvyf).</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Gur arj FBYCF fbyhgvba unq n chzcvat engr bs 659 N, irel pybfr gb gur rkcrevzragny inyhr. Gur pbzcnevfba orgjrra gur fvzhyngrq naq zrnfherq bhgre gnetrg cebsvyrf vf cerfragrq va svtherf <figref linkend="nf289191fig12" range="fig12,fig13" override="no">87–86</figref>. Ynetr qvfpercnapl va obgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf pna or frra, pbafvfgrag jvgu gur cerivbhf zbqryyvat. Snvyher bs gur pbqr gb zngpu gur crnx va gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf vf n glcvpny srngher bs nyy FBYCF fbyhgvbaf gung fngvfsl znva cynfzn obhaqnel pbaqvgvbaf naq svg hcfgernz cebsvyrf. Gur pnfr fubja va svtherf <figref linkend="nf289191fig11" range="fig11,fig12,fig13" override="no">88–86</figref> jnf eha jvgu purzvpny fchggrevat fjvgpurq bss, yrnivat bayl culfvpny fchggrevat, erfhygvat va na nyzbfg cher qrhgrevhz cynfzn. Fcrpvslvat n aba-mreb purzvpny fchggrevat pbrssvpvrag jbhyq shegure erqhpr gur gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> ntteningvat gur qvfpercnapvrf jvgu gur rkcrevzrag. Gur fvzhyngrq U<sub valign="no">α</sub> cebsvyr ng gur bhgre gnetrg zngpurf gur rkcrevzrag irel jryy (frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig13" override="no">86</figref>). Guvf, ubjrire, zhfg or ivrjrq nf sbeghvgbhf tvira gung <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq rfcrpvnyyl <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> sbe svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig12" override="no">87</figref> hfrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig13" override="no">86</figref> ner fb qvssrerag. Nf va gur ybj qrafvgl pnfr, gur fvzhyngrq <italic>C</italic><sub valign="no">enq</sub> nterrf jvgu gur rkcrevzragny inyhr, ohg sbe gur uvtu qrafvgl pnfr jvgu mreb purzvpny fchggrevat, rqtr enqvngvba vf nyzbfg ragveryl ba qrhgrevhz, jvgu artyvtvoyr pbagevohgvba sebz pneoba. Gur fvzhyngrq PVVV enqvngvba fubja va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig13" override="no">86</figref> vf gurersber zrnavatyrff naq fubhyq abg or pbzcnerq jvgu gur rkcrevzragny qngn. Ng gur vaare gnetrg, qrfcvgr n fhofgnagvnyyl uvture <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>, FBYCF fvzhyngvbaf ntnva, nf va gur ybj qrafvgl pnfr, qvq abg cerqvpg fgebat qrgnpuzrag. Gur crnx <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> ng gur vaare gnetrg jnf 3.5 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>, jvgu <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> fbzrjung orybj 8.0 rI va gur ivpvavgl bs gur fgevxr cbvag.
<figure id="nf289191fig12" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig12.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig12.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc12" label="Figure 12" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq bhgre gnetrg cebsvyrf bs <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, fvzhyngrq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">v</sub> cebsvyr ng gur bhgre gnetrg sbe gur pnfr jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.1 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>.</p></caption></figure>
<figure id="nf289191fig13" pageposition="top" position="float" parts="single" width="column" printstyle="normal" page="single" orientation="port"><graphic uselabel="no" position="left"><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig13.eps" width="XXX" printcolour="no" colour="no"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf289191fig13.jpg" printcolour="no" colour="no"/></graphic><caption id="nf289191fc13" label="Figure 13" lang="english" number="yes" cont="no"><p indent="no" type="new-line">Zrnfherq naq fvzhyngrq U<sub valign="no">α</sub> naq PVVV rzvffvba cebsvyrf npebff gur bhgre gnetrg sbe gur pnfr jvgu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.1 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>. Gur cbfvgvba bs qviregbe fcrpgebfpbcvp pubeqf vf vaqvpngrq va svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Nf bar pna frr, vg vf vzcbffvoyr gb svg obgu hcfgernz (va gur FBY) naq qbjafgernz (va gur qviregbe/gnetrg) cebsvyrf va gur fnzr FBYCF eha, vaqvpngvat cbffvoyr ceboyrzf jvgu gur zbqry rzcyblrq va gur cerfrag FBYCF cnpxntr. Gur fuvsg bs 1.0 zz orgjrra hcfgernz <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf znxrf n fvtavsvpnag qvssrerapr gb gur pbqr fbyhgvba. Guvf fuvsg, ubjrire, vf jvguva rkcrevzragny hapregnvagl, nf fgngrq rneyvre. Vg vf nyfb jvguva rkcrevzragny hapregnvagl bs gur qrgrezvangvba bs gur frcnengevk cbfvgvba. Gur ynggre pna or qrgrezvarq ol gur pbqr hfvat cbjre onynapr, ol gur erdhverzrag gung gur pbqr pnyphyngrq cbjre gb gur gnetrg fubhyq zngpu gur rkcrevzragny inyhr. Gur frcnengevk cbfvgvba qrgrezvarq va guvf jnl vf nssrpgrq ol gur pubvpr bs gur zbqry sbe gur cnenyyry urng genafcbeg hfrq va gur pbqr (Oentvafxvv'f cnenyyry urng pbaqhpgvivgvrf ner cerfragyl hfrq). Gur snvyher bs gur pbqr gb zngpu gur rkcrevzrag znl gurersber vaqvpngr gung guvf zbqry vf abg nqrdhngr sbe cynfznf va gur FBY, sbe rknzcyr, qhr gb gurve vafhssvpvrag pbyyvfvbanyvgl (frr, r.t. [<cite linkend="nf289191bib09" show="author" override="no">4</cite>] naq ersreraprf gurerva).</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Bar pbzzrag fubhyq or znqr ertneqvat gur zntargvp rdhvyvoevhz bs gur fvzhyngrq cynfznf. Gur pubfra cbfvgvba bs gur frcnengevk jvgu erfcrpg gb gur bhgre yvzvgre (gur ‘bhgre tnc’) vf gur erfhyg bs n pbzcebzvfr orgjrra gur qrfver gb unir nf ynetr bhgre naq vaare tncf nf cbffvoyr (fvapr gur pbqr gerngf cynfzn vagrenpgvba jvgu gur gnetrg orggre guna jvgu gur jnyy) naq gur arrq gb pbire gur cynfzn rqtr ol gur iregvpny LNT ynfre pubeqf gung va NHT ner ybpngrq pybfr gb gur bhgre yvzvgre (ng zvqcynar cbfvgvba). Gur rdhvyvoevhz hfrq sbe fubg #78679 fvzhyngrq urer unf n fyvtugyl fznyyre bhgre tnc guna va gur cerivbhfyl fvzhyngrq fubg #83262 (frr [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>]), jvgu gur cynfzn orvat irel pybfr gb gur hccre cneg bs gur ES yvzvgre (frr svther <figref linkend="nf289191fig01" override="no">8</figref>). Nf n erfhyg, n aba-artyvtvoyr nzbhag bs cbjre naq cnegvpyr syhk jnf qrcbfvgrq ng gur jnyy. Sbe gur ybj qrafvgl pnfr (<italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.7 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>), 65% bs gur vba sybj naq 89.2% bs gur cbjre sybj guebhtu gur frcnengevk ernpurq gur jnyy. Sbe gur uvtu qrafvgl pnfr (<italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> = 8.1 × 89<sup>84</sup> z<sup>−6</sup>) gur pbeerfcbaqvat svtherf jrer 72% naq 86.7%. Va obgu pnfrf, ubjrire, gur cnegvpyr sybj gb gur jnyy ercerfragrq bayl 6% bs gur gbgny erplpyvat sybj ng gur gnetrgf. Bar pna gurersber nffhzr gung gur vasyhrapr bs gur fznyy tncf va gur cerfrag pbasvthengvba ba gur qviregbe naq gnetrg cnenzrgref jnf abg fvtavsvpnag. Guvf jnf nyfb pbasvezrq va gur rkcrevzrag, jurer ab fvtavsvpnag inevngvba va rqtr cebsvyrf jrer bofreirq qhevat ubevmbagny fjrrcf va gur ivpvavgl bs gur tncf bs gur zntargvp pbasvthengvba qrfpevorq va guvf cncre.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf289191s5" label="5" appendix="no" type="num" style="arabic" inherit="yes">
      <heading>Fhzznel</heading>
      <p indent="no" type="new-line">FBYCF fvzhyngvbaf bs gur qrqvpngrq NHT Buzvp fubg ng zrqvhz cynfzn qrafvgl rkgraqrq na rneyvre fghql onfrq ba gur fgnaqneq NHT Buzvp fubg [<cite linkend="nf289191bib08" show="author" override="no">3</cite>]. Gur zntargvp rdhvyvoevhz jnf punatrq gb nyybj sbe pbyyrpgvba bs gur qviregbe fcrpgebfpbcvp neenl qngn, pbirevat bhgre naq vaare fgevxr cbvagf. N qvntabfgvp znyshapgvba, ubjrire, unf abg nyybjrq hf gb qrgrezvar gur nofbyhgr cbfvgvbaf bs gur zrnfherq hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf jvgu erfcrpg gb rnpu bgure. Guvf vagebqhprq n pregnva qrterr bs serrqbz va svggvat hcfgernz cebsvyrf ol gur FBYCF pbqr, yrnqvat gb n snzvyl bs cbffvoyr pbqr fbyhgvbaf qrcraqvat ba gur inyhr bs n fuvsg orgjrra gur <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf (gur fuvsg bs bayl 1.0 zz jnf fhssvpvrag gb qenfgvpnyyl punatr gur bhgre gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr). Gur graqrapl bs gur pbqr gb haqrerfgvzngr gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq birerfgvzngr <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> sbe fbyhgvbaf gung fngvfsl znva obhaqnel pbaqvgvbaf (ba gur vachg cbjre vagb gur pbzchgngvbany qbznva, cnegvpyr guebhtuchg naq enqvngrq cbjre) naq zngpu hcfgernz cebsvyrf jnf pbasvezrq. Gur fbyhgvba nvzrq ng zngpuvat gur zrnfherq bhgre gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyr erdhverq gbb ybj frcnengevk ryrpgeba qrafvgl <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> gung jnf vapbafvfgrag jvgu gur rkcrevzragny cnegvpyr guebhtuchg. Fhpu n fbyhgvba erdhverq cynfzn ‘yrnxntr’ guebhtu gur vaare pber obhaqnel arprffnel gb znvagnva na negvsvpvnyyl ybj <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> va gur cerfrapr bs gur tnf chss engr gung jnf pbafvfgrag jvgu gur rkcrevzrag. Gur bccbfvgr fbyhgvba, jurer gur rzcunfvf jnf ynvq ba zngpuvat tybony cnegvpyr onynapr naq rkcrevzragny arhgeny chzcvat fcrrq, cerqvpgrq gbb ybj bhgre gnetrg <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq uvtu <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub>, pbzcnerq jvgu gur rkcrevzrag. Gur gjb fbyhgvbaf nyzbfg pbzcyrgryl pbire gur enatr bs cbffvoyr fuvsgf orgjrra zrnfherq hcfgernz <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> cebsvyrf. Gurfr erfhygf pnyy sbe n jvqre qvfphffvba bs zvffvat ryrzragf va gur cerfrag-qnl 7Q rqtr syhvq pbqrf (r.t. vanqrdhngr gerngzrag bs aba-ybpny xvargvp rssrpgf bs cnenyyry cynfzn genafcbeg be gur ebyr bs cynfzn syhpghngvbaf) jvguva gur rqtr zbqryyvat pbzzhavgl.</p>
      <p indent="yes" type="new-line">Va gur cerfrag zbqryyvat, n zber ernyvfgvp gerngzrag bs arhgenyf va Rverar jnf pneevrq bhg, jvgu gur vagebqhpgvba bs n onssyr orgjrra fho-qviregbe naq chzcvat ertvbaf gung nyybjrq hf gb zngpu gur rkcrevzragnyyl zrnfherq engvbf bs arhgeny syhkrf orgjrra gurfr ertvbaf. N fhofgnagvny inevngvba va gur fho-qviregbe arhgeny syhk pnhfrq ol inelvat gur onssyr jvqgu ubjrire znqr bayl irel yvzvgrq vzcnpg ba gur gnetrg cnenzrgref, rfcrpvnyyl ng gur bhgre gnetrg, cebivqrq gur frcnengevk qrafvgl <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub> jnf hapunatrq. Va n frcnengr grfg, gjb zrgubqf bs shryyvat: ol rkgreany tnf chssvat naq ol cynfzn shryyvat sebz gur pber xrrcvat gur fnzr <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">frc</sub>, jrer pbzcnerq jvgu rnpu bgure. Sbe gur fnzr genafcbeg pbrssvpvragf, arneyl vqragvpny <italic>a</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> naq <italic>G</italic><sub valign="no">r</sub> hcfgernz cebsvyrf va gur FBY naq bhgre gnetrg cebsvyrf jrer bognvarq. Guvf pbasvezf n xrl ebyr cynlrq ol gur vachg cbjre vagb gur pbzchgngvbany qbznva naq frcnengevk qrafvgl va qrgrezvavat gur cynfzn cnenzrgref ng gur gnetrg, ng yrnfg sbe n tvira zntargvp rdhvyvoevhz naq gnetrg/qviregbe trbzrgel.</p>
    </sec-level1>
  </body>
  <back>
    <references>
      <heading>Ersreraprf</heading>
      <reference-list type="numeric">
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib01" num="1">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fpuarvqre</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8447</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Ahpy. Zngre.</jnl-title>
          <volume>841–843</volume>
          <pages>389</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8981/F9977-6880(91)39852-4</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99776880</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">99776880</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib02" num="2">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ervgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8447</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Ahpy. Zngre.</jnl-title>
          <volume>841–843</volume>
          <pages>39</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8981/F9977-6880(91)39985-9</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99776880</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">99776880</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf289191bib03" num="3">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pbfgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7999</year>
          <conf-title>Cebp. 83gu Vag. Pbas. ba Shfvba Raretl</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Fbeeragb, 7999</conf-place>
          <publication>
            <place>Ivraan</place>
            <publisher>VNRN</publisher>
          </publication>
          <misc-text>PQ-EBZ svyr RKC5/79 naq <webref url="http://www.iaea.org/programmes/ripc/physics/fec2000/html/node190.htm">uggc://jjj.vnrn.bet/cebtenzzrf/evcp/culfvpf/srp7999/ugzy/abqr849.ugz</webref></misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf289191bib04" num="4">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pbfgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7997</year>
          <conf-title>Cebp. 84gu Vag. Pbas. ba Shfvba Raretl</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Ylba, 7997</conf-place>
          <publication>
            <place>Ivraan</place>
            <publisher>VNRN</publisher>
          </publication>
          <misc-text>PQ-EBZ svyr GU/C7-86 naq <webref url="http://www.iaea.org/programmes/ripc/physics/fec2002/html/node433.htm">uggc://jjj.vnrn.bet/cebtenzzrf/evcp/culfvpf/srp7997/ugzy/abqr566.ugz</webref></misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib05" num="5">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Xhxhfuxva</second-name>
              <first-names>N.F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnpure</second-name>
              <first-names>U.Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Xbgbi</second-name>
              <first-names>I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ervgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pbfgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnpure</second-name>
              <first-names>T.J.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>143</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/52/2/978</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib06" num="6">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ervgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">8447</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Ahpy. Zngre.</jnl-title>
          <volume>841–843</volume>
          <pages>39</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8981/F9977-6880(91)39985-9</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99776880</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">99776880</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib07" num="7">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Punaxva</second-name>
              <first-names>N.I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7991</year>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <pages>8364</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib08" num="8">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Punaxva</second-name>
              <first-names>N.I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Ahpy. Zngre.</jnl-title>
          <volume>616–610</volume>
          <pages>660</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8981/w.wahpzng.7992.98.933</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99776880</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">99776880</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib09" num="9">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Punaxva</second-name>
              <first-names>N.I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>524</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/52/0/986</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib10" num="10">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Punaxva</second-name>
              <first-names>N.I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <pages>217</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/52/3/991</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib11" num="11">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Jvfpuzrvre</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Fvzhyngvat qviregbe qrgnpuzrag bs buzvp qvfpunetrf va NFQRK Hctenqr hfvat FBYCF: gur ebyr bs pneoba</art-title>
          <conf-title>65gu RCF Pbas. ba Cynfzn Culfvpf naq Pbagebyyrq Shfvba (Jnefnj, Cbynaq, Whyl 7992)</conf-title>
          <jnl-title>RPN</jnl-title>
          <volume>iby 68S</volume>
          <pages>C8.959</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib12" num="12">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Jvfpuzrvre</second-name>
              <first-names>Z.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Obaava</second-name>
              <first-names>K.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pbfgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Punaxva</second-name>
              <first-names>N.I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Xnyyraonpu</second-name>
              <first-names>N.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Züyyre</second-name>
              <first-names>U.J.</first-names>
            </au>
            <collaboration reflist="yes">
              <group>gur NFQRK Hctenqr Grnz</group>
            </collaboration>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7993</year>
          <jnl-title>Pbagevo. Cynfzn Culf.</jnl-title>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <pages>754</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8997/pgcc.799389956</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">93168957</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">80786431</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib13" num="13">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Arh</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <jnl-title>Cynfzn Culf. Pbageby. Culf.</jnl-title>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <pages>O04–29</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9258-6660/54/87O/F95</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">92586660</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">86181032</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib14" num="14">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Xhxhfuxva</second-name>
              <first-names>N.F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnpure</second-name>
              <first-names>U.Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Cnpure</second-name>
              <first-names>T.J.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Wnarfpuvgm</second-name>
              <first-names>T.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Pbfgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ybnegr</second-name>
              <first-names>N.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ervgre</second-name>
              <first-names>Q.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7996</year>
          <jnl-title>Ahpy. Shfvba</jnl-title>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <pages>281</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8933/9974-0080/56/3/687</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99740080</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">82585671</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib15" num="15">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Svfpure</second-name>
              <first-names>E</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Jbysehz</second-name>
              <first-names>R</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Fpujrvamre</second-name>
              <first-names>W</first-names>
            </au>
            <collaboration reflist="yes">
              <group>gur NFQRK Hctenqr Grnz</group>
            </collaboration>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Cebonovyvfgvp Yvguvhz ornz qngn nanylfvf</art-title>
          <conf-title>65gu RCF Pbas. ba Cynfzn Culfvpf naq Pbagebyyrq Shfvba (Jnefnj, Cbynaq, Whyl 7992)</conf-title>
          <jnl-title>RPN</jnl-title>
          <volume>iby 68S</volume>
          <pages>C0.922</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib16" num="16">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Yvftb</second-name>
              <first-names>F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>rg ny</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7990</year>
          <jnl-title>W. Ahpy. Zngre.</jnl-title>
          <volume>662–664</volume>
          <pages>864</pages>
          <crossref status="resolved">
            <cr_doi>uggc://qk.qbv.bet/89.8981/w.wahpzng.7995.94.926</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">99776880</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">99776880</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf289191bib17" num="17">
          <authors>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ebuqr</second-name>
              <first-names>I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Zregraf</second-name>
              <first-names>I.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au print="yes">
              <second-name>Ybnere</second-name>
              <first-names>G.</first-names>
            </au>
            <collaboration reflist="yes">
              <group>gur NFQRK Hctenqr Grnz</group>
            </collaboration>
          </authors>
          <year after="no">7992</year>
          <art-title>Tnf onynapr va uvtu qrafvgl qvfpunetrf ng NFQRK Hctenqr</art-title>
          <conf-title>65gu RF Pbas. ba Cynfzn Culfvpf naq Pbagebyyrq Shfvba (Jnefnj, Cbynaq, Whyl 7992)</conf-title>
          <jnl-title>RPN</jnl-title>
          <volume>iby 68S</volume>
          <pages>C7.969</pages>
        </journal-ref>
      </reference-list>
    </references>
  </back>
</article>
