<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../DTDs/IOP/iopv1_5_2.dtd">
<article artid="nf303578">
  <article-metadata>
    <jnl-data jnlid="nf">
      <jnl-fullname>Nuclear Fusion</jnl-fullname>
      <jnl-abbreviation>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-abbreviation>
      <jnl-shortname>NF</jnl-shortname>
      <jnl-issn>0029-5515</jnl-issn>
      <jnl-coden>NUFUAU</jnl-coden>
      <jnl-imprint>IOP Publishing and International Atomic Energy Agency</jnl-imprint>
      <jnl-web-address>stacks.iop.org/NF</jnl-web-address>
    </jnl-data>
    <volume-data>
      <year-publication>2009</year-publication>
      <volume-number>49</volume-number>
    </volume-data>
    <issue-data>
      <issue-number>5</issue-number>
      <coverdate>May 2009</coverdate>
    </issue-data>
    <article-data>
      <article-type type="paper" sort="regular"/>
      <type-number type="paper" numbering="article" artnum="055009"/>
      <article-number>303578</article-number>
      <first-page>1</first-page>
      <last-page>9</last-page>
      <length>9</length>
      <pii>S0029-5515(09)03578-9</pii>
      <doi>10.1088/0029-5515/49/5/055009</doi>
      <copyright>2009 IAEA, Vienna</copyright>
      <ccc>0029-5515/09/055009+09$30.00</ccc>
      <printed>Printed in the UK</printed>
      <features colour="global" mmedia="no" suppdata="no"/>
    </article-data>
  </article-metadata>
  <header>
    <title-group>
      <title>Improved confinement with internal electron transport barriers in RFX-mod</title>
      <short-title>Improved confinement with internal electron transport barriers in RFX-mod</short-title>
      <ej-title>Improved confinement with internal electron transport barriers in RFX-mod</ej-title>
    </title-group>
    <author-group>
      <author address="nf303578ad1" email="nf303578ea1">
        <first-names>L.</first-names>
        <second-name>Carraro</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>A.</first-names>
        <second-name>Alfier</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>F.</first-names>
        <second-name>Bonomo</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>A.</first-names>
        <second-name>Fassina</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>M.</first-names>
        <second-name>Gobbin</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>R.</first-names>
        <second-name>Lorenzini</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>P.</first-names>
        <second-name>Piovesan</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>M.E.</first-names>
        <second-name>Puiatti</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>G.</first-names>
        <second-name>Spizzo</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>D.</first-names>
        <second-name>Terranova</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>M.</first-names>
        <second-name>Valisa</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>M.</first-names>
        <second-name>Zuin</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>A.</first-names>
        <second-name>Canton</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>P.</first-names>
        <second-name>Franz</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>P.</first-names>
        <second-name>Innocente</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>R.</first-names>
        <second-name>Pasqualotto</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>F.</first-names>
        <second-name>Auriemma</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>S.</first-names>
        <second-name>Cappello</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>S.C.</first-names>
        <second-name>Guo</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>L.</first-names>
        <second-name>Marrelli</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>E.</first-names>
        <second-name>Martines</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>M.</first-names>
        <second-name>Spolaore</second-name>
      </author>
      <author address="nf303578ad1">
        <first-names>L.</first-names>
        <second-name>Zanotto</second-name>
      </author>
    </author-group>
    <address-group>
      <address id="nf303578ad1" showid="no"><orgname>Consorzio RFX, Associazione EURATOM-ENEA sulla fusione</orgname>, Padova, <country>Italy</country></address>
      <e-address id="nf303578ea1">
        <email mailto="lorella.carraro@igi.cnr.it">lorella.carraro@igi.cnr.it</email>
      </e-address>
    </address-group>
    <history received="23 December 2008" accepted="19 March 2009" online="9 April 2009"/>
    <abstract-group>
      <abstract>
        <heading>Abstract</heading>
        <p indent="no">RFX-mod reliably operates at 1.5 MA, the highest current ever achieved on a reversed field pinch device thanks to the the feedback control on multiple magnetohydrodynamic modes.</p>
        <p>In these high current discharges magnetic topology spontaneously self-organizes in an Ohmic helical symmetry, the quasi single helicity (QSH) state, in which the magnetic dynamics is dominated by the innermost resonant mode, with the new magnetic axis helically twisting around the geometrical axis of the torus.</p>
        <p>Inside the helical structure energy confinement is enhanced and electron temperatures exceeding 1 keV are measured, with steep gradients, which identify an internal transport barrier. Separatrix expulsion and symmetric electron temperature profiles with high gradients are obtained for ratios between the dominant mode and total <italic>B</italic> above about 4%. The measured electron temperature peak involves a large fraction of the plasma cross section, corresponding to an improvement in the global electron energy confinement up to a factor 2. The steep temperature profiles obtained in QSH conditions correspond to an electron thermal diffusivity reduced by more than one order of magnitude.</p>
        <p>Perturbative experiments (pellets and impurity laser blow off injections) have been performed to study particle confinement inside and outside the thermal island. Inside the helical structure experimental evidence of main gas confinement increase has been obtained, while for impurities there is no evidence of confinement increase.</p>
      </abstract>
    </abstract-group>
    <classifications>
      <class-codes scheme="pacs" print="yes">
        <code>52.55.Hc</code>
        <code>52.55.Tn</code>
        <code>52.55.Fi</code>
      </class-codes>
    </classifications>
  </header>
  <body numbering="bysection">
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s1" label="1">
      <heading>Introduction</heading>
      <p indent="no">The reversed field pinch (RFP) device RFX-mod (<italic>R</italic>/<italic>a</italic> = 2 m/0.459 m) is equipped with an actively controlled magnetic boundary which allows the compensation of error fields. The boundary control system is based on a full coverage mesh of 48×4 saddle coils [<cite linkend="nf303578bib01">1</cite>], with independent power supplies controlled by a digital feedback system, each with a sensor for the measurement of the radial, toroidal and poloidal magnetic field.</p>
      <p>The most recently developed control algorithm, dubbed clean mode control (CMC) [<cite linkend="nf303578bib02">2</cite>] allows a real time correction of the aliasing of the sideband harmonics generated by the discrete saddle coils. Plasma operation in CMC mode leads to a smoother (i.e. more axisymmetric) boundary, tearing modes rotation (up to 100 Hz) and partial unlocking. Plasma–wall interaction diminishes due to a decrease in the nonaxisymmetric perturbation of the plasma column. With this ameliorated boundary control, plasma current has been successfully increased to 1.5 MA, the highest reached by a RFP.</p>
      <p>At these high levels of plasma current, intermittently, but for a total duration covering most of the discharge, the magnetic dynamics is dominated by the innermost resonant mode and the internal magnetic topology approaches pure helical surfaces. This state dominated by a single mode corresponds to confinement enhancement since it is associated with the formation of a large hot helical core featuring large gradients of electron temperature (1/<italic>L</italic><sub>Te</sub> ∼ 20 m<sup>−1</sup> is measured, which is of the same order as the inverse gradient lengths measured in tokamak ITBs [<cite linkend="nf303578bib03">3</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib04">4</cite>]).</p>
      <p>On the theoretical side, visco-resistive MHD simulation predicts that the dynamo mechanism required to sustain the RFP equilibrium fields can be provided by the nonlinear saturation of a single kink-tearing mode: the single helicity (SH) regime [<cite linkend="nf303578bib05">5</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib06">6</cite>]. This Ohmic helical equilibrium is not affected by the high level of magnetic turbulence, typical of a RFP in a standard multiple helicity (MH) scenario, where many modes of comparable amplitude are simultaneously present. Abundant experimental evidence has been found in RFPs of a regime in which one mode, the resistive kink-tearing mode, intermittently grows much larger than the others [<cite linkend="nf303578bib07" range="bib7,bib8,bib9,bib10">7–10</cite>]. This regime, dubbed quasi single helicity (QSH), only approximates the theoretically predicted SH state, since the secondary mode amplitudes are low but not negligible.</p>
      <p>Experimentally, the probability of developing QSH and its persistency, defined as the ratio between the total time in which the plasma stays in QSH and the flattop duration, increases with plasma current. Above 1 MA QSH occupies a significant fraction of the current flat top, up to about 85% [<cite linkend="nf303578bib11">11</cite>]. It has been found that QSH states are favoured by high currents, low densities and high electron temperatures [<cite linkend="nf303578bib12">12</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib13">13</cite>]. As shown in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig01">1</figref> this implies a favourable scaling of QSH persistence and duration with the Lundquist number (ratio of resistive to Alfven times), which, according to Spitzer's formula may be written as
<display-eqn id="nf303578ueq001"><?TeX \[
\begin{equation*}
S=30I_\phi T_{\rme} (0)^{3/2}/\lfloor(0.4+0.6Z_{\rm eff})\ln
\Lambda \sqrt{m_{\rmi}\overline{n}_{\rme}}\rfloor.
\end{equation*}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578ude001.gif"/></display-eqn>
The paper is organized as follows: in section <secref linkend="nf303578s2">2</secref> the plasma conditions for the establishment of QSH regimes are analysed and the corresponding plasma performance is described (electron temperature and conductivity profiles, energy confinement properties, density limits), and then the effects of microinstabilities on transport are presented.
<figure id="nf303578fig01" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig01.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig01.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc01" label="Figure 1"><p indent="no">QSH persistency and duration as a function of the Lundquist number. For each pulse the QSH probability is computed as the ratio between the total time when QSH is present divided by the current flat-top period, the QSH duration is defined as the longest QSH time interval.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>In section <secref linkend="nf303578s3">3</secref> recent results on particle confinement properties in QSH and MH conditions are presented, discussed and compared with predictions of numerical simulations.</p>
      <p>In section <secref linkend="nf303578s4">4</secref> the ‘state of the art’ of understanding the QSH experimental findings is discussed. Conclusions are then drawn in section <secref linkend="nf303578s5">5</secref>.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s2" label="2">
      <heading>Plasma performances in QSH regimes</heading>
      <p indent="no">QSH regimes are systematically and spontaneously obtained in RFX-mod at high plasma current (<italic>I</italic><sub>p</sub> ⩾ 1 MA), while strong transient QSH is reproducibly induced by oscillating poloidal current drive operation (OPCD) [<cite linkend="nf303578bib14">14</cite>] also at lower current (<italic>I</italic><sub>p</sub> &gt; 500 kA). During OPCD the edge toroidal field is modulated in order to transiently induce a current profile modification in the plasma, concentrating the toroidal flux in the core. Secondary modes are found to decrease while the dominant one increases and the electron temperature and energy confinement increase. The reason why OPCD reproducibly stimulates QSH is not yet understood; a more detailed discussion of this aspect is postponed until section <secref linkend="nf303578s4">4</secref>.</p>
      <p>During the QSH regimes, both spontaneous or induced by OPCD, the formation of a clear structure in the soft-x-ray emissivity distribution is observed by the tomographic reconstruction [<cite linkend="nf303578bib15">15</cite>], well correlated with the observed magnetic topology. Inside the helical structure energy confinement is enhanced and at higher plasma current electron temperatures of the order of 1 keV are measured (figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig02">2</figref>). In these cases the QSH strongly affects the electron temperature profile which exhibits steep gradients, identifying an internal transport barrier.
<figure id="nf303578fig02" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig02.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig02.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc02" label="Figure 2"><p indent="no">Electron temperature profile measured by Thomson scattering [<cite linkend="nf303578bib16">16</cite>] in a QSH regime.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>The best results in terms of plasma energy content are obtained when the chaos reduction involves the whole plasma core. This happens when the X-point of the QSH thermal island and the unperturbed magnetic axis collide leading to the expulsion of the island separatrix, and to a hot, self-organized <italic>n</italic> = −7 (<italic>n</italic> being the toroidal periodicity number) helical structure [<cite linkend="nf303578bib17">17</cite>], as predicted by the theory [<cite linkend="nf303578bib18">18</cite>], without an island and with a single helical axis (SHAx regime) (left panel of figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig03">3</figref>).
<figure id="nf303578fig03" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig03.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig03.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc03" label="Figure 3"><p indent="no">Left: Plasma magnetic topology shown as a Poincarè plot (obtained with ORBIT code) in a SHAx regime. Right: Electron temperature profile measured by Thomson scattering in the same shot.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>This SHAx regime is still a QSH state, as secondary mode amplitudes do not vanish: it is the closest regime ever achieved to the SH predicted by theory and the volume affected by the ameliorated condition is large enough to impact on global confinement (see figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig03">3</figref>). In figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig04">4</figref> are shown, for the discharges of figures <figref linkend="nf303578fig02">2</figref> and <figref linkend="nf303578fig03">3</figref>, the time evolutions of the ratio between the dominant mode and the total <italic>B</italic>, <italic>B</italic><sub>T,<italic>n</italic>=−7</sub>(<italic>a</italic>)/<italic>B</italic>(<italic>a</italic>), and of the electron confinement times. The electron energy confinement time τ<sub>E,e</sub> is defined as
<display-eqn id="nf303578ueq002"><?TeX \[
\begin{leqnarray*}
\fl \tau _{\rm E,e}& =\int _{\rm Vol}3/2K_{\rm
B}n_{\rme}T_{\rme}\, {\rmd}V \Bigg/\nonumber\\\ms\fl&\quad\times
\left[P_{\rm Ohm} -P_{\rm rad}
-\frac{\rmd}{{\rmd}t}\left(\int_{\rm Vol}3/2K_{\rm
B}n_{\rme}T_{\rme}\,{\rmd}V \right) \right],
\end{leqnarray*}
\] ?><eqn-graphic format="GIF" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578ude002.gif"/></display-eqn>
where <italic>P</italic><sub>Ohm</sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub>rad</sub> are the Ohmic and the radiated powers, τ<sub>E,e</sub> increases with <italic>B</italic><sub>T,<italic>n</italic>=−7</sub>(<italic>a</italic>)/<italic>B</italic>(<italic>a</italic>) and the highest values in the SHAxs state are obtained for the largest ratio between the dominant mode and the total <italic>B</italic>: a threshold ratio <italic>B</italic><sub>T,<italic>n</italic>=−7</sub>(<italic>a</italic>)/<italic>B</italic>(<italic>a</italic>) = 0.04 has been identified for the onset of the SHAx state, as reported in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig05">5</figref> [<cite linkend="nf303578bib19">19</cite>]. It is worth noting that for ratios between the dominant mode and the total <italic>B</italic> greater than ∼5% every QSH corresponds to a SHAx [<cite linkend="nf303578bib20">20</cite>].
<figure id="nf303578fig04" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig04.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig04.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc04" label="Figure 4"><p indent="no">Time evolution of the ratio between the ratio <italic>B</italic><sub>T,<italic>n</italic>=7</sub>(<italic>a</italic>)/<italic>B</italic>(<italic>a</italic>) = 0.04 (star symbols indicate the times of Thomson scattering measurements) and of the electron energy confinement time (calculated at the times of Thomson scattering measurements ±3 ms) for the discharges in figures <figref linkend="nf303578fig02">2</figref> and <figref linkend="nf303578fig03">3</figref>, respectively.</p></caption></figure>
<figure id="nf303578fig05" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig05.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig05.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc05" label="Figure 5"><p indent="no">Normalized edge amplitudes of the <italic>n</italic> = −7 mode towards the normalized edge amplitude of the secondary modes. The electron temperature profiles corresponding to the discharges indicated by asterisks are represented by that in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig02">2</figref>, the electron temperature profiles corresponding to discharges indicated by circles are represented by that in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig03">3</figref>.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>The enhanced electron energy confinement times of the SHAxs shown in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig03">3</figref> are confirmed on a statistical basis: SHAxs have confinement times that can be a factor 2 higher than that of a QSH that has developed an island, as shown in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig06">6</figref> [<cite linkend="nf303578bib19">19</cite>]. The density profiles are essentially flat, except at the plasma edge, in both standard QSH and SHAxs regimes [<cite linkend="nf303578bib21">21</cite>] and the broader temperature profile of a SHAx increases the confinement times. The more ordered magnetic topology and the separatrix expulsion experimentally found at the highest dominant mode amplitudes agree with the theoretical predictions [<cite linkend="nf303578bib18">18</cite>], as will be discussed in section <secref linkend="nf303578s4">4</secref>. The crucial point is that numerical simulations show that the SHAxs states have strong resilience to residual chaotic perturbation, in agreement with experimental evidence of increased confinement.
<figure id="nf303578fig06" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig06.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig06.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc06" label="Figure 6"><p indent="no">Electron energy confinement time towards the secondary modes total amplitude.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>The radial profile of electron heat diffusivity χ<sub>e</sub> in stationary conditions has been determined by adopting a 1D single fluid approach and solving the power balance equation [<cite linkend="nf303578bib22">22</cite>]: during QSH states χ<sub>e</sub> strongly decreases in correspondence to the transport barrier of the thermal structure. The χ<sub>e</sub> improvement during a SHAx state in the best cases can be more than tenfold and involves about one half of the minor radius. As an example, figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig07">7</figref> shows the χ<sub>e</sub> profiles calculated during the MH and SHAx states in the same discharge. It has to be mentioned that, provided the island is nearly symmetric with respect to the centre [<cite linkend="nf303578bib22">22</cite>], the 1D power balance equation can be applied to approximately estimate the heat diffusivity during a QSH.
<figure id="nf303578fig07" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig07.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig07.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc07" label="Figure 7"><p indent="no">(<italic>a</italic>) Electron temperature profiles obtained by Thomson scattering diagnostics for the same high current discharge during QSH (<italic>a</italic>) (SHAx state) and in MH phases (black symbols). (<italic>b</italic>) Corresponding thermal diffusivity profiles (calculated in the region of not-vanishing electron temperature gradients). (<italic>c</italic>) In the same discharge: time evolutions of the <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −7 dominant mode (black) and of secondary modes (the secondary amplitudes are quite similar, the relatively most intense <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −8 is shown as an example).</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>In the past RFX-mod discharges with plasma current <italic>I</italic><sub>p</sub> ⩽ 1 MA, the heating of the magnetic island of a QSH state has been analysed with the M1TEV [<cite linkend="nf303578bib23">23</cite>] 2D transport code, indicating that the main cause of the heating of the magnetic island is the reduction of the thermal diffusion coefficient inside it. Indeed the simulated time evolution of the electron temperature and the values of thermal conductivity are consistent with the RFX-mod electron temperature increase inside the QSH.</p>
      <p>The spontaneous transitions to a QSH regime are observed in RFX-mod only for relatively low electron densities normalized to the Greenwald density: <italic>n</italic>/<italic>n</italic><sub>G</sub> ⩽ 0.3–0.4 [<cite linkend="nf303578bib24">24</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib25">25</cite>]. This is reflected in the behaviour of QSH persistency towards the Lundquist number, since high current plasmas at relatively high density (<italic>n</italic>/<italic>n</italic><sub>G</sub> &gt; 0.4) have a lower Lundquist number and a consistently lower dominant to residual modes ratio. When a transition to a multi-mode dynamo occurs the confinement degrades by approximately a factor 2. For this reason RFX-mod high current discharges have been run mainly at low densities, typically below <italic>n</italic>/<italic>n</italic><sub>G</sub> = 0.3. Moreover, at high current the input power increases and therefore the requirements for a low recycling wall become more stringent. A still open question is whether the QSH low persistency at higher densities reflects a fuelling problem which could be overcome by depositing particles in the plasma centre with pellets injection. In this respect, promising experimental evidence of dominant mode sustainment by pellets in a phase in which the QSH was disappearing have been found. As an example, in the discharge shown in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig08">8</figref> the pellet injection slows down the decrease in the dominant mode. Finding suitable conditions for high current high density discharges will be a matter for future investigation.
<figure id="nf303578fig08" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig08.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig08.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc08" label="Figure 8"><p indent="no">Example of sustainment of the dominant mode by pellet, RFX-mod discharge #24069: time behaviour of the toroidal component of dominant <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −7 and secondary modes (top) (the secondary mode amplitudes are quite similar, the relatively most intense <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −8 is reported as an example) and interferometer central chords measurements (bottom).</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>In SHAxs regimes with large gradients of <italic>T</italic><sub>e</sub> the magnetic turbulence is so small that drift modes, of an electrostatic nature, may become important. Both gyrokinetic and fluid approaches have been adopted to study ion temperature gradient (ITG) modes in RFP plasmas. The result is that these instabilities are in general more stable in a RFP than in a tokamak, due to the shorter connection length in RFP, but could be excited in the RFX-mod regions where experimentally very high <italic>T</italic><sub>e</sub> gradients are found, namely at the edge of the islands associated with a QSH and at the edge of the plasma [<cite linkend="nf303578bib26">26</cite>]. The fact that in a SHAxs state the temperature profiles are rather flat in the region inside the steep gradients might also support this hypothesis: an ITG turbulence which originates in the gradient regions and nonlinearly propagates nearby (turbulence spreading), might explain this flattening. Also, the presence of residual magnetic chaos in the interior of the transport barrier might be the cause for this observation. The present analysis holds on to the assumption that ion and electron temperatures have the same normalized gradient ∇<italic>T</italic>/<italic>T</italic>. Ion temperature profile measurements are not available on RFX-mod yet. Line of sight integrated Doppler broadening measurements on O <smallcap>VIII</smallcap>, O <smallcap>VII</smallcap>, C <smallcap>V</smallcap> coupled to simulations of impurity emission profiles indicate that <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> ≈ (0.6–0.7)<italic>T</italic><sub>e</sub>. Suitable ion temperature profile measurements will therefore clarify whether the scenario of a RFP core dominated by electrostatic instability is plausible. Tools developed to study drift turbulence in tokamaks such as TRB [<cite linkend="nf303578bib28">28</cite>] and GS2 [<cite linkend="nf303578bib29">29</cite>] are being adapted to investigate RFP plasmas.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s3" label="3">
      <heading>Particle transport</heading>
      <p indent="no">Perturbative experiments (pellets and impurity laser blow off (LBO) injections) have been performed to study particle confinement inside and outside the thermal island. Given the flatness of electron density profiles in RFX-mod and the transient nature of the QSH regimes, the presence of a particle source inside/outside the thermal structure is necessary to observe and measure any modification of the particle transport parameters.</p>
      <p>The multi pellet injector of RFX-mod [<cite linkend="nf303578bib29">29</cite>] was used to inject pellets with a nominal mass of 1.5 × 10<sup>20</sup> particles and velocity from 600 up to 1200 m s<sup>−1</sup>. Fast pellets are injected to deeply penetrate the QSH hot structure. An eight–chords CO<sub>2</sub> interferometer is used to measure the time evolution of the electron density [<cite linkend="nf303578bib30">30</cite>].</p>
      <p>Poincarè plots of magnetic field lines at the toroidal positions of the pellet injector and interferometer (which are 120° apart) have been obtained by means of the magnetic field line tracing code FLiT in toroidal geometry [<cite linkend="nf303578bib31">31</cite>] and are used to analyse pellet ablation and density behaviour with respect to magnetic topology. When the pellet enters the hot structure the ablation increases due to the higher electron temperature and the helical magnetic topology reflects in an <italic>m</italic> = 1 asymmetry in the density measurements along different homologous chords [<cite linkend="nf303578bib31">31</cite>].</p>
      <p>In most of the cases the pellet enters the hot region at the end of its life, with a low residual mass. In some cases when the pellet enters the hot region with enough particles, the time evolution of interferometer central chords does not decrease just after pellet ablation and stays constant for a while, indicating that the thermal structure can confine particles. In figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig09">9</figref> an example is given of the time evolution of the density following a pellet ablation in a MH plasma while a QSH state was forming (in the top panel the amplitudes of the dominant and secondary modes are shown). In this case the QSH phase is a SHAx state; the comparison of the line integrated density in the MH and saturated SHAx phase, where it is nearly constant, indicates an enhancement of the particle confinement time <italic>t</italic><sub>p</sub> by at least a factor 2: the hydrogen influx decreases by about a factor 2 in the saturated SHAx state and the density is higher (see the shaded regions in the figure).
<figure id="nf303578fig09" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig09.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig09.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc09" label="Figure 9"><p indent="no">RFX-mod discharge #24953: time evolution of dominant <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −7 and secondary mode (the secondary mode amplitudes are quite comparable, the relatively most intense <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −9 is drawn as an example) during a QSH evolving in a SHAXs and of the integrated electron density (interferometer four central chords) following a pellet injection.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>In addition to pellet injection, Ni LBO was also performed for the first time in RFX-mod as a way to provide a traceable impurity source inside the island present in the QSH states [<cite linkend="nf303578bib32">32</cite>]. The injected impurity reached the high temperature region inside the helical structure since the emission lines Ni <smallcap>XVII</smallcap> 249 Å and Ni <smallcap>XVIII</smallcap> 292 Å have been observed. Figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig10">10</figref> shows an example of the emission signals following Ni injection (by a single laser pulse) when a QSH was developing: the SXR signal and the Ni <smallcap>XVII</smallcap> 249 line last for the whole QSH phase, clearly following the time evolution of the electron temperature.
<figure id="nf303578fig10" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig10.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig10.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc10" label="Figure 10"><p indent="no">Shot #24073 at 1.2 MA. From the top: line integrated SXR brightness, Ni <smallcap>XVII</smallcap> 249 Å line brightness, <italic>T</italic><sub>e</sub> measured with a double filter diagnostic, bt of dominant mode <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −7 and <italic>m</italic> = 1, <italic>n</italic> = −11 (representative of the secondary modes). The LBO injection time is indicated by the vertical line.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>Due to the strongly varying plasma conditions (including the poloidal and toroidal asymmetries in the <italic>T</italic><sub>e</sub> profile due to the helical geometry) the Ni transport parameters evaluations obtained by reproducing the emission pattern by a 1D collisional–radiative impurity transport code [<cite linkend="nf303578bib33">33</cite>] are not fully reliable. However, the simulations indicate that the observed time evolution depends more on the electron temperature evolution (i.e. on the energy content of the island) rather than on strong differences in the Ni transport properties inside the thermal island. Ni emission data have been reasonably reproduced using the same transport parameters for both the MH and QSH phases (<italic>D</italic> ∼ 10–20 m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> in the plasma centre) [<cite linkend="nf303578bib34">34</cite>].</p>
      <p>Summarizing, experimental evidence seems to indicate different behaviour between the impurities and the main gas diffusion mechanisms in QSH. Transport of main gas appears to be positively influenced in some cases by QSH while impurity transport seems not to be strongly dependent on QSH.</p>
      <p>The diffusion coefficients for Ni impurities and main gas (H) ions have been estimated by the O<smallcap>RBIT</smallcap> code [<cite linkend="nf303578bib35">35</cite>] both in the MH and QSH regimes, at different levels of collisionality and energy of the test particles: simulations for <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> = 600 eV and <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> = 1200 eV have been performed to cover the possible temperature ranges in RFX-mod. Results are reported in figures <figref linkend="nf303578fig11">11(<italic>a</italic>) and (<italic>b</italic>)</figref>, respectively. The black curves (dots) are relative to H while the red ones (squares) are relative to Ni ions. The MH and QSH scenarios are shown by solid and dashed lines, respectively. In the numerical simulations the interaction of the test particles with the whole plasma background is taken into account, considering both collisions with the main gas (ions and electrons) and with intrinsic impurity ions such as oxygen and carbon. In the nickel case, collisions Ni–Ni are also considered.
<figure id="nf303578fig11" pageposition="top"><graphic><graphic-file version="print" format="EPS" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig11.eps" width="XXX"/><graphic-file version="ej" format="JPEG" align="middle" filename="images/nf303578fig11.jpg"/></graphic><caption id="nf303578fc11" label="Figure 11"><p indent="no">Hydrogen and nickel diffusion coefficients obtained by ORBIT as a function of collisions for toroidal transit both in MH and QSH plasmas at ion temperature <italic>T</italic><sub>e</sub> = 600 eV (<italic>a</italic>) and 1200 eV (<italic>b</italic>). The shaded regions refer to typical collisionality of RFX-mod.</p></caption></figure></p>
      <p>At <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> = 600 eV the total hydrogen ions collisionality is in the range 0.06–0.1 collisions per toroidal transit; this interval is marked by a yellow box in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig11">11(<italic>a</italic>)</figref>. As observed experimentally, diffusion of H ions in QSH (∼1 m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>) is found to be lower than in MH (∼20 m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>). At such low values of H collisionality, transport is strongly influenced by the magnetic field topology which is chaotic in the MH scenario and presents helical conserved magnetic surfaces in the QSH regime. On the contrary, the typical range for nickel ion collisionality at 600 eV is 5–20 collisions for toroidal transit, as shown by the corresponding yellow box in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig11">11(<italic>a</italic>)</figref> and the Ni diffusion coefficients are found to be about the same in the MH and QSH regimes (0.5–2 m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>). At such a level of collisionality, random-walk diffusion processes due to classical collisions are dominant and Ni ion transport is little influenced by the magnetic field topology.</p>
      <p>The results are confirmed by O<smallcap>RBIT</smallcap> simulations also at <italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub> = 1200 eV (figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig11">11(<italic>b</italic>)</figref>). In this latter case diffusion coefficients for Ni in QSH and MH are nearly the same, at about 1 m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>. In contrast, similar to what happens at lower temperature, H diffusion coefficients are one order of magnitude lower in QSH with respect to the MH regime. This is in agreement with the above experimental findings. On the other hand, the quantitative evaluation of the Ni diffusion coefficient performed with O<smallcap>RBIT</smallcap> is one order of magnitude smaller than the mentioned experimental estimate. This mismatch is currently being investigated and may be due to the mechanism not included in O<smallcap>RBIT</smallcap> which could be relevant in particle transport, such as turbulence or collective phenomena (blobs) (which are obviously beyond a single-particle approximation). Underestimation of the effective collisionality or numerical approximation (i.e. in O<smallcap>RBIT</smallcap> only monoenergetic test particles have been used and constant density profiles are assumed for the main gas and the impurities) could also play a role.</p>
      <p>As a general consideration, it should be mentioned that the diffusion coefficient <italic>D</italic> evaluated by reproducing the experimental emission pattern with the 1D collisonal radiative model is a fluid quantity, i.e. the result of an ensembling of the dynamical system over long distances and times. The diffusion coefficient calculated through O<smallcap>RBIT</smallcap> is instead a local evaluation based on the actual dynamics of the particles on shorter times and local space scales. There are theoretical indications [<cite linkend="nf303578bib36">36</cite>] that the fluid <italic>D</italic> and the ‘dynamical’ <italic>D</italic> are in principle different, and if plasma timescales are too fast (or space scales too short) to completely de-correlate the motion of particles (as is the case of a medium size experiment like RFX-mod) the fluid <italic>D</italic> could overestimate the ‘dynamical’ <italic>D</italic>. More extensive analysis, both from the experimental and theoretical sides, is the subject of ongoing work.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s4" label="4">
      <heading>Discussion and open issues</heading>
      <p indent="no">Experimentally QSH states are found strongly favoured by high currents, where high temperatures are achieved [<cite linkend="nf303578bib24">24</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib25">25</cite>]. A good scaling of the QSH persistency and duration with the dimensionless Lundquist number <italic>S</italic>, depending on the aforementioned quantities and on the electron densities, has been shown in figure <figref linkend="nf303578fig01">1</figref>.</p>
      <p>The experimental amplitude of the dominant mode displays a clear trend to increase versus <italic>S</italic> [<cite linkend="nf303578bib19">19</cite>] and saturates around a constant value (d<italic>B</italic>/<italic>B</italic> ∼ 5%) for <italic>S</italic> above 10<sup>7</sup>. This observation is consistent with 3D nonlinear visco-resistive MHD theoretical predictions (SpeCyl code), foreseeing a saturation of the dominant mode in the helical state as <italic>S</italic> increases [<cite linkend="nf303578bib37">37</cite>].</p>
      <p>On the other hand, in the frame SpeCyl simulations transitions to the QSH–SH regimes are predicted as the product of resistivity and viscosity increases (i.e. the dimensionless Hartmann number decreases [<cite linkend="nf303578bib06">6</cite>]). This prediction cannot be compared with the experimental findings since in RFX-mod the plasma viscosity is not measured. This still remains an open issue, as discussed in the final section of [<cite linkend="nf303578bib06">6</cite>].</p>
      <p>Also the reproducible QSH stimulation by OPCD is not fully explained by the theory [<cite linkend="nf303578bib20">20</cite>]: indeed, as reported in [<cite linkend="nf303578bib38">38</cite>, <cite linkend="nf303578bib39">39</cite>] both its descriptions with simple linear and nonlinear numerical simulations do not reproduce the experiment. The OPCD action systematically triggers and amplifies the dominant mode amplitude while secondary modes decrease but SpeCyl simulations [<cite linkend="nf303578bib40">40</cite>] predict the reduction of all the modes due to a global pinching of the plasma column. Transport effects (not included in SpeCyl and in linear stability analysis) may be envisaged to play a crucial role in dominant mode amplification experimentally observed. Actually, numerical simulations show a QSH amplification effect by OPCD only if the initial state of the system is a (even weak) QSH [<cite linkend="nf303578bib41">41</cite>].</p>
      <p>The enhanced confinement SHAxs regimes are obtained for the highest amplitude of the perturbation dominant mode. Such a feature would not be expected from the classical resonance overlap picture, as the separatrix disappearance occurs when the amplitude of the dominant mode increases. However, the QSH states numerically found with SpeCyl by increasing the amplitude of the dominant mode show a more ordered magnetic pattern, while chaos in the system increases with smaller amplitude of the dominant mode, even if this implies the decrease in overlapping islands [<cite linkend="nf303578bib18">18</cite>]. The single axis state found in the simulation shows strong resilience to residual chaos and this is in agreement with the increase in confinement experimentally found.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <sec-level1 id="nf303578s5" label="5">
      <heading>Conclusions</heading>
      <p indent="no">Thanks to improved feed back control and to advanced operation techniques, RFX-mod displays clear and robust transitions to QSH regimes as predicted by MHD modelling. The synergic interplay between the growth of the dominant mode and the reduction in the secondary modes provides enhanced confinement properties with steep gradients in the electron temperature profiles and enhanced energy confinement time by a factor up to 2. The higher energy content and steeper gradient measured during QSH regimes correspond to an electron thermal diffusivity reduction, which in the best cases can be more than one order of magnitude.</p>
      <p>Microstability analysis suggests the possible destabilization of ITG modes in the region of steep temperature gradients, and the associated turbulence could limit the electron temperature inside the island. The scenario of a core dominated by electrostatic instability would be a change in perspective for the RFP physics, where the dominant role of the chaos due to magnetic turbulence is being gradually substituted by the effects due to electrostatic turbulence, entering a field well known to the tokamak community.</p>
      <p>Experiments with pellet injection and nickel LBO in the MH and QSH regimes have been performed in RFX-mod to study particle transport inside and outside the hot helical structure. Even if more experiments are needed to properly evaluate the particle transport parameters, there is evidence of an improvement by a factor 2 of the main gas confinement time. As far as impurities are concerned, no clear evidence of strong transport modifications in the QSH states with respect to MH has been found. Impurity diffusion coefficient obtained by ORBIT single-particle model simulations confirms that the diffusivity of H particles in QSH is lower than in standard MH, both at 600 and at 1200 eV. On the contrary, impurity transport is not strongly influenced by magnetic field topology, by virtue of their higher collisionality. This is an indication that impurity accumulation is not likely to occur inside the thermal structure.</p>
    </sec-level1>
    <acknowledgment>
      <heading>Acknowledgment</heading>
      <p indent="no">This work was supported by the European Communities under the contract of Associations between EURATOM/ENEA.</p>
      <p>CONSORZIO RFX–EURATOM/ENEA Association © 2009.</p>
    </acknowledgment>
  </body>
  <back>
    <references>
      <heading>References</heading>
      <reference-list type="numeric">
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib01" num="1">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Martini</second-name>
              <first-names>S.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Active MHD control at high currents in RFX-mod</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <pages>783</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0029-5515/47/8/008</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00295515</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">17414326</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib02" num="2">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Zanca</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Beyond the intelligent shell concept: the clean-mode-control</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <pages>1425</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0029-5515/47/11/004</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00295515</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">17414326</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib03" num="3">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Fable</second-name>
              <first-names>E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <pages>115005</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0741-3335/50/11/115005</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">07413335</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">13616587</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib04" num="4">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Ida</second-name>
              <first-names>K.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2004</year>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <pages>A45–50</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0741-3335/46/5A/004</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">07413335</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">13616587</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib05" num="5">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Cappello</second-name>
              <first-names>S.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au>
              <second-name>Paccagnella</second-name>
              <first-names>R.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>1992</year>
          <art-title>Nonlinear plasma evolution and sustainment in the reversed field pinch</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Fluids</jnl-title>
          <part>B</part>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <pages>611</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.860471</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">08998221</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib06" num="6">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Cappello</second-name>
              <first-names>S.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2004</year>
          <art-title>Bifurcation in the MHD behaviour of a self-organizing system: the reversed field pinch (RFP)</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <pages>B313</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0741-3335/46/12B/027</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">07413335</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">13616587</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib07" num="7">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Martin</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2003</year>
          <art-title>Overview of quasi-single helicity experiments in reversed field pinches</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <pages>1855</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0029-5515/43/12/028</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00295515</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">17414326</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib08" num="8">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Piovesan</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2004</year>
          <art-title>Measurements of the MHD dynamo in the quasi-single-helicity reversed-field pinch</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <pages>235001</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.93.235001</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00319007</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">10797114</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib09" num="9">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Frassinetti</second-name>
              <first-names>L.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Spontaneous quasi single helicity regimes in EXTRAP T2R reversed-field pinch</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <pages>12510</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib10" num="10">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Piovesan</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2004</year>
          <art-title>Self-organization towards helical states in the toroidal pinch experiment reversed-field pinch</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <pages>151</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.1629693</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">1070664X</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib11" num="11">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Marrelli</second-name>
              <first-names>L.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2004</year>
          <art-title>Magnetic self organization, MHD active control and confinement in RFX-mod</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <pages>B359</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib12" num="12">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Valisa</second-name>
              <first-names>M.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <art-title>High current regimes in RFX-mod</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <pages>124031</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0741-3335/50/12/124031</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">07413335</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">13616587</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib13" num="13">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Lorenzini</second-name>
              <first-names>R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2009</year>
          <art-title>Self-organized helical equilibria as a new paradigm for ohmically heated fusion plasmas</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nature Phys.</jnl-title>
          <misc-text>at press</misc-text>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib14" num="14">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Terranova</second-name>
              <first-names>D.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Enhanced confinement and quasi-single-helicity regimes induced by poloidal current drive</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <pages>095001</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.99.095001</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00319007</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">10797114</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib15" num="15">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Martin</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>A new paradigm for RFP magnetic self-organization: results and challenge</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <pages>A177–93</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0741-3335/49/5A/S15</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">07413335</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">13616587</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib16" num="16">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Alfier</second-name>
              <first-names>A.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au>
              <second-name>Pasqualotto</second-name>
              <first-names>R.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>The main Thomson scattering diagnostic on RFX-mod</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Rev. Sci. Instrum.</jnl-title>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <pages>013505</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.2431769</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00346748</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib17" num="17">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Lorenzini</second-name>
              <first-names>R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <art-title>Single-helical-axis states in reversed-field-pinch plasmas</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <pages>025005</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.101.025005</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00319007</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">10797114</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib18" num="18">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Escande</second-name>
              <first-names>D.F.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2000</year>
          <art-title>Chaos healing by separatrix disappearance and quasi single helicity states of the reversed field pinch</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <pages>3169</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.85.3169</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00319007</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">10797114</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib19" num="19">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Piovesan</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <art-title>Magnetic order improvement through high current and MHD feedback control in RFX-mod</art-title>
          <conf-title>35th EPS Conf.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Hersonissis, Crete, 2008</conf-place>
          <misc-text>O-4.02 <webref url="http://eps2008.iesl.forth.gr/">http://eps2008.iesl.forth.gr/</webref></misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib20" num="20">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Cappello</second-name>
              <first-names>S.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <art-title>The reversed field pinch toward magnetic order: a genuine self-organization</art-title>
          <conf-title>Theory of Fusion Plasmas 2008 Joint Varenne–Lausanne Int. Workshop</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Varenna, Italy, August 2008</conf-place>
          <misc-text>(Invited talk) <webref url="http://varenna-lausanne.epfl.ch/">http://varenna-lausanne.epfl.ch/</webref></misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib21" num="21">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Lorenzini</second-name>
              <first-names>R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Toroidally asymmetric particle transport caused by phase-locking of MHD modes in RFX-mod</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <pages>1468</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0029-5515/47/11/008</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00295515</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">17414326</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib22" num="22">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Alfier</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <art-title>Electron temperature profiles in RFX-mod</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <pages>035013</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0741-3335/50/3/035013</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">07413335</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">13616587</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib23" num="23">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Annibaldi</second-name>
              <first-names>S.V.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Strong transport reduction in the helical core of the reversed-field pinch</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <pages>112515</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.2811933</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">1070664X</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib24" num="24">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Puiatti</second-name>
              <first-names>M.E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2009</year>
          <art-title>High density limit in reversed field pinches</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <pages>012505</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.3063060</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">1070664X</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib25" num="25">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Puiatti</second-name>
              <first-names>M.E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2009</year>
          <art-title>High density physics in reversed field pinches: comparison with tokamaks and stellarators</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <pages>045012</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0029-5515/49/4/045012</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00295515</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">17414326</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib26" num="26">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Guo</second-name>
              <first-names>S.C.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <art-title>Stability threshold of ion temperature gradient driven mode in reversed field pinch plasmas</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <pages>122510</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.3039895</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">1070664X</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib27" num="27">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Garbet</second-name>
              <first-names>X.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2001</year>
          <art-title>Turbulent particle transport in magnetized plasmas</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev. Lett.</jnl-title>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <pages>035001</pages>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib28" num="28">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Kotschenreuther</second-name>
              <first-names>M.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1995</year>
          <art-title>Comparison of initial value and eigenvalue codes for kinetic toroidal plasma instabilities</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Comput. Phys. Commun.</jnl-title>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <pages>128</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0010-4655(95)00035-E</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00104655</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib29" num="29">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Baker</second-name>
              <first-names>W.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1995</year>
          <art-title>Multi shot pellet injection system for RFX</art-title>
          <conf-title>Proc. 16th IEEE/NPSS Symp. Fusion Engineering</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Urbana-Champaign, IL, USA, 1995</conf-place>
          <pages>p 1570</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?tp=&amp;arnumber=534523&amp;isnumber=11108">http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?tp=&amp;arnumber=534523&amp;isnumber=11108</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib30" num="30">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Innocente</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>1997</year>
          <art-title>Upgrade of the RFX CO<sub>2</sub> interferometer using in-vessel optics for extended edge resolution</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Rev. Sci. Instrum.</jnl-title>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <pages>694</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.1147677</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00346748</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib31" num="31">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Innocente</second-name>
              <first-names>P.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Transport and confinement studies in the RFX-mod reversed-field pinch experiment</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <pages>1092</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0029-5515/47/9/004</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00295515</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">17414326</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib32" num="32">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Carraro</second-name>
              <first-names>L.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <art-title>Particle transport in different magnetic field topological configurations in the RFX-mod experiment</art-title>
          <conf-title>35th EPS Conf.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Hersonissis, Crete, 2008</conf-place>
          <pages>P-4.019</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://eps2008.iesl.forth.gr/">http://eps2008.iesl.forth.gr/</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib33" num="33">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Mattioli</second-name>
              <first-names>M.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2002</year>
          <art-title>Experimental and simulated VUV spectra from the JET tokamak and the reversed field pinch RFX</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Plasma Phys. Control. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <pages>33</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0741-3335/44/1/304</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">07413335</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">13616587</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib34" num="34">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Carraro</second-name>
              <first-names>L.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2006</year>
          <art-title>Effects on impurity transport of the active control of the magnetic boundary in RFX-mod</art-title>
          <conf-title>33th EPS Conf.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Rome, Italy, 2006</conf-place>
          <pages>P5.083</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://epsppd.epfl.ch/Roma/start.htm">http://epsppd.epfl.ch/Roma/start.htm</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib35" num="35">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Gobbin</second-name>
              <first-names>M.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Ion and electron local transport inside single helicity islands in the reversed field pinch</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <pages>072305</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.2747631</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">1070664X</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib36" num="36">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Sánchez</second-name>
              <first-names>R.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au>
              <second-name>Carreras</second-name>
              <first-names>B.A.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au>
              <second-name>Newman</second-name>
              <first-names>D.E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au>
              <second-name>Lynch</second-name>
              <first-names>V.E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <au>
              <second-name>van Milligen</second-name>
              <first-names>B.Ph.</first-names>
            </au>
          </authors>
          <year>2006</year>
          <art-title>Renormalization of tracer turbulence leading to fractional differential equations</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Rev.</jnl-title>
          <part>E</part>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <pages>016305</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.74.016305</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">15393755</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">15502376</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib37" num="37">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Bonfiglio</second-name>
              <first-names>D.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2006</year>
          <art-title>Impact of a uniform plasma resistivity in MHD modeling of helical solutions for the reversed field pinch dynamo</art-title>
          <conf-title>ICPP Conf. 2006</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Kiev, 22–26 May 2006</conf-place>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://icpp2006.kiev.ua/CD/B/B126p.pdf">http://icpp2006.kiev.ua/ CD/B/B126p.pdf</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib38" num="38">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Cappello</second-name>
              <first-names>S.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2003</year>
          <art-title>Comparison of linear properties and of nonlinear behaviour in a mhd simulation of pulsed poloidal current drive in the reversed field pinch</art-title>
          <conf-title>30th EPS Conf. (St Petersburg, 2003)</conf-title>
          <jnl-title>ECA</jnl-title>
          <volume>vol 27A</volume>
          <pages>P-1.201</pages>
          <misc-text>
            <webref url="http://www.ioffe.ru/EPS2003/">http://www.ioffe.ru/EPS2003/</webref>
          </misc-text>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib39" num="39">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Reynolds</second-name>
              <first-names>J.M.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2008</year>
          <art-title>Nonlinear magnetohydrodynamics of pulsed parallel current drive in reversed-field pinches</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Phys. Plasmas</jnl-title>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <pages>062512</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.2937770</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">1070664X</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <journal-ref id="nf303578bib40" num="40">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Puiatti</second-name>
              <first-names>M.E.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2003</year>
          <art-title>Analysis and modelling of the magnetic and plasma profiles during PPCD experiments in RFX</art-title>
          <jnl-title>Nucl. Fusion</jnl-title>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <pages>1057</pages>
          <crossref>
            <cr_doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0029-5515/43/10/006</cr_doi>
            <cr_issn type="print">00295515</cr_issn>
            <cr_issn type="electronic">17414326</cr_issn>
          </crossref>
        </journal-ref>
        <conf-ref id="nf303578bib41" num="41">
          <authors>
            <au>
              <second-name>Cappello</second-name>
              <first-names>S.</first-names>
            </au>
            <others>
              <italic>et al</italic>
            </others>
          </authors>
          <year>2007</year>
          <art-title>Ordered magnetic topology in reversed field pinch configurations</art-title>
          <conf-title>12th European Fusion Theory Conf.</conf-title>
          <conf-place>Madrid, Spain, 2007</conf-place>
          <misc-text><webref url="http://plasma2.ulb.ac.be/EFTC/Documents_EFTC12_191206SHORT_MADRID/index.html">http://plasma2.ulb.ac.be/EFTC/Documents_EFTC12_191206SHORT_MADRID/index.html</webref> Presentation P2-04</misc-text>
        </conf-ref>
      </reference-list>
    </references>
  </back>
</article>
