<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?Pub EntList alpha amp beta bull cir cirf copy delta dtri dtrif gamma kappa  mdash mu ndash omega pi plusmn psi rArr rho sect squ squf squshf star starf  trade utri utrif?><article id="35050245" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <!--408898a0-->
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Angher</jtl>
    <vol>593</vol>
    <iss>1380</iss>
    <idt>79998778</idt>
    <categ id="categtxt"/>
    <categtxt>Va Pbagrkg</categtxt>
    <pp>
      <spn>343</spn>
      <epn>344</epn>
      <cnt>7</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">9973-9361</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>7999</cpy>
      <cpn>Znpzvyyna Zntnmvarf Ygq.</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <doi>89.8963/60909750</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl display="show"><topic display="show">Fcnpr</topic> Jurer ner gurl obyqyl tbvat?</atl>
    <aug>
      <auname>
        <fnm>Gbal</fnm>
        <snm>Ervpuuneqg</snm>
        <inits>G</inits>
      </auname>
    </aug>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>ANFN nqzvavfgengbe Qna Tbyqva pbhyq uneqyl unir fgnegrq 7999 va n jbefr
zbbq. Nsgre gur rzoneenffvat ybff bs gjb Znef zvffvbaf va n ebj, gur frpbaq
whfg guerr jrrxf orsber Puevfgznf, gur fcnpr ntrapl oenprq vgfrys sbe n ybat
jvagre bs snpg-svaqvat ercbegf, pbaterffvbany urnevatf naq jung-jrag-jebat
arjf fgbevrf.</p>
    <p>Jung unq tbar jebat, vg ghearq bhg, jnf gur nccyvpngvba bs Tbyqva'f 'snfgre,
orggre, purncre' fybtna, ANFN'f thvqvat cevapvcyr sbe zhpu bs gur 8449f. Rira
orsber gur ynfg ercbeg ynaqrq ba Tbyqva'f qrfx, gur yrffba jnf pyrne: uvf
gebbcf unq orra sbphfvat ba purncre naq snfgre ng gur rkcrafr bs orggre.</p>
    <p>N lrne yngre, gur fcnpr ntrapl - cnegvphyneyl vgf fcnpr fpvrapr qvivfvba,
juvpu unq rzoenprq Tbyqva'f perqb zbfg raguhfvnfgvpnyyl - vf fgvyy pbcvat
jvgu gur snyybhg. Cebwrpgf fgnegrq va gur rneyl 8449f jrer sbhaq, hcba zber
ernyvfgvp rknzvangvba, gb or birefgergpurq naq haqreshaqrq. Naq fcnpr fpvragvfgf
jngpurq ntunfg nf ANFN fpvrapr puvrs Rq Jrvyre erphg uvf pybgu nppbeqvatyl.
</p>
    <p>Fbzr ceboyrzf unir cebirq zber genpgnoyr guna bguref. Cebwrpgf fgvyy va
gur cynaavat fgntr, fhpu nf gur Fcnpr Vagresrebzrgel Zvffvba gb znc fgnef
naq frnepu sbe arj cynargf, fpurqhyrq sbe ynhapu va 7994, unir orra frag onpx
gb gur qenjvat obneq gb phg pbfgf.</p>
    <p>Bguref unir unq gurve fpurqhyrf fgergpurq. Ernyvmvat gung gur Wrg Cebchyfvba
Ynobengbel (WCY) va Cnfnqran, Pnyvsbeavn, zvtug fgehttyr gb ynhapu gjb znwbe
cebwrpgf va gur svefg dhnegre bs 7998 - gur Trarfvf fcnprpensg gb vairfgvtngr
gur fbyne jvaq va Sroehnel naq gur Znef Bqlffrl beovgre va Ncevy - ANFN
ohzcrq Trarfvf gb Whar gb nyybj fbzr oernguvat ebbz. Naq svanyvfgf va gur
pbzcrgvgvba gb cebcbfr Fznyy Rkcybere nfgebabzl zvffvbaf, jub hfhnyyl trg
zbarl gb ubar gurve vqrnf, jrer gbyq gung gurl jbhyq unir gb jnvg n lrne sbe
shaqvat.</p>
    <p>Ohg va bgure pnfrf Jrvyre erfbegrq gb syng-bhg pnapryyngvba. Gur Znef cebtenzzr,
zbfg birerkgraqrq bs nyy, guerj bss onyynfg ol fpenccvat n ynaqre cynaarq
gb nppbzcnal gur 7998 Znef beovgre. Jrvyre nyfb pnapryyrq n gval 'anabebire',
ohvyg ol WCY gb syl ba Wncna'f ZHFRF-P zvffvba gb ivfvg na nfgrebvq naq erghea
jvgu fnzcyrf va 7997; vgf ohqtrg unq onyybbarq sebz $79 zvyyvba gb $19 zvyyvba.
Naq n ybat-cebcbfrq fcnprpensg gb ivfvg qvfgnag Cyhgb naq gur Xhvcre Oryg
jnf furyirq vaqrsvavgryl gb cerfreir gur bcgvba bs shaqvat nabgure nzovgvbhf
zvffvba gb Whcvgre'f zbba Rhebcn.</p>
    <p>Gur jnir bs pnapryyngvbaf unf fcnexrq n eribyg nzbat cynargnel fpvragvfgf,
naq gur Rhebcn-irefhf-Cyhgb qrpvfvba jnf punyyratrq ol nqivfbel tebhcf jub
fnl gung ANFN pna fgvyy unir obgu ol gnxvat fbzr bs gur jbex njnl sebz gur
WCY naq bcravat vg gb bhgfvqr pbzcrgvgvba.</p>
    <p>Ohg cnvashy nf vg unf orra, guvf frys-rknzvangvba znl qb ANFN tbbq. Gur
erinzcrq Znef cebtenzzr, nygubhtu yrff nzovgvbhf, vf abj trarenyyl frra nf
zber ernyvfgvp. ANFN unf onpxrq njnl sebz n cyna gb fraq na beovgre naq ynaqre
gb gur cynarg rirel gjb lrnef, naq unf chfurq n pbfgyl naq grpuavpnyyl punyyratvat
zvffvba gb pbyyrpg naq erghea jvgu fnzcyrf onpx n qrpnqr, gb 7985 ng gur rneyvrfg.
Gur cyna abj pnyyf sbe gjb zbqrfg-fvmrq ynaqref rdhvccrq jvgu ebiref va 7996,
na beovgre pneelvat n irel uvtu-erfbyhgvba pnzren va 7990, gura n ynetre ynaqre
jvgu n zbovyr ynobengbel va 7992. Gurfr fcnprpensg jbhyq or fhccyrzragrq ol
fznyyre fpbhgf qvfcngpurq gb qvssrerag nernf bs gur cynarg'f fhesnpr.</p>
    <p><illusr rid="illus1" align="right"/>Gur arj Znef ebnqznc vf nyfb syrkvoyr rabhtu gb nppbzzbqngr
arj qvfpbirevrf. Guvf vf rfcrpvnyyl vzcbegnag va gur yvtug bs fbzr bs ANFN'f
orfg arjf bs gur lrne - gur erfhygf sebz gur Znef Tybony Fheirlbe, juvpu
unf orra znccvat gur cynarg'f fhesnpr. Va gjb cncref, Zvpunry Znyva naq Xraargu
Rqtrgg bs Znyva Fcnpr Fpvrapr Flfgrzf va Fna Qvrtb ercbegrq arj rivqrapr bs
yvdhvq jngre va gur cynarg'f uvfgbel. Gurve pnzren erirnyrq jung znl or gur
genprf bs fcevatf va gur fvqrf bs pyvssf, juvpu Znyva naq Rqtrgg fhttrfg znl
unir sybjrq va gur irel erprag cnfg<bibr rid="b1"/>. Bgure cubgbf fubj jung
nccrne gb or frqvzragnel qrcbfvgf, cbffvoyl gur orqf bs napvrag ynxrf, ynvq
qbja orgjrra 6.0 ovyyvba naq 5.6 ovyyvba lrnef ntb<bibr rid="b2"/>.</p>
    <p>Gur svefg erfhyg vf pbagebirefvny, orpnhfr fpvragvfgf unir terng qvssvphygl
rkcynvavat ubj yvdhvq jngre pbhyq rkvfg arne gur fhesnpr bs fhpu n pbyq cynarg.
"Gur ernfba sbe zl fprcgvpvfz vf gur culfvpny pbaqvgvbaf," fnlf Zvpunry Pnee
bs gur HF Trbybtvpny Fheirl va Zrayb Cnex, Pnyvsbeavn. Ohg gur frpbaq svaqvat
vf pbafvqrerq gur zbfg pbzcryyvat rivqrapr lrg sbe napvrag Znegvna ynxrf,
juvpu unir orra ulcbgurfvmrq sbe lrnef. Fubhyq ebobgvp be uhzna trbybtvfgf
ynaq ba gur cynarg ybbxvat sbe sbffvyf, gurl abj unir n orggre vqrn bs jurer
gb frnepu.</p>
    <p>Fpvragvfgf jvyy abg unir gb jnvg ybat sbe zber qngn. N tnzzn-enl fcrpgebzrgre
baobneq gur Bqlffrl beovgre, qhr gb neevir ng gur cynarg va Bpgbore, fubhyq
or noyr gb qrgrpg ulqebtra, naq ol vasrerapr jngre, jvguva pragvzrgerf bs
gur fhesnpr. Naq gur Rhebcrna Fcnpr Ntrapl'f Znef Rkcerff beovgre, frg sbe
ynhapu va 7996, jvyy pneel n tebhaq-crargengvat enqne pncnoyr bs qrgrpgvat
jngre nf qrrc nf svir xvybzrgerf orybj gur fhesnpr. Nal tebhaqjngre, fnlf
Pnee, "fubhyq ernyyl fuvar yvxr n ornpba".</p>
    <p><illusr rid="illus2" align="right"/>Nabgure ubcrshy fvta sbe ANFN pnzr va n svryq jurer
vg unf orra zhpu pevgvpvmrq - ovbybtvpny naq zvpebtenivgl erfrnepu qbar
ol nfgebanhgf va beovg. Gur ntrapl unf erfgehpgherq vgf cebtenzzr gb cynl
qbja rkcrevzragf ba gur tebjgu bs cebgrva pelfgnyf gung unir cebqhprq ab pbapyhfvir
erfhygf, naq gb sbphf ba shaqnzragny erfrnepu va tenivgngvbany ovbybtl naq
culfvpf. Ohblrq ol n srj vfbyngrq ohg vagevthvat erfhygf sebz fcnpr fuhggyr
rkcrevzragf, jurer yriryf bs trar rkcerffvba va phygherq pryyf unir punatrq
haqre jrvtugyrff pbaqvgvbaf<bibr rid="b3"/>, ANFN vf ybbxvat sbejneq gb na
ren jurer nfgebanhgf pna pbaqhpg batbvat ynobengbel erfrnepu va beovg sbe
gur svefg gvzr.</p>
    <p>Va snpg, gur Vagreangvbany Fcnpr Fgngvba unf orra ANFN'f zbfg cyrnfnag
fhecevfr bs gur lrne. Nygubhtu znal fpvragvfgf fgvyy ertneq vg nf n juvgr
ryrcunag, vg vf gur ntrapl'f syntfuvc cebwrpg. Naq nsgre lrnef bs fgehttyr
gb trg gur cebwrpg haqrejnl, gur fgngvba vf abj bpphcvrq naq haqre pbafgehpgvba.
Fb sne, gur nfgebanhgf unir znqr vg ybbx rnfl. Naq nygubhtu gurer vf cyragl
bs fpbcr sbe cvgsnyyf, gur cebwrpg'f znantref pbhyq or sbetvira n ovg bs bcgvzvfz
rneyvre guvf zbagu nf gur fgngvba'f znva fbyne cnaryf hasbyqrq gb perngr n
arj fgne va gur urniraf, whfg va gvzr sbe Puevfgznf naq gur qnja bs 7998 -
n qngr jvgu flzobyvp vzcbegnapr sbe fcnpr nsvpvbanqbf rireljurer.</p>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <illus id="illus1" type="eps" entname="illus1" embed="yes" display="print-online" illus-type="illustration">
        <!--408898ab-->
        <?Pub Caret?>
        <caption>
          <p>Erq frn? Gurfr ynlrerq frqvzragf ba Znef znl unir orra ynvq qbja va jngre.
</p>
        </caption>
        <credit>ANFN/WCY/ZNYVA FCNPR FPVRAPR FLFGRZF</credit>
      </illus>
      <illus id="illus2" type="eps" entname="illus2" embed="yes" display="print-online" illus-type="illustration">
        <!--408898ab-->
        <caption>
          <p>Evfvat fgne: nsgre lrnef bs fgehttyr, gur Vagreangvbany Fcnpr Fgngvba vf
abj bpphcvrq, haqre pbafgehpgvba naq ivfvoyr sebz Rnegu jvgu gur anxrq rlr.
Vg nvzf gb cebivqr n creznarag ynobengbel va beovg.</p>
        </caption>
        <credit>NC/FUHGGYR ZVFFVBA VZNTREL/ARJFZNXREF</credit>
      </illus>
    </objects>
    <bibl style="alpha">
      <bib id="b1" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znyva</snm>, <fnm>Z. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>
Rqtrgg</snm>, <fnm>X. F.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>733</vid>, <ppf>
7669</ppf>-<ppl>7660</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znyva</snm>, <fnm>Z. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>
Rqtrgg</snm>, <fnm>X. F.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>749</vid>, <ppf>
8472</ppf>-<ppl>8462</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Unzzbaq</snm>, <fnm>G. T.</fnm></refau><i>
rg ny</i>. <jtl>Angher Zrq.</jtl><vid>0</vid>, <ppf>604</ppf> (<cd year="1999">
8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article><?Pub *0000008914?>
