<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article id="nrn1990" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <!--nrn1990-->
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Angher Erivrjf Arhebfpvrapr</jtl>
    <vol>2</vol>
    <iss>89</iss>
    <idt>799189</idt>
    <categ id="rv"/>
    <pp>
      <spn>227</spn>
      <epn>236</epn>
      <cnt>87</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">8528-996K</issn>
    <issn type="electronic">8528-9953</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>7991</cpy>
      <cpn>Angher Choyvfuvat Tebhc</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <doi>89.8963/aea8449</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl display="show">Zbecubtra gb zvgbtra: gur zhygvcyr ebyrf bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va iregroengr arheny qrirybczrag</atl>
    <aug>
      <au>
        <fnm>Znep</fnm>
        <snm>Shppvyyb</snm>
        <inits>Z</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <bio>
          <p>Znep Shppvyyb fghqvrq ovbybtl naq ivbyva cresbeznapr ng Oebja Havirefvgl, Cebivqrapr, Eubqr Vfynaq, HFN, tenqhngvat va 8443.  Nsgre jbexvat sbe gjb lrnef ng gur Ebpxrsryyre Havirefvgl, Arj Lbex, HFN, va gur ynobengbel bs Wnzrf Qnearyy, ur wbvarq gur Arj Lbex Havirefvgl Zrqvpny Fpvragvfg Genvavat Z.Q./Cu.Q. Cebtenz.  Cerfragyl, ur vf fghqlvat gur qrirybczragny zrpunavfzf bs pbegvpny vagrearheba qvirefvgl va gur ynobengbel bs Tbeq Svfuryy ng gur Fxveonyy Vafgvghgr, ALH.</p>
        </bio>
      </au>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Nyrknaqen Y.</fnm>
        <snm>Wblare</snm>
        <inits>N Y</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <bio>
          <p>Nyrknaqen Y. Wblare unf orra gur Pb-pbbeqvangbe bs gur Qrirybczragny Trargvpf Cebtenz ng gur Fxveonyy Vafgvghgr bs Ovbzbyrphyne Zrqvpvar jvguva gur Arj Lbex Havirefvgl Fpubby bs Zrqvpvar, HFN, sbe 87 lrnef. Fur vf nyfb gur Fxveonyy Sbhaqngvba Cebsrffbe bs Trargvpf naq n Cebsrffbe va gur Qrcnegzragf bs Pryy Ovbybtl naq bs Culfvbybtl naq Arhebfpvrapr. Fur jvyy fbba wbva gur Qrirybczragny Ovbybtl Cebtenz ng gur Fybna-Xrggrevat Vafgvghgr, Arj Lbex. N angvir Pnanqvna, fur erprvirq ure Cu.Q. sebz gur Havirefvgl bs Gbebagb, Pnanqn. Qhevat ure cbfgqbpgbeny erfrnepu jvgu Tnvy Znegva ng gur Havirefvgl bs Pnyvsbeavn, Fna Senapvfpb, HFN, fur pybarq fbzr bs gur svefg znzznyvna ubzrbobk trarf. Fur jnf gura n fravbe fpvragvfg va gur Fnzhry Yharasryq Erfrnepu Vafgvghgr ng Zg. Fvanv Ubfcvgny va Gbebagb sbe rvtug lrnef, jurer fur cvbarrerq n ahzore bs zbhfr trargvp nccebnpurf naq ortna ure fghqvrf bs gur <i>Tyv</i> trarf naq qrirybczrag bs gur preroryyhz. Ure erfrnepu sbphfrf ba trargvp naq pryyhyne riragf haqreylvat zbhfr zvqoenva naq preroryyhz qrirybczrag, naq gur ebyr bs <i>Fuu</i> va nqhyg fgrz pryyf.</p>
        </bio>
      </cau>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Tbeq</fnm>
        <snm>Svfuryy</snm>
        <inits>T</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <corf rid="c1"/>
        <bio>
          <p>Tbeq Svfuryy erprvirq uvf Cu.Q. va 8434 sebz gur Havirefvgl bs Gbebagb, Pnanqn, va gur ynobengbel bs Qrerx ina qre Xbbl. Fvapr guvf gvzr ur unf orra vagrerfgrq va gur zrpunavfzf gung npg gb cnggrea gur gryraprcunyba. Sbe gur cnfg gjryir lrnef, ur unf orra ng Arj Lbex Havirefvgl'f Fpubby bs Zrqvpvar, HFN, jurer ur vf n cebsrffbe. Ur vf n pbbeqvangbe bs gur Qrirybczragny Trargvpf Cebtenz ng gur ALH'f Fxveonyy Vafgvghgr, jvgu n cevznel nccbvagzrag va gur Qrcnegzrag bs Pryy Ovbybtl. Ur jvyy fbba orpbzr gur pbbeqvangbe bs gur Fzvybj Vagrtengrq Arhebfpvrapr cebtenz, n arj erfrnepu vavgvngvir ng ALH. Uvf ynobengbel fghqvrf inevbhf nfcrpgf bs gryraprcunyvp qrirybczrag, zbfg abgnoyl va gur qrirybczragny naq trargvp bevtvaf bs pbegvpny vagrearheba qvirefvgl.</p>
        </bio>
      </cau>
      <aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Qrirybczragny Trargvpf Cebtenz naq gur Qrcnegzrag bs Pryy Ovbybtl, Fxveonyy Vafgvghgr bs Ovbzbyrphyne Zrqvpvar, Arj Lbex Havirefvgl Zrqvpny Pragre</org>, <street>059 Svefg Nirahr</street>, <cty>Arj Lbex</cty>, <st>AL</st><zip>89981</zip>, <cny>HFN</cny>.</aff>
      <caff>
        <coid id="c1"/>
        <email>svfuryy@fnghea.zrq.alh.rqh</email>
      </caff>
    </aug>
    <execsumm>
      <p>
        <list id="l1" type="bullet">
          <li>Urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gur znzznyvna areibhf flfgrz unf orra genqvgvbanyyl nffbpvngrq jvgu qbefbirageny cnggreavat. Znal erprag svaqvatf unir qrzbafgengrq vgf vaibyirzrag va inevbhf grzcbenyyl erthyngrq qrirybczragny cebprffrf. Guvf erivrj cebivqrf na bireivrj bs gur fcngvny naq grzcbeny pbagrkgf va juvpu urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vf hgvyvmrq.</li>
          <li>Jr bhgyvar gur onfvp urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl naq qvfphff gur ebyrf bs arjyl vqragvsvrq erthyngbef bs guvf cngujnl, vapyhqvat rkgenpryyhyne zrqvngbef (fhpu nf VUBT) naq n snzvyl bs trarf nffbpvngrq jvgu pvyvn shapgvba.</li>
          <li>Gur erivrj qrfpevorf gur pber zbyrphyne pbzcbaragf hgvyvmrq va gur rfgnoyvfuzrag bs irageny cnggreavat va gur fcvany pbeq. Jr gura qvfphff gur ebyr bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va irageny cnggreavat va gur oebnqre pbagrkg bs vgf ebyr ng inevbhf zber nagrevbe yriryf bs gur arhenkvf, vapyhqvat gur sberoenva, zvqoenva naq uvaqoenva.</li>
          <li>N ahzore bs aba-cnggreavat shapgvbaf bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unir orra qvfpbirerq, vapyhqvat n ebyr va gur fcrpvsvpngvba bs byvtbqraqebplgr cerphefbef, nf jryy nf gur erthyngvba bs rzoelbavp cebyvsrengvba naq ncbcgbfvf.</li>
          <li>Na hasberfrra ebyr sbe urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va irageny zvqyvar nkbany thvqnapr unf orra hapbirerq. Vagevthvatyl, gur gvzr pbhefr bs riragf fhttrfgf guvf vf zrqvngrq ol aba-pnabavpny fvtanyyvat.</li>
          <li>Erpragyl, urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unf orra fubja gb or npgvir va nqhyg arheny fgrz pryyf naq gb or erdhverq sbe gur znvagranapr bs gur gryraprcunyvp cebtravgbe pryy avpur.</li>
        </list>
      </p>
    </execsumm>
    <websumm type="regular">Gur ebyr bs fbavp urqtrubt nf n zbecubtra vaibyirq va rfgnoyvfuvat irageny pryy vqragvgl va gur PAF vf jryy xabja. Svfuryy naq pbyyrnthrf bhgyvar gur pheerag haqrefgnaqvat bs gur zbyrphyne cngujnlf vaibyirq va cnggreavat naq qrfpevor frireny erpragyl vqragvsvrq naq haeryngrq ebyrf sbe urqtrubt fvtanyyvat.</websumm>
    <abs>
      <p>Fbavp urqtrubt unf erprvirq na rabezbhf nzbhag bs nggragvba fvapr vgf ebyr nf n zbecubtra gung qverpgf irageny cnggreavat va gur fcvany pbeq jnf qvfpbirerq n qrpnqr ntb. Fvapr gung gvzr, n orjvyqrevat neenl bs vasbezngvba unf orra trarengrq pbapreavat obgu gur pbzcbaragf bs gur urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl naq gur erznexnoyr ahzore bs pbagrkgf va juvpu vg shapgvbaf. Abjurer vf guvf zber rivqrag guna va gur areibhf flfgrz, jurer urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unf orra vzcyvpngrq va riragf nf qvfcnengr nf nkbany thvqnapr naq fgrz pryy znvagranapr. Urer jr erivrj bhe cerfrag xabjyrqtr bs gur urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl naq fcrphyngr nobhg nernf va juvpu shegure vafvtugf vagb guvf irefngvyr cngujnl zvtug or sbegupbzvat.</p>
    </abs>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>Gur orfg-fghqvrq shapgvbaf bs gur zrzoref bs gur urqtrubt cebgrva snzvyl va gur areibhf flfgrz ner gurve ebyrf nf <deflistr rid="df1">zbecubtraf</deflistr>; rnpu cebgrva npgf ng n qvfgnapr sebz gur fbhepr bs gur fvtany gb rfgnoyvfu pryy vqragvgvrf va gur irageny fcvany pbeq va n pbapragengvba-qrcraqrag znaare. Ubjrire, qhevat gur cnfg qrpnqr vg unf orpbzr nccnerag gung gur shapgvbaf bs gur zrzoref bs gur urqtrubt cebgrva snzvyl va qrirybczrag ner qvirefr, jvgu gurve fcrpvsvp npgvbaf punatvat jvgu obgu fcnpr naq gvzr. Guvf unf cebira gb or gehr jvgu erfcrpg gb gur zbyrphyne pbzcbaragf gung zbqhyngr naq genafqhpr urqtrubt fvtanyyvat, naq gur fcrpvsvp pryyhyne cebprffrf gung vg pbagebyf. Gur vapernfvat ahzore bs obgu vagen- naq vagrepryyhyne zbqhyngbef bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unir orra pbzcerurafviryl qvfphffrq va erprag erivrjf<bibr rid="b1 b2"/>.</p>
    <p>Urer, jr ynetryl pbasvar bhe qvfphffvba gb gur ebyrf bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gur znzznyvna areibhf flfgrz. Jr svefg qvfphff gur shapgvba bs urqtrubt cebgrvaf va qverpgvat arheny cebtravgbef gb npdhver fcrpvsvp pryy vqragvgvrf. Va cnegvphyne, jr sbphf ba ubj zrzoref bs gur TYV snzvyl bs genafpevcgvba snpgbef npg nf rssrpgbef bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gur fcvany pbeq, nyybjvat na rkgenpryyhyne pbapragengvba tenqvrag bs urqtrubt gb or genafyngrq vagb qvssrerag pryy vqragvgvrf. Jr gura qvfphff ubj vgrengvbaf bs guvf zbyrphyne cngujnl ng zber nagrevbe yriryf bs gur areibhf flfgrz yrnq gb gur vaqhpgvba bs pryy glcrf nccebcevngr sbe gur gryraprcunyba, qvraprcunyba, zvqoenva naq nagrevbe uvaqoenva. Va nqqvgvba gb guvf ebyr va cnggreavat, jr erivrj gur znal qrirybczragny riragf gung urqtrubt fvtanyyvat zrqvngrf, vapyhqvat gur trarengvba bs byvtbqraqebplgrf naq vgf <deflistr rid="df2">zvgbtravp</deflistr> ebyr va pbagebyyvat gur cebyvsrengvba bs arheny cebtravgbef. Svanyyl, jr qvfphff fbzr zber erpragyl erpbtavmrq ebyrf sbe urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va nkbany cngusvaqvat naq gur znvagranapr bs nqhyg fgrz pryyf.</p>
    <crosshd>Zbyrphyne zrpunavfzf bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat</crosshd>
    <p>Gur zbyrphyne zrpunavfzf ol juvpu rkgenpryyhyne urqtrubt fvtanyf ner erprvirq, vagrecergrq naq genafsbezrq vagb vagenpryyhyne pryy sngr qrpvfvbaf unir erprvirq n terng qrny bs nggragvba<bibr rid="b3 b4"/>. Jbex sebz obgu iregroengr naq vairegroengr fcrpvrf unf qryvarngrq n pnabavpny urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl, va juvpu pryy-fhesnpr ovaqvat bs urqtrubt yvtnaqf yrnqf hygvzngryl gb gur sbezngvba bs ercerffbe be npgvingbe sbezf bs zrzoref bs gur TYV/PV snzvyl bs mvap-svatre genafpevcgvba snpgbef (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8</figr>)<bibr rid="b5"/>. Va iregroengrf, gur shapgvbaf bs gur cebgrva rapbqrq ol gur naprfgeny vairegroengr trar phovghf vagreehcghf (<scientific id="43767" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene"><i>pv</i></scientific>) unir orra qvivqrq orgjrra gur guerr TYV cebgrvaf (<scientific id="14632" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">TYV8</scientific>, <scientific id="14633" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">TYV7</scientific> naq <scientific id="14634" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">TYV6</scientific>)<bibr rid="b6"/>. Urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va znzznyf vf vavgvngrq ol bar bs guerr ubzbybthrf bs gur Qebfbcuvyn urqtrubt cebgrva<bibr rid="b7"/> - fbavp urqtrubt (<scientific id="20423" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">FUU</scientific>), vaqvna urqtrubt (<scientific id="16147" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">VUU</scientific>) naq qrfreg urqtrubt (<scientific id="13363" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">QUU</scientific>), bs juvpu gur svefg gjb unir orra vzcyvpngrq va arheny qrirybczrag<bibr rid="b8 b9"/>.</p>
    <p>Gur genafqhpgvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va pryyf vf zrqvngrq ol vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra gjb cebgrvaf, gur gjryir-cnff zrzoenar urqtrubt erprcgbe cngpurq (<scientific id="19206" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">CGP8</scientific>)<bibr rid="b10 b11"/> naq gur frira-cnff T-cebgrva-pbhcyrq erprcgbe fzbbgurarq (<scientific id="319757" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">FZB</scientific>)<bibr rid="b2 b12"/>. Trargvp naq ovbpurzvpny qngn vaqvpngr gung, va gur nofrapr bs urqtrubt yvtnaq, CGP8 pbafgvghgviryl ercerffrf FZB npgvivgl<bibr rid="b120"/>. Guvf ercerffvba vf aba-fgbvpuvbzrgevp, vzcylvat gung CGP8 npgf ol n pngnylgvp zrpunavfz<bibr rid="b13"/>. Gur qrgnvyf bs guvf vagrenpgvba ner pheeragyl haxabja, nygubhtu gur ubzbybtl bs CGP8 gb onpgrevny cebgba-qevira genafzrzoenar zbyrphyne genafcbegref bssref gur vagevthvat cbffvovyvgl gung CGP8 erthyngrf gur qvfgevohgvba bs n fznyy zbyrphyr gung nygref FZB npgvivgl<bibr rid="b14"/>. Urqtrubt yvtnaq ovaqvat gb CGP8 eryvrirf guvf vauvovgvba guebhtu n zrpunavfz gung vf nyfb cbbeyl haqrefgbbq.</p>
    <p>Va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, gur cngujnl sebz FZB npgvingvba gb gur cebprffvat, npgvingvba naq genafybpnyvmngvba bs gur PV genafpevcgvbany zrqvngbe vaibyirf gur npgvivgl bs n ynetr cebgrva pbzcyrk vapyhqvat gur xvarfva-yvxr cebgrva pbfgny 7 (<scientific id="35653" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">PBF7</scientific>), gur frevar/guerbavar cebgrva xvanfr shfrq (SH), naq fhccerffbe bs shfrq (FHSH)<bibr rid="b1 b15"/>. Ubjrire, jbex vaibyivat fcrpvrf sebz svfu gb zvpr fubjf gung gurfr pbzcbaragf zvtug abg or hgvyvmrq va n pbafreirq znaare va zrqvngvat iregroengr vagenpryyhyne urqtrubt fvtanyyvat, rira orgjrra gurfr eryngviryl pybfr fcrpvrf. Sbe rknzcyr, gur shapgvba bs PBF7 nf n artngvir erthyngbe bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gur nofrapr bs urqtrubt yvtnaq frrzf gb or pbafreirq va svfu<bibr rid="b16"/> ohg abg va zvpr<bibr rid="b17"/> (sbe n erivrj, frr Ers. <bibrinl rid="b1">8</bibrinl>).</p>
    <p>Va nqqvgvba, ahzrebhf hasberfrra vagenpryyhyne pbzcbaragf gung zbqvsl urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unir orra erirnyrq guebhtu sbejneq trargvp fperraf. Va iregroengrf, zhgngvbaf va guerr frcnengr vagensyntryyne genafcbeg cebgrvaf - jvzcyr (VSG827), syrkb (ulcbzbecuvp nyyryr bs cbynevf, VSG33) naq gur vagensyntryyne genafcbeg zbgbe cebgrva XVS6n - erfhyg va fvzvyne arheny curabglcrf va zvpr, jvgu punenpgrevfgvpf bs obgu erqhprq naq rkprff urqtrubt fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b18 b19"/>. Nabgure yvax orgjrra arheny urqtrubt fvtanyyvat naq vagenpryyhyne irfvpyr genafcbeg jnf erirnyrq ol gur <i>bcra-oenva</i> zbhfr zhgnag, juvpu unf gur ybff-bs-shapgvba <i>Eno76</i> nyyryr, n zrzore bs gur Eno snzvyl bs TGCnfrf<bibr rid="b20"/>. Vagrerfgvatyl, znal bs gur cebgrvaf zragvbarq nobir ner nffbpvngrq jvgu pvyvn shapgvba, fhttrfgvat n ebyr sbe guvf fgehpgher va urqtrubt fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b19 b21"/>. Zhgnagf gung erfhyg va gur ybff bs pvyvn, fhpu nf gubfr nffbpvngrq jvgu beny-snpvny-qvtvgny flaqebzr 8 (<i>BSQ8</i>) ybff-bs-shapgvba naq <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=209900">Oneqrg-Ovrqy flaqebzr</weblink>, unir qrsrpgf va cnggreavat erzvavfprag bs erqhprq urqtrubt fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b22"/> naq, pbafvfgrag jvgu guvf ulcbgurfvf, n erprag fghql unf qrzbafgengrq gung FZB pna ybpnyvmr gb pvyvn va erfcbafr gb urqtrubt cngujnl fgvzhyngvba<bibr rid="b23"/>. Zberbire, zhgngvbaf bs nzvab npvq erfvqhrf va FZB gung cerirag guvf ybpnyvmngvba erfhyg va n shapgvbanyyl vanpgvir sbez bs FZB. Jvgu gur qvfpbirel gung gur guerr TYV cebgrvaf naq gur artngvir erthyngbe FHSH ner ybpngrq ng gur qvfgny gvcf bs gur pvyvn va nqqvgvba gb gur ahpyrhf, vg frrzf yvxryl gung gur pvyvn shapgvba nf ybpnyvmrq zrqvngbef bs urqtrubt fvtany cebcntngvba<bibr rid="b24"/>. Pregnvayl gur cerfrapr bs cevznel aba-zbgvyr pvyvn ba zbfg PAF arhebaf nyybjf sbe gur cbffvovyvgl gung urqtrubt fvtanyyvat hgvyvmrf guvf irfgvtvny fgehpgher<bibr rid="b25"/>.</p>
    <crosshd>Cnggreavat gur irageny fcvany pbeq</crosshd>
    <p>Bhe terngrfg haqrefgnaqvat bs gur shapgvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat nf n zbecubtra va gur iregroengr areibhf flfgrz unf pbzr sebz nanylfvf bs gur zbhfr naq puvpx fcvany pbeq, jurer FUU vf rkcerffrq ol gur zbfg irageny pryyf, gur sybbe cyngr (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7</figr>). Va guvf frggvat, FUU fubjf nyy gur punenpgrevfgvpf bs n zbecubtra: vg npgf ng n qvfgnapr sebz gur cbvag fbhepr va n pbapragengvba-qrcraqrag znaare naq npgf qverpgyl ba gur erpvcvrag pryy jvgubhg nal erynl zrpunavfz<bibr rid="b9 b26 b27 b28 b29"/>.</p>
    <p>Gur svefg fghqvrf fhccbegvat gur ebyr bs FUU nf n zbecubtra pnzr sebz <i>va ivgeb</i> phygher nffnlf hgvyvmvat vagrezrqvngr ertvbaf bs puvpx rzoelb fcvany pbeq gung jrer pbyyrpgrq cevbe gb gur boivbhf rfgnoyvfuzrag bs qbefbirageny vqragvgl. Jura gurfr rkcynagf jrer rkcbfrq gb pbagebyyrq yriryf bs erpbzovanag FUU, vg jnf sbhaq gung cnegvphyne irageny fcvany pbeq vqragvgvrf pbhyq or vaqhprq, onfrq ba gur pbapragengvba bs FUU<bibr rid="b27"/>. Vzcbegnagyl, qvssrerag pbapragengvbaf bs FUU jrer fhssvpvrag gb vaqhpr fcrpvsvp irageny fcvany pbeq arhebany cbchyngvbaf. Sbe rknzcyr, jurernf gur ybjrfg yriryf bs FUU pbhyq vaqhpr vagrezrqvngr irageny vqragvgvrf, fhpu nf <deflistr rid="df3">I9, I8 naq I7 vagrearhebaf</deflistr> (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7</figr>), uvture pbapragengvbaf jrer erdhverq gb vaqhpr zbgbe arhebaf naq gur uvturfg pbapragengvba jnf arprffnel gb vaqhpr gur zbfg irageny arhebany pryy glcrf: gur I6 vagrearhebaf naq gur sybbe cyngr.</p>
    <p><i>Va ivib</i> rivqrapr sbe FUU'f npgvba nf n zbecubtra qhevat arheny qrirybczrag unf orra orfg qrzbafgengrq ol gjb fghqvrf rzcyblvat pryy-nhgbabzbhf zrgubqf gb eraqre pryyf haerfcbafvir gb FUU va zvpr naq puvpxf<bibr rid="b9 b28"/>. Va gurfr rkcrevzragf, FUU erfcbafvirarff unf orra noyngrq rvgure guebhtu gur rkcerffvba bs n qrygn-ybbc qryrgvba zhgnag bs CGP8 gung eraqref pryyf rkcerffvat guvf zhgnag cebgrva vafrafvgvir gb gur raqbtrabhf yvtnaq, be guebhtu gur trarengvba bs <i>Fzb</i> -ahyy puvznrenf, va juvpu FUU aba-erfcbafvir pryyf jrer vagrezvatyrq jvgu jvyq-glcr pryyf va gur arheny ghor. Va gur qrygn-ybbc CGP8 fghqvrf, va nqqvgvba gb gur pryy-nhgbabzbhf rssrpgf rkcrpgrq va irageny cebtravgbef ynpxvat FUU fvtanyyvat, gurer jnf nyfb n znexrq aba-pryy-nhgbabzbhf ercnggreavat nebhaq zhgnag tebhcf bs pryyf. Guvf curabzraba vf cebonoyl qhr gb n ybpny fxrjvat va gur tenqvrag bs FUU, orpnhfr vg vf noyr gb geniry havzcrqrq npebff pryyf gung rkcerff gur zhgnag CGP8 erprcgbe.</p>
    <p>Gur FUU tenqvrag va gur fcvany pbeq vf abg n cnffvir fbhepr-fvax tenqvrag ohg vf vafgrnq znvagnvarq ol npgvir zrpunavfzf gung erthyngr gur npgvivgl, eryrnfr, genafcbeg naq ergragvba bs FUU cebgrva npebff gur arhebrcvguryvhz (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8</figr>). Gurfr zbqhyngbef bs FUU fvtanyyvat vapyhqr fvtugyrff/fxvaal urqtrubt, na nprglygenafsrenfr gung zbqvsvrf FUU ol nqqvat cnyzvgvp npvq gb vgf nzvab (A) grezvahf<bibr rid="b30 b31"/>, nf jryy nf cebgrvaf fhpu nf qvfcngpurq, Lbh/Fphor7 naq gbhg-iryh (gur zbhfr ubzbybthr bs guvf trar vf rkbfgbfva (RKG8)) gung pbageby gur eryrnfr naq genafcbeg bs urqtrubt cebgrvaf va qvssrerag fcrpvrf<bibr rid="b32 b33 b34 b35"/>. Va nqqvgvba, frireny bgure rkgenpryyhyne cebgrvaf yvzvg gur enatr bs FUU zbirzrag fhpu nf CGP8 naq urqtrubt vagrenpgvat cebgrva (UVC)<bibr rid="b10 b36"/> (sbe n zber qrgnvyrq qvfphffvba bs gurfr pbzcbaragf bs FUU fvtanyyvat, frr Ers. <bibrinl rid="b2">7</bibrinl>). Zber erpragyl, n abiry rkgenpryyhyne cebgrva PQB (vagresrerapr urqtrubt (VUBT) va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>) naq vgf eryngvir OBP unir orra sbhaq gb cbfvgviryl erthyngr urqtrubt fvtanyyvat guebhtu gur ovaqvat naq frdhrfgengvba bs urqtrubt yvtnaq, erfhygvat va ybpnyyl raunaprq fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b37 b38 b39"/>.</p>
    <p>N shaqnzragny dhrfgvba va qrirybczrag vf ubj gur rkgenpryyhyne pbapragengvba tenqvrag bs n zbecubtra vf genafyngrq vagb gur vagenpryyhyne fcrpvsvpngvba bs zhygvcyr pryy vqragvgvrf (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7</figr>). Vg vf abj pyrne gung nyy gur rssrpgf bs FUU va irageny fcvany pbeq cnggreavat va znzznyf ner zrqvngrq ol gur pbzovarq npgvivgl bs gur guerr TYV genafpevcgvba snpgbef<bibr rid="b6 b40"/>. Ryrtnag trargvp fghqvrf unir abj rkcbfrq obgu gur cnegvnyyl erqhaqnag naq znvayl havdhr shapgvbaf bs rnpu zbhfr <i>Tyv</i> trar va na <i>va ivib</i> pbagrkg. Trargvp ybff-bs-shapgvba naq xabpx-va fghqvrf va juvpu gur <i>Tyv</i> trarf unir orra noyngrq<bibr rid="b41 b42 b43 b44"/> be trargvpnyyl fhofgvghgrq<bibr rid="b6 b45"/> unir fubja gung, ng yrnfg va gur pbagrkg bs irageny arheny ghor fcrpvsvpngvba, TYV6 shapgvbaf cevznevyl nf n genafpevcgvbany ercerffbe jurernf TYV8 naq TYV7 shapgvba nf npgvingbef<bibr rid="b6 b41 b42 b43 b44 b45 b46 b47"/>. Cbfvgvir FUU fvtanyyvat vaqhprf gur sbezngvba bs TYV7 naq (gb n yrffre rkgrag) TYV6 npgvingbef, juvpu vaqhpr genafpevcgvba bs gur pbafgvghgvir npgvingbe TYV8. Ol pbagenfg, nofrapr bs gur yvtnaq nyybjf sbe gur sbezngvba bs gur TYV6 ercerffbe. Bgure ertvbaf bs gur areibhf flfgrz rzcybl gurfr fnzr npgvingbe/ercerffbe pbzovangvbaf gb qvssrerag rkgragf va genafsbezvat FUU fvtanyf vagb pryyhyne erfcbafrf.</p>
    <p>Cevznevyl TYV7 npgvingbe shapgvba vf rffragvny sbe gur vaqhpgvba bs gur irageny-zbfg pryy glcrf, vapyhqvat gur sybbe cyngr naq I6 vagrearhebaf<bibr rid="b41 b43 b44"/>, jurernf gur cebcre erthyngvba bs TYV6 ercerffbe yriryf pbagebyf gur ahzore naq ybpngvba bs I9, I8 naq I7 cebtravgbef<bibr rid="b6 b42"/>. Fvghngrq orgjrra gurfr rkgerzrf ner zbgbe arhebaf, gur qvssreragvngvba bs juvpu vf erthyngrq ol n pbzovangvba bs TYV7 naq TYV6. Va pbagenfg gb gur cbfvgvir npgvivgl bs FUU fvtanyyvat va gur sybbe cyngr naq I6 vagrearhebaf<bibr rid="b6 b45"/>, FUU frrzf gb shapgvba cevznevyl nf n artngvir erthyngbe va vagrezrqvngr irageny fcvany pbeq cnggreavat<bibr rid="b42"/>. Vagrerfgvatyl, vg qbrf fb ol fhccerffvat phrf gung jbhyq bgurejvfr qverpg cebtravgbef gb nqbcg n qbefny sngr, engure guna ol fcrpvslvat irageny sngr qverpgyl<bibr rid="b52"/>.</p>
    <p>Qbjafgernz bs gur TYV cebgrvaf, urqtrubt fvtanyyvat zrqvngrf pryy fcrpvsvpngvba guebhtu gur fvzhygnarbhf ercerffvba bs Pynff V ubzrbqbznva genafpevcgvba snpgbef (sbe rknzcyr, <i>Cnk1</i>, <i>Cnk2</i>, <i>Vek6</i> naq <i>Qok8/7</i>) naq gur vaqhpgvba bs Pynff VV ubzrbqbznva genafpevcgvba snpgbef (sbe rknzcyr, <i>Axk7.7</i>, <i>Axk1.8</i>) va irageny fcvany pbeq cebtravgbef<bibr rid="b48 b49 b50"/>. Pebff-ercerffvir vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra gurfr erfhygnag ubzrbqbznva genafpevcgvba snpgbef gura npg gb funecra gur rkcerffvba obhaqnevrf naq fhofrdhragyl qverpg pryyf gb qvssreragvngr vagb fcrpvsvp fhoglcrf<bibr rid="b48"/>. Gur zrpunavfgvp yvax orgjrra gur TYV genafpevcgvbany npgvingbef naq ercerffbef naq gur erfhygnag ubzrbqbznva cnggrea unf lrg gb or ryhpvqngrq. Vg frrzf yvxryl gung qvssreragvny cebzbgre nssvavgvrf naq ertvba-fcrpvsvp pbsnpgbef nvq va genafyngvat gur bireylvat pbzovangbevny TYV genafpevcgvba snpgbe tenqvragf vagb pryyhyne qrpvfvbaf. Va nqqvgvba, erprag ryrpgebcbengvba fghqvrf va puvpx rzoelbf unir fhttrfgrq gung TYV genafpevcgvbany zrqvngbef pna or phzhyngviryl vagrtengrq bire gvzr gb npuvrir nccebcevngr ubzrbqbznva genafpevcgvba snpgbe cnggreavat<bibr rid="b51"/>.</p>
    <p>Gung cbfvgvir FUU fvtanyyvat vf abg erdhverq sbe gur trarengvba bs fbzr irageny pryy glcrf vf rivqrag sebz pbzcbhaq zhgnagf bs <i>Fuu</i> be <i>Fzb</i> naq <i>Tyv6</i> (Ersf <bibrinl rid="b9">4</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b52">07</bibrinl>), nf jryy nf zbhfr rzoelbf qrsvpvrag va nyy guerr TYV cebgrvaf<bibr rid="b6 b40"/>. Va gurfr zhgnagf, fbzr nfcrpgf bs irageny fcvany pbeq cnggreavat ner znvagnvarq, jvgu gur rkprcgvba bs gur sybbe cyngr, I6 vagrearhebaf naq fbzr zbgbe arheba cbchyngvbaf. Gurersber, TYV npgvingbef ner abg erdhverq gb vaqhpr gurfr vagrezrqvngr irageny pryy glcrf. Jvgu ertneq gb gur cbgragvny fvtanyyvat cngujnlf erfcbafvoyr sbe gur vaqhpgvba bs gur pryy glcrf sbe juvpu FUU fvtanyyvat vf abg erdhverq, obgu svoeboynfg tebjgu snpgbe (STS) naq ergvabvq fvtanyyvat unir orra cebcbfrq gb unir n ebyr va irageny cnggreavat va gur arheny ghor. STS fvtanyyvat frrzf gb erthyngr gur gvzvat bs irageny pryy glcr fcrpvsvpngvba. Ryrpgebcbengvba fghqvrf naq rkcynag jbex sebz puvpx rzoelbf unir fhttrfgrq gung ergvabvqf cebivqr gur cbfvgvir erthyngvba bs pynff V ubzrbqbznva cebgrvaf gung pbzcyrzrag gur npgvbaf bs FUU va ercerffvat qbefny arheny vqragvgvrf naq vaqhpvat pynff VV trar rkcerffvba iragenyyl<bibr rid="b53"/>.</p>
    <p>N fhecevfvat frg bs svaqvatf vaqvpngr gung urqtrubt fvtanyyvat zvtug abg bayl pbageby irageny cebtravgbe fcrpvsvpngvba, ohg pbhyq nyfb npg gb znvagnva gur cebcre fgengvsvpngvba bs gurfr qvfgvapg cebtravgbe qbznvaf va gurve nccebcevngr arhebany cbbyf. Trargvp erzbiny bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat erfhygf va qvfbetnavmngvba bs gur irageny cebtravgbe cbbyf, jvgu rkgrafvir pryy zvkvat qvfehcgvat gur abezny frtertngvba bs cebtravgbef nybat gur qbefbirageny rkgrag bs gur arheny ghor<bibr rid="b6 b9 b40"/>. Guvf fhttrfgf gung, va nqqvgvba gb n ebyr va irageny fhoglcr fcrpvsvpngvba, urqtrubt fvtanyyvat guebhtu TYV genafpevcgvbany zrqvngbef pbagebyf fbegvat bs qvfgvapg cebtravgbe tebhcf, creuncf ol zbqhyngvat pryy nssvavgvrf. Ng cerfrag, ubjrire, gurer vf bayl rivqrapr sebz <i>va ivgeb</i> arhebrcvguryvny phygherf gb pbaarpg FUU fvtanyyvat jvgu xabja nqurfvba zrpunavfzf nffbpvngrq jvgu urgreb- naq <deflistr rid="df4">ubzbgbcvp pryy fbegvat</deflistr><bibr rid="b54"/>.</p>
    <crosshd>Pryy fcrpvsvpngvba guebhtubhg gur arhenkvf</crosshd>
    <p>Orlbaq gur fcvany pbeq, gur ebyr bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va irageny cnggreavat va gur areibhf flfgrz unf orra rknzvarq va frireny qvssrerag ertvbaf bs gur qrirybcvat iregroengr PAF, vapyhqvat gur sberoenva, zvqoenva naq preroryyhz. Jbex sebz rnpu bs gurfr svryqf vf erivrjrq urer jvgu n sbphf ba abiry vafvtugf vagb ertvbany qvssreraprf va gur cnggreavat shapgvbaf bs FUU (<figr rid="f3">Svt. 6</figr>).</p>
    <p><bi>Sberoenva</bi>. Gur qrirybcvat sberoenva, pbzcevfvat gur gryraprcunyba naq qvraprcunyba, unf zhygvcyr fbheprf bs FUU fvtany gung vasyhrapr cnggreavat naq fcrpvsvpngvba va guvf ertvba. Va gur rzoelbavp gryraprcunyba, FUU vf rkcerffrq jvguva gur znagyr bs gur <deflistr rid="df5">zrqvny tnatyvbavp rzvarapr</deflistr> (ZTR), gur cerbcgvp nern naq gur nzltqnyn, jurernf gur rkcerffvba bs FUU va gur rzoelbavp qvraprcunyba vf sbhaq jvguva gur ulcbgunynzhf naq va gur <deflistr rid="df6">mban yvzvgnaf vagregunynzvpn</deflistr> (MYV), n onaq bs pryyf ng gur obeqre orgjrra gur irageny naq qbefny gunynzv<bibr rid="b7 b55"/>. Vagrerfgvatyl, gur bafrg bs gur rkcerffvba bs <scientific id="21869" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene"><i>Axk7.8</i></scientific>, na rneyl znexre bs irageny sberoenva fcrpvsvpngvba, cerprqrf gur rkcerffvba bs FUU va gur sberoenva, vzcylvat gung irageny fcrpvsvpngvba va gurfr fgehpgherf vf gur erfhyg bs n aba-arheny fbhepr bs FUU fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b56"/>. <i>Va ivgeb</i> jbex jvgu puvpx rzoelbf naq pbaqvgvbany trar noyngvba va zvpr unir fhccbegrq guvf abgvba, fhttrfgvat gung FUU fbheprf sebz gur abqr naq gur cerpubeqny cyngr, juvpu haqreyvrf gur qrirybcvat gryraprcunyvp cevzbevhz, cnggrea gur irageny sberoenva<bibr rid="b57 b58"/>. Shegurezber, vg frrzf gung ol gur gvzr FUU vf rkcerffrq va gur gryraprcunyba, gur vavgvny cnggreavat bs guvf fgehpgher vf pbzcyrgr naq FUU fvtanyyvat vf erdhverq sbe gur znvagranapr bs irageny-zbfg gryraprcunyvp trar rkcerffvba<bibr rid="b59"/>. Noebtngvba bs FUU fvtanyyvat nsgre guvf vavgvny cnggreavat fgntr yrnqf gb n qrpernfr va <i>Axk7.8</i> rkcerffvba va ZTR cebtravgbef naq n erfhygvat erqhpgvba va gur gjb znwbe cbchyngvbaf bs pbegvpny vagrearhebaf qrevirq sebz guvf ertvba<bibr rid="b60"/>. Gur ervgrengvir hfr bs FUU fvtanyyvat gb rssrpg qvirefr gryraprcunyvp shapgvbaf uvtuyvtugf gur vzcbegnapr bs gur fcrpvsvp pbzcrgrapr bs gur arheny cebtravgbef erprvivat naq vagrtengvat gur fvtany. Va gur gryraprcunyba, grzcbeny punatrf va gur pbzcrgrapr bs pryyf gb erfcbaq gb FUU fvtanyf frrz gb or gur ehyr engure guna gur rkprcgvba. Va onfvp irageny gryraprcunyvp cnggreavat, vg frrzf gung gur gvzvat bs rkcbfher gb FUU vf pehpvny va rfgnoyvfuvat zrqvny irefhf yngreny tnatyvbavp rzvarapr sngrf<bibr rid="b61"/>. Yvxrjvfr, va byvtbqraqebplgr fcrpvsvpngvba naq cbchyngvba bs gur <deflistr rid="df7">nqhyg cebyvsrengvir avpur</deflistr>, bayl fcrpvsvp pbubegf bs pryyf gung erfcbaq gb FUU jvguva qvfpergr gvzr jvaqbjf sbyybj gurfr znghengvba cebtenzf, nf jvyy or qrfpevorq orybj.</p>
    <p>Erpragyl, gur cebgrva <scientific id="14725" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">Zrtnyva</scientific>, juvpu vf n ybj-qrafvgl yvcbcebgrva erprcgbe-eryngrq cebgrva, jnf fubja gb fcrpvsvpnyyl rssrpg irageny gryraprcunyvp cnggreavat guebhtu jung frrzf gb or n FUU zrqvngrq zrpunavfz<bibr rid="b62"/>. Ybff bs <i>Zrtnyva</i> erfhygf va gur ybff bs iragenyyl-qrevirq vagrearhebaf naq byvtbqraqebplgrf va gur zbhfr sberoenva. Gur curabglcr frra va gurfr zvpr vf erzvavfprag bs gung bofreirq va zhgnagf va juvpu FUU fvtanyyvat va gur gryraprcunyba jnf pbaqvgvbanyyl noyngrq ng rzoelbavp qnl (R) 4 ol gur erzbiny bs <i>Fzb</i> hfvat n Per/YbkC flfgrz qevira ol gur gryraprcunyba-fcrpvsvp trar <i>Sbkt8</i> (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b57">02</bibrinl>). Gur tebhc gung bevtvanyyl vqragvsvrq Zrtnyva cebcbfrq gung vgf ebyr va FUU fvtanyyvat zvtug or gb shapgvba nf n FUU pb-erprcgbe<bibr rid="b63"/>. Zber erpragyl, bguref unir nethrq gung vgf rssrpgf ner vaqverpg naq npg guebhtu na vapernfr va obar zbecubtrargvp cebgrva fvtanyyvat, juvpu gura npgf gb nggrahngr FUU fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b62"/>. Arireguryrff, jurgure nf n erfhyg bs qverpg be vaqverpg rssrpgf, gurfr svaqvatf fubj gung FUU fvtanyyvat va gur gryraprcunyba vf fcrpvnyvmrq ng yrnfg va vgf erdhverzrag sbe Zrtnyva.</p>
    <p>Nabgure havdhr punenpgrevfgvp bs FUU fvtanyyvat va gryraprcunyvp qrirybczrag vf vgf ebyr va gur fcrpvsvpngvba bs gur qbefny pbegvpny zvqyvar, juvpu yngre tvirf evfr gb gur uvccbpnzcny cevzbeqvhz naq zvqyvar pubebvq cyrkhf rcvguryvhz<bibr rid="b64 b65"/>. Guvf npgvivgl vf va znexrq pbagenfg gb gur ebyr bs FUU va gur fcvany pbeq, va juvpu ybff-bs-shapgvba zhgngvbaf va gur urqtrubt cngujnl unir ab boivbhf rssrpgf ba cnggreavat bs gur qbefny cebtravgbe qbznvaf<bibr rid="b45"/>. Gur zrpunavfz bs FUU'f qbefny npgvba va gur gryraprcunyba, va nqqvgvba gb jurgure vgf npgvbaf ner qverpg be vaqverpg, guebhtu gur zbqhyngvba bs bgure xrl fvtanyyvat pragerf, vf cerfragyl hapyrne.</p>
    <p>Nabgure vagrerfgvat nfcrpg bs gryraprcunyvp urqtrubt fvtanyyvat gung pbagenfgf jvgu vgf npgvba va gur fcvany pbeq vf gur nccnerag nofrapr bs TYV npgvingbe shapgvba va gur fcrpvsvpngvba bs zbfg gryraprcunyvp cebtravgbef. <i>Tyv8<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Tyv7<super>-/-</super></i> qbhoyr-ahyy zhgnag zvpr unir ab znwbe gryraprcunyvp qrsrpgf<bibr rid="b41"/>, naq zbfg bs gur cnggreavat qrsrpgf bs gur <i>Fuu</i> -ahyy zvpr pna or erfphrq ol erzbivat gur ercerffbe sbez bs TYV6 (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b65">10</bibrinl>). Guvf vzcyvrf gung n tenqvrag bs gur ercerffbe sbez bs TYV6 vf cevznevyl vzcbegnag sbe gryraprcunyvp pryy fcrpvsvpngvba, jurernf gur fcvany pbeq hfrf gur shyy pbzcyrzrag bs TYV npgvingbe naq ercerffbe sbezf gb fcrpvsl irageny naq vagrezrqvngr pryy glcrf. Creuncf guvf vf abg fhecevfvat tvira gung gur gryraprcunyba vf rkpyhfviryl qrevirq sebz gur <deflistr rid="df8">nyne cyngr</deflistr>, jurernf gur TYV npgvingbef frrz trarenyyl gb or yvaxrq gb gur fcrpvsvpngvba bs onfny cyngr cebtravgbef. Gur snpg gung gur qbefbirageny cnggreavat vf erfphrq va <i>Fuu<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Tyv6<super>-/-</super></i> naq <i>Fzb<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Tyv6<super>-/-</super></i> pbzcbhaq zhgnagf fhttrfgf gung, nf va gur fcvany pbeq, cbfvgvir erthyngbef vaqrcraqrag bs FUU zhfg nyfb erthyngr irageny gryraprcunyvp cnggreavat. <scientific id="14179" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene"><i>Sts3</i></scientific> naq ergvabvqf frrz gb obgu or yvxryl pnaqvqngrf gb zrqvngr guvf cnggreavat<bibr rid="b66 b67"/>. Erzvavfprag bs FUU'f ebyr va pbagebyyvat STS3 rkcerffvba va gur zvqoenva-uvaqoenva obhaqnel, erprag jbex fhttrfgf gung STS fvtanyyvat pna zrqvngr irageny cnggreavat vaqrcraqragyl bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gur gryraprcunyba<bibr rid="b68"/>. Fcrpvsvpnyyl, hayvxr <i>Fuu<super>-/-</super></i> zvpr, va juvpu gur ybff bs irageny cnggreavat pna or erirefrq ol gur pbzcbhaq erzbiny bs <i>Tyv6</i> (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b65">10</bibrinl>), ab vzcebirzrag va gur irageny gryraprcunyvp cnggrea vf frra va svoeboynfg tebjgu snpgbe erprcgbe 8/6 pbaqvgvbany zhgnagf jura <i>Tyv6</i> trar shapgvba vf nyfb erqhprq (gung vf, <i>Stse8<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Stse6<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Tyv6<super>+/-</super></i>)<bibr rid="b68"/>. Frireny bgure cncref unir fubja gung FUU vaqverpgyl erthyngrf <i>Sts3</i> genafpevcgvba guebhtu zbqhyngvba bs gur TYV6 ercerffbe. Guvf fhttrfgf gung STS fvtanyyvat shapgvbaf nf n cbfvgvir erthyngbe bs irageny gryraprcunyvp cnggreavat, jurernf FUU fvtanyyvat shapgvbaf artngviryl gb cerirag qbefnyvmngvba bs irageny gryraprcunyvp qbznvaf.</p>
    <p>FUU fvtanyyvat va gur irageny qvraprcunyba unf ybat orra nffbpvngrq jvgu gur irageny frcnengvba bs gur rlr svryqf, zbfg boivbhfyl qrzbafgengrq ol gur plpybcvn frra va FUU ybff-bs-shapgvba zhgnagf<bibr rid="b8 b69"/>. Ahzrebhf fghqvrf unir vzcyvpngrq FUU va cnggreavat zhygvcyr nfcrpgf bs gur ivfhny flfgrz, vapyhqvat gur ergvan, bcgvp puvnfz naq bcgvp fgnyx<bibr rid="b70 b71 b72"/>. Jvgu ertneqf gb qbefbirageny cnggreavat va gur qvraprcunyba, FUU fvtanyyvat unf orra nffbpvngrq jvgu gur irageny rkcerffvba bs CNK7, nf jryy nf gur irageny ercerffvba bs CNK1 - n znfgre erthyngbe bs rlr qrirybczrag, juvpu vf erdhverq sbe gur frcnengvba bs gur ovyngrenyyl cbfvgvbarq rlr svryqf<bibr rid="b73"/>. Gung TYV npgvivgl vf gur zrqvngbe bs cnggreavat va guvf ertvba vf vaqvpngrq ol gur cnegvny nofrapr bs gur qvraprcunyba frra va <i>Tyv8<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Tyv7<super>-/-</super></i> qbhoyr zhgnagf<bibr rid="b41"/>.</p>
    <p>Jvgu ertneq gb zber qbefny ertvbaf bs gur qvraprcunyba, erprag fghqvrf bs <i>FUU</i> va gur puvpxra MYV unir ryhpvqngrq n abiry zrpunavfz bs FUU-vaqhprq arheny pryy fcrpvsvpngvba nf jryy nf n ebyr sbe FUU fvtanyyvat va cnggreavat. Vagrerfgvatyl, gur zrpunavfzf bs FUU fvtanyyvat ng gur MYV frrz nxva gb gur npgvbaf bs <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> urqtrubt va nagrevbe-cbfgrevbe pbzcnegzragf bs gur jvat vzntvany qvfp. Gur MYV, juvpu rkcerffrf <i>FUU</i> nybat vgf ragver qbefbirageny rkgrag, fcyvgf gur cergunynzhf nagrevbeyl sebz gur cbfgrevbe gunynzhf. Gurfr nohggvat qvraprcunyvp ertvbaf ner cnggrearq ol gur fnzr MYV FUU fbhepr, lrg gurl npdhver qvfgvapg ertvbany trar rkcerffvba sngrf, vzcylvat gung gur gjb qvraprcunyvp ertvbaf unir n qvssreragvny pbzcrgrapr. <i>Va bib</i> ryrpgebcbengvba fghqvrf va puvpx rzoelbf unir fubja gung gur ubzrbobk trar <i>VEK6</i>, rkcerffrq cbfgrevbe gb gur MYV, perngrf n fgngr bs gunynzvp pbzcrgrapr, fhpu gung zvfrkcerffvba bs <i>VEK6</i> va gur cergunynzvp pbzcnegzrag nyybjrq MYV-qrevirq <i>FUU</i> gb vaqhpr qbefny gunynzvp trar rkcerffvba cebsvyrf rpgbcvpnyyl<bibr rid="b74"/>. Gur qvirefr erfcbafrf bs gurfr gjb nqwnprag pbzcnegzragf gb na vqragvpny FUU fbhepr vyyhfgengrf gur vzcbegnapr bs ertvba-fcrpvsvp snpgbef va trarengvat shapgvbany qvirefvgl sebz n fvatyr cebgrva rkcerffrq jvqryl npebff gur arhenkvf. Fb, whfg nf gur vagrecergngvba bs FUU fvtanyf frrzf va fbzr pbagrkgf gb eryl ba punatrf va grzcbeny pbzcrgrapr, urer qvssreragvny ertvbany trar rkcerffvba zrqvngrf qvssreragvny fcngvny pbzcrgrapr va gur znaare va juvpu fcrpvsvp gvffhrf erfcbaq gb FUU.</p>
    <p><bi>Zvqoenva, uvaqoenva, preroryyhz</bi>. Nygubhtu gur ebyr bs gur vfguzvp betnavmre zbyrphyr STS3 va nagrevbe-cbfgrevbe cnggreavat bs gur zvq/uvaqoenva ertvba unf orra fghqvrq rkgrafviryl, gur ebyr bs FUU va qbefbirageny cnggreavat bs gur ertvba naq vgf yngre shapgvbaf va preroryyhz qrirybczrag unir bayl erpragyl orra nqqerffrq. Fghqvrf bs FUU naq TYV shapgvba va gur zvqoenva naq eubzobzrer 8 (e8), n frtzrag bs gur uvaqoenva, unir hapbirerq gur grzcbeny erdhverzragf sbe FUU fvtanyyvat naq fubja n qvfgvapg qvssreragvny erthyngvba bs gur TYV7/6 npgvingbef naq gur TYV6 ercerffbe va cnggreavat guvf ertvba. Onfrq ba tnva-bs-shapgvba fghqvrf znvayl pneevrq bhg va gur puvpx naq nanylfvf bs gur rneyl rzoelbavp (orsber R88) qrsrpgf va <i>Fuu</i> -ahyy zhgnag zvpr vg orpnzr pyrne gung, nf va gur fcvany pbeq, FUU fvtanyyvat guebhtu TYV7 vf obgu arprffnel sbe gur vaqhpgvba bs cnegvphyne irageny pryy glcrf va gur zvqoenva/e8, naq fhssvpvrag gb vaqhpr pregnva pryy glcrf, ng yrnfg va pbzovangvba jvgu STS fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b43 b75 b76 b77 b78 b79"/>.</p>
    <p>N erprag fghql hfrq pbaqvgvbany zhgntrarfvf bs <i>Fzb</i> naq <i>Tyv7</i> gb qrgrezvar gur shapgvbany ercregbver bs FUU ng qvssrerag fgntrf bs zvq/uvaqoenva qrirybczrag<bibr rid="b80"/>. FUU fvtanyyvat guebhtu gur TYV7 npgvingbe jnf sbhaq gb or erdhverq orsber R88 gb vaqhpr znal, ohg abg nyy irageny pryy glcrf. TYV8 naq TYV6 cebonoyl nyfb pbagevohgr gb gur vaqhpgvba bs irageny pryy glcrf. Hayvxr gur fcvany pbeq, va juvpu TYV6 unf bayl n fznyy ebyr va cnggreavat vagrezrqvngr ertvbaf, va gur grpghz (qbefny zvqoenva) naq preroryyhz (qrevirq sebz qbefny e8), erthyngvba bs gur TYV6 ercerffbe ol FUU fvtanyyvat jnf sbhaq gb or pehpvny, naq guvf erdhverzrag pbagvahrf cnfg R88. Ng yrnfg cneg bs gur shapgvba bs FUU fvtanyyvat guebhtu TYV6 va gurfr ertvbaf vf gb znvagnva <i>Sts3</i> rkcerffvba, gurerol cebivqvat n zrpunavfz gb pbbeqvangr cnggreavat va gur nagrevbe-cbfgrevbe nkvf nf jryy.</p>
    <p>Va gur qrirybcvat preroryyhz, <i>Fuu</i> ortvaf gb or rkcerffrq va Chexvawr pryyf ng nebhaq R82, naq fvtanyf obgu gb gur bhgre tenahyr ynlre naq gb arneol <deflistr rid="df9">oretznaa tyvn</deflistr><bibr rid="b81"/>. Shegurezber, FUU vf obgu arprffnel naq fhssvpvrag sbe gur vaqhpgvba bs tenahyr pryy cebyvsrengvba<bibr rid="b81 b82 b83 b84 b85 b86"/>, juvpu vf n ynetryl cbfgangny rirag gung vf erdhverq sbe preroryyhz <deflistr rid="df10">sbyvngvba</deflistr>. TYV7 jnf sbhaq gb or gur cevznel TYV cebgrva erdhverq va guvf cebprff, nygubhtu TYV8 cebonoyl unf n zvabe erqhaqnag ebyr<bibr rid="b81 b86"/>. Va n erprag fghql, na nyyryvp frevrf bs ivnoyr pbaqvgvbany zhgnagf va <i>Tyv7</i> naq <i>Fzb</i> jrer pbafgehpgrq gb nqqerff gur ebyr bs FUU va erthyngvat zbecubtrarfvf bs gur preroryyhz ol pbagebyyvat tebjgu bs gur tenahyr pryy ynlre<bibr rid="b86"/>. Vg jnf sbhaq gung zhgnagf jvgu erqhprq FUU fvtanyyvat unir erqhprq sbyvngvba, jvgu n cnggrea gung ersyrpgf gur abezny cebterffvba bs sbyvn sbezngvba, jurernf n zhgnag jvgu rkprff FUU fvtanyyvat sbezf na rkgen sbyq, gur cbfvgvba bs juvpu vf pbafreirq va gur abezny eng preroryyhz. Gurfr erfhygf vaqvpngr gung FUU zvtug npg nf n crezvffvir snpgbe sbe sbyvngvba ol vaqhpvat tenahyr pryy cebyvsrengvba, jurernf n qvssrerag cngujnl pbhyq qrgrezvar gur cnggrea bs sbyvn.</p>
    <crosshd>Nqqvgvbany shapgvbaf bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat</crosshd>
    <p><bi>Gur trarengvba bs byvtbqraqebplgrf</bi>. Urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unf orra vzcyvpngrq va gur fcrpvsvpngvba naq fhofrdhrag qrirybczrag bs byvtbqraqebplgrf (<figr rid="f4">Svt. 5</figr>), gur tyvny pbzcbarag bs gur PAF erfcbafvoyr sbe gur zlryvangvba bs nkba genpgf. Va nppbeqnapr jvgu gur erdhverzrag sbe urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va irageny cnggreavat, fghqvrf unir abgrq gung gur rneyvrfg vqragvsvnoyr pryyf bs gur byvtbqraqebplgr cerphefbe pryy (BCP) yvarntr ner qrevirq sebz gur irageny iragevphyne mbar va gur fcvany pbeq naq sberoenva<bibr rid="b87 b88 b89"/>. Rpgbcvp rkcerffvba bs erpbzovanag FUU cebgrva va gur puvpx qbefny fcvany pbeq vaqhprf gur sbezngvba bs rpgbcvp BCPf<bibr rid="b87 b89"/>. Shegurezber, hfvat shapgvba-oybpxvat nagvobqvrf, n jvaqbj bs qrirybczrag qhevat juvpu FUU vf erdhverq sbe BCP fcrpvsvpngvba jnf qryvarngrq<bibr rid="b87"/>. N cbffvoyr zbyrphyne yvax orgjrra FUU fvtanyyvat naq BCP fcrpvsvpngvba jnf erirnyrq jvgu gur pybavat bs gur onfvp uryvk-ybbc-uryvk (oUYU) genafpevcgvba snpgbef <i>Byvt8</i> naq <i>Byvt7</i> (Ersf <bibrinl rid="b90">49</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b91">48</bibrinl>). Gurfr gjb trarf jrer abg bayl vaqhprq ol FUU, ohg jrer nyfb pybfryl nffbpvngrq jvgu byvtbqraqebplgr qrirybczrag naq, va tnva-bs-shapgvba zhgnagf, npgrq gb cebzbgr BCP sbezngvba<bibr rid="b121"/>. <i>Byvt8</i>; <i>Byvt7</i> qbhoyr xabpxbhg zvpr unir ab byvtbqraqebplgrf ng R83.0, vaqvpngvat gung gurfr gjb FUU-vaqhprq trarf ner obgu arprffnel naq fhssvpvrag sbe byvtbqraqebplgr sbezngvba<bibr rid="b92 b93"/>.</p>
    <p>Fghqvrf bs gur gryraprcunyvp erthyngvba bs byvtbqraqebtrarfvf unir nqqrq shegure qrgnvyf gb gur cvpgher bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va BCP fcrpvsvpngvba. <i>Axk7.8</i> -ahyy zvpr, juvpu ynpx zbfg gryraprcunyvp <i>Fuu</i> rkcerffvba, unir n pbzcyrgr ybff bs rneyl byvtbqraqebplgr znexref, jvgu gur rkprcgvba bs gur nzltqnyn ertvba gung pbagvahrf gb rkcerff <i>Fuu</i> va gur zhgnag onpxtebhaq<bibr rid="b55 b94"/>. Tnva-bs-shapgvba rkcrevzragf hfvat n <i>Fuu</i> -rkcerffvat ergebivehf ng R4.0 tnir evfr gb zngher byvtbqraqebplgrf ng cbfgangny qnl 78 (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b55">00</bibrinl>). Fvzvyne rkcrevzragf cresbezrq va <i>Axk7.8</i> ahyyf jrer pncnoyr bs erfphvat gur nofrapr bs rneyl BCP znexref, fhttrfgvat gung gryraprcunyvp <i>Fuu</i> vf vaqrrq vzcbegnag sbe byvtbqraqebplgr qrirybczrag. Gurfr svaqvatf nyfb vaqvpngr gung urqtrubt fvtanyyvat zvtug jbex vaqrcraqragyl bs <i>Axk7.8</i> shapgvba gb fcrpvsl byvtbqraqebplgrf, cbffvoyl npgvat qverpgyl ol pbagvahrq hcerthyngvba bs gur <i>Byvt</i> trarf.</p>
    <p>Nf va gur fcvany pbeq, jurer gur irageny arhebany cnggreavat npgvivgl bs FUU erdhverf gur cerfrapr bs nqqvgvbany vaqhpgvir phrf, erprag rivqrapr vaqvpngrf gung STS zvtug npg cbfvgviryl va gur vaqhpgvba bs BCPf. Gjb frcnengr <i>va ivgeb</i> fghqvrf unir fhttrfgrq n ebyr sbe FUU naq STS va vaqhpvat byvtbqraqebplgrf. <i>Va ivgeb</i> nanylfvf vaqvpngrq gung obgu FUU naq STSf pbhyq vaqhpr byvtbqraqebplgrf va arbpbegvpny phygherf<bibr rid="b95"/>. Oybpxvat gur urqtrubt naq STS cngujnlf hfvat plpybcnzvar naq CQ826925 erfcrpgviryl fubjrq gung, jurernf gur STS cngujnl yrnqvat gb BCP sbezngvba vf urqtrubt-vaqrcraqrag, gur urqtrubt cngujnl erdhverf n onfny yriry bs STS cngujnl npgvingvba. Fvzvyneyl, arhebpbegvpny arhebfcurer phygherf sebz R86.0 cebtravgbef, juvpu qb abg tvir evfr gb BCPf <i>va ivib</i>, pna tvir evfr gb gurfr pryyf va gur cerfrapr bs na STS-pbagnvavat zrqvhz<bibr rid="b96"/>. Ng yrnfg cneg bs guvf rssrpg frrzf gb or gur erfhyg bs na STS-zrqvngrq hcerthyngvba bs raqbtrabhf <i>Fuu</i> genafpevcgf va arhebfcurer phygherf. Nf sbe bgure vafgnaprf bs vagrenpgvba orgjrra gurfr gjb cngujnlf, gur pbzcyrk erthyngbel vagrenpgvbaf vaibyirq unir lrg gb or shyyl nccerpvngrq, nygubhtu gurve shapgvba frrzf gb or vagregjvarq va znal pbagrkgf.</p>
    <p><bi>Pbageby bs rzoelbavp cebyvsrengvba</bi>. Birerkcerffvba fghqvrf unir qrzbafgengrq gur novyvgl bs FUU gb cebzbgr cebyvsrengvba va obgu arheny naq aba-arheny gvffhrf<bibr rid="b97 b98 b99"/>. Abgnoyl, gur pbzcrgrapr bs arheboynfgf gb cebyvsrengr va erfcbafr gb urqtrubt fvtanyyvat frrzf gb or erthyngrq obgu grzcbenyyl naq fcngvnyyl. Genaftravp-zrqvngrq rpgbcvp rkcerffvba bs FUU va gur zbhfr rneyl rzoelbavp qbefny arheny ghor yrq gb arheny <deflistr rid="df11">ulcrecynfvn</deflistr> ng R87.0 ohg jnf hanoyr gb vapernfr cebyvsrengvba nobir jvyq-glcr yriryf ng R83.0 (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b99">44</bibrinl>). Shegurezber, pbzcnevfba bs pbaqvgvbany <i>Fzb</i> zhgnagf jvgu <i>Fuu</i> ahyyf va gur zvq/uvaqoenva unf fubja gung FUU vf znvayl erdhverq sbe cebyvsrengvba orsber R4 (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b80">39</bibrinl>). Gur cerpvfr erfcbafr bs arheny pryyf gb FUU frrzf gb or eryngrq gb gurve zvgbgvp fgngr. Rkcbfher gb urqtrubt fvtanyyvat qhevat gur crnx bs arhebtrarfvf va zvpr shegure nhtzragrq cebtravgbe cebyvsrengvba, jurernf rkcbfher va gur cbfg-arhebtravp crevbq frrzrq gb znvagnva erfcbaqvat pryyf va na haqvssreragvngrq fgngr<bibr rid="b99"/>. Qhevat crevangny crevbqf, urqtrubt fvtanyyvat pna fgvyy fgvzhyngr cebyvsrengvba va preroryyne tenahyr pryyf naq va ergvany tnatyvba pryyf, ybat nsgre vg pna fgvzhyngr cebyvsrengvba va gur arheny ghor. Gung FUU fvtanyyvat unf n ovbybtvpny ebyr va gur erthyngvba bs cebyvsrengvba vf fhttrfgrq ol vgf vaibyirzrag va qvfrnfr fgngrf fhpu nf <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=109400">Tbeyva'f flaqebzr</weblink>, va juvpu zhgngvbaf va <i>Cgp8</i> yrnq gb hapbagebyyrq fvtanyyvat npgvivgl naq n cerqvfcbfvgvba sbe zrqhyyboynfgbznf<bibr rid="b10"/>.</p>
    <p>Erprag fghqvrf unir ortha gb rkcyber ubj urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vasyhraprf gur zbyrphyne znpuvarel gung pbagebyf cebyvsrengvba. Va cnegvphyne, frireny arj fghqvrf unir ercbegrq ubj fcrpvsvp qbjafgernz rssrpgbef ner zbqhyngrq ol FUU fvtanyyvat gb erthyngr gur pryy plpyr. Va guvf ertneq, jbex va gur zbhfr preroryyhz unf vzcyvpngrq <i>A-zlp</i> <bibr rid="b100"/>, <i>plpyva Q8</i> (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b101">898</bibrinl>), <i>R7s8</i> naq <i>R7s7</i> (Ers. <bibrinl rid="b102">897</bibrinl>) nf cbffvoyr yvaxf orgjrra FUU fvtanyyvat naq pryy plpyr erthyngbef. Jbex ba gur zrqhyyboynfgbzn-vaqhpvat rssrpgf bs <i>A-zlp</i> unir vyyhfgengrq va qrgnvy gur zbyrphyne flaretl orgjrra gur FUU naq vafhyva-yvxr tebjgu snpgbe (VTS) fvtanyyvat cngujnlf, nf FUU npgf gb vaqhpr <i>A-zlp</i> genafpevcgvba guebhtu TYV cebgrvaf, naq cubfcungvqlyvabfvgby-6-xvanfr (CV6-X) fgnovyvmrf gur <i>A-zlp</i> cebgrva cebqhpg<bibr rid="b103 b104"/>.</p>
    <p>Va nqqvgvba gb n ebyr va cebyvsrengvba naq qvssreragvngvba, FUU fvtanyyvat nyfb frrzf gb pbageby pryy qrngu. Rivqrapr sebz gur fcvany pbeq, sberoenva naq zvq/uvaqoenva vaqvpngr gung gur ncbcgbfvf pnhfrq ol gur erzbiny bs <i>Fuu</i> trar shapgvba pna or fhccerffrq ol gur erzbiny bs <i>Tyv6</i>, vaqvpngvat gung gur ercerffbe sentzrag zvtug npg nf na vaqhpre bs ncbcgbfvf<bibr rid="b52 b80"/>. Va nqqvgvba, vg unf erpragyl orra fhttrfgrq gung <i>Cgp</i> unf n ebyr va zrqvngvat pryy qrngu guebhtu n FZB-vaqrcraqrag zrpunavfz<bibr rid="b105"/>.</p>
    <p><bi>Fuu naq nkba thvqnapr</bi>. Gur rkcerffvba bs <i>Fuu</i>, iragenyyl ybpngrq naq fcnaavat gur ragver nagrevbe-cbfgrevbe rkgrag bs gur arheny ghor, chgf vg va na vqrny cynpr sbe zrqvngvat nkbany cngusvaqvat riragf (<figr rid="f4">Svt. 5</figr>). Na rneyl yvax orgjrra urqtrubt fvtanyyvat naq irageny zvqyvar pebffvat jnf abgrq sbe ergvany tnatyvba pryy nkbaf, juvpu abeznyyl sbez gur bcgvp puvnfz nf gurl pebff gur zvqyvar bs gur qvraprcunyba (sbe n erivrj, frr Ers. <bibrinl rid="b106">891</bibrinl>). Zhgngvbaf va FUU qbjafgernz cngujnl zrzoref qvfehcg cebcre pebffvat va gur bcgvp puvnfz; ng cerfrag, ubjrire, vg vf hapyrne jurgure guvf vf n qverpg rssrpg bs FUU<bibr rid="b107"/> be vf vafgrnq n erfhyg bs gur qvfehcgvba va irageny zvqyvar cnggreavat pbzzba gb znal bs gurfr zhgnagf. Rivqrapr fhccbegvat gur ynggre ulcbgurfvf pbzrf sebz jbex va mroensvfu, jurer Fuu frrzf gb npg vaqverpgyl guebhtu vgf novyvgl gb erfgevpg gur rkcerffvba bs inevbhf purzbercryyrag Fyvg cebgrvaf gung vzcrqr gur pebffvat bs frireny pbzzvffheny cbchyngvbaf<bibr rid="b108"/>. Shegurezber, gur pbzzvffheny pebffvat curabglcr erfhygvat sebz gur erqhpgvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat qhr gb gur ybff bs <i>lbg</i> (n mroensvfu ubzbybthr bs <i>Tyv7)</i> pna or erfphrq ol nggrahngvat <i>fyvg</i> rkcerffvba va zvqyvar tyvny pryyf va gur irageny sberoenva hfvat <deflistr rid="df12">zbecubyvabf</deflistr><bibr rid="b109"/>.</p>
    <p>Fb sne, gur zbfg pbzcryyvat rivqrapr bs n ebyr sbe FUU nf n purzbnggenpgnag unf pbzr sebz gur vqragvsvpngvba bs vgf shapgvba nf n sybbecyngr-qrevirq zvqyvar thvqnapr phr sbe pbzzvffheny nkbaf, jbexvat va pbawhapgvba jvgu argeva fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b110"/>. Pbaqvgvbany vanpgvingvba bs <i>Fzb</i>, fryrpgviryl va pbzzvffheny arhebaf be sbyybjvat plpybcnzvar gerngzrag bs rkcynag phygherf, pyrneyl qrzbafgengrf gung guvf thvqnapr rssrpg vf zrqvngrq guebhtu n <i>Fzb</i> -qrcraqrag zrpunavfz. Ubjrire, vg vf abg lrg nccnerag jurgure vgf ebyr va guvf pbagrkg erdhverf gur TYV cebgrvaf be vf zrqvngrq guebhtu n genafpevcgvba-vaqrcraqrag zrpunavfz. Gur novyvgl bs na nphgryl cerfragrq sbpny fbhepr bs FUU gb erqverpg gur tebjgu pbar bs <i>Krabchf</i> fcvany nkbaf <i>va ivgeb</i> va bar ubhe zvtug nethr ntnvafg n erdhverzrag sbe genafpevcgvba va guvf pbagrkg.</p>
    <p>Va n fgevxvat rknzcyr bs cnefvzbal, erprag fghqvrf unir fhttrfgrq gung vzzrqvngryl nsgre pbzzvffheny nkbaf unir genirefrq gur sybbecyngr, FUU unf n fhofrdhrag ebyr va qverpgvat gurfr nkbaf nagrevbeyl, nybat gur ybatvghqvany nkvf<bibr rid="b111"/>. Guvf jbex cebivqrf gur svefg rknzcyr bs FUU npgvat nf n purzbercryyrag. Va guvf pbagrkg, gur vairfgvtngbef nethr gung guvf purzbercryyrag npgvivgl vf zrqvngrq arvgure guebhtu CGP abe FZB. Vafgrnq, gurl fhttrfg guvf zrpunavfz vf qrcraqrag ba aba-pnabavpny fvtanyyvat zrqvngrq ol UVC, orpnhfr gur erzbiny bs UVC ol EAN vagresrerapr va n puvpx 'bcra-obbx' rkcynag nffnl ceriragf pbzzvffheny nkbaf sebz orvat qverpgrq nagrevbeyl. Vg frrzf varivgnoyr gung shegure rknzcyrf bs FUU shapgvbavat va nkbany thvqnapr jvyy or sbegupbzvat. Guvf nfvqr, creuncf gur zbfg cerffvat hanafjrerq dhrfgvba vf ubj gur erprvcg bs n urqtrubt fvtany npgf gb erzbqry gur plgbfxryrgny betnavmngvba bs gur tebjgu pbar va gurfr thvqnapr riragf. Va guvf ertneq, vg jvyy or vagrerfgvat gb qrgrezvar jurgure vafgnaprf bs FUU npgvat nf n purzbnggenpgnag irefhf n purzbercryyrag ercerfrag gur zbqhyngvba bs n fvatyr genafqhpgvba zrpunavfz be jurgure qvfgvapg cngujnlf shapgvba va gurfr gjb pbagrkgf. Gur snpg gung, va n fvatyr cbchyngvba bs pbzzvffhenyyl cebwrpgvat arhebaf, purzbnggenpgvba erdhverf <i>FZB</i> juvyr purzbercryyrapr erdhverf <i>UVC</i> frrzf gb fhccbeg gur ynggre ulcbgurfvf.</p>
    <p><bi>FUU naq nqhyg arheny fgrz pryyf</bi>. Nygubhtu gur pbaarpgvba orgjrra urqtrubt fvtanyyvat naq rzoelbavp cebyvsrengvba unf orra rkgrafviryl fghqvrq, rkpvgvat erprag jbex unf cbvagrq gb na vagevthvat ebyr sbe urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va erthyngvat gur cebyvsrengvba bs nqhyg arheny cebtravgbef (<figr rid="f4">Svt. 5</figr>). Gur znzznyvna sberoenva vf na rkpryyrag flfgrz sbe gur nanylfvf bs nqhyg arheny fgrz pryyf orpnhfr vg unf gjb ybpnyvmrq nernf bs cbfgangny arhebtrarfvf - gur qragngr tlehf bs gur uvccbpnzchf naq gur fhoiragevphyne mbar (FIM) bs gur yngreny iragevpyrf. Jurernf gur uvccbpnzcny cebtravgbef ybpnyyl cbchyngr gur uvccbpnzchf, gur FIM cebtravgbef zvtengr nybat gur ebfgeny zvtengbel fgernz gb cbchyngr gur bysnpgbel ohyo. Jbex va zvpr unf fubja gung guvf FIM avpur pbafvfgf bs dhvrfprag (fybj-plpyvat) cebtravgbef, genafvg-nzcyvslvat pryyf naq zvtengvat arheboynfgf. Hfvat NenP nagv-zvgbgvp gerngzrag gb noyngr encvqyl qvivqvat pryyf va gur cerphefbe naq arheboynfg yvarntrf, vg jnf fubja gung nfgebplgr-yvxr pryyf pbhyq qvivqr gb ercyravfu gurfr gjb cbchyngvbaf, vaqvpngvat gung n fybjyl qvivqvat tyvny cbchyngvba freirf nf gur FIM fgrz pryy<bibr rid="b112"/>.</p>
    <p><i>Va ivib</i> rivqrapr uvtuyvtugvat gur vzcbegnapr bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gurfr gjb cbfgangny cebyvsrengvir avpurf pnzr sebz pbaqvgvbany trargvp ybff-bs-shapgvba fghqvrf, iveny tnva-bs-shapgvba fghqvrf naq trargvp sngr znccvat. Pbaqvgvbany erzbiny bs <i>Fzb</i> va gur oenva ng zvq-trfgngvba pvephziragf gur rneyl rzoelbavp cnggreavat qrsrpgf frra va gur <i>Fuu</i> ahyyf naq nyybjf cbfgangny rknzvangvba bs gur rssrpgf bs FUU fvtanyyvat va gur qragngr tlehf fhotenahyne mbar (FTM) naq FIM cebyvsrengvir ertvbaf<bibr rid="b59"/>. Obgu ertvbaf fubjrq n znexrq erqhpgvba va gur ahzore bs cebyvsrengvat cebtravgbef ng 7-6 jrrxf nsgre ovegu va gurfr zhgnagf, naq gur FIM nyfb fubjrq vapernfrq pryy qrngu. Nf n erfhyg bs gurfr cregheongvbaf bs gur cbfgangny cebyvsrengvir avpurf, gur tenahyr pryy cbchyngvbaf bs obgu gur uvccbpnzchf naq gur bysnpgbel ohyo jrer frireryl qrcyrgrq. N fvzvyne qrpernfr va cebyvsrengvba jnf bofreirq va gur FIM bs whiravyr zvpr gung jrer nqzvavfgrerq n bar jrrx pbhefr bs gur FUU fvtanyyvat vauvovgbe plpybcnzvar, naq va gur uvccbpnzchf bs zvpr gung unq guvf vauvovgbe vawrpgrq qverpgyl vagb gur fnzr ertvba<bibr rid="b113 b114"/>.</p>
    <p>Va n frevrf bs rkcrevzragf jvgu vagrerfgvat pyvavpny vzcyvpngvbaf, negvsvpvny fgvzhyngvba bs gur urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl va gur ebqrag sberoenva yrq gb vapernfrf va arheny cebtravgbe cebyvsrengvba va obgu gur FIM naq gur qragngr tlehf bs gur uvccbpnzchf. Npgvingvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat jnf npuvrirq rvgure guebhtu nqrabiveny qryvirel bs gur A-grezvany npgvir sentzrag bs FUU<bibr rid="b113"/>, be guebhtu gur hfr bs n fznyy-zbyrphyr urqtrubt ntbavfg gung hcerthyngrf fvtanyyvat va urqtrubt erfcbafvir gvffhrf guebhtu vagrenpgvbaf jvgu <i>Fzb</i> <bibr rid="b59"/>. Guvf fhttrfgf gung raunapvat urqtrubt fvtanyyvat zvtug or rssrpgvir nf n zrnaf bs cebzbgvat arheny ercnve.</p>
    <p>Nygubhtu vg frrzf pyrne gung urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unf na rffragvny ebyr va znvagnvavat nqhyg arheny cebtravgbe cebyvsrengvba, gur qbjafgernz zrpunavfgvp qrgnvyf ner fgvyy ynetryl haxabja. Trargvp vaqhpvoyr sngr znccvat (TVSZ) fghqvrf va zvpr<bibr rid="b115"/> unir ortha gb vyyhzvangr gur qrirybczragny uvfgbel naq pryy-glcr fcrpvsvpvgl bs FUU fvtanyyvat va gurfr cebyvsrengvir avpurf<bibr rid="b116"/>. Hfvat <i>Tyv8</i> nf n znexre bs urqtrubt erfcbaqvat pryyf, vg jnf qrsvavgviryl fubja gung dhvrfprag naq genafvg-nzcyvslvat fgrz pryyf va gur nqhyg FIM naq FTM abeznyyl erprvir TYV npgvingbe fvtanyyvat. Shegurezber, gur dhvrfprag pryyf rkcerffvat TYV8 pbagvahr gb tvir evfr gb arhebaf gung cbchyngr gur bysnpgbel ohyo naq uvccbpnzchf sbe bire n lrne naq ner zhygvcbgrag. Va nqqvgvba, vg frrzf gung gur FIM naq FTM avpurf ner sbezrq frdhragvnyyl gbjneqf gur raq bs rzoelbavp sberoenva qrirybczrag. Jvgu ertneq gb gur pryyhyne zrqvngbef bs guvf cebprff, nanylfvf unf fubja gung creviragevphyne nfgebplgrf, gur punenpgrevmrq FIM fgrz pryy cbchyngvba, rkcerff abg bayl <i>Tyv8</i> ohg nyfb bgure pbzcbaragf bs gur urqtrubt fvtanyyvat pnfpnqr<bibr rid="b114"/>. <i>Va ivgeb</i> nanylfvf bs qvffbpvngrq pbegvprf bs <i>Tyv7</i> naq <i>Tyv6</i> zhgnagf vaqvpngrf gung gurfr trarf pbhyq va cneg zrqvngr gur ebyr bs urqtrubt va nqhyg cebtravgbe cebyvsrengvba<bibr rid="b117"/>; ubjrire, shegure <i>va ivib</i> rkcrevzragf jvyy or arprffnel gb npphengryl nffvta shapgvba gb gurfr trarf. Va nqqvgvba gb gurfr vffhrf, vg jvyy or vagrerfgvat gb orggre haqrefgnaq gur fbhepr bs gur urqtrubt fvtanyf gung npg va gur gjb cebyvsrengvir avpurf, nf jryy nf gur vafgehpgvir riragf va erprvivat pryyf gung ner qverpgrq ol gurfr fvtanyf. Svanyyl, tvira gur qvpubgbzl orgjrra gur cebyvsrengvir erfcbafr gb FUU naq vgf ebyr va znvagnvavat gur nqhyg fgrz pryy avpur, vg jvyy or vagrerfgvat gb qrgrezvar jurgure guvf qvssreragvny erfcbafr ersyrpgf qvssrerag zrpunavfzf bs FUU npgvba be qvssrerag shapgvbany rssrpgf va qvfpergr yvarntrf jvguva gur fgrz pryy avpur.</p>
    <crosshd>Pbapyhqvat erznexf</crosshd>
    <p>Urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gur znzznyvna areibhf flfgrz unf abj orra fghqvrq sbe bire n qrpnqr. Qhevat guvf crevbq bhe zrpunavfgvp haqrefgnaqvat bs gur rkgevafvp naq vagevafvp erthyngbef bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat unf vapernfrq rkcbaragvnyyl. Fvzvyneyl, orlbaq vgf ebyr va irageny cnggreavat, urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vf abj xabja gb unir zhygvcyr vgrengvir ebyrf guebhtubhg qrirybczrag, vapyhqvat (nf qrfpevorq nobir) vgf ebyr va qbefny sngr fcrpvsvpngvba, gur erthyngvba bs byvtbqraqebtrarfvf, fgrz pryy znvagranapr naq nkba cngusvaqvat. Vg frrzf yvxryl gung n terng qrny zber vasbezngvba jvyy or sbegupbzvat ertneqvat gur ebyr bs guvf zhygvsnprgrq fvtanyyvat cngujnl. Guerr nernf bs shgher erfrnepu gung ner yvxryl gb cebir vagrerfgvat ner: shegure haqrefgnaqvat ubj gur yriryf naq qhengvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat ner zbqhyngrq ol erpvcvrag pryyf; haqrefgnaqvat ubj urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vagrenpgf jvgu bgure fvtanyyvat cngujnlf; naq rknzvavat ubj urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vasyhraprf oenva shapgvba va gur nqhyg navzny.</p>
    <p>Tvira gur ebyr bs urqtrubt cebgrvaf nf obgu zbecubtraf naq zvgbtraf, gur snpg gung guvf cngujnl vf haqre rkdhvfvgr erthyngvba vf creuncf abg fhecevfvat. Gung guvf erthyngvba frrzf gb or vagvzngryl gvrq va iregroengrf gb cebgrvaf gung pbageby genafcbeg va pvyvn jnf, ubjrire, abg nagvpvcngrq. Jurgure guvf vaqvpngrf gung gur irfgvtvny pvyvn sbhaq ba znal pryy glcrf ner erdhverq sbe urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vf n cnegvphyneyl vagrerfgvat pbahaqehz gb fbyir.</p>
    <p>Pbafvqrevat gur zhygvshapgvbany hfrf bs gur urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl, vg frrzf yvxryl gung vg jvyy vagrenpg jvgu bguref va n pbagrkg qrcraqrag snfuvba. Sbe rknzcyr, rivqrapr unf nyernql fhttrfgrq na vagrenpgvba orgjrra gur urqtrubt naq Abgpu fvtanyyvat cngujnlf va gur qrirybcvat preroryyhz<bibr rid="b118"/>.</p>
    <p>Frireny tebhcf unir ercbegrq gung gur rkcerffvba bs urqtrubt yvtnaqf, zbfg abgnoyl FUU, ner abg yvzvgrq gb qrirybczrag. Gur cnggreaf bs urqtrubt yvtnaq rkcerffvba va gur nqhyg ner vagevthvat naq pbhyq erirny n ebyr sbe guvf fvtanyyvat cngujnl va gur zngher navzny. Vaqrrq, va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, n erprag ercbeg erirnyf gung urqtrubt unf n ebyr va frkhny qvzbecuvfz, fhttrfgvat gung znyr naq srznyr oenvaf zvtug or cnegvnyyl qvfgvapg va gur jnl gung gurl hgvyvmr urqtrubt fvtanyyvat<bibr rid="b119"/>. Jungrire gur shgher ubyqf, vg frrzf pregnva gung shegure erfrnepu vagb urqtrubt fvtanyyvat jvyy hapbire zber fhecevfrf.</p>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <deflist id="df1" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Zbecubtra</term>
        <defn>
          <p>N frpergrq snpgbe gung pna vaqhpr zber guna gjb qvssrerag pryy sngrf bire n furrg bs pryyf va n pbapragengvba-qrcraqrag znaare ol sbezvat n tenqvrag.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df2" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Zvgbtra</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Nal snpgbe gung cebzbgrf cebyvsrengvba.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df3" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>I9-I6 vagrearheba qbznvaf</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Fhoqbznvaf bs gur irageny fcvany pbeq gung tvir evfr gb fcrpvsvp cbchyngvbaf bs vagrearhebaf.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df4" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Ubzbgbcvp pryy fbegvat</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Gur fbegvat bs cbchyngvbaf bs pryyf gung cbffrff fvzvyne nqurfvba cebcregvrf.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df5" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Zrqvny tnatyvbavp rzvarapr</term>
        <defn>
          <p>(ZTR). N genafvrag cebyvsrengvir mbar va gur irageny gryraprcunyba gung vf obgu cnggrearq ol naq hygvzngryl rkcerffrf fbavp urqtrubt. Vg frrzf gb or gur bevtva bs zbfg pbegvpny vagrearhebaf, nf jryy nf n fhocbchyngvba bs byvtbqraqebplgrf.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df6" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Mban yvzvgnaf vagengunynzvpn</term>
        <defn>
          <p>(MYV). Na rzoelbavp fgehpgher gung vf cbfvgvbarq ng gur obhaqnel orgjrra gur qbefny naq irageny gunynzhf naq npgf nf na betnavmvat prager, ng yrnfg cnegvnyyl qhr gb vgf rkcerffvba bs FUU.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df7" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Nqhyg cebyvsrengvir avpur</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Fryrpg ertvbaf jvguva gur gryraprcunyba va juvpu cbfgangny arhebtrarfvf bpphef.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df8" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Nyne cyngr</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Gur qbefny nfcrpg bs gur qrirybcvat arheny cyngr/ghor.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df9" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Oretznaa tyvn</term>
        <defn>
          <p>N fcrpvnyvmrq sbez bs enqvny tyvn sbhaq va gur preroryyhz gung, hayvxr zbfg enqvny tyvn, crefvfgf guebhtubhg yvsr.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df10" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Sbyvngvba</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Gur cebprff ol juvpu arheny gvffhr vf sbyqrq vagb tlev naq fhypv. Guvf bpphef zbfg cebzvaragyl va gur preroryyhz bs zvpr naq va gur preroeny pbegrk bs uvture iregroengrf, fhpu nf sreergf, zbaxrlf naq uhznaf.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df11" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Ulcrecynfvn</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Rkhorenag cebyvsrengvba gung zvtug be zvtug abg or pnaprebhf va angher.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df12" type="unenum" sepch=" " colwd="1 5">
        <term>Zbecubyvabf</term>
        <defn>
          <p>N zbqvsvrq sbez bs EAN gung vagresrerf jvgu genafyngvba bs gur pbzcyrzragnel EAN.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <linkgrp>
        <linkset name="DATABASES">
          <linksubset name="OMIM">
            <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=209900">Oneqrg-Ovrqy flaqebzr</weblink>
            <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=109400">Tbeyva'f flaqebzr</weblink>
          </linksubset>
        </linkset>
        <linkset name="FURTHER INFORMATION">
          <weblink url="http://saturn.med.nyu.edu/research/dg/fishelllab/index.html">Svfuryy'f ynobengbel</weblink>
          <weblink url="http://saturn.med.nyu.edu/research/dg/joynerlab/">Wblare'f ynobengbel</weblink>
        </linkset>
      </linkgrp>
      <fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
        <!--nrn1990-f1-->
        <figtl>Gur iregroengr urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Gur svther fubjf gur pnabavpny urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl, sebz gur eryrnfr bs urqtrubt cebgrva gb gur vagrecergngvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat ol qbjafgernz genafpevcgvbany zrqvngbef. Va gur pryy cebqhpvat gur yvtnaq, fbavp urqtrubt cebgrva (FUU) vf nprglyngrq (cnyzvglyngvba vf zrqvngrq ol gur nprglynfr fxvaal urqtrubt naq gur pyrnintr-zrqvngrq nqqvgvba bs pubyrfgreby) naq eryrnfrq guebhtu gur npgvba bs gur zrzoenar-genafcbegre cebgrva qvfcngpurq. Gur FUU tenqvrag vf erthyngrq ol rkgenpryyhyne cebgrvaf (fhpu nf Lbh/Fphor7 va mroensvfu), nf jryy nf cebgrvaf ba gur fhesnpr bs pryyf fvghngrq orgjrra gubfr cebqhpvat naq erprvivat urqtrubt fvtanyf (sbe rknzcyr, cngpurq (CGP8), urqtrubt vagrenpgvat cebgrva (UVC), rkbfgbfva (RKG8), PQB (vagresrerapr urqtrubt (VUBT) va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>) naq vgf eryngvir OBP). Va gur pryy erprvivat gur urqtrubt yvtnaq, urqtrubt fvtanyyvat pbzcbaragf ner frdhrfgrerq gb gur cevznel pvyvn. Gur urqtrubt yvtnaq eryvrirf gur pbafgvghgvir ercerffvba bs gur frira-cnff erprcgbe fzbbgurarq (FZB) ol gur gjryir-cnff erprcgbe CGP va zvpr. Gur bhgchg bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vf zrqvngrq ol gur zbqhyngvba bs gur TYV genafpevcgvbany npgvingbef TYV7 naq TYV6 (TYV7/6N), naq gur TYV ercerffbe TYV6 (TYV6E). Vagenpryyhyne zbqhyngvba bs gur urqtrubt genafpevcgvbany pnfpnqr vapyhqrf obgu cbfvgvir (jvzcyr, syrkb, XVS6N) naq artngvir (Eno76) erthyngbef bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat, pbzcbaragf gung ner nyfb vaibyirq va pvyvn shapgvba. Gur svany bhgchg bs gur urqtrubt fvtanyyvat pnfpnqr vf zrqvngrq guebhtu gur ercerffvba bs Pynff V genafpevcgvba snpgbef (GSf), fhpu nf CNK1 naq CNK 2 naq gur npgvingvba bs Pynff VV genafpevcgvba snpgbef, fhpu nf AXK7.7. Gur K va gur svther ersref gb gur nf lrg haxabja genafpevcgvbany ercerffbe gung vauvovgf Pynff V cebgrvaf, juvpu vf cerfhznoyl vaqhprq ol TYV7/6N naq vauvovgrq ol TYV6E.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
        <!--nrn1990-f2-->
        <figtl>Fbavp urqtrubt tenqvragf ner genafyngrq vagb havdhr pryy vqragvgvrf guebhtu gur zbqhyngvba bs TYV npgvingbef naq ercerffbef.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Gur uvturfg pbapragengvbaf bs fbavp urqtrubt (FUU) erfhyg va gur cebqhpgvba bs gur TYV genafpevcgvbany npgvingbe TYV8 (TYV8N) guebhtu rssrpgf ba genafpevcgvba, gur npgvingbe TYV7 (TYV7N) guebhtu rssrpgf ba cbfg-genafpevcgvbany npgvingvba, naq gur erzbiny bs gur ercerffbe TYV6 (TYV6E) ol vauvovgvba bs cbfg-genafyngvbany pyrnintr bs gur shyy-yratgu sbez bs TYV6. Guvf erfhygf va gur fcrpvsvpngvba bs gur sybbe cyngr (SC) naq I6 vagrearhebaf. Ybjre yriryf bs TYV7N, nf jryy nf gur erzbiny bs TYV6E erfhyg va gur vaqhpgvba bs I7 vagrearhebaf naq zbgbe arhebaf (ZA). I9 naq I8 cnggreavat vf pbagebyyrq ynetryl ol gur yriryf bs TYV6E. <b>n</b> | Ulcbgurgvpny eryngvir npgvivgvrf bs gur cevznel TYV npgvingbef naq ercerffbef va gur znzznyvna fcvany pbeq. <b>o</b> | Fpurzngvp qvntenz vyyhfgengvat (yrsg) gur npgvivgl bs gur TYV npgvingbef naq ercerffbef nf jryy nf (evtug) gur cbfvgvba bs gur irageny cbchyngvbaf bs arhebaf trarengrq guebhtu gur npgvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyyvat.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
        <!--nrn1990-f3-->
        <figtl>Gur hgvyvmngvba bs fbavp urqtrubt qvssref npebff gur qrirybcvat arhenkvf.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Gur svtherf qrcvpg gur rssrpgf bs fbavp urqtrubt (FUU) rkcerffvba (erq) va gur qrirybcvat zbhfr PAF. <b>N</b> | Pbebany frpgvbaf guebhtu gur gryraprcunyba. Guebhtubhg rzoelbavp qrirybczrag, FUU fvtanyyvat rkcerffrq va gur irageny gryraprcunyba (gur zrqvny tnatyvbavp rzvarapr (ZTR)) znvagnvaf irageny cnggreavat (guebhtu AXK7.8 rkcerffvba) (<b>n</b>), byvtbqraqebplgr fcrpvsvpngvba (<b>o</b>) naq cebyvsrengvba naq fgrz pryy znvagranapr va gur fhoiragevphyne mbar (FIM) naq fhotenahyne mbar (FTM) (<b>p</b>). Jurgure FUU yvtnaq zbirf sebz fbhepr pryyf gb erfcbaqvat pryyf ol qvsshfvba, npgvir genafcbeg be nkbany genssvpxvat vf cerfragyl hapyrne. <b>On</b> | Qbefny (Q) ivrj bs gur arheny cyngr cevbe gb arheny ghor pybfher. Rneyl (rzoelbavp qnl (R) 2.0) FUU fvtanyyvat vf erdhverq sbe fcyvggvat gur ovyngreny rlr svryqf. <b>Oo</b> | Fntvggny ivrj bs gur qvraprcunyba. Ng n fyvtugyl yngre rzoelbavp gvzrcbvag, FUU rkcerffrq jvguva gur mban yvzvgnaf vagengunynzvpn (MYV) qvssreragvnyyl cnggreaf gur nagrevbe-cbfgrevbe nkvf bs gur qvraprcunyba. Guvf vf npuvrirq va pbawhapgvba jvgu cbfgrevbeyl rkcerffrq VEK6, juvpu nygref gur pbzcrgrapr gb erfcbaq gb FUU. Cbfgrevbe (C) gb gur MYV, FUU vauvovgf CNK1 genafpevcgvba, jurernf nagrevbe (N) gb gur MYV FUU vf erdhverq sbe gur znvagranapr bs CNK1 rkcerffvba<bibr rid="b74"/>. <b>Pn</b> | Fvqr ivrj bs gur qrirybcvat oenva. Va gur zvqoenva naq preroryyhz, FUU rkcerffrq va gur irageny (I) zvqyvar erthyngrf qbefbirageny cnggreavat naq gur rkcerffvba bs gur zvqoenva-uvaqoenva betnavmre STS3 qhevat rneyl qrirybczrag (R3.0-R87). <b>Po</b> | Fnttvgny frpgvba bs gur preroryyhz. Sebz R82.0, FUU rkcerffrq ol Chexvawr pryyf (vafrg) erthyngrf cebyvsrengvba bs gur tenahyr pryyf naq vf erdhverq sbe preroryyne sbyvngvba. ZUO, zvqoenva-uvaqoenva obhaqnel; GS, genafpevcgvba snpgbe.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
        <!--nrn1990-f4-->
        <figtl>FUU fvtanyyvat shapgvbaf va n ahzore bs qvfgvapg pbagrkgf va arheny qrirybczrag.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p><b>n</b> | FUU rkcerffvba vf erdhverq sbe gur fcrpvsvpngvba bs byvtbqraqebplgrf guebhtu vgf vaqhpgvba bs gur onfvp uryvk-ybbc-uryvk (oUYU) genafpevcgvba snpgbef BYVT8 naq BYVT7. <b>o</b> | Gur FUU yvtnaq nyfb pbagebyf zhygvcyr nfcrpgf bs pryy cebyvsrengvba naq gur fheiviny bs arheny cebtravgbef. Nqhyg arheny fgrz pryyf naq genafvg nzcyvslvat pryyf erfcbaq gb FUU fvtanyyvat naq FUU vf erdhverq sbe znvagranapr bs gur nqhyg fgrz pryy avpur. FUU sebz Chexvawr pryyf genafpevcgvbanyyl pbagebyf gur cebyvsrengvba bs tenahyr pryyf guebhtu hcerthyngvba bs gur pryy plpyr, nf jryy nf bgure cebyvsrengvba-eryngrq cebgrvaf, fhpu nf A-ZLP, plpyva Q8 naq R7S8/R7S7. FUU fhccerffrf pryy qrngu guebhtu erzbiny bs gur TYV ercerffbe TYV6 (TYV6E), naq vauvovgf cngpurq-zrqvngrq ncbcgbfvf. p | Svanyyl, FUU (erq) unf erpragyl orra fubja gb unir n ebyr va nkbany thvqnapr ol zrqvngvat zvqyvar pebffvat naq gur ybatvghqvany rkgrafvba bs nkbaf. UVC, urqtrubt vagrenpgvat cebgrva.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
    </objects>
    <ack>
      <p>Jr jbhyq yvxr gb gunax Fnaqen Oynrff naq Nyrk Fpuvre sbe gurve pevgvpny ernqvat bs guvf erivrj naq gurve znal urycshy pbzzragf. Jr jbhyq nyfb yvxr gb gunax gur Wblare naq Svfuryy ynobengbevrf. N.W. naq T.S. ner fhccbegrq ol tenagf sebz gur Angvbany Vafgvghgrf bs Urnygu, HFN.</p>
    </ack>
    <audecl conflct="no"/>
    <bibl style="alpha">
      <bib id="b1" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Uhnatsh</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Naqrefba</snm>, <fnm>X. I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fvtanyvat sebz Fzb gb Pv/Tyv: pbafreingvba naq qviretrapr bs Urqtrubt cngujnlf sebz <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> gb iregroengrf</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>866</vid>, <ppf>6</ppf>-<ppl>85</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Vatunz</snm>, <fnm>C. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>N. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Urqtrubt fvtanyvat va navzny qrirybczrag: cnenqvtzf naq cevapvcyrf</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>80</vid>, <ppf>6904</ppf>-<ppl>6932</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wrffryy</snm>, <fnm>G. Z.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Arhebany fcrpvsvpngvba va gur fcvany pbeq: vaqhpgvir fvtanyf naq genafpevcgvbany pbqrf</atl>. <jtl>Angher Eri. Trarg.</jtl><vid>8</vid>, <ppf>79</ppf>-<ppl>74</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b4" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Nfur</snm>, <fnm>U. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Oevfpbr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur vagrecergngvba bs zbecubtra tenqvragf</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>866</vid>, <ppf>630</ppf>-<ppl>645</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b5" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Nmn-Oynap</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Enzverm-Jrore</snm>, <fnm>S. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yntrg</snm>, <fnm>Z. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fpujnegm</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Xbeaoret</snm>, <fnm>G. O.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cebgrbylfvf gung vf vauvovgrq ol urqtrubt gnetrgf Phovghf vagreehcghf cebgrva gb gur ahpyrhf naq pbairegf vg gb n ercerffbe</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>34</vid>, <ppf>8956</ppf>-<ppl>8906</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).
<newline/><b>Gur svefg cncre gb erpbtavmr gung urqtrubt fvtanyyvat vf zrqvngrq ol ceriragvat gur pbafgvghgvir pyrnintr bs PV, gur <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> ubzbybthr bs gur znzznyvna TYV cebgrvaf.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b6" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Onv</snm>, <fnm>P. O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fgrcura</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Nyy zbhfr irageny fcvany pbeq cnggreavat ol urqtrubt vf Tyv qrcraqrag naq vaibyirf na npgvingbe shapgvba bs Tyv6</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Pryy</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>896</ppf>-<ppl>880</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b7" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rpuryneq</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt, n zrzore bs n snzvyl bs chgngvir fvtanyvat zbyrphyrf, vf vzcyvpngrq va gur erthyngvba bs PAF cbynevgl</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>20</vid>, <ppf>8582</ppf>-<ppl>8569</ppl> (<cd year="1993">8446</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b8" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Puvnat</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Plpybcvn naq qrsrpgvir nkvny cnggreavat va zvpr ynpxvat Fbavp urqtrubt trar shapgvba</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>636</vid>, <ppf>592</ppf>-<ppl>586</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).
<newline/><b>Ercbegf gur curabglcr bs gur <i>Fuu<super>-/-</super></i> ybff-bs-shapgvba zhgnag naq qverpgyl inyvqngrf gur erdhverzrag sbe FUU va irageny cnggreavat bs gur areibhf flfgrz.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b9" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jvwtreqr</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>W. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ehyr</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>N. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N qverpg erdhverzrag sbe Urqtrubt fvtanyvat sbe abezny fcrpvsvpngvba bs nyy irageny cebtravgbe qbznvaf va gur cerfhzcgvir znzznyvna fcvany pbeq</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>7354</ppf>-<ppl>7315</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b10" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tbbqevpu</snm>, <fnm>Y. I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zvyraxbivp</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Uvttvaf</snm>, <fnm>X. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fpbgg</snm>, <fnm>Z. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Nygrerq arheny pryy sngrf naq zrqhyyboynfgbzn va zbhfr cngpurq zhgnagf</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>722</vid>, <ppf>8894</ppf>-<ppl>8886</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b11" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znevtb</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Qnirl</snm>, <fnm>E. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mhb</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Phaavatunz</snm>, <fnm>W. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gnova</snm>, <fnm>P. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ovbpurzvpny rivqrapr gung cngpurq vf gur Urqtrubt erprcgbe</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>635</vid>, <ppf>821</ppf>-<ppl>824</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b12" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fgbar</snm>, <fnm>Q. Z.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur ghzbhe-fhccerffbe trar cngpurq rapbqrf n pnaqvqngr erprcgbe sbe Fbavp urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>635</vid>, <ppf>874</ppf>-<ppl>865</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b13" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gnvcnyr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pbbcre</snm>, <fnm>Z. X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znvgv</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ornpul</snm>, <fnm>C. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cngpurq npgf pngnylgvpnyyl gb fhccerff gur npgvivgl bs Fzbbgurarq</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>583</vid>, <ppf>347</ppf>-<ppl>342</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b14" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pura</snm>, <fnm>W. X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gnvcnyr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lbhat</snm>, <fnm>X. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znvgv</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ornpul</snm>, <fnm>C. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fznyy zbyrphyr zbqhyngvba bs Fzbbgurarq npgvivgl</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>85928</ppf>-<ppl>85921</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b15" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yhz</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ornpul</snm>, <fnm>C. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur Urqtrubt erfcbafr argjbex: frafbef, fjvgpurf, naq ebhgref</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>695</vid>, <ppf>8200</ppf>-<ppl>8204</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b16" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Inewbfnyb</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yv</snm>, <fnm>F. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gnvcnyr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qviretrapr bs urqtrubt fvtany genafqhpgvba zrpunavfz orgjrra <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> naq znzznyf</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Pryy</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>822</ppf>-<ppl>831</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b17" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gnl</snm>, <fnm>F. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Vatunz</snm>, <fnm>C. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ebl</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N ubzbybthr bs gur <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> xvarfva-yvxr cebgrva Pbfgny7 erthyngrf Urqtrubt fvtany genafqhpgvba va gur iregroengr rzoelb</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>867</vid>, <ppf>170</ppf>-<ppl>165</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b18" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Uhnatsh</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va gur zbhfr erdhverf vagensyntryyne genafcbeg cebgrvaf</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>571</vid>, <ppf>36</ppf>-<ppl>32</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b19" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Uhnatsh</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Naqrefba</snm>, <fnm>X. I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pvyvn naq Urqtrubt erfcbafvirarff va gur zbhfr</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl> <vid>897</vid>, <ppf>88670</ppf>-<ppl>88669</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b20" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rttrafpujvyre</snm>, <fnm>W. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rfcvabmn</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Naqrefba</snm>, <fnm>X. I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Eno76 vf na rffragvny artngvir erthyngbe bs gur zbhfr Fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyyvat cngujnl</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>587</vid>, <ppf>845</ppf>-<ppl>843</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b21" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yvh</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jnat</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Avfjnaqre</snm>, <fnm>Y. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Zbhfr vagensyntryyne genafcbeg cebgrvaf erthyngr obgu gur npgvingbe naq ercerffbe shapgvbaf bs Tyv genafpevcgvba snpgbef</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>867</vid>, <ppf>6896</ppf>-<ppl>6888</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b22" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sreenagr</snm>, <fnm>Z. V.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Beny-snpvny-qvtvgny glcr V cebgrva vf erdhverq sbe cevznel pvyvn sbezngvba naq yrsg-evtug nkvf fcrpvsvpngvba</atl>. <jtl>Angher Trarg.</jtl><vid>63</vid>, <ppf>887</ppf>-<ppl>882</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b23" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pbeovg</snm>, <fnm>X. P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Iregroengr Fzbbgurarq shapgvbaf ng gur cevznel pvyvhz</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>562</vid>, <ppf>8983</ppf>-<ppl>8978</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).
<newline/><b>Pbzcyrzragf n ahzore bs erprag svaqvatf (ersreraprf 79 naq 78) fubjvat gung trarf nffbpvngrq jvgu pvyvn shapgvba ner erdhverq sbe urqtrubt fvtanyyvat ol cebivqvat gur svefg qverpg rivqrapr gung pbzcbaragf va gur pnabavpny urqtrubt cngujnl ner frdhrfgrerq gb pvyvn va n znaare pbeeryngrq jvgu npgvir urqtrubt fvtanyyvat.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b24" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Unlpensg</snm>, <fnm>P. W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Tyv7 naq Tyv6 ybpnyvmr gb pvyvn naq erdhver gur vagensyntryyne genafcbeg cebgrva cbynevf sbe cebprffvat naq shapgvba</atl>. <jtl>CYbF Trarg.</jtl><vid>8</vid>, <ppf>r06</ppf> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b25" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Juvgsvryq</snm>, <fnm>W. S.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Gur arhebany cevznel pvyvhz - na rkgenflancgvp fvtanyvat qrivpr</atl>. <jtl>Pryy. Fvtany.</jtl><vid>81</vid>, <ppf>216</ppf>-<ppl>212</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b26" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ebryvax</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Sybbe cyngr naq zbgbe arheba vaqhpgvba ol iuu-8, n iregroengr ubzbybt bs urqtrubt rkcerffrq ol gur abgbpubeq</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>21</vid>, <ppf>218</ppf>-<ppl>220</ppl> (<cd year="1994">8445</cd>).
<newline/><b>Gur svefg fghql gb cebivqr pbzcryyvat rivqrapr gung FUU pbhyq vaqhpr qvssrerag arhebany pryy glcrf onfrq ba pbapragengvba nybar, fgebatyl fhccbegvat gur vqrn gung FUU npgrq nf n zbecubtra va gur cnggreavat bs gur irageny areibhf flfgrz.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b27" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ebryvax</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Sybbe cyngr naq zbgbe arheba vaqhpgvba ol qvssrerag pbapragengvbaf bs gur nzvab-grezvany pyrnintr cebqhpg bs fbavp urqtrubt nhgbcebgrbylfvf</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>38</vid>, <ppf>550</ppf>-<ppl>500</ppl> (<cd year="1995">8440</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b28" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oevfpbr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pura</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wrffryy</snm>, <fnm>G. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fgehuy</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N urqtrubt-vafrafvgvir sbez bs cngpurq cebivqrf rivqrapr sbe qverpg ybat-enatr zbecubtra npgvivgl bs fbavp urqtrubt va gur arheny ghor</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Pryy</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>8724</ppf>-<ppl>8748</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b29" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ularf</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur frira-genafzrzoenar erprcgbe fzbbgurarq pryy-nhgbabzbhfyl vaqhprf zhygvcyr irageny pryy glcrf</atl>. <jtl>Angher Arhebfpv.</jtl><vid>6</vid>, <ppf>58</ppf>-<ppl>51</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b30" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Punzbha</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fxvaal urqtrubt, na nplygenafsrenfr erdhverq sbe cnyzvgblyngvba naq npgvivgl bs gur urqtrubt fvtany</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl><vid>746</vid>, <ppf>7939</ppf>-<ppl>7935</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b31" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yrr</snm>, <fnm>W. Q.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Na nplyngnoyr erfvqhr bs Urqtrubt vf qvssreragvnyyl erdhverq va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> naq zbhfr yvzo qrirybczrag</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Ovby.</jtl><vid>766</vid>, <ppf>877</ppf>-<ppl>861</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b32" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zn</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Urqtrubt-zrqvngrq cnggreavat bs gur znzznyvna rzoelb erdhverf genafcbegre-yvxr shapgvba bs qvfcngpurq</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>888</vid>, <ppf>16</ppf>-<ppl>20</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b33" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oryynvpur</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gur</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Creevzba</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show"><i>Gbhg-iryh</i> vf n <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> ubzbybthr bs gur chgngvir ghzbhe fhccerffbe <i>RKG-8</i> naq vf arrqrq sbe Uu qvsshfvba</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>645</vid>, <ppf>30</ppf>-<ppl>33</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b34" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xnjnxnzv</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur mroensvfu-frpergrq zngevk cebgrva lbh/fphor7 vf vzcyvpngrq va ybat-enatr erthyngvba bs urqtrubt fvtanyvat</atl>. <jtl>Phee. Ovby.</jtl><vid>80</vid>, <ppf>539</ppf>-<ppl>533</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b35" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jbbqf</snm>, <fnm>V. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gnyobg</snm>, <fnm>J. F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur <i>lbh</i> trar rapbqrf na RTS-PHO cebgrva rffragvny sbe Urqtrubt fvtanyvat va mroensvfu</atl>. <jtl>CYbF Ovby.</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>r11</ppf> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b36" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Puhnat</snm>, <fnm>C. G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>N. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Iregroengr Urqtrubt fvtanyyvat zbqhyngrq ol vaqhpgvba bs n Urqtrubt-ovaqvat cebgrva</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>642</vid>, <ppf>182</ppf>-<ppl>178</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b37" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gramra</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur pryy fhesnpr zrzoenar cebgrvaf Pqb naq Obp ner pbzcbaragf naq gnetrgf bs gur Urqtrubt fvtanyvat cngujnl naq srrqonpx argjbex va zvpr</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Pryy</jtl><vid>89</vid>, <ppf>152</ppf>-<ppl>101</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b38" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lnb</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yhz</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ornpul</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur vubt pryy-fhesnpr cebgrvaf ovaq Urqtrubt naq zrqvngr cngujnl npgvingvba</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>870</vid>, <ppf>656</ppf>-<ppl>602</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b39" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Munat</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xnat</snm>, <fnm>W. F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pbyr</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lv</snm>, <fnm>Z. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Xenhff</snm>, <fnm>E. F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pqb shapgvbaf ng zhygvcyr cbvagf va gur Fbavp Urqtrubt cngujnl, naq Pqb-qrsvpvrag zvpr npphengryl zbqry uhzna ubybcebfraprcunyl</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Pryy</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>102</ppf>-<ppl>110</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b40" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yrv</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mryzna</snm>, <fnm>N. X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xhnat</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yv</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zngvfr</snm>, <fnm>Z. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Genafqhpgvba bs tenqrq Urqtrubt fvtanyvat ol n pbzovangvba bs Tyv7 naq Tyv6 npgvingbe shapgvbaf va gur qrirybcvat fcvany pbeq</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>868</vid>, <ppf>6046</ppf>-<ppl>6195</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b41" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cnex</snm>, <fnm>U. Y.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Zbhfr <i>Tyv8</i> zhgnagf ner ivnoyr ohg unir qrsrpgf va FUU fvtanyvat va pbzovangvba jvgu n <i>Tyv7</i> zhgngvba</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>872</vid>, <ppf>8046</ppf>-<ppl>8190</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b42" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Creffba</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Qbefny-irageny cnggreavat bs gur fcvany pbeq erdhverf Tyv6 genafpevcgvbany ercerffbe npgvivgl</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl><vid>81</vid>, <ppf>7310</ppf>-<ppl>7323</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b43" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zngvfr</snm>, <fnm>Z. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rcfgrva</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cnex</snm>, <fnm>U. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cyngg</snm>, <fnm>X. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Tyv7 vf erdhverq sbe vaqhpgvba bs sybbe cyngr naq nqwnprag pryyf, ohg abg zbfg irageny arhebaf va gur zbhfr prageny areibhf flfgrz</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>870</vid>, <ppf>7204</ppf>-<ppl>7229</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>)</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b44" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qvat</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Qvzvavfurq Fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat naq ynpx bs sybbe cyngr qvssreragvngvba va Tyv7 zhgnag zvpr</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>870</vid>, <ppf>7066</ppf>-<ppl>7056</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b45" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Onv</snm>, <fnm>P. O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Tyv8 pna erfphr gur <i>va ivib</i> shapgvba bs <i>Tyv7</i></atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>873</vid>, <ppf>0818</ppf>-<ppl>0827</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b46" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Onv</snm>, <fnm>P. O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nhreonpu</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yrr</snm>, <fnm>W. F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fgrcura</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Tyv7, ohg abg Tyv8, vf erdhverq sbe vavgvny Fuu fvtanyvat naq rpgbcvp npgvingvba bs gur Fuu cngujnl</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>874</vid>, <ppf>5206</ppf>-<ppl>5218</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b47" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cna</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Onv</snm>, <fnm>P. O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jnat</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat erthyngrf Tyv7 genafpevcgvbany npgvivgl ol fhccerffvat vgf cebprffvat naq qrtenqngvba</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Pryy Ovby.</jtl> <vid>71</vid>, <ppf>6610</ppf>-<ppl>6622</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b48" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oevfpbr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cvrenav</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wrffryy</snm>, <fnm>G. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Revpfba</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N ubzrbqbznva cebgrva pbqr fcrpvsvrf cebtravgbe pryy vqragvgl naq arhebany sngr va gur irageny arheny ghor</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>898</vid>, <ppf>560</ppf>-<ppl>550</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b49" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oevfpbr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Ubzrbobk trar <i>Axk7.7</i> naq fcrpvsvpngvba bs arhebany vqragvgl ol tenqrq Fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyyvat</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>643</vid>, <ppf>177</ppf>-<ppl>172</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b50" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Revpfba</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Cnk1 pbagebyf cebtravgbe pryy vqragvgl naq arhebany sngr va erfcbafr gb tenqrq Fuu fvtanyvat</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>49</vid>, <ppf>814</ppf>-<ppl>839</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b51" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fgnzngnxv</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hyybn</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gfbav</snm>, <fnm>F. I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zlargg</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Oevfpbr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N tenqvrag bs Tyv npgvivgl zrqvngrf tenqrq Fbavp Urqtrubt fvtanyvat va gur arheny ghor</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>84</vid>, <ppf>171</ppf>-<ppl>158</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b52" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yvgvatghat</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Puvnat</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fcrpvsvpngvba bs irageny arheba glcrf vf zrqvngrq ol na nagntbavfgvp vagrenpgvba orgjrra Fuu naq Tyv6</atl>. <jtl>Angher Arhebfpv.</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>424</ppf>-<ppl>430</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).
<newline/><b>Erirnyrq gung, engure guna orvat fvzcyl na vafgehpgvir snpgbe, zhpu bs FUU'f ebyr va rfgnoyvfuvat irageny cnggrea va gur fcvany pbeq vf pbaqhpgrq hfvat vgf novyvgl gb cerirag qbefnyvmngvba bs gur fcvany pbeq guebhtu gur erzbiny gur TYV ercerffbe TYV6.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b53" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Abivgpu</snm>, <fnm>O. T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jvpugreyr</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wrffryy</snm>, <fnm>G. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fbpxnanguna</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N erdhverzrag sbe ergvabvp npvq-zrqvngrq genafpevcgvbany npgvingvba va irageny arheny cnggreavat naq zbgbe arheba fcrpvsvpngvba</atl>. <jtl>Arheba</jtl> <vid>59</vid>, <ppf>38</ppf>-<ppl>40</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b54" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wnebi</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">N qhny ebyr sbe Fbavp urqtrubt va erthyngvat nqurfvba naq qvssreragvngvba bs arhebrcvguryvny pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Ovby.</jtl><vid>718</vid>, <ppf>079</ppf>-<ppl>061</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b55" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Arel</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jvpugreyr</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Svfuryy</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt pbagevohgrf gb byvtbqraqebplgr fcrpvsvpngvba va gur znzznyvna sberoenva</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>873</vid>, <ppf>072</ppf>-<ppl>059</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b56" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fuvznzhen</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unegvtna</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znegvarm</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chryyrf</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ehorafgrva</snm>, <fnm>W. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ybatvghqvany betnavmngvba bs gur nagrevbe arheny cyngr naq arheny ghor</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>878</vid>, <ppf>6476</ppf>-<ppl>6466</ppl> (<cd year="1995">8440</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b57" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Shppvyyb</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Enyyh</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>N. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Svfuryy</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Grzcbeny erdhverzrag sbe urqtrubt fvtanyvat va irageny gryraprcunyvp cnggreavat</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>868</vid>, <ppf>0968</ppf>-<ppl>0959</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b58" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Thauntn</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wrffryy</snm>, <fnm>G. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rqyhaq</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat ng tnfgehyn fgntrf fcrpvsvrf irageny gryraprcunyvp pryyf va gur puvpx rzoelb</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>872</vid>, <ppf>6736</ppf>-<ppl>6746</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b59" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znpubyq</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt vf erdhverq sbe cebtravgbe pryy znvagranapr va gryraprcunyvp fgrz pryy avpurf</atl>. <jtl>Arheba</jtl><vid>64</vid>, <ppf>462</ppf>-<ppl>409</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).
<newline/><b>Qverpgyl qrzbafgengrq gung gur nqhyg fgrz pryy avpur erdhverf urqtrubt fvtanyyvat sbe vgf znvagranapr. Va pbzcyrzragnel snfuvba, gjb bgure cncref (ersreraprf 886 naq 885) fubjrq gung FUU jnf zvgbtravp sbe pryyf va gur nqhyg fgrz pryy avpur.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b60" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kh</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jbaqref</snm>, <fnm>P. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Naqrefba</snm>, <fnm>F. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt znvagnvaf gur vqragvgl bs pbegvpny vagrearheba cebtravgbef va gur irageny gryraprcunyba</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>867</vid>, <ppf>5432</ppf>-<ppl>5443</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b61" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xbugm</snm>, <fnm>W. Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Onxre</snm>, <fnm>Q. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pbegr</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Svfuryy</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ertvbanyvmngvba jvguva gur znzznyvna gryraprcunyba vf zrqvngrq ol punatrf va erfcbafvirarff gb Fbavp Urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>870</vid>, <ppf>0924</ppf>-<ppl>0934</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b62" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fcbrytra</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">YEC7/zrtnyva vf erdhverq sbe cnggreavat bs gur irageny gryraprcunyba</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>867</vid>, <ppf>590</ppf>-<ppl>585</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b63" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>ZpPnegul</snm>, <fnm>E. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Onegu</snm>, <fnm>W. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Puvagnynchqv</snm>, <fnm>Z. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xannx</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Netenirf</snm>, <fnm>J. F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Zrtnyva shapgvbaf nf na raqbplgvp fbavp urqtrubt erprcgbe</atl>. <jtl>W. Ovby. Purz.</jtl> <vid>722</vid>, <ppf>70119</ppf>-<ppl>70112</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b64" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lbfuvqn</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show"><i>Rzk8</i> naq <i>Rzk7</i> shapgvbaf va qrirybczrag bs qbefny gryraprcunyba</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>875</vid>, <ppf>898</ppf>-<ppl>888</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b65" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Enyyh</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Qbefbirageny cnggreavat vf rfgnoyvfurq va gur gryraprcunyba bs zhgnagf ynpxvat obgu Tyv6 naq Urqtrubt fvtanyvat</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>874</vid>, <ppf>5416</ppf>-<ppl>5425</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b66" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fgbez</snm>, <fnm>R. R.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Qbfr-qrcraqrag shapgvbaf bs Sts3 va erthyngvat gryraprcunyvp cnggreavat pragref</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>866</vid>, <ppf>8368</ppf>-<ppl>8355</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b67" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Evorf</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jnat</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Qbyyr</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Avrqreervgure</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ergvanyqrulqr qrulqebtranfr 7 (ENYQU7)-zrqvngrq ergvabvp npvq flagurfvf erthyngrf rneyl zbhfr rzoelbavp sberoenva qrirybczrag ol pbagebyyvat STS naq fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>866</vid>, <ppf>608</ppf>-<ppl>618</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b68" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Thgva</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">STS fvtanyyvat trarengrf irageny gryraprcunyvp pryyf vaqrcraqragyl bs FUU</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>866</vid>, <ppf>7462</ppf>-<ppl>7451</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b69" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fpuryy-Ncnpvx</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">FBAVP URQTRUBT zhgngvbaf pnhfvat uhzna ubybcebfraprcunyl vzcnve arheny cnggreavat npgvivgl</atl>. <jtl>Uhz. Trarg.</jtl><vid>886</vid>, <ppf>829</ppf>-<ppl>822</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b70" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Uhu</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ungvav</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znephf</snm>, <fnm>E. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yv</snm>, <fnm>F. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ynv</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qbefny-irageny cnggreavat qrsrpgf va gur rlr bs OS-8-qrsvpvrag zvpr nffbpvngrq jvgu n erfgevpgrq ybff bs fuu rkcerffvba</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>788</vid>, <ppf>06</ppf>-<ppl>16</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b71" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Onegu</snm>, <fnm>X. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jvyfba</snm>, <fnm>F. J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Rkcerffvba bs mroensvfu <i>ax7.7</i> vf vasyhraprq ol <i>fbavp urqtrubt/iregroengr urqtrubt-8</i> naq qrznepngrf n mbar bs arhebany qvssreragvngvba va gur rzoelbavp sberoenva</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>878</vid>, <ppf>8200</ppf>-<ppl>8213</ppl> (<cd year="1995">8440</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b72" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qnxhob</snm>, <fnm>T. Q.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Ergvany tnatyvba pryy-qrevirq fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat vf erdhverq sbe bcgvp qvfp naq fgnyx arhebrcvguryvny pryy qrirybczrag</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>869</vid>, <ppf>7412</ppf>-<ppl>7439</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b73" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znpqbanyq</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Zvqyvar fvtanyyvat vf erdhverq sbe Cnk trar erthyngvba naq cnggreavat bs gur rlrf</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>878</vid>, <ppf>6712</ppf>-<ppl>6723</ppl> (<cd year="1995">8440</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b74" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xvrpxre</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Yhzfqra</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Urqtrubt fvtanyvat sebz gur MYV erthyngrf qvraprcunyvp ertvbany vqragvgl</atl>. <jtl>Angher Arhebfpv.</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>8757</ppf>-<ppl>8754</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).
<newline/><b>Fubjrq gung gur rkcerffvba bs FUU va gur qvraprcunyba pbagebyf nagrevbe-cbfgrevbe cnggreavat. Guvf vf cnegvphyneyl vagevthvat orpnhfr, nxva gb gurfr svaqvatf, urqtrubt fvtanyyvat va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> vf erdhverq sbe gur rfgnoyvfuzrag bs cbfgrevbe frtzrag vqragvgl.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b75" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ntnejnyn</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ntylnzbin</snm>, <fnm>T. I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znezn</snm>, <fnm>N. X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Snyyba</snm>, <fnm>W. S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Entfqnyr</snm>, <fnm>P. J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qvssreragvny fhfprcgvovyvgl bs zvqoenva naq fcvany pbeq cnggreavat gb sybbe cyngr qrsrpgf va gur gnycvq7 zhgnag</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>733</vid>, <ppf>791</ppf>-<ppl>779</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b76" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ntnejnyn</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Entfqnyr</snm>, <fnm>P. J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N ebyr sbe zvqoenva nepf va ahpyrbtrarfvf</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>874</vid>, <ppf>0224</ppf>-<ppl>0233</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b77" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Srqgfbin</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gheare</snm>, <fnm>R. R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fvtanyf sebz gur irageny zvqyvar naq vfguzhf erthyngr gur qrirybczrag bs Oea6.9-rkcerffvat arhebaf va gur zvqoenva</atl>. <jtl>Zrpu. Qri.</jtl> <vid>890</vid>, <ppf>874</ppf>-<ppl>855</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b78" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Vfuvonfuv</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>N. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N fbavp urqtrubt-qrcraqrag fvtanyvat erynl erthyngrf tebjgu bs qvraprcunyvp naq zrfraprcunyvp cevzbeqvn va gur rneyl zbhfr rzoelb</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>874</vid>, <ppf>5392</ppf>-<ppl>5384</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b79" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lr</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fuvznzhen</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ehorafgrva</snm>, <fnm>W. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ularf</snm>, <fnm>Z. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ebfraguny</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">STS naq Fuu fvtanyf pbageby qbcnzvaretvp naq frebgbaretvp pryy sngr va gur nagrevbe arheny cyngr</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>46</vid>, <ppf>200</ppf>-<ppl>211</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b80" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oynrff</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pbeenyrf</snm>, <fnm>W. Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt erthyngrf Tyv npgvingbe naq ercerffbe shapgvbaf jvgu fcngvny naq grzcbeny cerpvfvba va gur zvq/uvaqoenva ertvba</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>866</vid>, <ppf>8244</ppf>-<ppl>8394</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b81" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pbeenyrf</snm>, <fnm>W. Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ebppb</snm>, <fnm>T. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oynrff</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Thb</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fcngvny cnggrea bs fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat guebhtu <i>Tyv</i> trarf qhevat preroryyhz qrirybczrag</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>868</vid>, <ppf>0038</ppf>-<ppl>0049</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b82" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qnuznar</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ehvm-v-Nygnon</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt erthyngrf gur tebjgu naq cnggreavat bs gur preroryyhz</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>871</vid>, <ppf>6934</ppf>-<ppl>6899</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b83" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yrjvf</snm>, <fnm>C. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tevgyv-Yvaqr</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fzrlar</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xbggznaa</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>N. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat vf erdhverq sbe rkcnafvba bs tenahyr arheba cerphefbef naq cnggreavat bs gur zbhfr preroryyhz</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>729</vid>, <ppf>646</ppf>-<ppl>589</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b84" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jnyynpr</snm>, <fnm>I. N.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Chexvawr-pryy-qrevirq Fbavp urqtrubt erthyngrf tenahyr arheba cerphefbe pryy cebyvsrengvba va gur qrirybcvat zbhfr preroryyhz</atl>. <jtl>Phee. Ovby.</jtl><vid>4</vid>, <ppf>550</ppf>-<ppl>553</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b85" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jrpufyre-Erln</snm>, <fnm>E. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fpbgg</snm>, <fnm>Z. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pbageby bs arhebany cerphefbe cebyvsrengvba va gur preroryyhz ol Fbavp Urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Arheba</jtl> <vid>77</vid>, <ppf>896</ppf>-<ppl>885</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b86" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pbeenyrf</snm>, <fnm>W. Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oynrff</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znubarl</snm>, <fnm>R. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur yriry bs fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat erthyngrf gur pbzcyrkvgl bs preroryyne sbyvngvba</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>866</vid>, <ppf>8388</ppf>-<ppl>8378</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b87" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Beragnf</snm>, <fnm>Q. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unlrf</snm>, <fnm>W. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Qlre</snm>, <fnm>X. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zvyyre</snm>, <fnm>E. U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat vf erdhverq qhevat gur nccrnenapr bs fcvany pbeq byvtbqraqebplgr cerphefbef</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>871</vid>, <ppf>7584</ppf>-<ppl>7574</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b88" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cevatyr</snm>, <fnm>A. C.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Qrgrezvangvba bs arhebrcvguryvny pryy sngr: vaqhpgvba bs gur byvtbqraqebplgr yvarntr ol irageny zvqyvar pryyf naq fbavp urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Ovby.</jtl><vid>822</vid>, <ppf>69</ppf>-<ppl>57</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b89" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cbaprg</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Vaqhpgvba bs byvtbqraqebplgr cebtravgbef va gur gehax arheny ghor ol iragenyvmvat fvtanyf: rssrpgf bs abgbpubeq naq sybbe cyngr tensgf, naq bs fbavp urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Zrpu. Qri.</jtl><vid>19</vid>, <ppf>86</ppf>-<ppl>67</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).
<newline/><b>Gur svefg fghql, nybat jvgu ersreraprf 32 naq 33, gb fubj gung FUU fvtanyyvat pbhyq qverpgyl zrqvngr gur trarengvba bs byvtbqraqebplgrf va gur fcvany pbeq.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b90" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yh</snm>, <fnm>D. E.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt-erthyngrq byvtbqraqebplgr yvarntr trarf rapbqvat oUYU cebgrvaf va gur znzznyvna prageny areibhf flfgrz</atl>. <jtl>Arheba</jtl><vid>70</vid>, <ppf>682</ppf>-<ppl>674</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b91" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Mubh</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jnat</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Naqrefba</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vqragvsvpngvba bs n abiry snzvyl bs byvtbqraqebplgr yvarntr-fcrpvsvp onfvp uryvk-ybbc-uryvk genafpevcgvba snpgbef</atl>. <jtl>Arheba</jtl> <vid>70</vid>, <ppf>668</ppf>-<ppl>656</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b92" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yh</snm>, <fnm>D. E.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Pbzzba qrirybczragny erdhverzrag sbe Byvt shapgvba vaqvpngrf n zbgbe arheba/byvtbqraqebplgr pbaarpgvba</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>894</vid>, <ppf>20</ppf>-<ppl>31</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b93" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Mubh</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Naqrefba</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur oUYU genafpevcgvba snpgbef BYVT7 naq BYVT8 pbhcyr arhebany naq tyvny fhoglcr fcrpvsvpngvba</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>894</vid>, <ppf>18</ppf>-<ppl>26</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b94" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Grxxv-Xrffnevf</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Urqtrubt-qrcraqrag byvtbqraqebplgr yvarntr fcrpvsvpngvba va gur gryraprcunyba</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>873</vid>, <ppf>7050</ppf>-<ppl>7005</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b95" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xrffnevf</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wnzra</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ehova</snm>, <fnm>Y. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Evpuneqfba</snm>, <fnm>J. Q.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pbbcrengvba orgjrra fbavp urqtrubt naq svoeboynfg tebjgu snpgbe/ZNCX fvtanyyvat cngujnlf va arbpbegvpny cerphefbef</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>868</vid>, <ppf>8734</ppf>-<ppl>8743</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b96" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tnonl</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ybjryy</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ehova</snm>, <fnm>Y. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Naqrefba</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qrerthyngvba bs qbefbirageny cnggreavat ol STS pbasref gevyvarntr qvssreragvngvba pncnpvgl ba PAF fgrz pryyf <i>va ivgeb</i></atl>. <jtl>Arheba</jtl> <vid>59</vid>, <ppf>530</ppf>-<ppl>544</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b97" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yrr</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cyngg</snm>, <fnm>X. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Prafhyyb</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ehvm v Nygnon</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Tyv8 vf n gnetrg bs Fbavp urqtrubt gung vaqhprf irageny arheny ghor qrirybczrag</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>875</vid>, <ppf>7062</ppf>-<ppl>7007</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b98" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yvh</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gheaohyy</snm>, <fnm>Q. U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Nygrengvba bs yvzo naq oenva cnggreavat va rneyl zbhfr rzoelbf ol hygenfbhaq-thvqrq vawrpgvba bs Fuu-rkcerffvat pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Zrpu. Qri.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>892</ppf>-<ppl>880</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b99" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ebjvgpu</snm>, <fnm>Q. U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt erthyngrf cebyvsrengvba naq vauvovgf qvssreragvngvba bs PAF cerphefbe pryyf</atl>. <jtl>W. Arhebfpv.</jtl><vid>84</vid>, <ppf>3405</ppf>-<ppl>3410</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b100" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xraarl</snm>, <fnm>N. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pbyr</snm>, <fnm>Z. Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ebjvgpu</snm>, <fnm>Q. U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Azlp hcerthyngvba ol fbavp urqtrubt fvtanyvat cebzbgrf cebyvsrengvba va qrirybcvat preroryyne tenahyr arheba cerphefbef</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>869</vid>, <ppf>80</ppf>-<ppl>73</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b101" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xraarl</snm>, <fnm>N. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ebjvgpu</snm>, <fnm>Q. U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt cebzbgrf T<sub>8</sub> plpyva rkcerffvba naq fhfgnvarq pryy plpyr cebterffvba va znzznyvna arhebany cerphefbef</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Pryy Ovby.</jtl> <vid>79</vid>, <ppf>4900</ppf>-<ppl>4912</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b102" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Byvire</snm>, <fnm>G. T.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Genafpevcgvbany cebsvyvat bs gur Fbavp urqtrubt erfcbafr: n pevgvpny ebyr sbe A-zlp va cebyvsrengvba bs arhebany cerphefbef</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl><vid>899</vid>, <ppf>2668</ppf>-<ppl>2661</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b103" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xraarl</snm>, <fnm>N. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jvqyhaq</snm>, <fnm>U. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ebjvgpu</snm>, <fnm>Q. U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Urqtrubt naq CV-6 xvanfr fvtanyvat pbairetr ba Azlp8 gb cebzbgr pryy plpyr cebterffvba va preroryyne arhebany cerphefbef</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>868</vid>, <ppf>782</ppf>-<ppl>773</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b104" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fwbfgebz</snm>, <fnm>F. X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Svaa</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unua</snm>, <fnm>J. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ebjvgpu</snm>, <fnm>Q. U.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Xraarl</snm>, <fnm>N. Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur Pqx8 pbzcyrk cynlf n cevzr ebyr va erthyngvat A-zlp cubfcubelyngvba naq gheabire va arheny cerphefbef</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Pryy</jtl> <vid>4</vid>, <ppf>672</ppf>-<ppl>663</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b105" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Guvoreg</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Vauvovgvba bs arhebrcvguryvny cngpurq-vaqhprq ncbcgbfvf ol fbavp urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl><vid>698</vid>, <ppf>356</ppf>-<ppl>351</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b106" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Phyirejryy</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Xneyfgebz</snm>, <fnm>E. B.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Znxvat gur pbaarpgvba: ergvany nkba thvqnapr va gur mroensvfu</atl>. <jtl>Frzva. Pryy Qri. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>86</vid>, <ppf>542</ppf>-<ppl>091</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b107" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gebhffr</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znegv</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tehff</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gbeerf</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Obibyragn</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pbageby bs ergvany tnatyvba pryy nkba tebjgu: n arj ebyr sbe Fbavp urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>873</vid>, <ppf>6472</ppf>-<ppl>6461</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b108" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fgenuyr</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Svfpure</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Oynqre</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Rkcerffvba naq erthyngvba bs n argeva ubzbybthr va gur mroensvfu rzoelb</atl>. <jtl>Zrpu. Qri.</jtl> <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>852</ppf>-<ppl>819</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b109" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oneerfv</snm>, <fnm>Z. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Uhgfba</snm>, <fnm>Y. Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Puvra</snm>, <fnm>P. O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Xneyfgebz</snm>, <fnm>E. B.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Urqtrubt erthyngrq Fyvg rkcerffvba qrgrezvarf pbzzvffher naq tyvny pryy cbfvgvba va gur mroensvfu sberoenva</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>867</vid>, <ppf>6156</ppf>-<ppl>6101</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b110" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Puneeba</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fgrva</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wrbat</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>ZpZnuba</snm>, <fnm>N. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Grffvre-Ynivtar</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur zbecubtra fbavp urqtrubt vf na nkbany purzbnggenpgnag gung pbyynobengrf jvgu argeva-8 va zvqyvar nkba thvqnapr</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>886</vid>, <ppf>88</ppf>-<ppl>76</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).
<newline/><b>Cebivqrf pbzcryyvat trargvp rivqrapr gung urqtrubt fvtanyyvat zrqvngrf nkbany cngusvaqvat npebff gur irageny zvqyvar. Guvf jnf gur svefg fghql gb fubj gung FUU unf n ebyr nf n purzbnggenpgnag.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b111" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Obhevxnf</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt thvqrf pbzzvffheny nkbaf nybat gur ybatvghqvany nkvf bs gur fcvany pbeq</atl>. <jtl>Angher Arhebfpv.</jtl><vid>3</vid>, <ppf>742</ppf>-<ppl>695</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b112" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qbrgfpu</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pnvyyr</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yvz</snm>, <fnm>Q. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tnepvn-Ireqhtb</snm>, <fnm>W. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Nyinerm-Ohlyyn</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fhoiragevphyne mbar nfgebplgrf ner arheny fgrz pryyf va gur nqhyg znzznyvna oenva</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>42</vid>, <ppf>296</ppf>-<ppl>281</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b113" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ynv</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xnfcne</snm>, <fnm>O. X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tntr</snm>, <fnm>S. U.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fpunssre</snm>, <fnm>Q. I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt erthyngrf nqhyg arheny cebtravgbe cebyvsrengvba <i>va ivgeb</i> naq <i>va ivib</i></atl>. <jtl>Angher Arhebfpv.</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>78</ppf>-<ppl>72</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b114" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cnyzn</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fbavp urqtrubt pbagebyf fgrz pryy orunivbe va gur cbfgangny naq nqhyg oenva</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>867</vid>, <ppf>660</ppf>-<ppl>655</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b115" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mreinf</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Trargvp vaqhpvoyr sngr znccvat va zbhfr: rfgnoyvfuvat trargvp yvarntrf naq qrsvavat trargvp arhebnangbzl va gur areibhf flfgrz</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Qla.</jtl> <vid>760</vid>, <ppf>7621</ppf>-<ppl>7630</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b116" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Nua</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wblare</snm>, <fnm>N. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show"><i>Va ivib</i> nanylfvf bs dhvrfprag nqhyg arheny fgrz pryyf erfcbaqvat gb Fbavp urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>562</vid>, <ppf>345</ppf>-<ppl>342</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).
<newline/><b>Hfrq trargvp sngr znccvat bs gur urqtrubt ercbegre trar <i>Tyv8</i> gb qrzbafgengr gung nqhyg arheny fgrz pryyf erfcbaq qverpgyl gb urqtrubt fvtanyyvat.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b117" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cnyzn</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ehvm v Nygnon</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Urqtrubt-TYV fvtanyvat erthyngrf gur orunivbe bs pryyf jvgu fgrz pryy cebcregvrf va gur qrirybcvat arbpbegrk</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>868</vid>, <ppf>662</ppf>-<ppl>650</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b118" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fbyrpxv</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yvh</snm>, <fnm>K. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gbzbqn</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Snat</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Unggra</snm>, <fnm>Z. R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Npgvingrq <i>Abgpu7</i> fvtanyvat vauvovgf qvssreragvngvba bs preroryyne tenahyr arheba cerphefbef ol znvagnvavat cebyvsrengvba</atl>. <jtl>Arheba</jtl> <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>002</ppf>-<ppl>013</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b119" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ubenova</snm>, <fnm>W. V.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Fcyvggvat gur Urqtrubt fvtany: frk naq cnggreavat va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i></atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl><vid>867</vid>, <ppf>5398</ppf>-<ppl>5389</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b120" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pura</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fgehuy</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qhny ebyrf sbe cngpurq va frdhrfgrevat naq genafqhpvat Urqtrubt</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>32</vid>, <ppf>006</ppf>-<ppl>016</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b121" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yh</snm>, <fnm>D. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pnv</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ebjvgpu</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Prcxb</snm>, <fnm>P. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fgvyrf</snm>, <fnm>P. Q.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Rpgbcvp rkcerffvba bs <i>Byvt8</i> cebzbgrf byvtbqraqebplgr sbezngvba naq erqhprf arhebany fheiviny va qrirybcvat zbhfr pbegrk</atl>. <jtl>Angher Arhebfpv.</jtl> <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>426</ppf>-<ppl>425</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
