<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "NPG_XML_Article.dtd" [
<!ENTITY figf1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nrn1990-f1//EN" "//snapple/web_d/web/npg/nrn/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrn1990-f1" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf2 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nrn1990-f2//EN" "//snapple/web_d/web/npg/nrn/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrn1990-f2" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf3 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nrn1990-f3//EN" "//snapple/web_d/web/npg/nrn/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrn1990-f3" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf4 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nrn1990-f4//EN" "//snapple/web_d/web/npg/nrn/journal/vaop/ncurrent/images/nrn1990-f4" NDATA ITEM>
]>
<article id="nrn1990" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <!--nrn1990-->
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</jtl>
    <vol>7</vol>
    <iss>10</iss>
    <idt>200610</idt>
    <categ id="rv"/>
    <pp>
      <spn>772</spn>
      <epn>783</epn>
      <cnt>12</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">1471-003X</issn>
    <issn type="electronic">1471-0048</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>2006</cpy>
      <cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <doi>10.1038/nrn1990</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl>Morphogen to mitogen: the multiple roles of hedgehog signalling in vertebrate neural development</atl>
    <aug>
      <au>
        <fnm>Marc</fnm>
        <snm>Fuccillo</snm>
        <inits>M</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <bio>
          <p>Marc Fuccillo studied biology and violin performance at Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island, USA, graduating in 1998.  After working for two years at the Rockefeller University, New York, USA, in the laboratory of James Darnell, he joined the New York University Medical Scientist Training M.D./Ph.D. Program.  Presently, he is studying the developmental mechanisms of cortical interneuron diversity in the laboratory of Gord Fishell at the Skirball Institute, NYU.</p>
        </bio>
      </au>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Alexandra L.</fnm>
        <snm>Joyner</snm>
        <inits>A L</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <bio>
          <p>Alexandra L. Joyner has been the Co-coordinator of the Developmental Genetics Program at the Skirball Institute of Biomolecular Medicine within the New York University School of Medicine, USA, for 12 years. She is also the Skirball Foundation Professor of Genetics and a Professor in the Departments of Cell Biology and of Physiology and Neuroscience. She will soon join the Developmental Biology Program at the Sloan-Kettering Institute, New York. A native Canadian, she received her Ph.D. from the University of Toronto, Canada. During her postdoctoral research with Gail Martin at the University of California, San Francisco, USA, she cloned some of the first mammalian homeobox genes. She was then a senior scientist in the Samuel Lunenfeld Research Institute at Mt. Sinai Hospital in Toronto for eight years, where she pioneered a number of mouse genetic approaches and began her studies of the <i>Gli</i> genes and development of the cerebellum. Her research focuses on genetic and cellular events underlying mouse midbrain and cerebellum development, and the role of <i>Shh</i> in adult stem cells.</p>
        </bio>
      </cau>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Gord</fnm>
        <snm>Fishell</snm>
        <inits>G</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <corf rid="c1"/>
        <bio>
          <p>Gord Fishell received his Ph.D. in 1989 from the University of Toronto, Canada, in the laboratory of Derek van der Kooy. Since this time he has been interested in the mechanisms that act to pattern the telencephalon. For the past twelve years, he has been at New York University's School of Medicine, USA, where he is a professor. He is a coordinator of the Developmental Genetics Program at the NYU's Skirball Institute, with a primary appointment in the Department of Cell Biology. He will soon become the coordinator of the Smilow Integrated Neuroscience program, a new research initiative at NYU. His laboratory studies various aspects of telencephalic development, most notably in the developmental and genetic origins of cortical interneuron diversity.</p>
        </bio>
      </cau>
      <aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Developmental Genetics Program and the Department of Cell Biology, Skirball Institute of Biomolecular Medicine, New York University Medical Center</org>, <street>540 First Avenue</street>, <cty>New York</cty>, <st>NY</st><zip>10016</zip>, <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
      <caff>
        <coid id="c1"/>
        <email>fishell@saturn.med.nyu.edu</email>
      </caff>
    </aug>
    <execsumm>
      <p>
        <list id="l1" type="bullet">
          <li>Hedgehog signalling in the mammalian nervous system has been traditionally associated with dorsoventral patterning. Many recent findings have demonstrated its involvement in various temporally regulated developmental processes. This review provides an overview of the spatial and temporal contexts in which hedgehog signalling is utilized.</li>
          <li>We outline the basic hedgehog signalling pathway and discuss the roles of newly identified regulators of this pathway, including extracellular mediators (such as IHOG) and a family of genes associated with cilia function.</li>
          <li>The review describes the core molecular components utilized in the establishment of ventral patterning in the spinal cord. We then discuss the role of hedgehog signalling in ventral patterning in the broader context of its role at various more anterior levels of the neuraxis, including the forebrain, midbrain and hindbrain.</li>
          <li>A number of non-patterning functions of hedgehog signalling have been discovered, including a role in the specification of oligodendrocyte precursors, as well as the regulation of embryonic proliferation and apoptosis.</li>
          <li>An unforeseen role for hedgehog signalling in ventral midline axonal guidance has been uncovered. Intriguingly, the time course of events suggests this is mediated by non-canonical signalling.</li>
          <li>Recently, hedgehog signalling has been shown to be active in adult neural stem cells and to be required for the maintenance of the telencephalic progenitor cell niche.</li>
        </list>
      </p>
    </execsumm>
    <websumm>The role of sonic hedgehog as a morphogen involved in establishing ventral cell identity in the CNS is well known. Fishell and colleagues outline the current understanding of the molecular pathways involved in patterning and describe several recently identified and unrelated roles for hedgehog signalling.</websumm>
    <abs>
      <p>Sonic hedgehog has received an enormous amount of attention since its role as a morphogen that directs ventral patterning in the spinal cord was discovered a decade ago. Since that time, a bewildering array of information has been generated concerning both the components of the hedgehog signalling pathway and the remarkable number of contexts in which it functions. Nowhere is this more evident than in the nervous system, where hedgehog signalling has been implicated in events as disparate as axonal guidance and stem cell maintenance. Here we review our present knowledge of the hedgehog signalling pathway and speculate about areas in which further insights into this versatile pathway might be forthcoming.</p>
    </abs>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>The best-studied functions of the members of the hedgehog protein family in the nervous system are their roles as <deflistr rid="df1">morphogens</deflistr>; each protein acts at a distance from the source of the signal to establish cell identities in the ventral spinal cord in a concentration-dependent manner. However, during the past decade it has become apparent that the functions of the members of the hedgehog protein family in development are diverse, with their specific actions changing with both space and time. This has proven to be true with respect to the molecular components that modulate and transduce hedgehog signalling, and the specific cellular processes that it controls. The increasing number of both intra- and intercellular modulators of hedgehog signalling have been comprehensively discussed in recent reviews<bibr rid="b1 b2"/>.</p>
    <p>Here, we largely confine our discussion to the roles of hedgehog signalling in the mammalian nervous system. We first discuss the function of hedgehog proteins in directing neural progenitors to acquire specific cell identities. In particular, we focus on how members of the GLI family of transcription factors act as effectors of hedgehog signalling in the spinal cord, allowing an extracellular concentration gradient of hedgehog to be translated into different cell identities. We then discuss how iterations of this molecular pathway at more anterior levels of the nervous system lead to the induction of cell types appropriate for the telencephalon, diencephalon, midbrain and anterior hindbrain. In addition to this role in patterning, we review the many developmental events that hedgehog signalling mediates, including the generation of oligodendrocytes and its <deflistr rid="df2">mitogenic</deflistr> role in controlling the proliferation of neural progenitors. Finally, we discuss some more recently recognized roles for hedgehog signalling in axonal pathfinding and the maintenance of adult stem cells.</p>
    <crosshd>Molecular mechanisms of hedgehog signalling</crosshd>
    <p>The molecular mechanisms by which extracellular hedgehog signals are received, interpreted and transformed into intracellular cell fate decisions have received a great deal of attention<bibr rid="b3 b4"/>. Work from both vertebrate and invertebrate species has delineated a canonical hedgehog signalling pathway, in which cell-surface binding of hedgehog ligands leads ultimately to the formation of repressor or activator forms of members of the GLI/CI family of zinc-finger transcription factors (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>)<bibr rid="b5"/>. In vertebrates, the functions of the protein encoded by the ancestral invertebrate gene cubitus interruptus (<scientific id="43767" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene"><i>ci</i></scientific>) have been divided between the three GLI proteins (<scientific id="14632" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">GLI1</scientific>, <scientific id="14633" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">GLI2</scientific> and <scientific id="14634" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">GLI3</scientific>)<bibr rid="b6"/>. Hedgehog signalling in mammals is initiated by one of three homologues of the Drosophila hedgehog protein<bibr rid="b7"/> - sonic hedgehog (<scientific id="20423" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">SHH</scientific>), indian hedgehog (<scientific id="16147" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">IHH</scientific>) and desert hedgehog (<scientific id="13363" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">DHH</scientific>), of which the first two have been implicated in neural development<bibr rid="b8 b9"/>.</p>
    <p>The transduction of hedgehog signalling in cells is mediated by interactions between two proteins, the twelve-pass membrane hedgehog receptor patched (<scientific id="19206" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">PTC1</scientific>)<bibr rid="b10 b11"/> and the seven-pass G-protein-coupled receptor smoothened (<scientific id="319757" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">SMO</scientific>)<bibr rid="b2 b12"/>. Genetic and biochemical data indicate that, in the absence of hedgehog ligand, PTC1 constitutively represses SMO activity<bibr rid="b120"/>. This repression is non-stoichiometric, implying that PTC1 acts by a catalytic mechanism<bibr rid="b13"/>. The details of this interaction are currently unknown, although the homology of PTC1 to bacterial proton-driven transmembrane molecular transporters offers the intriguing possibility that PTC1 regulates the distribution of a small molecule that alters SMO activity<bibr rid="b14"/>. Hedgehog ligand binding to PTC1 relieves this inhibition through a mechanism that is also poorly understood.</p>
    <p>In <i>Drosophila</i>, the pathway from SMO activation to the processing, activation and translocalization of the CI transcriptional mediator involves the activity of a large protein complex including the kinesin-like protein costal 2 (<scientific id="35653" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">COS2</scientific>), the serine/threonine protein kinase fused (FU), and suppressor of fused (SUFU)<bibr rid="b1 b15"/>. However, work involving species from fish to mice shows that these components might not be utilized in a conserved manner in mediating vertebrate intracellular hedgehog signalling, even between these relatively close species. For example, the function of COS2 as a negative regulator of hedgehog signalling in the absence of hedgehog ligand seems to be conserved in fish<bibr rid="b16"/> but not in mice<bibr rid="b17"/> (for a review, see Ref. <bibrinl rid="b1">1</bibrinl>).</p>
    <p>In addition, numerous unforeseen intracellular components that modify hedgehog signalling have been revealed through forward genetic screens. In vertebrates, mutations in three separate intraflagellar transport proteins - wimple (IFT172), flexo (hypomorphic allele of polaris, IFT88) and the intraflagellar transport motor protein KIF3a - result in similar neural phenotypes in mice, with characteristics of both reduced and excess hedgehog signalling<bibr rid="b18 b19"/>. Another link between neural hedgehog signalling and intracellular vesicle transport was revealed by the <i>open-brain</i> mouse mutant, which has the loss-of-function <i>Rab23</i> allele, a member of the Rab family of GTPases<bibr rid="b20"/>. Interestingly, many of the proteins mentioned above are associated with cilia function, suggesting a role for this structure in hedgehog signalling<bibr rid="b19 b21"/>. Mutants that result in the loss of cilia, such as those associated with oral-facial-digital syndrome 1 (<i>OFD1</i>) loss-of-function and <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=209900">Bardet-Biedl syndrome</weblink>, have defects in patterning reminiscent of reduced hedgehog signalling<bibr rid="b22"/> and, consistent with this hypothesis, a recent study has demonstrated that SMO can localize to cilia in response to hedgehog pathway stimulation<bibr rid="b23"/>. Moreover, mutations of amino acid residues in SMO that prevent this localization result in a functionally inactive form of SMO. With the discovery that the three GLI proteins and the negative regulator SUFU are located at the distal tips of the cilia in addition to the nucleus, it seems likely that the cilia function as localized mediators of hedgehog signal propagation<bibr rid="b24"/>. Certainly the presence of primary non-motile cilia on most CNS neurons allows for the possibility that hedgehog signalling utilizes this vestigial structure<bibr rid="b25"/>.</p>
    <crosshd>Patterning the ventral spinal cord</crosshd>
    <p>Our greatest understanding of the function of hedgehog signalling as a morphogen in the vertebrate nervous system has come from analysis of the mouse and chick spinal cord, where SHH is expressed by the most ventral cells, the floor plate (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). In this setting, SHH shows all the characteristics of a morphogen: it acts at a distance from the point source in a concentration-dependent manner and acts directly on the recipient cell without any relay mechanism<bibr rid="b9 b26 b27 b28 b29"/>.</p>
    <p>The first studies supporting the role of SHH as a morphogen came from <i>in vitro</i> culture assays utilizing intermediate regions of chick embryo spinal cord that were collected prior to the obvious establishment of dorsoventral identity. When these explants were exposed to controlled levels of recombinant SHH, it was found that particular ventral spinal cord identities could be induced, based on the concentration of SHH<bibr rid="b27"/>. Importantly, different concentrations of SHH were sufficient to induce specific ventral spinal cord neuronal populations. For example, whereas the lowest levels of SHH could induce intermediate ventral identities, such as <deflistr rid="df3">V0, V1 and V2 interneurons</deflistr> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>), higher concentrations were required to induce motor neurons and the highest concentration was necessary to induce the most ventral neuronal cell types: the V3 interneurons and the floor plate.</p>
    <p><i>In vivo</i> evidence for SHH's action as a morphogen during neural development has been best demonstrated by two studies employing cell-autonomous methods to render cells unresponsive to SHH in mice and chicks<bibr rid="b9 b28"/>. In these experiments, SHH responsiveness has been ablated either through the expression of a delta-loop deletion mutant of PTC1 that renders cells expressing this mutant protein insensitive to the endogenous ligand, or through the generation of <i>Smo</i> -null chimaeras, in which SHH non-responsive cells were intermingled with wild-type cells in the neural tube. In the delta-loop PTC1 studies, in addition to the cell-autonomous effects expected in ventral progenitors lacking SHH signalling, there was also a marked non-cell-autonomous repatterning around mutant groups of cells. This phenomenon is probably due to a local skewing in the gradient of SHH, because it is able to travel unimpeded across cells that express the mutant PTC1 receptor.</p>
    <p>The SHH gradient in the spinal cord is not a passive source-sink gradient but is instead maintained by active mechanisms that regulate the activity, release, transport and retention of SHH protein across the neuroepithelium (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>). These modulators of SHH signalling include sightless/skinny hedgehog, an acetyltransferase that modifies SHH by adding palmitic acid to its amino (N) terminus<bibr rid="b30 b31"/>, as well as proteins such as dispatched, You/Scube2 and tout-velu (the mouse homologue of this gene is exostosin (EXT1)) that control the release and transport of hedgehog proteins in different species<bibr rid="b32 b33 b34 b35"/>. In addition, several other extracellular proteins limit the range of SHH movement such as PTC1 and hedgehog interacting protein (HIP)<bibr rid="b10 b36"/> (for a more detailed discussion of these components of SHH signalling, see Ref. <bibrinl rid="b2">2</bibrinl>). More recently, a novel extracellular protein CDO (interference hedgehog (IHOG) in <i>Drosophila</i>) and its relative BOC have been found to positively regulate hedgehog signalling through the binding and sequestration of hedgehog ligand, resulting in locally enhanced signalling<bibr rid="b37 b38 b39"/>.</p>
    <p>A fundamental question in development is how the extracellular concentration gradient of a morphogen is translated into the intracellular specification of multiple cell identities (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). It is now clear that all the effects of SHH in ventral spinal cord patterning in mammals are mediated by the combined activity of the three GLI transcription factors<bibr rid="b6 b40"/>. Elegant genetic studies have now exposed both the partially redundant and mainly unique functions of each mouse <i>Gli</i> gene in an <i>in vivo</i> context. Genetic loss-of-function and knock-in studies in which the <i>Gli</i> genes have been ablated<bibr rid="b41 b42 b43 b44"/> or genetically substituted<bibr rid="b6 b45"/> have shown that, at least in the context of ventral neural tube specification, GLI3 functions primarily as a transcriptional repressor whereas GLI1 and GLI2 function as activators<bibr rid="b6 b41 b42 b43 b44 b45 b46 b47"/>. Positive SHH signalling induces the formation of GLI2 and (to a lesser extent) GLI3 activators, which induce transcription of the constitutive activator GLI1. By contrast, absence of the ligand allows for the formation of the GLI3 repressor. Other regions of the nervous system employ these same activator/repressor combinations to different extents in transforming SHH signals into cellular responses.</p>
    <p>Primarily GLI2 activator function is essential for the induction of the ventral-most cell types, including the floor plate and V3 interneurons<bibr rid="b41 b43 b44"/>, whereas the proper regulation of GLI3 repressor levels controls the number and location of V0, V1 and V2 progenitors<bibr rid="b6 b42"/>. Situated between these extremes are motor neurons, the differentiation of which is regulated by a combination of GLI2 and GLI3. In contrast to the positive activity of SHH signalling in the floor plate and V3 interneurons<bibr rid="b6 b45"/>, SHH seems to function primarily as a negative regulator in intermediate ventral spinal cord patterning<bibr rid="b42"/>. Interestingly, it does so by suppressing cues that would otherwise direct progenitors to adopt a dorsal fate, rather than by specifying ventral fate directly<bibr rid="b52"/>.</p>
    <p>Downstream of the GLI proteins, hedgehog signalling mediates cell specification through the simultaneous repression of Class I homeodomain transcription factors (for example, <i>Pax6</i>, <i>Pax7</i>, <i>Irx3</i> and <i>Dbx1/2</i>) and the induction of Class II homeodomain transcription factors (for example, <i>Nkx2.2</i>, <i>Nkx6.1</i>) in ventral spinal cord progenitors<bibr rid="b48 b49 b50"/>. Cross-repressive interactions between these resultant homeodomain transcription factors then act to sharpen the expression boundaries and subsequently direct cells to differentiate into specific subtypes<bibr rid="b48"/>. The mechanistic link between the GLI transcriptional activators and repressors and the resultant homeodomain pattern has yet to be elucidated. It seems likely that differential promoter affinities and region-specific cofactors aid in translating the overlying combinatorial GLI transcription factor gradients into cellular decisions. In addition, recent electroporation studies in chick embryos have suggested that GLI transcriptional mediators can be cumulatively integrated over time to achieve appropriate homeodomain transcription factor patterning<bibr rid="b51"/>.</p>
    <p>That positive SHH signalling is not required for the generation of some ventral cell types is evident from compound mutants of <i>Shh</i> or <i>Smo</i> and <i>Gli3</i> (Refs <bibrinl rid="b9">9</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b52">52</bibrinl>), as well as mouse embryos deficient in all three GLI proteins<bibr rid="b6 b40"/>. In these mutants, some aspects of ventral spinal cord patterning are maintained, with the exception of the floor plate, V3 interneurons and some motor neuron populations. Therefore, GLI activators are not required to induce these intermediate ventral cell types. With regard to the potential signalling pathways responsible for the induction of the cell types for which SHH signalling is not required, both fibroblast growth factor (FGF) and retinoid signalling have been proposed to have a role in ventral patterning in the neural tube. FGF signalling seems to regulate the timing of ventral cell type specification. Electroporation studies and explant work from chick embryos have suggested that retinoids provide the positive regulation of class I homeodomain proteins that complement the actions of SHH in repressing dorsal neural identities and inducing class II gene expression ventrally<bibr rid="b53"/>.</p>
    <p>A surprising set of findings indicate that hedgehog signalling might not only control ventral progenitor specification, but could also act to maintain the proper stratification of these distinct progenitor domains in their appropriate neuronal pools. Genetic removal of hedgehog signalling results in disorganization of the ventral progenitor pools, with extensive cell mixing disrupting the normal segregation of progenitors along the dorsoventral extent of the neural tube<bibr rid="b6 b9 b40"/>. This suggests that, in addition to a role in ventral subtype specification, hedgehog signalling through GLI transcriptional mediators controls sorting of distinct progenitor groups, perhaps by modulating cell affinities. At present, however, there is only evidence from <i>in vitro</i> neuroepithelial cultures to connect SHH signalling with known adhesion mechanisms associated with hetero- and <deflistr rid="df4">homotopic cell sorting</deflistr><bibr rid="b54"/>.</p>
    <crosshd>Cell specification throughout the neuraxis</crosshd>
    <p>Beyond the spinal cord, the role of hedgehog signalling in ventral patterning in the nervous system has been examined in several different regions of the developing vertebrate CNS, including the forebrain, midbrain and cerebellum. Work from each of these fields is reviewed here with a focus on novel insights into regional differences in the patterning functions of SHH (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3</figr>).</p>
    <p><bi>Forebrain</bi>. The developing forebrain, comprising the telencephalon and diencephalon, has multiple sources of SHH signal that influence patterning and specification in this region. In the embryonic telencephalon, SHH is expressed within the mantle of the <deflistr rid="df5">medial ganglionic eminence</deflistr> (MGE), the preoptic area and the amygdala, whereas the expression of SHH in the embryonic diencephalon is found within the hypothalamus and in the <deflistr rid="df6">zona limitans interthalamica</deflistr> (ZLI), a band of cells at the border between the ventral and dorsal thalami<bibr rid="b7 b55"/>. Interestingly, the onset of the expression of <scientific id="21869" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene"><i>Nkx2.1</i></scientific>, an early marker of ventral forebrain specification, precedes the expression of SHH in the forebrain, implying that ventral specification in these structures is the result of a non-neural source of SHH signalling<bibr rid="b56"/>. <i>In vitro</i> work with chick embryos and conditional gene ablation in mice have supported this notion, suggesting that SHH sources from the node and the prechordal plate, which underlies the developing telencephalic primorium, pattern the ventral forebrain<bibr rid="b57 b58"/>. Furthermore, it seems that by the time SHH is expressed in the telencephalon, the initial patterning of this structure is complete and SHH signalling is required for the maintenance of ventral-most telencephalic gene expression<bibr rid="b59"/>. Abrogation of SHH signalling after this initial patterning stage leads to a decrease in <i>Nkx2.1</i> expression in MGE progenitors and a resulting reduction in the two major populations of cortical interneurons derived from this region<bibr rid="b60"/>. The reiterative use of SHH signalling to effect diverse telencephalic functions highlights the importance of the specific competence of the neural progenitors receiving and integrating the signal. In the telencephalon, temporal changes in the competence of cells to respond to SHH signals seem to be the rule rather than the exception. In basic ventral telencephalic patterning, it seems that the timing of exposure to SHH is crucial in establishing medial versus lateral ganglionic eminence fates<bibr rid="b61"/>. Likewise, in oligodendrocyte specification and population of the <deflistr rid="df7">adult proliferative niche</deflistr>, only specific cohorts of cells that respond to SHH within discrete time windows follow these maturation programs, as will be described below.</p>
    <p>Recently, the protein <scientific id="14725" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene">Megalin</scientific>, which is a low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein, was shown to specifically effect ventral telencephalic patterning through what seems to be a SHH mediated mechanism<bibr rid="b62"/>. Loss of <i>Megalin</i> results in the loss of ventrally-derived interneurons and oligodendrocytes in the mouse forebrain. The phenotype seen in these mice is reminiscent of that observed in mutants in which SHH signalling in the telencephalon was conditionally ablated at embryonic day (E) 9 by the removal of <i>Smo</i> using a Cre/LoxP system driven by the telencephalon-specific gene <i>Foxg1</i> (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b57">57</bibrinl>). The group that originally identified Megalin proposed that its role in SHH signalling might be to function as a SHH co-receptor<bibr rid="b63"/>. More recently, others have argued that its effects are indirect and act through an increase in bone morphogenetic protein signalling, which then acts to attenuate SHH signalling<bibr rid="b62"/>. Nevertheless, whether as a result of direct or indirect effects, these findings show that SHH signalling in the telencephalon is specialized at least in its requirement for Megalin.</p>
    <p>Another unique characteristic of SHH signalling in telencephalic development is its role in the specification of the dorsal cortical midline, which later gives rise to the hippocampal primordium and midline choroid plexus epithelium<bibr rid="b64 b65"/>. This activity is in marked contrast to the role of SHH in the spinal cord, in which loss-of-function mutations in the hedgehog pathway have no obvious effects on patterning of the dorsal progenitor domains<bibr rid="b45"/>. The mechanism of SHH's dorsal action in the telencephalon, in addition to whether its actions are direct or indirect, through the modulation of other key signalling centres, is presently unclear.</p>
    <p>Another interesting aspect of telencephalic hedgehog signalling that contrasts with its action in the spinal cord is the apparent absence of GLI activator function in the specification of most telencephalic progenitors. <i>Gli1<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Gli2<super>-/-</super></i> double-null mutant mice have no major telencephalic defects<bibr rid="b41"/>, and most of the patterning defects of the <i>Shh</i> -null mice can be rescued by removing the repressor form of GLI3 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b65">65</bibrinl>). This implies that a gradient of the repressor form of GLI3 is primarily important for telencephalic cell specification, whereas the spinal cord uses the full complement of GLI activator and repressor forms to specify ventral and intermediate cell types. Perhaps this is not surprising given that the telencephalon is exclusively derived from the <deflistr rid="df8">alar plate</deflistr>, whereas the GLI activators seem generally to be linked to the specification of basal plate progenitors. The fact that the dorsoventral patterning is rescued in <i>Shh<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Gli3<super>-/-</super></i> and <i>Smo<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Gli3<super>-/-</super></i> compound mutants suggests that, as in the spinal cord, positive regulators independent of SHH must also regulate ventral telencephalic patterning. <scientific id="14179" type="gene" dbtype="entrezgene"><i>Fgf8</i></scientific> and retinoids seem to both be likely candidates to mediate this patterning<bibr rid="b66 b67"/>. Reminiscent of SHH's role in controlling FGF8 expression in the midbrain-hindbrain boundary, recent work suggests that FGF signalling can mediate ventral patterning independently of hedgehog signalling in the telencephalon<bibr rid="b68"/>. Specifically, unlike <i>Shh<super>-/-</super></i> mice, in which the loss of ventral patterning can be reversed by the compound removal of <i>Gli3</i> (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b65">65</bibrinl>), no improvement in the ventral telencephalic pattern is seen in fibroblast growth factor receptor 1/3 conditional mutants when <i>Gli3</i> gene function is also reduced (that is, <i>Fgfr1<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Fgfr3<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Gli3<super>+/-</super></i>)<bibr rid="b68"/>. Several other papers have shown that SHH indirectly regulates <i>Fgf8</i> transcription through modulation of the GLI3 repressor. This suggests that FGF signalling functions as a positive regulator of ventral telencephalic patterning, whereas SHH signalling functions negatively to prevent dorsalization of ventral telencephalic domains.</p>
    <p>SHH signalling in the ventral diencephalon has long been associated with the ventral separation of the eye fields, most obviously demonstrated by the cyclopia seen in SHH loss-of-function mutants<bibr rid="b8 b69"/>. Numerous studies have implicated SHH in patterning multiple aspects of the visual system, including the retina, optic chiasm and optic stalk<bibr rid="b70 b71 b72"/>. With regards to dorsoventral patterning in the diencephalon, SHH signalling has been associated with the ventral expression of PAX2, as well as the ventral repression of PAX6 - a master regulator of eye development, which is required for the separation of the bilaterally positioned eye fields<bibr rid="b73"/>. That GLI activity is the mediator of patterning in this region is indicated by the partial absence of the diencephalon seen in <i>Gli1<super>-/-</super></i>; <i>Gli2<super>-/-</super></i> double mutants<bibr rid="b41"/>.</p>
    <p>With regard to more dorsal regions of the diencephalon, recent studies of <i>SHH</i> in the chicken ZLI have elucidated a novel mechanism of SHH-induced neural cell specification as well as a role for SHH signalling in patterning. Interestingly, the mechanisms of SHH signalling at the ZLI seem akin to the actions of <i>Drosophila</i> hedgehog in anterior-posterior compartments of the wing imaginal disc. The ZLI, which expresses <i>SHH</i> along its entire dorsoventral extent, splits the prethalamus anteriorly from the posterior thalamus. These abutting diencephalic regions are patterned by the same ZLI SHH source, yet they acquire distinct regional gene expression fates, implying that the two diencephalic regions have a differential competence. <i>In ovo</i> electroporation studies in chick embryos have shown that the homeobox gene <i>IRX3</i>, expressed posterior to the ZLI, creates a state of thalamic competence, such that misexpression of <i>IRX3</i> in the prethalamic compartment allowed ZLI-derived <i>SHH</i> to induce dorsal thalamic gene expression profiles ectopically<bibr rid="b74"/>. The diverse responses of these two adjacent compartments to an identical SHH source illustrates the importance of region-specific factors in generating functional diversity from a single protein expressed widely across the neuraxis. So, just as the interpretation of SHH signals seems in some contexts to rely on changes in temporal competence, here differential regional gene expression mediates differential spatial competence in the manner in which specific tissues respond to SHH.</p>
    <p><bi>Midbrain, hindbrain, cerebellum</bi>. Although the role of the isthmic organizer molecule FGF8 in anterior-posterior patterning of the mid/hindbrain region has been studied extensively, the role of SHH in dorsoventral patterning of the region and its later functions in cerebellum development have only recently been addressed. Studies of SHH and GLI function in the midbrain and rhombomere 1 (r1), a segment of the hindbrain, have uncovered the temporal requirements for SHH signalling and shown a distinct differential regulation of the GLI2/3 activators and the GLI3 repressor in patterning this region. Based on gain-of-function studies mainly carried out in the chick and analysis of the early embryonic (before E11) defects in <i>Shh</i> -null mutant mice it became clear that, as in the spinal cord, SHH signalling through GLI2 is both necessary for the induction of particular ventral cell types in the midbrain/r1, and sufficient to induce certain cell types, at least in combination with FGF signalling<bibr rid="b43 b75 b76 b77 b78 b79"/>.</p>
    <p>A recent study used conditional mutagenesis of <i>Smo</i> and <i>Gli2</i> to determine the functional repertoire of SHH at different stages of mid/hindbrain development<bibr rid="b80"/>. SHH signalling through the GLI2 activator was found to be required before E11 to induce many, but not all ventral cell types. GLI1 and GLI3 probably also contribute to the induction of ventral cell types. Unlike the spinal cord, in which GLI3 has only a small role in patterning intermediate regions, in the tectum (dorsal midbrain) and cerebellum (derived from dorsal r1), regulation of the GLI3 repressor by SHH signalling was found to be crucial, and this requirement continues past E11. At least part of the function of SHH signalling through GLI3 in these regions is to maintain <i>Fgf8</i> expression, thereby providing a mechanism to coordinate patterning in the anterior-posterior axis as well.</p>
    <p>In the developing cerebellum, <i>Shh</i> begins to be expressed in Purkinje cells at around E17, and signals both to the outer granule layer and to nearby <deflistr rid="df9">bergmann glia</deflistr><bibr rid="b81"/>. Furthermore, SHH is both necessary and sufficient for the induction of granule cell proliferation<bibr rid="b81 b82 b83 b84 b85 b86"/>, which is a largely postnatal event that is required for cerebellum <deflistr rid="df10">foliation</deflistr>. GLI2 was found to be the primary GLI protein required in this process, although GLI1 probably has a minor redundant role<bibr rid="b81 b86"/>. In a recent study, an allelic series of viable conditional mutants in <i>Gli2</i> and <i>Smo</i> were constructed to address the role of SHH in regulating morphogenesis of the cerebellum by controlling growth of the granule cell layer<bibr rid="b86"/>. It was found that mutants with reduced SHH signalling have reduced foliation, with a pattern that reflects the normal progression of folia formation, whereas a mutant with excess SHH signalling forms an extra fold, the position of which is conserved in the normal rat cerebellum. These results indicate that SHH might act as a permissive factor for foliation by inducing granule cell proliferation, whereas a different pathway could determine the pattern of folia.</p>
    <crosshd>Additional functions of hedgehog signalling</crosshd>
    <p><bi>The generation of oligodendrocytes</bi>. Hedgehog signalling has been implicated in the specification and subsequent development of oligodendrocytes (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>), the glial component of the CNS responsible for the myelination of axon tracts. In accordance with the requirement for hedgehog signalling in ventral patterning, studies have noted that the earliest identifiable cells of the oligodendrocyte precursor cell (OPC) lineage are derived from the ventral ventricular zone in the spinal cord and forebrain<bibr rid="b87 b88 b89"/>. Ectopic expression of recombinant SHH protein in the chick dorsal spinal cord induces the formation of ectopic OPCs<bibr rid="b87 b89"/>. Furthermore, using function-blocking antibodies, a window of development during which SHH is required for OPC specification was delineated<bibr rid="b87"/>. A possible molecular link between SHH signalling and OPC specification was revealed with the cloning of the basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) transcription factors <i>Olig1</i> and <i>Olig2</i> (Refs <bibrinl rid="b90">90</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b91">91</bibrinl>). These two genes were not only induced by SHH, but were also closely associated with oligodendrocyte development and, in gain-of-function mutants, acted to promote OPC formation<bibr rid="b121"/>. <i>Olig1</i>; <i>Olig2</i> double knockout mice have no oligodendrocytes at E18.5, indicating that these two SHH-induced genes are both necessary and sufficient for oligodendrocyte formation<bibr rid="b92 b93"/>.</p>
    <p>Studies of the telencephalic regulation of oligodendrogenesis have added further details to the picture of hedgehog signalling in OPC specification. <i>Nkx2.1</i> -null mice, which lack most telencephalic <i>Shh</i> expression, have a complete loss of early oligodendrocyte markers, with the exception of the amygdala region that continues to express <i>Shh</i> in the mutant background<bibr rid="b55 b94"/>. Gain-of-function experiments using a <i>Shh</i> -expressing retrovirus at E9.5 gave rise to mature oligodendrocytes at postnatal day 21 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b55">55</bibrinl>). Similar experiments performed in <i>Nkx2.1</i> nulls were capable of rescuing the absence of early OPC markers, suggesting that telencephalic <i>Shh</i> is indeed important for oligodendrocyte development. These findings also indicate that hedgehog signalling might work independently of <i>Nkx2.1</i> function to specify oligodendrocytes, possibly acting directly by continued upregulation of the <i>Olig</i> genes.</p>
    <p>As in the spinal cord, where the ventral neuronal patterning activity of SHH requires the presence of additional inductive cues, recent evidence indicates that FGF might act positively in the induction of OPCs. Two separate <i>in vitro</i> studies have suggested a role for SHH and FGF in inducing oligodendrocytes. <i>In vitro</i> analysis indicated that both SHH and FGFs could induce oligodendrocytes in neocortical cultures<bibr rid="b95"/>. Blocking the hedgehog and FGF pathways using cyclopamine and PD173074 respectively showed that, whereas the FGF pathway leading to OPC formation is hedgehog-independent, the hedgehog pathway requires a basal level of FGF pathway activation. Similarly, neurocortical neurosphere cultures from E13.5 progenitors, which do not give rise to OPCs <i>in vivo</i>, can give rise to these cells in the presence of an FGF-containing medium<bibr rid="b96"/>. At least part of this effect seems to be the result of an FGF-mediated upregulation of endogenous <i>Shh</i> transcripts in neurosphere cultures. As for other instances of interaction between these two pathways, the complex regulatory interactions involved have yet to be fully appreciated, although their function seems to be intertwined in many contexts.</p>
    <p><bi>Control of embryonic proliferation</bi>. Overexpression studies have demonstrated the ability of SHH to promote proliferation in both neural and non-neural tissues<bibr rid="b97 b98 b99"/>. Notably, the competence of neuroblasts to proliferate in response to hedgehog signalling seems to be regulated both temporally and spatially. Transgenic-mediated ectopic expression of SHH in the mouse early embryonic dorsal neural tube led to neural <deflistr rid="df11">hyperplasia</deflistr> at E12.5 but was unable to increase proliferation above wild-type levels at E18.5 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b99">99</bibrinl>). Furthermore, comparison of conditional <i>Smo</i> mutants with <i>Shh</i> nulls in the mid/hindbrain has shown that SHH is mainly required for proliferation before E9 (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b80">80</bibrinl>). The precise response of neural cells to SHH seems to be related to their mitotic state. Exposure to hedgehog signalling during the peak of neurogenesis in mice further augmented progenitor proliferation, whereas exposure in the post-neurogenic period seemed to maintain responding cells in an undifferentiated state<bibr rid="b99"/>. During perinatal periods, hedgehog signalling can still stimulate proliferation in cerebellar granule cells and in retinal ganglion cells, long after it can stimulate proliferation in the neural tube. That SHH signalling has a biological role in the regulation of proliferation is suggested by its involvement in disease states such as <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=109400">Gorlin's syndrome</weblink>, in which mutations in <i>Ptc1</i> lead to uncontrolled signalling activity and a predisposition for medulloblastomas<bibr rid="b10"/>.</p>
    <p>Recent studies have begun to explore how hedgehog signalling influences the molecular machinery that controls proliferation. In particular, several new studies have reported how specific downstream effectors are modulated by SHH signalling to regulate the cell cycle. In this regard, work in the mouse cerebellum has implicated <i>N-myc</i> <bibr rid="b100"/>, <i>cyclin D1</i> (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b101">101</bibrinl>), <i>E2f1</i> and <i>E2f2</i> (Ref. <bibrinl rid="b102">102</bibrinl>) as possible links between SHH signalling and cell cycle regulators. Work on the medulloblastoma-inducing effects of <i>N-myc</i> have illustrated in detail the molecular synergy between the SHH and insulin-like growth factor (IGF) signalling pathways, as SHH acts to induce <i>N-myc</i> transcription through GLI proteins, and phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase (PI3-K) stabilizes the <i>N-myc</i> protein product<bibr rid="b103 b104"/>.</p>
    <p>In addition to a role in proliferation and differentiation, SHH signalling also seems to control cell death. Evidence from the spinal cord, forebrain and mid/hindbrain indicate that the apoptosis caused by the removal of <i>Shh</i> gene function can be suppressed by the removal of <i>Gli3</i>, indicating that the repressor fragment might act as an inducer of apoptosis<bibr rid="b52 b80"/>. In addition, it has recently been suggested that <i>Ptc</i> has a role in mediating cell death through a SMO-independent mechanism<bibr rid="b105"/>.</p>
    <p><bi>Shh and axon guidance</bi>. The expression of <i>Shh</i>, ventrally located and spanning the entire anterior-posterior extent of the neural tube, puts it in an ideal place for mediating axonal pathfinding events (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). An early link between hedgehog signalling and ventral midline crossing was noted for retinal ganglion cell axons, which normally form the optic chiasm as they cross the midline of the diencephalon (for a review, see Ref. <bibrinl rid="b106">106</bibrinl>). Mutations in SHH downstream pathway members disrupt proper crossing in the optic chiasm; at present, however, it is unclear whether this is a direct effect of SHH<bibr rid="b107"/> or is instead a result of the disruption in ventral midline patterning common to many of these mutants. Evidence supporting the latter hypothesis comes from work in zebrafish, where Shh seems to act indirectly through its ability to restrict the expression of various chemorepellent Slit proteins that impede the crossing of several commissural populations<bibr rid="b108"/>. Furthermore, the commissural crossing phenotype resulting from the reduction of hedgehog signalling due to the loss of <i>yot</i> (a zebrafish homologue of <i>Gli2)</i> can be rescued by attenuating <i>slit</i> expression in midline glial cells in the ventral forebrain using <deflistr rid="df12">morpholinos</deflistr><bibr rid="b109"/>.</p>
    <p>So far, the most compelling evidence of a role for SHH as a chemoattractant has come from the identification of its function as a floorplate-derived midline guidance cue for commissural axons, working in conjunction with netrin signalling<bibr rid="b110"/>. Conditional inactivation of <i>Smo</i>, selectively in commissural neurons or following cyclopamine treatment of explant cultures, clearly demonstrates that this guidance effect is mediated through a <i>Smo</i> -dependent mechanism. However, it is not yet apparent whether its role in this context requires the GLI proteins or is mediated through a transcription-independent mechanism. The ability of an acutely presented focal source of SHH to redirect the growth cone of <i>Xenopus</i> spinal axons <i>in vitro</i> in one hour might argue against a requirement for transcription in this context.</p>
    <p>In a striking example of parsimony, recent studies have suggested that immediately after commissural axons have traversed the floorplate, SHH has a subsequent role in directing these axons anteriorly, along the longitudinal axis<bibr rid="b111"/>. This work provides the first example of SHH acting as a chemorepellent. In this context, the investigators argue that this chemorepellent activity is mediated neither through PTC nor SMO. Instead, they suggest this mechanism is dependent on non-canonical signalling mediated by HIP, because the removal of HIP by RNA interference in a chick 'open-book' explant assay prevents commissural axons from being directed anteriorly. It seems inevitable that further examples of SHH functioning in axonal guidance will be forthcoming. This aside, perhaps the most pressing unanswered question is how the receipt of a hedgehog signal acts to remodel the cytoskeletal organization of the growth cone in these guidance events. In this regard, it will be interesting to determine whether instances of SHH acting as a chemoattractant versus a chemorepellent represent the modulation of a single transduction mechanism or whether distinct pathways function in these two contexts. The fact that, in a single population of commissurally projecting neurons, chemoattraction requires <i>SMO</i> while chemorepellence requires <i>HIP</i> seems to support the latter hypothesis.</p>
    <p><bi>SHH and adult neural stem cells</bi>. Although the connection between hedgehog signalling and embryonic proliferation has been extensively studied, exciting recent work has pointed to an intriguing role for hedgehog signalling in regulating the proliferation of adult neural progenitors (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). The mammalian forebrain is an excellent system for the analysis of adult neural stem cells because it has two localized areas of postnatal neurogenesis - the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus and the subventricular zone (SVZ) of the lateral ventricles. Whereas the hippocampal progenitors locally populate the hippocampus, the SVZ progenitors migrate along the rostral migratory stream to populate the olfactory bulb. Work in mice has shown that this SVZ niche consists of quiescent (slow-cycling) progenitors, transit-amplifying cells and migrating neuroblasts. Using AraC anti-mitotic treatment to ablate rapidly dividing cells in the precursor and neuroblast lineages, it was shown that astrocyte-like cells could divide to replenish these two populations, indicating that a slowly dividing glial population serves as the SVZ stem cell<bibr rid="b112"/>.</p>
    <p><i>In vivo</i> evidence highlighting the importance of hedgehog signalling in these two postnatal proliferative niches came from conditional genetic loss-of-function studies, viral gain-of-function studies and genetic fate mapping. Conditional removal of <i>Smo</i> in the brain at mid-gestation circumvents the early embryonic patterning defects seen in the <i>Shh</i> nulls and allows postnatal examination of the effects of SHH signalling in the dentate gyrus subgranular zone (SGZ) and SVZ proliferative regions<bibr rid="b59"/>. Both regions showed a marked reduction in the number of proliferating progenitors at 2-3 weeks after birth in these mutants, and the SVZ also showed increased cell death. As a result of these perturbations of the postnatal proliferative niches, the granule cell populations of both the hippocampus and the olfactory bulb were severely depleted. A similar decrease in proliferation was observed in the SVZ of juvenile mice that were administered a one week course of the SHH signalling inhibitor cyclopamine, and in the hippocampus of mice that had this inhibitor injected directly into the same region<bibr rid="b113 b114"/>.</p>
    <p>In a series of experiments with interesting clinical implications, artificial stimulation of the hedgehog signalling pathway in the rodent forebrain led to increases in neural progenitor proliferation in both the SVZ and the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus. Activation of hedgehog signalling was achieved either through adenoviral delivery of the N-terminal active fragment of SHH<bibr rid="b113"/>, or through the use of a small-molecule hedgehog agonist that upregulates signalling in hedgehog responsive tissues through interactions with <i>Smo</i> <bibr rid="b59"/>. This suggests that enhancing hedgehog signalling might be effective as a means of promoting neural repair.</p>
    <p>Although it seems clear that hedgehog signalling has an essential role in maintaining adult neural progenitor proliferation, the downstream mechanistic details are still largely unknown. Genetic inducible fate mapping (GIFM) studies in mice<bibr rid="b115"/> have begun to illuminate the developmental history and cell-type specificity of SHH signalling in these proliferative niches<bibr rid="b116"/>. Using <i>Gli1</i> as a marker of hedgehog responding cells, it was definitively shown that quiescent and transit-amplifying stem cells in the adult SVZ and SGZ normally receive GLI activator signalling. Furthermore, the quiescent cells expressing GLI1 continue to give rise to neurons that populate the olfactory bulb and hippocampus for over a year and are multipotent. In addition, it seems that the SVZ and SGZ niches are formed sequentially towards the end of embryonic forebrain development. With regard to the cellular mediators of this process, analysis has shown that periventricular astrocytes, the characterized SVZ stem cell population, express not only <i>Gli1</i> but also other components of the hedgehog signalling cascade<bibr rid="b114"/>. <i>In vitro</i> analysis of dissociated cortices of <i>Gli2</i> and <i>Gli3</i> mutants indicates that these genes could in part mediate the role of hedgehog in adult progenitor proliferation<bibr rid="b117"/>; however, further <i>in vivo</i> experiments will be necessary to accurately assign function to these genes. In addition to these issues, it will be interesting to better understand the source of the hedgehog signals that act in the two proliferative niches, as well as the instructive events in receiving cells that are directed by these signals. Finally, given the dichotomy between the proliferative response to SHH and its role in maintaining the adult stem cell niche, it will be interesting to determine whether this differential response reflects different mechanisms of SHH action or different functional effects in discrete lineages within the stem cell niche.</p>
    <crosshd>Concluding remarks</crosshd>
    <p>Hedgehog signalling in the mammalian nervous system has now been studied for over a decade. During this period our mechanistic understanding of the extrinsic and intrinsic regulators of hedgehog signalling has increased exponentially. Similarly, beyond its role in ventral patterning, hedgehog signalling is now known to have multiple iterative roles throughout development, including (as described above) its role in dorsal fate specification, the regulation of oligodendrogenesis, stem cell maintenance and axon pathfinding. It seems likely that a great deal more information will be forthcoming regarding the role of this multifaceted signalling pathway. Three areas of future research that are likely to prove interesting are: further understanding how the levels and duration of hedgehog signalling are modulated by recipient cells; understanding how hedgehog signalling interacts with other signalling pathways; and examining how hedgehog signalling influences brain function in the adult animal.</p>
    <p>Given the role of hedgehog proteins as both morphogens and mitogens, the fact that this pathway is under exquisite regulation is perhaps not surprising. That this regulation seems to be intimately tied in vertebrates to proteins that control transport in cilia was, however, not anticipated. Whether this indicates that the vestigial cilia found on many cell types are required for hedgehog signalling is a particularly interesting conundrum to solve.</p>
    <p>Considering the multifunctional uses of the hedgehog signalling pathway, it seems likely that it will interact with others in a context dependent fashion. For example, evidence has already suggested an interaction between the hedgehog and Notch signalling pathways in the developing cerebellum<bibr rid="b118"/>.</p>
    <p>Several groups have reported that the expression of hedgehog ligands, most notably SHH, are not limited to development. The patterns of hedgehog ligand expression in the adult are intriguing and could reveal a role for this signalling pathway in the mature animal. Indeed, in <i>Drosophila</i>, a recent report reveals that hedgehog has a role in sexual dimorphism, suggesting that male and female brains might be partially distinct in the way that they utilize hedgehog signalling<bibr rid="b119"/>. Whatever the future holds, it seems certain that further research into hedgehog signalling will uncover more surprises.</p>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <deflist id="df1">
        <term>Morphogen</term>
        <defn>
          <p>A secreted factor that can induce more than two different cell fates over a sheet of cells in a concentration-dependent manner by forming a gradient.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df2">
        <term>Mitogen</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Any factor that promotes proliferation.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df3">
        <term>V0-V3 interneuron domains</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Subdomains of the ventral spinal cord that give rise to specific populations of interneurons.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df4">
        <term>Homotopic cell sorting</term>
        <defn>
          <p>The sorting of populations of cells that possess similar adhesion properties.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df5">
        <term>Medial ganglionic eminence</term>
        <defn>
          <p>(MGE). A transient proliferative zone in the ventral telencephalon that is both patterned by and ultimately expresses sonic hedgehog. It seems to be the origin of most cortical interneurons, as well as a subpopulation of oligodendrocytes.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df6">
        <term>Zona limitans intrathalamica</term>
        <defn>
          <p>(ZLI). An embryonic structure that is positioned at the boundary between the dorsal and ventral thalamus and acts as an organizing centre, at least partially due to its expression of SHH.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df7">
        <term>Adult proliferative niche</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Select regions within the telencephalon in which postnatal neurogenesis occurs.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df8">
        <term>Alar plate</term>
        <defn>
          <p>The dorsal aspect of the developing neural plate/tube.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df9">
        <term>Bergmann glia</term>
        <defn>
          <p>A specialized form of radial glia found in the cerebellum that, unlike most radial glia, persists throughout life.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df10">
        <term>Foliation</term>
        <defn>
          <p>The process by which neural tissue is folded into gyri and sulci. This occurs most prominently in the cerebellum of mice and in the cerebral cortex of higher vertebrates, such as ferrets, monkeys and humans.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df11">
        <term>Hyperplasia</term>
        <defn>
          <p>Exuberant proliferation that might or might not be cancerous in nature.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <deflist id="df12">
        <term>Morpholinos</term>
        <defn>
          <p>A modified form of RNA that interferes with translation of the complementary RNA.</p>
        </defn>
      </deflist>
      <linkgrp>
        <linkset name="DATABASES">
          <linksubset name="OMIM">
            <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=209900">Bardet-Biedl syndrome</weblink>
            <weblink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=109400">Gorlin's syndrome</weblink>
          </linksubset>
        </linkset>
        <linkset name="FURTHER INFORMATION">
          <weblink url="http://saturn.med.nyu.edu/research/dg/fishelllab/index.html">Fishell's laboratory</weblink>
          <weblink url="http://saturn.med.nyu.edu/research/dg/joynerlab/">Joyner's laboratory</weblink>
        </linkset>
      </linkgrp>
      <fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
        <!--nrn1990-f1-->
        <figtl>The vertebrate hedgehog signalling pathway.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>The figure shows the canonical hedgehog signalling pathway, from the release of hedgehog protein to the interpretation of hedgehog signalling by downstream transcriptional mediators. In the cell producing the ligand, sonic hedgehog protein (SHH) is acetylated (palmitylation is mediated by the acetylase skinny hedgehog and the cleavage-mediated addition of cholesterol) and released through the action of the membrane-transporter protein dispatched. The SHH gradient is regulated by extracellular proteins (such as You/Scube2 in zebrafish), as well as proteins on the surface of cells situated between those producing and receiving hedgehog signals (for example, patched (PTC1), hedgehog interacting protein (HIP), exostosin (EXT1), CDO (interference hedgehog (IHOG) in <i>Drosophila</i>) and its relative BOC). In the cell receiving the hedgehog ligand, hedgehog signalling components are sequestered to the primary cilia. The hedgehog ligand relieves the constitutive repression of the seven-pass receptor smoothened (SMO) by the twelve-pass receptor PTC in mice. The output of hedgehog signalling is mediated by the modulation of the GLI transcriptional activators GLI2 and GLI3 (GLI2/3A), and the GLI repressor GLI3 (GLI3R). Intracellular modulation of the hedgehog transcriptional cascade includes both positive (wimple, flexo, KIF3A) and negative (Rab23) regulators of hedgehog signalling, components that are also involved in cilia function. The final output of the hedgehog signalling cascade is mediated through the repression of Class I transcription factors (TFs), such as PAX6 and PAX 7 and the activation of Class II transcription factors, such as NKX2.2. The X in the figure refers to the as yet unknown transcriptional repressor that inhibits Class I proteins, which is presumably induced by GLI2/3A and inhibited by GLI3R.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
        <!--nrn1990-f2-->
        <figtl>Sonic hedgehog gradients are translated into unique cell identities through the modulation of GLI activators and repressors.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>The highest concentrations of sonic hedgehog (SHH) result in the production of the GLI transcriptional activator GLI1 (GLI1A) through effects on transcription, the activator GLI2 (GLI2A) through effects on post-transcriptional activation, and the removal of the repressor GLI3 (GLI3R) by inhibition of post-translational cleavage of the full-length form of GLI3. This results in the specification of the floor plate (FP) and V3 interneurons. Lower levels of GLI2A, as well as the removal of GLI3R result in the induction of V2 interneurons and motor neurons (MN). V0 and V1 patterning is controlled largely by the levels of GLI3R. <b>a</b> | Hypothetical relative activities of the primary GLI activators and repressors in the mammalian spinal cord. <b>b</b> | Schematic diagram illustrating (left) the activity of the GLI activators and repressors as well as (right) the position of the ventral populations of neurons generated through the action of hedgehog signalling.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
        <!--nrn1990-f3-->
        <figtl>The utilization of sonic hedgehog differs across the developing neuraxis.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>The figures depict the effects of sonic hedgehog (SHH) expression (red) in the developing mouse CNS. <b>A</b> | Coronal sections through the telencephalon. Throughout embryonic development, SHH signalling expressed in the ventral telencephalon (the medial ganglionic eminence (MGE)) maintains ventral patterning (through NKX2.1 expression) (<b>a</b>), oligodendrocyte specification (<b>b</b>) and proliferation and stem cell maintenance in the subventricular zone (SVZ) and subgranular zone (SGZ) (<b>c</b>). Whether SHH ligand moves from source cells to responding cells by diffusion, active transport or axonal trafficking is presently unclear. <b>Ba</b> | Dorsal (D) view of the neural plate prior to neural tube closure. Early (embryonic day (E) 7.5) SHH signalling is required for splitting the bilateral eye fields. <b>Bb</b> | Sagittal view of the diencephalon. At a slightly later embryonic timepoint, SHH expressed within the zona limitans intrathalamica (ZLI) differentially patterns the anterior-posterior axis of the diencephalon. This is achieved in conjunction with posteriorly expressed IRX3, which alters the competence to respond to SHH. Posterior (P) to the ZLI, SHH inhibits PAX6 transcription, whereas anterior (A) to the ZLI SHH is required for the maintenance of PAX6 expression<bibr rid="b74"/>. <b>Ca</b> | Side view of the developing brain. In the midbrain and cerebellum, SHH expressed in the ventral (V) midline regulates dorsoventral patterning and the expression of the midbrain-hindbrain organizer FGF8 during early development (E8.5-E12). <b>Cb</b> | Saggital section of the cerebellum. From E17.5, SHH expressed by Purkinje cells (inset) regulates proliferation of the granule cells and is required for cerebellar foliation. MHB, midbrain-hindbrain boundary; TF, transcription factor.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
        <!--nrn1990-f4-->
        <figtl>SHH signalling functions in a number of distinct contexts in neural development.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p><b>a</b> | SHH expression is required for the specification of oligodendrocytes through its induction of the basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) transcription factors OLIG1 and OLIG2. <b>b</b> | The SHH ligand also controls multiple aspects of cell proliferation and the survival of neural progenitors. Adult neural stem cells and transit amplifying cells respond to SHH signalling and SHH is required for maintenance of the adult stem cell niche. SHH from Purkinje cells transcriptionally controls the proliferation of granule cells through upregulation of the cell cycle, as well as other proliferation-related proteins, such as N-MYC, cyclin D1 and E2F1/E2F2. SHH suppresses cell death through removal of the GLI repressor GLI3 (GLI3R), and inhibits patched-mediated apoptosis. c | Finally, SHH (red) has recently been shown to have a role in axonal guidance by mediating midline crossing and the longitudinal extension of axons. HIP, hedgehog interacting protein.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
    </objects>
    <ack>
      <p>We would like to thank Sandra Blaess and Alex Schier for their critical reading of this review and their many helpful comments. We would also like to thank the Joyner and Fishell laboratories. A.J. and G.F. are supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health, USA.</p>
    </ack>
    <audecl conflct="no"/>
    <bibl>
      <bib id="b1">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Huangfu</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>K. V.</fnm></refau> <atl>Signaling from Smo to Ci/Gli: conservation and divergence of Hedgehog pathways from <i>Drosophila</i> to vertebrates</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>133</vid>, <ppf>3</ppf>-<ppl>14</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ingham</snm>, <fnm>P. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Hedgehog signaling in animal development: paradigms and principles</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>15</vid>, <ppf>3059</ppf>-<ppl>3087</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jessell</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau><atl>Neuronal specification in the spinal cord: inductive signals and transcriptional codes</atl>. <jtl>Nature Rev. Genet.</jtl><vid>1</vid>, <ppf>20</ppf>-<ppl>29</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b4">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ashe</snm>, <fnm>H. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Briscoe</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The interpretation of morphogen gradients</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>133</vid>, <ppf>385</ppf>-<ppl>394</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b5">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Aza-Blanc</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ramirez-Weber</snm>, <fnm>F. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Laget</snm>, <fnm>M. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Schwartz</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kornberg</snm>, <fnm>T. B.</fnm></refau> <atl>Proteolysis that is inhibited by hedgehog targets Cubitus interruptus protein to the nucleus and converts it to a repressor</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>1043</ppf>-<ppl>1053</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).
<newline/><b>The first paper to recognize that hedgehog signalling is mediated by preventing the constitutive cleavage of CI, the <i>Drosophila</i> homologue of the mammalian GLI proteins.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b6">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bai</snm>, <fnm>C. B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Stephen</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>All mouse ventral spinal cord patterning by hedgehog is Gli dependent and involves an activator function of Gli3</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Cell</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>103</ppf>-<ppl>115</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b7">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Echelard</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Sonic hedgehog, a member of a family of putative signaling molecules, is implicated in the regulation of CNS polarity</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl><vid>75</vid>, <ppf>1417</ppf>-<ppl>1430</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b8">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Chiang</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Cyclopia and defective axial patterning in mice lacking Sonic hedgehog gene function</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl><vid>383</vid>, <ppf>407</ppf>-<ppl>413</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).
<newline/><b>Reports the phenotype of the <i>Shh<super>-/-</super></i> loss-of-function mutant and directly validates the requirement for SHH in ventral patterning of the nervous system.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b9">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wijgerde</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>J. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rule</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>A direct requirement for Hedgehog signaling for normal specification of all ventral progenitor domains in the presumptive mammalian spinal cord</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>2849</ppf>-<ppl>2864</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b10">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Goodrich</snm>, <fnm>L. V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Milenkovic</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Higgins</snm>, <fnm>K. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Scott</snm>, <fnm>M. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Altered neural cell fates and medulloblastoma in mouse patched mutants</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>277</vid>, <ppf>1109</ppf>-<ppl>1113</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b11">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Marigo</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Davey</snm>, <fnm>R. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zuo</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cunningham</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tabin</snm>, <fnm>C. J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Biochemical evidence that patched is the Hedgehog receptor</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>384</vid>, <ppf>176</ppf>-<ppl>179</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b12">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Stone</snm>, <fnm>D. M.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>The tumour-suppressor gene patched encodes a candidate receptor for Sonic hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl><vid>384</vid>, <ppf>129</ppf>-<ppl>134</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b13">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Taipale</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cooper</snm>, <fnm>M. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Maiti</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Beachy</snm>, <fnm>P. A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Patched acts catalytically to suppress the activity of Smoothened</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>418</vid>, <ppf>892</ppf>-<ppl>897</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b14">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>J. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Taipale</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Young</snm>, <fnm>K. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Maiti</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Beachy</snm>, <fnm>P. A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Small molecule modulation of Smoothened activity</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>99</vid>, <ppf>14071</ppf>-<ppl>14076</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b15">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lum</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Beachy</snm>, <fnm>P. A.</fnm></refau> <atl>The Hedgehog response network: sensors, switches, and routers</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>304</vid>, <ppf>1755</ppf>-<ppl>1759</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b16">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Varjosalo</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>S. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Taipale</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Divergence of hedgehog signal transduction mechanism between <i>Drosophila</i> and mammals</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Cell</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>177</ppf>-<ppl>186</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b17">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tay</snm>, <fnm>S. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ingham</snm>, <fnm>P. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Roy</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>A homologue of the <i>Drosophila</i> kinesin-like protein Costal2 regulates Hedgehog signal transduction in the vertebrate embryo</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>132</vid>, <ppf>625</ppf>-<ppl>634</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b18">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Huangfu</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Hedgehog signalling in the mouse requires intraflagellar transport proteins</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl><vid>426</vid>, <ppf>83</ppf>-<ppl>87</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b19">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Huangfu</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>K. V.</fnm></refau> <atl>Cilia and Hedgehog responsiveness in the mouse</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>102</vid>, <ppf>11325</ppf>-<ppl>11330</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b20">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Eggenschwiler</snm>, <fnm>J. T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Espinoza</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>K. V.</fnm></refau> <atl>Rab23 is an essential negative regulator of the mouse Sonic hedgehog signalling pathway</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>412</vid>, <ppf>194</ppf>-<ppl>198</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b21">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Niswander</snm>, <fnm>L. A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Mouse intraflagellar transport proteins regulate both the activator and repressor functions of Gli transcription factors</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>132</vid>, <ppf>3103</ppf>-<ppl>3111</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b22">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ferrante</snm>, <fnm>M. I.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Oral-facial-digital type I protein is required for primary cilia formation and left-right axis specification</atl>. <jtl>Nature Genet.</jtl><vid>38</vid>, <ppf>112</ppf>-<ppl>117</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b23">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Corbit</snm>, <fnm>K. C.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Vertebrate Smoothened functions at the primary cilium</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl><vid>437</vid>, <ppf>1018</ppf>-<ppl>1021</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).
<newline/><b>Complements a number of recent findings (references 20 and 21) showing that genes associated with cilia function are required for hedgehog signalling by providing the first direct evidence that components in the canonical hedgehog pathway are sequestered to cilia in a manner correlated with active hedgehog signalling.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b24">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Haycraft</snm>, <fnm>C. J.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Gli2 and Gli3 localize to cilia and require the intraflagellar transport protein polaris for processing and function</atl>. <jtl>PLoS Genet.</jtl><vid>1</vid>, <ppf>e53</ppf> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b25">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Whitfield</snm>, <fnm>J. F.</fnm></refau><atl>The neuronal primary cilium - an extrasynaptic signaling device</atl>. <jtl>Cell. Signal.</jtl><vid>16</vid>, <ppf>763</ppf>-<ppl>767</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b26">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Roelink</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Floor plate and motor neuron induction by vhh-1, a vertebrate homolog of hedgehog expressed by the notochord</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl><vid>76</vid>, <ppf>761</ppf>-<ppl>775</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).
<newline/><b>The first study to provide compelling evidence that SHH could induce different neuronal cell types based on concentration alone, strongly supporting the idea that SHH acted as a morphogen in the patterning of the ventral nervous system.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b27">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Roelink</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Floor plate and motor neuron induction by different concentrations of the amino-terminal cleavage product of sonic hedgehog autoproteolysis</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl><vid>81</vid>, <ppf>445</ppf>-<ppl>455</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b28">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Briscoe</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jessell</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Struhl</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl>A hedgehog-insensitive form of patched provides evidence for direct long-range morphogen activity of sonic hedgehog in the neural tube</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>1279</ppf>-<ppl>1291</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b29">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Hynes</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>The seven-transmembrane receptor smoothened cell-autonomously induces multiple ventral cell types</atl>. <jtl>Nature Neurosci.</jtl><vid>3</vid>, <ppf>41</ppf>-<ppl>46</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b30">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Chamoun</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Skinny hedgehog, an acyltransferase required for palmitoylation and activity of the hedgehog signal</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl><vid>293</vid>, <ppf>2080</ppf>-<ppl>2084</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b31">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>An acylatable residue of Hedgehog is differentially required in <i>Drosophila</i> and mouse limb development</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl><vid>233</vid>, <ppf>122</ppf>-<ppl>136</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b32">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ma</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Hedgehog-mediated patterning of the mammalian embryo requires transporter-like function of dispatched</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl><vid>111</vid>, <ppf>63</ppf>-<ppl>75</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b33">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bellaiche</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>The</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Perrimon</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl><i>Tout-velu</i> is a <i>Drosophila</i> homologue of the putative tumour suppressor <i>EXT-1</i> and is needed for Hh diffusion</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>394</vid>, <ppf>85</ppf>-<ppl>88</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b34">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kawakami</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>The zebrafish-secreted matrix protein you/scube2 is implicated in long-range regulation of hedgehog signaling</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Biol.</jtl><vid>15</vid>, <ppf>480</ppf>-<ppl>488</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b35">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Woods</snm>, <fnm>I. G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Talbot</snm>, <fnm>W. S.</fnm></refau> <atl>The <i>you</i> gene encodes an EGF-CUB protein essential for Hedgehog signaling in zebrafish</atl>. <jtl>PLoS Biol.</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>e66</ppf> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b36">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Chuang</snm>, <fnm>P. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Vertebrate Hedgehog signalling modulated by induction of a Hedgehog-binding protein</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>397</vid>, <ppf>617</ppf>-<ppl>621</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b37">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tenzen</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>The cell surface membrane proteins Cdo and Boc are components and targets of the Hedgehog signaling pathway and feedback network in mice</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Cell</jtl><vid>10</vid>, <ppf>647</ppf>-<ppl>656</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b38">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yao</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lum</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Beachy</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl>The ihog cell-surface proteins bind Hedgehog and mediate pathway activation</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>125</vid>, <ppf>343</ppf>-<ppl>357</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b39">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhang</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kang</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cole</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yi</snm>, <fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Krauss</snm>, <fnm>R. S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Cdo functions at multiple points in the Sonic Hedgehog pathway, and Cdo-deficient mice accurately model human holoprosencephaly</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Cell</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>657</ppf>-<ppl>665</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b40">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lei</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zelman</snm>, <fnm>A. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kuang</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Matise</snm>, <fnm>M. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Transduction of graded Hedgehog signaling by a combination of Gli2 and Gli3 activator functions in the developing spinal cord</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>3593</ppf>-<ppl>3604</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b41">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Park</snm>, <fnm>H. L.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Mouse <i>Gli1</i> mutants are viable but have defects in SHH signaling in combination with a <i>Gli2</i> mutation</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>127</vid>, <ppf>1593</ppf>-<ppl>1605</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b42">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Persson</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Dorsal-ventral patterning of the spinal cord requires Gli3 transcriptional repressor activity</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl><vid>16</vid>, <ppf>2865</ppf>-<ppl>2878</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b43">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Matise</snm>, <fnm>M. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Epstein</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Park</snm>, <fnm>H. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Platt</snm>, <fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Gli2 is required for induction of floor plate and adjacent cells, but not most ventral neurons in the mouse central nervous system</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>125</vid>, <ppf>2759</ppf>-<ppl>2770</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>)</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b44">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ding</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Diminished Sonic hedgehog signaling and lack of floor plate differentiation in Gli2 mutant mice</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>125</vid>, <ppf>2533</ppf>-<ppl>2543</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b45">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bai</snm>, <fnm>C. B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Gli1 can rescue the <i>in vivo</i> function of <i>Gli2</i></atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>128</vid>, <ppf>5161</ppf>-<ppl>5172</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b46">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bai</snm>, <fnm>C. B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Auerbach</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Stephen</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Gli2, but not Gli1, is required for initial Shh signaling and ectopic activation of the Shh pathway</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>129</vid>, <ppf>4753</ppf>-<ppl>4761</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b47">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pan</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bai</snm>, <fnm>C. B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog signaling regulates Gli2 transcriptional activity by suppressing its processing and degradation</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>26</vid>, <ppf>3365</ppf>-<ppl>3377</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b48">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Briscoe</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pierani</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jessell</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ericson</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>A homeodomain protein code specifies progenitor cell identity and neuronal fate in the ventral neural tube</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>101</vid>, <ppf>435</ppf>-<ppl>445</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b49">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Briscoe</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Homeobox gene <i>Nkx2.2</i> and specification of neuronal identity by graded Sonic hedgehog signalling</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl><vid>398</vid>, <ppf>622</ppf>-<ppl>627</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b50">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ericson</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Pax6 controls progenitor cell identity and neuronal fate in response to graded Shh signaling</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl><vid>90</vid>, <ppf>169</ppf>-<ppl>180</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b51">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Stamataki</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ulloa</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tsoni</snm>, <fnm>S. V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mynett</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Briscoe</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>A gradient of Gli activity mediates graded Sonic Hedgehog signaling in the neural tube</atl>. <jtl>Genes Dev.</jtl> <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>626</ppf>-<ppl>641</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b52">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Litingtung</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Chiang</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <atl>Specification of ventral neuron types is mediated by an antagonistic interaction between Shh and Gli3</atl>. <jtl>Nature Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>979</ppf>-<ppl>985</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).
<newline/><b>Revealed that, rather than being simply an instructive factor, much of SHH's role in establishing ventral pattern in the spinal cord is conducted using its ability to prevent dorsalization of the spinal cord through the removal the GLI repressor GLI3.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b53">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Novitch</snm>, <fnm>B. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wichterle</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jessell</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sockanathan</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>A requirement for retinoic acid-mediated transcriptional activation in ventral neural patterning and motor neuron specification</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>81</ppf>-<ppl>95</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b54">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jarov</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>A dual role for Sonic hedgehog in regulating adhesion and differentiation of neuroepithelial cells</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl><vid>261</vid>, <ppf>520</ppf>-<ppl>536</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b55">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Nery</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wichterle</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fishell</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog contributes to oligodendrocyte specification in the mammalian forebrain</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>128</vid>, <ppf>527</ppf>-<ppl>540</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b56">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Shimamura</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hartigan</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Martinez</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Puelles</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rubenstein</snm>, <fnm>J. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Longitudinal organization of the anterior neural plate and neural tube</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>121</vid>, <ppf>3923</ppf>-<ppl>3933</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b57">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fuccillo</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rallu</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fishell</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Temporal requirement for hedgehog signaling in ventral telencephalic patterning</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>5031</ppf>-<ppl>5040</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b58">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gunhaga</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jessell</snm>, <fnm>T. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Edlund</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog signaling at gastrula stages specifies ventral telencephalic cells in the chick embryo</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>127</vid>, <ppf>3283</ppf>-<ppl>3293</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b59">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Machold</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Sonic hedgehog is required for progenitor cell maintenance in telencephalic stem cell niches</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl><vid>39</vid>, <ppf>937</ppf>-<ppl>950</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).
<newline/><b>Directly demonstrated that the adult stem cell niche requires hedgehog signalling for its maintenance. In complementary fashion, two other papers (references 113 and 114) showed that SHH was mitogenic for cells in the adult stem cell niche.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b60">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xu</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wonders</snm>, <fnm>C. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>S. A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog maintains the identity of cortical interneuron progenitors in the ventral telencephalon</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>132</vid>, <ppf>4987</ppf>-<ppl>4998</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b61">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kohtz</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Baker</snm>, <fnm>D. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Corte</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fishell</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Regionalization within the mammalian telencephalon is mediated by changes in responsiveness to Sonic Hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>125</vid>, <ppf>5079</ppf>-<ppl>5089</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b62">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Spoelgen</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>LRP2/megalin is required for patterning of the ventral telencephalon</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>132</vid>, <ppf>405</ppf>-<ppl>414</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b63">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>McCarthy</snm>, <fnm>R. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Barth</snm>, <fnm>J. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chintalapudi</snm>, <fnm>M. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Knaak</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Argraves</snm>, <fnm>W. S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Megalin functions as an endocytic sonic hedgehog receptor</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>277</vid>, <ppf>25660</ppf>-<ppl>25667</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b64">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yoshida</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl><i>Emx1</i> and <i>Emx2</i> functions in development of dorsal telencephalon</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>124</vid>, <ppf>101</ppf>-<ppl>111</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b65">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rallu</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Dorsoventral patterning is established in the telencephalon of mutants lacking both Gli3 and Hedgehog signaling</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>129</vid>, <ppf>4963</ppf>-<ppl>4974</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b66">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Storm</snm>, <fnm>E. E.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Dose-dependent functions of Fgf8 in regulating telencephalic patterning centers</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>133</vid>, <ppf>1831</ppf>-<ppl>1844</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b67">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ribes</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dolle</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Niederreither</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Retinaldehyde dehydrogenase 2 (RALDH2)-mediated retinoic acid synthesis regulates early mouse embryonic forebrain development by controlling FGF and sonic hedgehog signaling</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>133</vid>, <ppf>351</ppf>-<ppl>361</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b68">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gutin</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>FGF signalling generates ventral telencephalic cells independently of SHH</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>133</vid>, <ppf>2937</ppf>-<ppl>2946</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b69">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Schell-Apacik</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>SONIC HEDGEHOG mutations causing human holoprosencephaly impair neural patterning activity</atl>. <jtl>Hum. Genet.</jtl><vid>113</vid>, <ppf>170</ppf>-<ppl>177</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b70">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Huh</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hatini</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Marcus</snm>, <fnm>R. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>S. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lai</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl>Dorsal-ventral patterning defects in the eye of BF-1-deficient mice associated with a restricted loss of shh expression</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl> <vid>211</vid>, <ppf>53</ppf>-<ppl>63</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b71">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Barth</snm>, <fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wilson</snm>, <fnm>S. W.</fnm></refau> <atl>Expression of zebrafish <i>nk2.2</i> is influenced by <i>sonic hedgehog/vertebrate hedgehog-1</i> and demarcates a zone of neuronal differentiation in the embryonic forebrain</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>121</vid>, <ppf>1755</ppf>-<ppl>1768</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b72">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Dakubo</snm>, <fnm>G. D.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Retinal ganglion cell-derived sonic hedgehog signaling is required for optic disc and stalk neuroepithelial cell development</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>130</vid>, <ppf>2967</ppf>-<ppl>2980</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b73">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Macdonald</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Midline signalling is required for Pax gene regulation and patterning of the eyes</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>121</vid>, <ppf>3267</ppf>-<ppl>3278</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b74">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kiecker</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lumsden</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Hedgehog signaling from the ZLI regulates diencephalic regional identity</atl>. <jtl>Nature Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>1242</ppf>-<ppl>1249</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).
<newline/><b>Showed that the expression of SHH in the diencephalon controls anterior-posterior patterning. This is particularly intriguing because, akin to these findings, hedgehog signalling in <i>Drosophila</i> is required for the establishment of posterior segment identity.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b75">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Agarwala</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Aglyamova</snm>, <fnm>G. V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Marma</snm>, <fnm>A. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fallon</snm>, <fnm>J. F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ragsdale</snm>, <fnm>C. W.</fnm></refau> <atl>Differential susceptibility of midbrain and spinal cord patterning to floor plate defects in the talpid2 mutant</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl> <vid>288</vid>, <ppf>206</ppf>-<ppl>220</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b76">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Agarwala</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ragsdale</snm>, <fnm>C. W.</fnm></refau> <atl>A role for midbrain arcs in nucleogenesis</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>129</vid>, <ppf>5779</ppf>-<ppl>5788</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b77">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fedtsova</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Turner</snm>, <fnm>E. E.</fnm></refau> <atl>Signals from the ventral midline and isthmus regulate the development of Brn3.0-expressing neurons in the midbrain</atl>. <jtl>Mech. Dev.</jtl> <vid>105</vid>, <ppf>129</ppf>-<ppl>144</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b78">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ishibashi</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>A sonic hedgehog-dependent signaling relay regulates growth of diencephalic and mesencephalic primordia in the early mouse embryo</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>129</vid>, <ppf>4807</ppf>-<ppl>4819</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b79">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ye</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shimamura</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rubenstein</snm>, <fnm>J. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hynes</snm>, <fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rosenthal</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>FGF and Shh signals control dopaminergic and serotonergic cell fate in the anterior neural plate</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>93</vid>, <ppf>755</ppf>-<ppl>766</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b80">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Blaess</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Corrales</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog regulates Gli activator and repressor functions with spatial and temporal precision in the mid/hindbrain region</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>133</vid>, <ppf>1799</ppf>-<ppl>1809</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b81">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Corrales</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rocco</snm>, <fnm>G. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Blaess</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Guo</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Spatial pattern of sonic hedgehog signaling through <i>Gli</i> genes during cerebellum development</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>5581</ppf>-<ppl>5590</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b82">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Dahmane</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ruiz-i-Altaba</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog regulates the growth and patterning of the cerebellum</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>126</vid>, <ppf>3089</ppf>-<ppl>3100</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b83">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lewis</snm>, <fnm>P. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gritli-Linde</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Smeyne</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kottmann</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog signaling is required for expansion of granule neuron precursors and patterning of the mouse cerebellum</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl> <vid>270</vid>, <ppf>393</ppf>-<ppl>410</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b84">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wallace</snm>, <fnm>V. A.</fnm></refau><atl>Purkinje-cell-derived Sonic hedgehog regulates granule neuron precursor cell proliferation in the developing mouse cerebellum</atl>. <jtl>Curr. Biol.</jtl><vid>9</vid>, <ppf>445</ppf>-<ppl>448</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b85">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wechsler-Reya</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Scott</snm>, <fnm>M. P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Control of neuronal precursor proliferation in the cerebellum by Sonic Hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>22</vid>, <ppf>103</ppf>-<ppl>114</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b86">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Corrales</snm>, <fnm>J. D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Blaess</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mahoney</snm>, <fnm>E. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl>The level of sonic hedgehog signaling regulates the complexity of cerebellar foliation</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>133</vid>, <ppf>1811</ppf>-<ppl>1821</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b87">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Orentas</snm>, <fnm>D. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hayes</snm>, <fnm>J. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dyer</snm>, <fnm>K. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Miller</snm>, <fnm>R. H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog signaling is required during the appearance of spinal cord oligodendrocyte precursors</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>126</vid>, <ppf>2419</ppf>-<ppl>2429</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b88">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pringle</snm>, <fnm>N. P.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Determination of neuroepithelial cell fate: induction of the oligodendrocyte lineage by ventral midline cells and sonic hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Biol.</jtl><vid>177</vid>, <ppf>30</ppf>-<ppl>42</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b89">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Poncet</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Induction of oligodendrocyte progenitors in the trunk neural tube by ventralizing signals: effects of notochord and floor plate grafts, and of sonic hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Mech. Dev.</jtl><vid>60</vid>, <ppf>13</ppf>-<ppl>32</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).
<newline/><b>The first study, along with references 87 and 88, to show that SHH signalling could directly mediate the generation of oligodendrocytes in the spinal cord.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b90">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lu</snm>, <fnm>Q. R.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Sonic hedgehog-regulated oligodendrocyte lineage genes encoding bHLH proteins in the mammalian central nervous system</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl><vid>25</vid>, <ppf>317</ppf>-<ppl>329</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b91">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhou</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Identification of a novel family of oligodendrocyte lineage-specific basic helix-loop-helix transcription factors</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>25</vid>, <ppf>331</ppf>-<ppl>343</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b92">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lu</snm>, <fnm>Q. R.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Common developmental requirement for Olig function indicates a motor neuron/oligodendrocyte connection</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl><vid>109</vid>, <ppf>75</ppf>-<ppl>86</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b93">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhou</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau> <atl>The bHLH transcription factors OLIG2 and OLIG1 couple neuronal and glial subtype specification</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>109</vid>, <ppf>61</ppf>-<ppl>73</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b94">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tekki-Kessaris</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Hedgehog-dependent oligodendrocyte lineage specification in the telencephalon</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>128</vid>, <ppf>2545</ppf>-<ppl>2554</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b95">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kessaris</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jamen</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rubin</snm>, <fnm>L. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Richardson</snm>, <fnm>W. D.</fnm></refau> <atl>Cooperation between sonic hedgehog and fibroblast growth factor/MAPK signalling pathways in neocortical precursors</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>1289</ppf>-<ppl>1298</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b96">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gabay</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lowell</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rubin</snm>, <fnm>L. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Deregulation of dorsoventral patterning by FGF confers trilineage differentiation capacity on CNS stem cells <i>in vitro</i></atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>485</ppf>-<ppl>499</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b97">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Platt</snm>, <fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Censullo</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ruiz i Altaba</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Gli1 is a target of Sonic hedgehog that induces ventral neural tube development</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>124</vid>, <ppf>2537</ppf>-<ppl>2552</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b98">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Turnbull</snm>, <fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Alteration of limb and brain patterning in early mouse embryos by ultrasound-guided injection of Shh-expressing cells</atl>. <jtl>Mech. Dev.</jtl> <vid>75</vid>, <ppf>107</ppf>-<ppl>115</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b99">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rowitch</snm>, <fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Sonic hedgehog regulates proliferation and inhibits differentiation of CNS precursor cells</atl>. <jtl>J. Neurosci.</jtl><vid>19</vid>, <ppf>8954</ppf>-<ppl>8965</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b100">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kenney</snm>, <fnm>A. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cole</snm>, <fnm>M. D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rowitch</snm>, <fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Nmyc upregulation by sonic hedgehog signaling promotes proliferation in developing cerebellar granule neuron precursors</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>130</vid>, <ppf>15</ppf>-<ppl>28</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b101">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kenney</snm>, <fnm>A. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rowitch</snm>, <fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog promotes G<sub>1</sub> cyclin expression and sustained cell cycle progression in mammalian neuronal precursors</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Cell Biol.</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>9055</ppf>-<ppl>9067</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b102">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oliver</snm>, <fnm>T. G.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Transcriptional profiling of the Sonic hedgehog response: a critical role for N-myc in proliferation of neuronal precursors</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl><vid>100</vid>, <ppf>7331</ppf>-<ppl>7336</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b103">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kenney</snm>, <fnm>A. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Widlund</snm>, <fnm>H. R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rowitch</snm>, <fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Hedgehog and PI-3 kinase signaling converge on Nmyc1 to promote cell cycle progression in cerebellar neuronal precursors</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>217</ppf>-<ppl>228</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b104">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sjostrom</snm>, <fnm>S. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Finn</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hahn</snm>, <fnm>W. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rowitch</snm>, <fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kenney</snm>, <fnm>A. M.</fnm></refau> <atl>The Cdk1 complex plays a prime role in regulating N-myc phosphorylation and turnover in neural precursors</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Cell</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>327</ppf>-<ppl>338</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b105">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Thibert</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Inhibition of neuroepithelial patched-induced apoptosis by sonic hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Science</jtl><vid>301</vid>, <ppf>843</ppf>-<ppl>846</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b106">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Culverwell</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Karlstrom</snm>, <fnm>R. O.</fnm></refau> <atl>Making the connection: retinal axon guidance in the zebrafish</atl>. <jtl>Semin. Cell Dev. Biol.</jtl> <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>497</ppf>-<ppl>506</ppl> (<cd year="2002">2002</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b107">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Trousse</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Marti</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gruss</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Torres</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bovolenta</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Control of retinal ganglion cell axon growth: a new role for Sonic hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>128</vid>, <ppf>3927</ppf>-<ppl>3936</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b108">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Strahle</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fischer</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Blader</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Expression and regulation of a netrin homologue in the zebrafish embryo</atl>. <jtl>Mech. Dev.</jtl> <vid>62</vid>, <ppf>147</ppf>-<ppl>160</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b109">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Barresi</snm>, <fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hutson</snm>, <fnm>L. D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chien</snm>, <fnm>C. B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Karlstrom</snm>, <fnm>R. O.</fnm></refau> <atl>Hedgehog regulated Slit expression determines commissure and glial cell position in the zebrafish forebrain</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>132</vid>, <ppf>3643</ppf>-<ppl>3656</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b110">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Charron</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Stein</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jeong</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>McMahon</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tessier-Lavigne</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>The morphogen sonic hedgehog is an axonal chemoattractant that collaborates with netrin-1 in midline axon guidance</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>113</vid>, <ppf>11</ppf>-<ppl>23</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).
<newline/><b>Provides compelling genetic evidence that hedgehog signalling mediates axonal pathfinding across the ventral midline. This was the first study to show that SHH has a role as a chemoattractant.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b111">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bourikas</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Sonic hedgehog guides commissural axons along the longitudinal axis of the spinal cord</atl>. <jtl>Nature Neurosci.</jtl><vid>8</vid>, <ppf>297</ppf>-<ppl>304</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b112">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Doetsch</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Caille</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lim</snm>, <fnm>D. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Garcia-Verdugo</snm>, <fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Alvarez-Buylla</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Subventricular zone astrocytes are neural stem cells in the adult mammalian brain</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>97</vid>, <ppf>703</ppf>-<ppl>716</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b113">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lai</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kaspar</snm>, <fnm>B. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gage</snm>, <fnm>F. H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Schaffer</snm>, <fnm>D. V.</fnm></refau> <atl>Sonic hedgehog regulates adult neural progenitor proliferation <i>in vitro</i> and <i>in vivo</i></atl>. <jtl>Nature Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>21</ppf>-<ppl>27</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b114">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Palma</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau><i>et al</i>. <atl>Sonic hedgehog controls stem cell behavior in the postnatal and adult brain</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>132</vid>, <ppf>335</ppf>-<ppl>344</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b115">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zervas</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Genetic inducible fate mapping in mouse: establishing genetic lineages and defining genetic neuroanatomy in the nervous system</atl>. <jtl>Dev. Dyn.</jtl> <vid>235</vid>, <ppf>2376</ppf>-<ppl>2385</ppl> (<cd year="2006">2006</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b116">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ahn</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Joyner</snm>, <fnm>A. L.</fnm></refau> <atl><i>In vivo</i> analysis of quiescent adult neural stem cells responding to Sonic hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Nature</jtl> <vid>437</vid>, <ppf>894</ppf>-<ppl>897</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).
<newline/><b>Used genetic fate mapping of the hedgehog reporter gene <i>Gli1</i> to demonstrate that adult neural stem cells respond directly to hedgehog signalling.</b></reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b117">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Palma</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ruiz i Altaba</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Hedgehog-GLI signaling regulates the behavior of cells with stem cell properties in the developing neocortex</atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl> <vid>131</vid>, <ppf>337</ppf>-<ppl>345</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b118">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Solecki</snm>, <fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>X. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tomoda</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fang</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hatten</snm>, <fnm>M. E.</fnm></refau> <atl>Activated <i>Notch2</i> signaling inhibits differentiation of cerebellar granule neuron precursors by maintaining proliferation</atl>. <jtl>Neuron</jtl> <vid>31</vid>, <ppf>557</ppf>-<ppl>568</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b119">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Horabin</snm>, <fnm>J. I.</fnm></refau><atl>Splitting the Hedgehog signal: sex and patterning in <i>Drosophila</i></atl>. <jtl>Development</jtl><vid>132</vid>, <ppf>4801</ppf>-<ppl>4810</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b120">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Chen</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Struhl</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Dual roles for patched in sequestering and transducing Hedgehog</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>87</vid>, <ppf>553</ppf>-<ppl>563</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b121">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lu</snm>, <fnm>Q. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cai</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rowitch</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cepko</snm>, <fnm>C. L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Stiles</snm>, <fnm>C. D.</fnm></refau> <atl>Ectopic expression of <i>Olig1</i> promotes oligodendrocyte formation and reduces neuronal survival in developing mouse cortex</atl>. <jtl>Nature Neurosci.</jtl> <vid>4</vid>, <ppf>973</ppf>-<ppl>974</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
