<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?Pub EntList alpha amp beta bull cir cirf copy delta dtri dtrif gamma kappa  mdash mu ndash omega pi plusmn psi rArr rho sect squ squf squshf star starf  trade utri utrif?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "NPG_XML_Article.dtd" [
<!ENTITY illus1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI 35050247//EN" "//snapple/web_d/web/npg/nature/journal/v408/n6815/images/408898aa.0.jpg" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY illus2 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI 35050248//EN" "//snapple/web_d/web/npg/nature/journal/v408/n6815/images/408898ab.0.jpg" NDATA ITEM>
]>
<article id="35050245" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <!--408898a0-->
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Nature</jtl>
    <vol>408</vol>
    <iss>6815</iss>
    <idt>20001221</idt>
    <categ id="categtxt"/>
    <categtxt>In Context</categtxt>
    <pp>
      <spn>898</spn>
      <epn>899</epn>
      <cnt>2</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">0028-0836</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>2000</cpy>
      <cpn>Macmillan Magazines Ltd.</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <doi>10.1038/35050245</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl><topic>Space</topic> Where are they boldly going?</atl>
    <aug>
      <auname>
        <fnm>Tony</fnm>
        <snm>Reichhardt</snm>
        <inits>T</inits>
      </auname>
    </aug>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>NASA administrator Dan Goldin could hardly have started 2000 in a worse
mood. After the embarrassing loss of two Mars missions in a row, the second
just three weeks before Christmas, the space agency braced itself for a long
winter of fact-finding reports, congressional hearings and what-went-wrong
news stories.</p>
    <p>What had gone wrong, it turned out, was the application of Goldin's 'faster,
better, cheaper' slogan, NASA's guiding principle for much of the 1990s. Even
before the last report landed on Goldin's desk, the lesson was clear: his
troops had been focusing on cheaper and faster at the expense of better.</p>
    <p>A year later, the space agency - particularly its space science division,
which had embraced Goldin's credo most enthusiastically - is still coping
with the fallout. Projects started in the early 1990s were found, upon more
realistic examination, to be overstretched and underfunded. And space scientists
watched aghast as NASA science chief Ed Weiler recut his cloth accordingly.
</p>
    <p>Some problems have proved more tractable than others. Projects still in
the planning stage, such as the Space Interferometry Mission to map stars
and search for new planets, scheduled for launch in 2009, have been sent back
to the drawing board to cut costs.</p>
    <p>Others have had their schedules stretched. Realizing that the Jet Propulsion
Laboratory (JPL) in Pasadena, California, might struggle to launch two major
projects in the first quarter of 2001 - the Genesis spacecraft to investigate
the solar wind in February and the Mars Odyssey orbiter in April - NASA
bumped Genesis to June to allow some breathing room. And finalists in the
competition to propose Small Explorer astronomy missions, who usually get
money to hone their ideas, were told that they would have to wait a year for
funding.</p>
    <p>But in other cases Weiler resorted to flat-out cancellation. The Mars programme,
most overextended of all, threw off ballast by scrapping a lander planned
to accompany the 2001 Mars orbiter. Weiler also cancelled a tiny 'nanorover',
built by JPL to fly on Japan's MUSES-C mission to visit an asteroid and return
with samples in 2002; its budget had ballooned from $20 million to $60 million.
And a long-proposed spacecraft to visit distant Pluto and the Kuiper Belt
was shelved indefinitely to preserve the option of funding another ambitious
mission to Jupiter's moon Europa.</p>
    <p>The wave of cancellations has sparked a revolt among planetary scientists,
and the Europa-versus-Pluto decision was challenged by advisory groups who
say that NASA can still have both by taking some of the work away from the
JPL and opening it to outside competition.</p>
    <p>But painful as it has been, this self-examination may do NASA good. The
revamped Mars programme, although less ambitious, is now generally seen as
more realistic. NASA has backed away from a plan to send an orbiter and lander
to the planet every two years, and has pushed a costly and technically challenging
mission to collect and return with samples back a decade, to 2014 at the earliest.
The plan now calls for two modest-sized landers equipped with rovers in 2003,
an orbiter carrying a very high-resolution camera in 2005, then a larger lander
with a mobile laboratory in 2007. These spacecraft would be supplemented by
smaller scouts dispatched to different areas of the planet's surface.</p>
    <p><illusr rid="illus1" align="right"/>The new Mars roadmap is also flexible enough to accommodate
new discoveries. This is especially important in the light of some of NASA's
best news of the year - the results from the Mars Global Surveyor, which
has been mapping the planet's surface. In two papers, Michael Malin and Kenneth
Edgett of Malin Space Science Systems in San Diego reported new evidence of
liquid water in the planet's history. Their camera revealed what may be the
traces of springs in the sides of cliffs, which Malin and Edgett suggest may
have flowed in the very recent past<bibr rid="b1"/>. Other photos show what
appear to be sedimentary deposits, possibly the beds of ancient lakes, laid
down between 3.5 billion and 4.3 billion years ago<bibr rid="b2"/>.</p>
    <p>The first result is controversial, because scientists have great difficulty
explaining how liquid water could exist near the surface of such a cold planet.
"The reason for my scepticism is the physical conditions," says Michael Carr
of the US Geological Survey in Menlo Park, California. But the second finding
is considered the most compelling evidence yet for ancient Martian lakes,
which have been hypothesized for years. Should robotic or human geologists
land on the planet looking for fossils, they now have a better idea of where
to search.</p>
    <p>Scientists will not have to wait long for more data. A gamma-ray spectrometer
onboard the Odyssey orbiter, due to arrive at the planet in October, should
be able to detect hydrogen, and by inference water, within centimetres of
the surface. And the European Space Agency's Mars Express orbiter, set for
launch in 2003, will carry a ground-penetrating radar capable of detecting
water as deep as five kilometres below the surface. Any groundwater, says
Carr, "should really shine like a beacon".</p>
    <p><illusr rid="illus2" align="right"/>Another hopeful sign for NASA came in a field where
it has been much criticized - biological and microgravity research done
by astronauts in orbit. The agency has restructured its programme to play
down experiments on the growth of protein crystals that have produced no conclusive
results, and to focus on fundamental research in gravitational biology and
physics. Buoyed by a few isolated but intriguing results from space shuttle
experiments, where levels of gene expression in cultured cells have changed
under weightless conditions<bibr rid="b3"/>, NASA is looking forward to an
era where astronauts can conduct ongoing laboratory research in orbit for
the first time.</p>
    <p>In fact, the International Space Station has been NASA's most pleasant
surprise of the year. Although many scientists still regard it as a white
elephant, it is the agency's flagship project. And after years of struggle
to get the project underway, the station is now occupied and under construction.
So far, the astronauts have made it look easy. And although there is plenty
of scope for pitfalls, the project's managers could be forgiven a bit of optimism
earlier this month as the station's main solar panels unfolded to create a
new star in the heavens, just in time for Christmas and the dawn of 2001 -
a date with symbolic importance for space aficionados everywhere.</p>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <illus id="illus1" type="eps" entname="illus1" embed="yes" display="print-online">
        <!--408898ab-->
        <?Pub Caret?>
        <caption>
          <p>Red sea? These layered sediments on Mars may have been laid down in water.
</p>
        </caption>
        <credit>NASA/JPL/MALIN SPACE SCIENCE SYSTEMS</credit>
      </illus>
      <illus id="illus2" type="eps" entname="illus2" embed="yes" display="print-online">
        <!--408898ab-->
        <caption>
          <p>Rising star: after years of struggle, the International Space Station is
now occupied, under construction and visible from Earth with the naked eye.
It aims to provide a permanent laboratory in orbit.</p>
        </caption>
        <credit>AP/SHUTTLE MISSION IMAGERY/NEWSMAKERS</credit>
      </illus>
    </objects>
    <bibl>
      <bib id="b1">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Malin</snm>, <fnm>M. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>
Edgett</snm>, <fnm>K. S.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>288</vid>, <ppf>
2330</ppf>-<ppl>2335</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Malin</snm>, <fnm>M. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>
Edgett</snm>, <fnm>K. S.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Science</jtl> <vid>290</vid>, <ppf>
1927</ppf>-<ppl>1937</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Hammond</snm>, <fnm>T. G.</fnm></refau><i>
et al</i>. <jtl>Nature Med.</jtl><vid>5</vid>, <ppf>359</ppf> (<cd year="1999">
1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
<?Pub *0000008914?>
