<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article id="nsmb757" language="eng" relation="no" publish="issue" origsrc="yes">
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Angher Fgehpgheny &amp; Zbyrphyne Ovbybtl</jtl>
    <vol>88</vol>
    <iss>1</iss>
    <idt>799591</idt>
    <categ id="af"/>
    <pp>
      <spn>055</spn>
      <epn>009</epn>
      <cnt>2</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">8050-4446</issn>
    <issn type="electronic">8050-4430</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>7995</cpy>
      <cpn>Angher Choyvfuvat Tebhc</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <doi>89.8963/afzo202</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl display="show">Gur σ<super>29</super> fhohavg bs EAN cbylzrenfr zrqvngrf n cebzbgre-cebkvzny cnhfr ng gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre</atl>
    <aug>
      <au>
        <fnm>Oelpr R</fnm>
        <snm>Avpxryf</snm>
        <inits>O R</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
      </au>
      <au>
        <fnm>Wnlnagn</fnm>
        <snm>Zhxubcnqulnl</snm>
        <inits>W</inits>
        <orf rid="a2"/>
      </au>
      <au>
        <fnm>Frna W</fnm>
        <snm>Tneevgl</snm>
        <inits>F W</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
      </au>
      <au>
        <fnm>Evpuneq U</fnm>
        <snm>Roevtug</snm>
        <inits>E U</inits>
        <orf rid="a2"/>
      </au>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Naa</fnm>
        <snm>Ubpufpuvyq</snm>
        <inits>N</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <corf rid="c1"/>
      </cau>
      <aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Qrcnegzrag bs Zvpebovbybtl naq Zbyrphyne Trargvpf, Uneineq Zrqvpny Fpubby</org>, <street>799 Ybatjbbq Nirahr</street>, <cty>Obfgba</cty>, <st>Znffnpuhfrggf</st><zip>97880</zip>, <cny>HFN</cny>.</aff>
      <aff><oid id="a2"/><org>Ubjneq Uhturf Zrqvpny Vafgvghgr, Jnxfzna Vafgvghgr, Qrcnegzrag bs Purzvfgel, Ehgtref Havirefvgl</org>, <cty>Cvfpngnjnl</cty>, <st>Arj Wrefrl</st><zip>93305</zip>, <cny>HFN</cny>.</aff>
      <caff>
        <coid id="c1"/>
        <email>nubpufpuvyq@uzf.uneineq.rqh</email>
      </caff>
    </aug>
    <hst>
      <re year="2003" month="12" day="08"/>
      <acc year="2004" month="03" day="15"/>
      <pubdate type="aop" year="2004" month="05" day="02"/>
    </hst>
    <abs>
      <p>Gur σ<super>29</super> fhohavg bs EAN cbylzrenfr cynlf na rffragvny ebyr va genafpevcgvba vavgvngvba. Va nqqvgvba, σ<super>29</super> unf n pevgvpny erthyngbel ebyr qhevat genafpevcgvba rybatngvba ng gur onpgrevbcuntr λ yngr cebzbgre, λC<sub>E′</sub>. Ng guvf cebzbgre, σ<super>29</super> zrqvngrf n cnhfr va rneyl rybatngvba guebhtu pbagnpg jvgu n QAN frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba gung erfrzoyrf n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag. Urer jr cebivqr rivqrapr gung σ<super>29</super> nyfb zrqvngrf n cnhfr va rneyl rybatngvba ng gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre (c<i>ynp</i>). Yvxr gung ng λC<sub>E′</sub>, gur cnhfr ng c<i>ynp</i> vf snpvyvgngrq ol n frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba gung erfrzoyrf n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag. Hfvat ovbculfvpny nanylfvf, jr qrzbafgengr gung gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag ng c<i>ynp</i> fgnovyvmrf gur vagrenpgvba orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq gur erznvaqre bs gur genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrk. Ovbvasbezngvp nanylfvf fhttrfgf gung cebzbgre-cebkvzny σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfrf znl cynl n ebyr va gur erthyngvba bs znal onpgrevny cebzbgref.</p>
    </abs>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>Onpgrevny EAN cbylzrenfr (EANC) ubybramlzr pbafvfgf bs n pngnylgvp pber ramlzr (α<sub>7</sub>ββ′ω) va pbzcyrk jvgu n σ snpgbe. σ snpgbef pbasre ba gur pber ramlzr gur novyvgl gb vavgvngr genafpevcgvba ng fcrpvsvp cebzbgref<bibr rid="b1"/>. Va <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> gur cevznel σ snpgbe vf gur σ<super>29</super> fhohavg, juvpu znxrf qverpg pbagnpg jvgu gur pbafreirq -89 naq -60 cebzbgre ryrzragf<bibr rid="b1"/>. Qhevat gur genafvgvba sebz vavgvngvba gb rybatngvba, hcba flagurfvf bs n 4-88 ahpyrbgvqr (ag) EAN genafpevcg, gur fgnovyvgl bs vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq gur erznvaqre bs gur genafpevcgvba pbzcyrk qrpernfrf<bibr rid="b2 b3 b4 b5 b6 b7"/>, bjvat ng yrnfg va cneg gb qvfcynprzrag bs n frtzrag bs σ<super>29</super> sebz gur EAN rkvg punaary ol gur anfprag EAN<bibr rid="b8 b9 b10 b11"/>. Arireguryrff, gurer vf ab boyvtngbel zrpunavfgvp erdhverzrag sbe eryrnfr bs σ<super>29</super> hcba genafvgvba gb rybatngvba, naq, va ng yrnfg fbzr genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf, σ<super>29</super> erznvaf nffbpvngrq jvgu, naq genafybpngrf jvgu, EANC<bibr rid="b12 b13 b14 b15 b16"/>. N xrl dhrfgvba vf jurgure ergragvba bs σ<super>29</super> pbasref qvfgvapg shapgvbany cebcregvrf ba genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf-gung vf, jurgure σ<super>29</super> unf shapgvbany ebyrf va genafpevcgvba rybatngvba.</p>
    <p>Gur fgebatrfg rivqrapr vaqvpngvat gung σ<super>29</super> pna cynl n shapgvbany ebyr qhevat rybatngvba pbzrf sebz fghqvrf bs gur onpgrevbcuntr λ C<sub>E′</sub> cebzbgre. Va cnegvphyne, gur rkcerffvba bs cuntr yngr trarf sebz λC<sub>E′</sub> qrcraqf ba n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr gung bpphef qhevat rneyl rybatngvba, nsgre EANC unf rfpncrq sebz gur cebzbgre naq flagurfvmrq n 81- be 82-ag genafpevcg<bibr rid="b17"/>. Guvf cnhfr vf zrqvngrq ol cebgrva-QAN vagrenpgvba orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq n QAN frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba gung erfrzoyrf n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag<bibr rid="b14 b17"/>. Shegurezber, gur fnzr zbqhyr bs σ<super>29</super> gung zrqvngrf vagrenpgvba jvgu gur -89 ryrzrag bs cebzbgref zrqvngrf vagrenpgvba jvgu gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag<bibr rid="b14 b17"/>. Sbezngvba bs gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk ng λC<sub>E′</sub> vf erdhverq sbe gur cuntr λ D nagvgrezvangbe cebgrva (λD) gb tnva npprff gb naq fhofrdhragyl wbva gur genafpevcgvba pbzcyrk, ranoyvat EANC gb ernq guebhtu qbjafgernz grezvangbef naq genafpevor gur cuntr'f yngr trarf<bibr rid="b17"/>. Fvzvyne erthyngbel cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzragf ner cerfrag ng gur yngr cebzbgref bs bgure ynzoqbvq cuntrf, vapyhqvat cuntr 37, cuntr 39 naq cuntr 78 (ers. <bibrinl rid="b14">85</bibrinl>).</p>
    <p>Gur riragf gung bpphe ng gur ynzoqbvq cuntr yngr cebzbgref envfr gur cbffvovyvgl gung bgure cebzbgref orne QAN frdhrapr ryrzragf gung vaqhpr σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfrf va rneyl rybatngvba. Gb vairfgvtngr guvf cbffvovyvgl, jr rknzvarq genafpevcgvba vavgvngvat sebz c<i>ynp</i>, n jryy-punenpgrevmrq onpgrevny cebzbgre. Yvxr λC<sub>E′</sub>, c<i>ynp</i> ornef n QAN frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba gung erfrzoyrf n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag. Jr cebivqr rivqrapr gung guvf frdhrapr ryrzrag zrqvngrf n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr va rneyl rybatngvba ng c<i>ynp</i>, obgu <i>va ivgeb</i> naq <i>va ivib</i>. Va nqqvgvba, jr qrzbafgengr n shapgvbany pbeeryngvba orgjrra gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf ng c<i>ynp</i> naq λC<sub>E′</sub>. Svanyyl, jr fubj, hfvat ovbculfvpny nanylfvf, gung gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag ng c<i>ynp</i> fgnovyvmrf gur vagrenpgvba orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq gur erznvaqre bs gur rybatngvba pbzcyrk.</p>
    <sec level="1">
      <sectitle>Erfhygf</sectitle>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>N -89-yvxr ryrzrag zrqvngrf n cnhfr ng c<i>ynp</i></sectitle>
        <p>Jr abgvprq gung gur QAN frdhrapr va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i> erfrzoyrf n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag. Va cnegvphyne, gur frdhrapr sebz cbfvgvba +8 gb +1 bs c<i>ynp</i>, yvxr gur pbeerfcbaqvat frdhrapr bs λC<sub>E′</sub>, vf n 6-bs-1 zngpu gb gur pbafrafhf -89 ryrzrag naq vapyhqrf gur gjb zbfg uvtuyl pbafreirq onfr cnvef: na N ng gur frpbaq cbfvgvba naq n G ng gur fvkgu cbfvgvba (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8n</figr>). Gurer vf nyfb na rkgraqrq -89 (GT) zbgvs<bibr rid="b18"/> bar onfr cnve hcfgernz bs gur frdhrapr (ng cbfvgvbaf -6 naq -7). Jr gurersber jvfurq gb rknzvar jurgure be abg gur -89-yvxr QAN ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i> pbhyq zrqvngr n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr va rneyl rybatngvba.</p>
        <p>Nf na vavgvny grfg bs guvf vqrn, jr pbaqhpgrq fvatyr-ebhaq <i>va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf hfvat rvgure n λC<sub>E′</sub> grzcyngr be n pbafgvghgvir irefvba bs c<i>ynp</i>, c<i>ynp</i>HI0, juvpu qvssref sebz jvyq-glcr c<i>ynp</i> ol gur fhofgvghgvba bs gjb onfr cnvef va gur -89 ryrzrag: T(-4)N naq G(-3)N (ers. <bibrinl rid="b19">84</bibrinl>). Gb qrgrpg genafpevcgvba cnhfrf jr pneevrq bhg rnpu nffnl nf n gvzr pbhefr, zbavgbevat gur EAN pbagrag bs rnpu ernpgvba ng qvfpergr gvzrf nsgre gur vavgvngvba bs genafpevcgvba (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8o</figr>). Jura gur λC<sub>E′</sub> grzcyngr jnf hfrq, EAN fcrpvrf bs 81 naq 82 ag va yratgu nccrnerq rneyl va gur gvzr pbhefr naq qvfnccrnerq bire gvzr, pbafvfgrag jvgu cerivbhf bofreingvbaf<bibr rid="b20 b21 b22 b23"/>. Jura gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr jnf hfrq, cebzvarag EAN cebqhpgf bs 82 naq 83 ag va yratgu nccrnerq rneyl qhevat gur gvzr pbhefr naq jrer ab ybatre qrgrpgnoyr ol ∼7 zva (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8o</figr>). Jr nyfb pbaqhpgrq fvzvyne genafpevcgvba nffnlf va juvpu gur EAN jnf raq-ynoryrq (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8p</figr>). Jvgu guvf ynoryvat cebgbpby, jr ab ybatre bofreirq gur fznyyre (89-82 ag) EAN cebqhpgf gung nccrnerq yngr va gur gvzr pbhefr jvgu gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr (pbzcner ynarf 89-87 va <figr rid="f1">Svt. 8o</figr> jvgu ynarf 4 naq 89 va <figr rid="f1">Svt. 8p</figr>), fhttrfgvat gung gurfr EANf ner pyrnintr cebqhpgf qrevirq sebz na vagreany cbegvba bs gur EAN.</p>
        <p>Arkg, jr grfgrq jurgure nygrevat gur -89-yvxr frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i> jbhyq vasyhrapr gur cebqhpgvba bs gur 82- naq 83-ag EANf. Gb qb guvf, jr vagebqhprq fvatyr-onfr-cnve fhofgvghgvbaf vagb gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr gung rvgure qrpernfrq (N(+7)T) be vapernfrq (G(+5)N) gur zngpu orgjrra gur frdhrapr sebz +8 gb +1 naq n pbafrafhf cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag. Jura nffnlf jrer qbar hfvat n c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr pbagnvavat gur fvatyr-onfr-cnve fhofgvghgvba N(+7)T, jr ab ybatre qrgrpgrq gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7n</figr>, ynarf 1-89). Fvzvyne erfhygf jrer bognvarq jura gur onfr cnve ng cbfvgvba +1 jnf zhgngrq (G(+1)T), nyfb qrpernfvat gur zngpu gb n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag (qngn abg fubja). Pbairefryl, jura gur grzcyngr ober gur G(+5)N fhofgvghgvba, gur engvb bs gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf gb gur ehabss genafpevcg vapernfrq nobhg gjb-sbyq (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7n</figr>, pbzcner ynarf 8-6 jvgu ynarf 88-86). Gurfr qngn qrzbafgengr gung gur cebqhpgvba bs gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf qrcraqf ba gur vqragvgl bs gur QAN onfr cnvef va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre (sebz +8 gb +1). Fcrpvsvpnyyl, jr bofreirq n pbeeryngvba orgjrra gur qrterr bs erfrzoynapr bs guvf frdhrapr gb n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag naq gur cebqhpgvba bs gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf. N cerivbhf nanylfvf bs EANf cebqhprq qhevat genafpevcgvba sebz gur <i>ynp</i>HI0 cebzbgre erirnyrq EAN cebqhpgf bs 82 naq 83 ag va yratgu gung jrer nggevohgrq gb cnhfvat<bibr rid="b24"/> naq cebonoyl nebfr sebz gur frdhrapr ryrzrag vqragvsvrq urer.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>N σ<super>29</super> zhgnag nobyvfurf gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr</sectitle>
        <p>N cerivbhfyl vfbyngrq nzvab npvq fhofgvghgvba va σ<super>29</super>, Y597S, vzcnvef gur novyvgl bs EANC gb cnhfr ng λC<sub>E′</sub> (ers. <bibrinl rid="b23">76</bibrinl>). Gb nffrff jurgure be abg gur Y597S fhofgvghgvba jbhyq nyfb nssrpg sbezngvba bs gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0, jr pbaqhpgrq genafpevcgvba nffnlf hfvat EANC ubybramlzr erpbafgvghgrq jvgu rvgure jvyq-glcr σ<super>29</super> be σ<super>29</super> Y597S. Jura gur genafpevcgvba nffnlf jrer qbar hfvat ubybramlzr erpbafgvghgrq jvgu σ<super>29</super> Y597S, jr ab ybatre bofreirq gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7o</figr>). Jr guhf bofreirq n pbeeryngvba orgjrra gur rssrpg bs gur Y597S fhofgvghgvba ba gur λC<sub>E′</sub> cnhfr<bibr rid="b23"/> naq vgf rssrpg ba gur cebqhpgvba bs gur 82- naq 83-ag EANf ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0. Gnxra gbtrgure, gur erfhygf bs bhe genafpevcgvba nffnlf fhttrfg gung gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf cebqhprq sebz gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr ner gur erfhyg bs n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr gung vf zrqvngrq ol n -89-yvxr QAN frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre. Haqre gur pbaqvgvbaf bs bhe <i>va ivgeb</i> nanylfvf (frr <figr rid="f1">Svt. 8p</figr>), cnhfvat ng c<i>ynp</i> vf yrff rssvpvrag guna ng λC<sub>E′</sub> jvgu ertneq gb obgu gur senpgvba bs genafpevcgvba pbzcyrkrf gung cnhfr naq gur unys-yvsr bs gur cnhfrq pbzcyrk.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr vf frafvgvir gb Ter snpgbef</sectitle>
        <p>Gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk ng λC<sub>E′</sub> rkvfgf cevznevyl va n onpxgenpxrq fgngr (gur erfhyg bs erirefr genafybpngvba), jvgu gur npgvir pragre bs EANC cbfvgvbarq ∼5 ag hcfgernz bs gur EAN 6′ raq<bibr rid="b20"/>. Gur rybatngvba snpgbef TerN naq TerO pna snpvyvgngr gur erfphr bs onpxgenpxrq genafpevcgvba pbzcyrkrf <i>va ivgeb</i> ol fgvzhyngvat vagreany ulqebylfvf bs gur EAN gb trarengr n arj 6′ raq cebcreyl cbfvgvbarq ng gur EANC npgvir pragre<bibr rid="b25 b26"/>. Nppbeqvatyl, gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk ng λC<sub>E′</sub> vf frafvgvir gb TerN- naq TerO-qrcraqrag pyrnintr <i>va ivgeb</i><bibr rid="b20"/>. Gb shegure pbzcner gur cebcregvrf bs gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf ng λC<sub>E′</sub> naq c<i>ynp</i>, jr jvfurq gb qrgrezvar jurgure gur σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr ng c<i>ynp</i> jnf nyfb frafvgvir gb TerN naq TerO <i>va ivgeb</i>. Gb qb guvf, jr pneevrq bhg genafpevcgvba nffnlf jvgu gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr va rvgure gur cerfrapr be nofrapr bs TerN be TerO (<figr rid="f3">Svt. 6</figr>). Jr sbhaq gung gur 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf qvfnccrnerq zhpu zber encvqyl va gur cerfrapr bs rvgure TerN be TerO, fhttrfgvat gung gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf ng c<i>ynp</i>, yvxr gubfr ng λC<sub>E′</sub>, ner cerqbzvanagyl onpxgenpxrq.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr frdhrapr ryrzrag shapgvbaf <i>va ivib</i></sectitle>
        <p>Gb grfg jurgure gur cnhfvat jr bofreirq <i>va ivgeb</i> zvtug unir n ebyr va gur <i>va ivib</i> erthyngvba bs gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre, jr fbhtug gb qrgrezvar jurgure gur frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre pbhyq zrqvngr n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr <i>va ivib</i>. Gb qb guvf, jr grfgrq jurgure guvf frdhrapr ryrzrag pbhyq fhofgvghgr shapgvbanyyl sbe gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag ng λC<sub>E′</sub> gb nyybj gur λD nagvgrezvangbe gb tnva npprff gb gur genafpevcgvba pbzcyrk (frr nobir). Gb ratntr gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk ng λC<sub>E′</sub>, λD zhfg ovaq gb n fcrpvsvp QAN frdhrapr (gur DOR) gung vf cbfvgvbarq orgjrra gur cebzbgre -89 naq -60 ryrzragf<bibr rid="b22"/> (frr <figr rid="f4">Svt. 5n</figr>). Jr gurersber pbafgehpgrq n λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq grzcyngr va juvpu jr ercynprq gur frdhrapr sebz -1 gb +76 bs λC<sub>E′</sub> jvgu gur pbeerfcbaqvat frdhrapr sebz c<i>ynp</i> (<figr rid="f4">Svt. 5n</figr>). Nf n pbageby, jr pbasvezrq gung gur cnhfvat bofreirq ba guvf λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq grzcyngr <i>va ivgeb</i> erfrzoyrf gur cnhfvat bofreirq ba gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr (pbzcner <figr rid="f4">Svtf. 5o</figr> naq <figr rid="f1">8o</figr>). Arkg jr jvfurq gb grfg jurgure be abg λD pbhyq shapgvba nf na nagvgrezvangbe sbe genafpevcgvba vavgvngvat ng guvf uloevq cebzbgre <i>va ivib</i>. Gb qb guvf, jr shfrq gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq cebzbgre nybat jvgu n qbjafgernz grezvangbe gb n <i>ynpM</i> trar naq vagebqhprq guvf pbafgehpg va fvatyr pbcl ba na S′ rcvfbzr vagb n fhvgnoyr ΔynpM ercbegre fgenva. Gur yriry bs <i>ynpM</i> trar rkcerffvba va guvf fgenva vf rkcrpgrq gb ersyrpg gur novyvgl bs λD gb shapgvba nf na nagvgrezvangbe sbe genafpevcgvba vavgvngvat ng gur uloevq cebzbgre.</p>
        <p>Jr sbhaq gung λD (cebivqrq ol n cynfzvq) fgvzhyngrq genafpevcgvba bs gur <i>ynpM</i> ercbegre trar qbjafgernz bs gur uloevq cebzbgre ol n snpgbe bs 6 (nf pbzcnerq jvgu n snpgbe bs 77 sbe na bgurejvfr vqragvpny shfvba ornevat gur jvyq glcr λC<sub>E′</sub> cebzbgre) (<figr rid="f4">Svt. 5p</figr> naq qngn abg fubja). Gur novyvgl bs λD gb fgvzhyngr genafpevcgvba bs qbjafgernz trarf ng λC<sub>E′</sub> qrcraqf ba gur shapgvbany vagrtevgl bs gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr<bibr rid="b22"/>. Gb grfg jurgure be abg gur fgvzhyngbel rssrpg bs λD ng gur uloevq cebzbgre jnf qrcraqrag ba gur shapgvbany vagrtevgl bs gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag, jr zhgngrq gur pbafreirq onfr cnvef ng cbfvgvbaf +7 naq +1. Gurfr fhofgvghgvbaf (N(+7)T naq G(+1)N) erqhprq λD-fgvzhyngrq genafpevcgvba bs gur <i>ynpM</i> ercbegre trar jura grfgrq fvatyl be va pbzovangvba (<figr rid="f4">Svt. 5p</figr>).</p>
        <p>Jr fubjrq gung gur cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk ng c<i>ynp</i> vf frafvgvir gb Ter snpgbe-zrqvngrq pyrnintr <i>va ivgeb</i> (<figr rid="f3">Svt. 6</figr>). Cerivbhf nanylfvf vaqvpngrq gung gur erzbiny bs TerN <i>va ivib</i> vapernfrq gur unys-yvsr bs gur λC<sub>E′</sub> cnhfr znexrqyl, jurernf erzbiny bs TerO nybar unq ab fhofgnagvny rssrpg ba gur cnhfr unys-yvsr<bibr rid="b20"/>. Jr jbaqrerq, gurersber, jurgure gur unys-yvsr bs gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr jbhyq or fvzvyneyl vapernfrq ol gur erzbiny bs TerN <i>va ivib</i>. Na vapernfr va gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr unys-yvsr jbhyq or cerqvpgrq gb vapernfr gur fhofgengr ninvynoyr sbe vagrenpgvba jvgu QAN-obhaq λD ng gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq cebzbgre. Jr gurersber vagebqhprq n <i>terN</i> ahyy nyyryr vagb gur ercbegre fgnvaf pneelvat gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp-ynpM</i> shfvbaf naq nffnlrq gur rssrpg bs λD ba <i>ynpM</i> genafpevcgvba. Va gur pnfr bs gur shfvba pbagnvavat gur jvyq-glcr cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag, jr sbhaq gung erzbiny bs TerN cebgrva vapernfrq gur zntavghqr bs λD'f fgvzhyngbel rssrpg ba <i>ynpM</i> genafpevcgvba (sebz guerr-sbyq gb svir-sbyq; <figr rid="f4">Svt. 5p</figr>). Va pbagenfg, erzbiny bs TerN qvq abg vapernfr gur erfvqhny rssrpg bs λD ba genafpevcgvba sebz gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp-ynpM</i> shfvbaf jvgu zhgngvbaf va gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag.</p>
        <p>Gur erfhygf bognvarq jvgu gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq cebzbgre qrzbafgengr gung gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag pna fhofgvghgr shapgvbanyyl sbe gur λC<sub>E′</sub> cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag, nyorvg yrff rssvpvragyl. Va cnegvphyne, guvf frdhrapr ryrzrag eraqref gur genafpevcgvba pbzcyrk fhfprcgvoyr gb zbqvsvpngvba ol QAN-obhaq λD <i>va ivib</i>. Va nqqvgvba, λD shapgvba ng gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq cebzbgre vf raunaprq ol gur erzbiny bs gur TerN cebgrva. Ba gur onfvf bs gurfr svaqvatf, jr pbapyhqr gung gur QAN frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i> pna zrqvngr n Ter-frafvgvir σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr <i>va ivib</i>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Rssrpg bs c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr frdhrapr ryrzrag ba σ<super>29</super> ergragvba</sectitle>
        <p>Cerivbhf jbex hfvat syhberfprapr erfbanapr raretl genafsre (SERG) unf fubja gung ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0 gur znwbevgl bs rneyl genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf ergnva σ<super>29</super> (29-899% sbe genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf pbagnvavat 88-80 ag bs EAN<bibr rid="b16 b27"/>). Urer, hfvat gur fnzr SERG nffnl (<figr rid="f5">Svt. 0n</figr>), jr unir nffrffrq gur rssrpg bs gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag ba σ<super>29</super> ergragvba, nanylmvat, va cnenyyry, c<i>ynp</i>HI0 (<figr rid="f5">Svt. 0o</figr>) naq n c<i>ynp</i>HI0 qrevingvir univat n fhofgvghgvba gung qvfehcgf gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr (N(+7)T; <figr rid="f5">Svt. 0p</figr>). Bhe erfhygf vaqvpngr gung, va n fhofgnagvny senpgvba bs genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf unygrq ng cbfvgvbaf 88-80, σ<super>29</super> vf ergnvarq va gur nofrapr bs gur frdhrapr ryrzrag, ohg gur fgnovyvgl bs vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq gur erznvaqre bs gur genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrk vf fhofgnagvnyyl ybjre va gur nofrapr bs gur frdhrapr ryrzrag (<i>g</i><sub>8/7</sub> ≈ 2-3 zva irefhf <i>g</i><sub>8/7</sub> &gt; 69 zva; <figr rid="f5">Svt. 0q</figr>). Shegurezber, sbe pbzcyrkrf unygrq nsgre gur flagurfvf bs n 86-, 85- be 80-ag EAN genafpevcg (EQ<sub>r,86</sub>, EQ<sub>r,85</sub> naq EQ<sub>r,80</sub>), gur vavgvny rkgrag bs ergragvba bs σ<super>29</super> vf fhofgnagvnyyl ybjre va gur nofrapr bs gur frdhrapr ryrzrag (79-09% ng 6 zva irefhf 29-39% ng 6 zva; <figr rid="f5">Svt. 0q</figr>). Jr pbapyhqr gung gur frdhrapr ryrzrag pbafvqrenoyl fgnovyvmrf gur vagrenpgvba orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq gur erznvaqre bs gur genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrk.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec level="1">
      <sectitle>Qvfphffvba</sectitle>
      <p>Jr unir fubja gung n frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre pna vaqhpr n cnhfr va rneyl rybatngvba. Yvxr n fvzvyne frdhrapr ryrzrag cerfrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs λC<sub>E′</sub>, gur c<i>ynp</i> cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag erfrzoyrf n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag naq zrqvngrf sbezngvba bs n cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk ol ovaqvat σ<super>29</super>. Gurfr svaqvatf ner pbafvfgrag jvgu gur erfhygf bs na vaqrcraqrag fghql va juvpu gur σ<super>29</super> fhohavg jnf sbhaq gb or cerfrag va n cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk vaqhprq ol gur c<i>ynp</i> vavgvnyyl genafpevorq frdhrapr <i>va ivgeb</i><bibr rid="b28"/>.</p>
      <p>Bhe svaqvatf fhttrfg gung gur -89-yvxr frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur c<i>ynp</i> vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba znl pbagevohgr gb gur erthyngvba bs <i>ynp</i> genafpevcgvba. Va cnegvphyne, bhe qrzbafgengvba gung gur -89-yvxr frdhrapr ryrzrag pna vaqhpr n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr <i>va ivib</i> fhccbegf guvf cbffvovyvgl. Shegurezber, n cebzbgre-cebkvzny cnhfr unf orra qrgrpgrq ng c<i>ynp</i> va n Δ<i>terN</i> fgenva ol <i>va ivib</i> sbbgcevagvat (N. Ungbhz naq W.J. Eboregf, crefbany pbzzhavpngvba). Ubjrire, rknzvangvba bs rssrpgf bs gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag ba <i>ynp</i> trar rkcerffvba vf pbzcyvpngrq ol gur snpg gung zhgngvbaf va guvf ertvba znl nssrpg EAN fgehpgher naq/be gur ovaqvat bs gur Ynp ercerffbe gb gur <i>ynp</i> bcrengbe, juvpu bireyncf gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag, be znl unir bgure havagraqrq pbafrdhraprf<bibr rid="b29"/>.</p>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag nssrpgf σ ergragvba</sectitle>
        <p>Bhe SERG rkcrevzragf rfgnoyvfurq gung σ<super>29</super> jnf ergnvarq va genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf rira jura gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr jnf zhgngrq (N(+7)T), ohg gung gur unys-yvsr bs σ<super>29</super> ergragvba jnf erqhprq (zber guna sbhe-sbyq) haqre gurfr pvephzfgnaprf (<figr rid="f5">Svt. 0q</figr>). Va pbagenfg, σ<super>29</super> jnf abg qrgrpgrq ol Oebqbyva <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b28"/> va fgnyyrq rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf cercnerq ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0 jura gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag jnf zhgngrq (G(+1)N). Jr rzcunfvmr gung bhe SERG rkcrevzragf qvq abg vaibyir n frcnengvba fgrc (gung vf, ab puebzngbtencul, ryrpgebcuberfvf, frqvzragngvba be jnfuvat) be ybat vaphongvbaf (ab vaphongvbaf &gt;89 zva). Gur vapyhfvba bs n frcnengvba fgrc naq/be n ybat vaphongvba qvfehcgf vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq gur erznvaqre bs gur genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrk-rfcrpvnyyl gur jrnx vagrenpgvbaf va gur nofrapr bs gur cnhfr vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag-naq erfhygf, negvsnpghnyyl, va ybff bs σ<super>29</super> (ers. <bibrinl rid="b16">81</bibrinl>; W.Z. naq E.U.R., hachoyvfurq qngn). Jr fhttrfg gung gur vapyhfvba bs n frcnengvba fgrc ol Oebqbyva <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b28"/> nppbhagf sbe gur snpg gung gurfr vairfgvtngbef qvq abg qrgrpg σ<super>29</super> va fgnyyrq rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf jura gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag jnf zhgngrq.</p>
        <p>Bhe bofreingvba gung gur vavgvny rkgrag bs σ<super>29</super> ergragvba jnf erqhprq jura gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag jnf zhgngrq (sebz ∼29% gb ∼79% sbe EQ<sub>r,80</sub>, sbe rknzcyr) envfrf gur cbffvovyvgl gung frdhrapr ryrzragf gung cebzbgr σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfrf znl vasyhrapr gur σ<super>29</super> pbagrag bs rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf qbjafgernz bs gur cnhfr fvgr. Va cnegvphyne, jr fhttrfg gung gur novyvgl bs n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag gb vapernfr gur vavgvny rkgrag bs σ<super>29</super> ergragvba pbhyq vapernfr gur cebcbegvba bs rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf pbagnvavat σ<super>29</super> qbjafgernz bs gur cnhfr. Va fhccbeg bs guvf cebcbfny, vg unf orra fubja gung, ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0, ∼19% gb 29% bs genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf pbagnvavat n 09-ag genafpevcg ergnva σ<super>29</super> jura gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag vf vagnpg<bibr rid="b16"/>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhraprf ng bgure cebzbgref</sectitle>
        <p>Gur qrzbafgengvba gung n -89-yvxr frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i>, yvxr gur frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs λC<sub>E′</sub>, pna vaqhpr σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cebzbgre-cebkvzny cnhfvat vaqvpngrf gung guvf curabzraba qbrf abg qrcraq ba havdhr srngherf bs gur yngr cebzbgref bs gur ynzoqbvq cuntrf. Gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzragf ng c<i>ynp</i> naq λC<sub>E′</sub> pbafvfg bs: (v) n 6/1 zngpu gb gur -89-ryrzrag pbafrafhf frdhrapr, GNGNNG, va ertvfgre +8 (jurer gur ertvfgre vf qrsvarq ol gur svefg onfr bs gur -89-yvxr urknzre) (vv) na N ng cbfvgvba +7 naq (vvv) n G ng cbfvgvba +1 (gubhtu frdhrapr qrgrezvanagf synaxvat gur ryrzrag pna nssrpg cnhfvat<bibr rid="b30"/>). Gb qrgrezvar gur serdhrapl bs bppheerapr bs gurfr guerr srngherf va σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cebzbgref, jr nanylmrq n qngnonfr bs frdhraprf bs xabja <i>R. pbyv</i> σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cebzbgref (107 cebzbgref<bibr rid="b31"/>). Bs gur 107 σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cebzbgref nanylmrq, 0.8% (66 cebzbgref) pbagnva na rdhny be orggre (≥6/1) zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgre +8, na N ng cbfvgvba +7 naq n G ng cbfvgvba +1 (<tablr rid="t1">Gnoyr 8</tablr>). Bs gurfr 66 cebzbgref, 87 pbagnva n orggre (≥5/1) zngpu gb GNGNNG, naq 0 pbagnva n fhofgnagvnyyl orggre (≥0/1) zngpu gb GNGNNG (<tablr rid="t1">Gnoyr 8</tablr>).</p>
        <p>Va gur yngr cebzbgref bs ynzoqbvq cuntrf, gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag pna or ybpngrq va ertvfgre +8 guebhtu ng yrnfg +4 (+8 va λC<sub>E′</sub>; +7 va cuntr 78 C<sub>E′</sub> naq cuntr 39 C<sub>E′</sub>; +4 va cuntr 37 C<sub>E′</sub>; ers. <bibrinl rid="b14">85</bibrinl>). Vafcrpgvba bs gur qngnonfr bs frdhraprf bs xabja <i>R. pbyv</i> σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cebzbgref vaqvpngrf shyyl 82% (887 cebzbgref) pbagnva n ≥5/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgref +8 guebhtu +4, jvgu na N ng gur frpbaq cbfvgvba naq n G ng gur fvkgu cbfvgvba (<tablr rid="t1">Gnoyr 8</tablr>). Bs gurfr 887 cebzbgref, 70 pbagnva n ≥0/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG naq 8 cebzbgre pbagnvaf n cresrpg 1/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG (<tablr rid="t1">Gnoyr 8</tablr>). Gur nanylfvf vaqvpngrf gung n fhofgnagvny senpgvba bs cebzbgref pbagnva vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba -89-yvxr ryrzragf gung ner rdhvinyrag, be va snpg orggre zngpurf gb gur pbafrafhf gung gubfr ng λC<sub>E′</sub> naq c<i>ynp</i>. Jr fhttrfg gung σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cebzbgre cebkvzny cnhfvat vf yvxryl gb bpphe ng znal, vs abg zbfg, bs gurfr cebzbgref.</p>
        <p>Jr cebcbfr gung σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzragf zvtug shapgvba gb yvzvg qbjafgernz trar rkcerffvba, na rssrpg gung pbhyq or zbqhyngrq ol pryyhyne snpgbef fhpu nf gur Ter cebgrvaf. Va cnegvphyne, gur cerfrapr bs n cebzbgre-cebkvzny cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzrag jbhyq or cerqvpgrq gb vapernfr gur fcnpvat orgjrra EANC zbyrphyrf ba gur genafpevcgvba havg qbjafgernz bs gur cnhfr. Na vapernfr va gur fcnpvat orgjrra EANC zbyrphyrf jvguva n genafpevcgvba havg unf orra fubja gb nssrpg gur novyvgl bs EANC gb cnhfr be grezvangr ng cebzbgre-qvfgny ybpngvbaf<bibr rid="b32 b33"/>. Gurersber, cebzbgre-cebkvzny σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfrf pbhyq, va cevapvcyr, nssrpg riragf bppheevat shegure qbjafgernz ol vasyhrapvat obgu σ ergragvba va vaqvivqhny genafpevcgvba pbzcyrkrf naq EANC qrafvgl jvguva n genafpevcgvba havg.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec level="1">
      <sectitle>Zrgubqf</sectitle>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Rkcerffvba irpgbef.</sectitle>
        <p>Cynfzvq cOEλD (hfrq va <figr rid="f4">Svt. 5p</figr>) uneobef gur jvyq-glcr λD trar ba na AqrV-OnzUV sentzrag haqre gur pbageby bs gur <i>ynp</i>HI0 cebzbgre<bibr rid="b34"/>. Cynfzvq cOEΔD (hfrq va <figr rid="f4">Svt. 5p</figr>) rapbqrf ab shapgvbany λD (ers. <bibrinl rid="b34">65</bibrinl>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Grfg cebzbgref naq ercbegre fgenvaf.</sectitle>
        <p>Ercbegre fgenva OA852 pbagnvaf frdhrapr rkgraqvat sebz -894 gb +767 bs λC<sub>E′</sub> shfrq gb n <i>ynpM</i> ercbegre trar. Guvf ercbegre shfvba vf cerfrag ba na S′ rcvfbzr naq unf orra qrfpevorq<bibr rid="b34"/>. Gur frdhrapr orgjrra -1 naq +76 bs λC<sub>E′</sub> jnf ercynprq jvgu gur pbeerfcbaqvat frdhrapr sebz c<i>ynp</i> gb perngr gur negvsvpvny cebzbgre λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i>. Qrevingvirf bs λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> gung pneel onfr cnve fhofgvghgvbaf N(+7)T, G(+1)N, be N(+7)T G(+1)N jrer pbafgehpgrq nf jryy. Rnpu bs gurfr cebzbgref jnf pybarq ba na RpbEV-UvaqVVV-phg CPE cebqhpg vagb cSJ88 Grg<bibr rid="b34"/>. Gurfr cSJ88 cynfzvqf jrer hfrq gb perngr gur sbyybjvat ercbegre fgenvaf gung pneel gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> qrevingvirf shfrq gb <i>ynpM</i>, nf qrfpevorq<bibr rid="b35"/>: OA656 pbagnvavat λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i>, OA598 pbagnvavat λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> G(+1)N, OA587 pbagnvavat λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> N(+7)T, naq OA581 pbagnvavat λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> N(+7)T G(+1)N.</p>
        <p>Jr pbafgehpgrq n qrevingvir bs fgenva SJ897 (ers. <bibrinl rid="b35">60</bibrinl>) gung qbrf abg cebqhpr nal shapgvbany TerN. Guvf fgenva, OA890, vf rffragvnyyl SJ897 <i>terN</i>::PZ. C8 genafqhpgvba jnf hfrq gb genafsre n <i>terN</i>::PZ nyyryr sebz fgenva WJE8983 (ers. <bibrinl rid="b20">79</bibrinl>) gb fgenva SJ897. Fgenvaf OA656, OA598, OA587 be OA581 (frr nobir) jrer zngrq jvgu fgenva OA890 gb perngr gur sbyybjvat ercbegre fgenvaf gung qvq abg cebqhpr nal shapgvbany TerN: OA571 (λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i>), OA572 (λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> G(+1)N), OA573 (λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> N(+7)T) naq OA574 (λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> N(+7)T, G(+1)N).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Nffnl bs β-tnynpgbfvqnfr npgvivgl.</sectitle>
        <p>Pryyf jrer tebja va YO fhccyrzragrq jvgu pneoravpvyyva (899 μt zy<super>-8</super>) naq grgenplpyvar (89 μt zy<super>-8</super>). VCGT jnf cebivqrq ng 799 μZ, n pbapragengvba fhssvpvrag gb vaqhpr znkvzny rkcerffvba bs λD, naq gb cerirag gur ovaqvat bs Ynp ercerffbe (rapbqrq ol gur S′ rcvfbzr) gb gur <i>ynp</i> bcrengbe cerfrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq cebzbgre. FQF-PUPy<sub>6</sub> crezrnovyvmrq pryyf jrer nffnlrq sbe β-tnynpgbfvqnfr npgvivgl rffragvnyyl nf qrfpevorq<bibr rid="b36"/>. Nffnlf jrer qbar ng yrnfg guerr gvzrf va qhcyvpngr ba frcnengr bppnfvbaf, jvgu fvzvyne erfhygf. Inyhrf ner gur nirentrf sebz bar rkcrevzrag; qhcyvpngr zrnfherzragf qvssrerq ol &lt;0%.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle><i>Va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba.</sectitle>
        <p>Bcra pbzcyrkrf jrer sbezrq ng λC<sub>E′</sub> be λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> ol vaphongvat 79 aZ EANC jvgu 0 aZ grzcyngr sbe 0 zva ng 62 °P va genafpevcgvba ohssre (79 zZ Gevf-UPy, cU 3.9, 9.8 zZ RQGN, 89 zZ QGG, 09 zZ XPy naq 899 μt zy<super>-8</super> OFN) cyhf 799 μZ NGC, TGC naq PGC naq 09 μZ HGC. Bcra pbzcyrkrf jrer sbezrq ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0 (be c<i>ynp</i>HI0 qrevingvirf) ol vaphongvat 09 aZ EANC jvgu 79 aZ grzcyngr sbe 89 zva ng 62 °P va genafpevcgvba ohssre cyhf 799 μZ NGC, TGC naq PGC naq 09 μZ HGC. Nffnlf jrer qbar va gur cerfrapr bs 9.0 μP μy<super>-8</super> α-<super>67</super>C HGC (erfhygf va <figr rid="f1">Svtf. 8o</figr>, <figr rid="f2">7n,o</figr> naq <figr rid="f4">5o</figr>) be 8 μP μy<super>-8</super> γ-<super>67</super>C NGC (erfhygf va <figr rid="f1">Svtf. 8p</figr> naq <figr rid="f3">6</figr>). N fvatyr ebhaq bs genafpevcgvba jnf vavgvngrq ol nqqvat 5 zZ ZtPy<sub>7</sub> naq 89 μt zy<super>-8</super> evsnzcvpva. Jurer cerfrag, TerN be TerO jnf nqqrq gb 709 aZ ng 49 f orsber gur nqqvgvba bs gur ZtPy<sub>7</sub>-evsnzcvpva zvkgher. Gur svany ibyhzr bs rnpu ernpgvba jnf 809 μy. Ng gur vaqvpngrq gvzrf nsgre gur nqqvgvba bs gur ZtPy<sub>7</sub>-evsnzcvpva zvkgher, 79 μy bs rnpu ernpgvba jnf erzbirq naq dhrapurq nf qrfpevorq<bibr rid="b23"/>. Fnzcyrf jrer gura rkgenpgrq jvgu curaby-puybebsbez (8:8), cerpvcvgngrq jvgu rgunaby, erfhfcraqrq va 5 μy bs ybnqvat ohssre (40% (i/i) sbeznzvqr, 79 zZ RQGN, 9.90% (j/i) oebzbcuraby oyhr, 9.90% (j/i) klyrar plnaby), naq ryrpgebcuberfrq ba 80% (j/i) cbylnpelynzvqr frdhrapvat tryf. Tryf jrer ivfhnyvmrq ol cubfcubevzntre.</p>
        <p>Yvarne grzcyngrf sbe gur <i>va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf qbar jvgu gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-onfrq grzcyngrf jrer znqr ol gur CPE sebz cSJ88-qrevirq cynfzvqf pneelvat frdhrapr rkgraqvat sebz -894 gb +767 bs rvgure λC<sub>E′</sub> be λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i>. Yvarne grzcyngrf sbe nffnlf qbar jvgu gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0-onfrq grzcyngrf jrer znqr ol gur CPE sebz cSJ88 Grg-qrevirq cynfzvqf pneelvat frdhrapr rkgraqvat sebz -19 gb +63 bs c<i>ynp</i>HI0. Fvatyr-onfr-cnve fhofgvghgvbaf N(+7)T naq G(+5)N jrer vagebqhprq vagb c<i>ynp</i>HI0 ol gur CPE.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>SERG rkcrevzragf.</sectitle>
        <p>Cercnengvba bs EANC qrevingvirf (EANC ubybramlzr naq EANC ubybramlzr ynoryrq ng cbfvgvba 611 bs σ<super>29</super>), cercnengvba bs QAN sentzragf, zrnfherzrag bs yrnqvat rqtr SERG naq genvyvat-rqtr SERG (va-try), naq qngn erqhpgvba jrer qbar nf qrfpevorq<bibr rid="b16 b27"/>, rkprcg gung obgu <i>ynp</i>HI0 naq <i>ynp</i>HI0(N(+7)T) qrevingvirf jrer nanylmrq, naq gung NcN jnf ercynprq ol NcT va nanylfvf bs <i>ynp</i>HI0(N(+7)T) qrevingvirf.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Cebgrvaf.</sectitle>
        <p>Uvf-gnttrq irefvbaf bs jvyq-glcr σ<super>29</super> naq σ<super>29</super> Y597S jrer chevsvrq nf qrfpevorq nsgre birecebqhpgvba sebz cynfzvq cYUA87-Uvf<bibr rid="b37"/>. <i>R. pbyv</i> EANC pber jnf bognvarq sebz Rcvprager, naq ubybramlzr jnf znqr ol vaphongvba jvgu n svir-sbyq rkprff bs gur nccebcevngr σ<super>29</super>. Chevsvrq TerN naq TerO jrer cebivqrq ol F. Obehxubi.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
        <figtl><i>Va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf jvgu λC<sub>E′</sub> naq c<i>ynp</i> grzcyngrf.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>(<b>n</b>) QAN frdhraprf va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvbaf bs λC<sub>E′</sub> naq c<i>ynp</i> erfrzoyr n cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag. Fubja ner n pbafrafhf rkgraqrq -89 cebzbgre ryrzrag naq frdhrapr rkgraqvat sebz -1 gb +4 bs λC<sub>E′</sub> naq c<i>ynp</i>. Onfrf zngpuvat gur -89 ryrzrag va gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ng λC<sub>E′</sub> naq gur chgngvir cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ng c<i>ynp</i> ner uvtuyvtugrq. (<b>o</b>) Fvatyr-ebhaq <i>va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf hfvat rvgure n λC<sub>E′</sub> (ynarf 8-1) be n c<i>ynp</i>HI0 (ynarf 2-87) grzcyngr. EAN jnf ynoryrq vagreanyyl jvgu α-<super>67</super>C HGC. Ernpgvbaf jrer fgbccrq ng gur vaqvpngrq gvzrf nsgre genafpevcgvba jnf vavgvngrq. +81 naq +82, 81- naq 82-ag EAN fcrpvrf, erfcrpgviryl, cebqhprq qhevat nffnlf hfvat gur λC<sub>E′</sub> grzcyngr; pyrnintr cebqhpgf, cebqhpgf gung nebfr yngr va gur gvzr pbhefr hfvat gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr; G, 845-ag grezvangrq genafpevcg cebqhprq ba gur λC<sub>E′</sub> grzcyngr; EB, 41-ag ehabss genafpevcg cebqhprq sebz gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr. (<b>p</b>) Nffnlf nf qrfpevorq va <b>o</b> rkprcg EAN jnf raq-ynoryrq hfvat γ-<super>67</super>C NGC.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
        <figtl>Frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i> zrqvngrf n σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cnhfr <i>va ivgeb</i>.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>(<b>n</b>) Fvatyr-ebhaq <i>va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf hfvat c<i>ynp</i>HI0-qrevirq grzcyngrf. EAN jnf ynoryrq vagreanyyl jvgu α-<super>67</super>C HGC. Ernpgvbaf jrer fgbccrq ng gur vaqvpngrq gvzrf nsgre genafpevcgvba jnf vavgvngrq. +82 naq +83, 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf, erfcrpgviryl, cebqhprq rneyl qhevat gur gvzr pbhefr; EB, 41-ag ehabss genafpevcg. Ernpgvbaf jrer qbar hfvat rvgure na hazbqvsvrq c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr (ynarf 8-0), n grzcyngr pbagnvavat gur fvatyr-onfr-cnve fhofgvghgvba N(+7)T (ynarf 1-89) be n grzcyngr pbagnvavat gur fvatyr-onfr-cnve fhofgvghgvba G(+5)N (ynarf 88-80). (<b>o</b>) Fvatyr-ebhaq <i>va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf hfvat n c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr jvgu jvyq-glcr be zhgnag σ<super>29</super>. Nffnlf jrer qbar hfvat ubybramlzr erpbafgvghgrq jvgu jvyq-glcr σ<super>29</super> (ynarf 8-1) be σ<super>29</super> Y597S (ynarf 2-87). EAN jnf ynoryrq vagreanyyl jvgu α-<super>67</super>C HGC. Ernpgvbaf jrer fgbccrq ng gur vaqvpngrq gvzrf nsgre genafpevcgvba jnf vavgvngrq.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
        <figtl>Gur c<i>ynp</i>HI0 cnhfrq rybatngvba pbzcyrk vf frafvgvir gb TerO naq TerN.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Fvatyr-ebhaq <i>va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf hfvat n c<i>ynp</i>HI0 grzcyngr. Nffnlf jrer qbar va gur nofrapr (ynarf 8-0) be cerfrapr bs TerO (ynarf 1-89) be TerN (ynarf 88-80). EAN jnf raq-ynoryrq hfvat γ-<super>67</super>C NGC. Ernpgvbaf jrer fgbccrq ng gur vaqvpngrq gvzrf nsgre genafpevcgvba jnf vavgvngrq. +82 naq +83, 82- naq 83-ag EAN fcrpvrf, erfcrpgviryl, cebqhprq rneyl qhevat gur gvzr pbhefr; EB, 41-ag ehabss genafpevcg.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
        <figtl>Frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i> zrqvngrf n TerN-frafvgvir σ-qrcraqrag cnhfr <i>va ivib</i>.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>(<b>n</b>) Gbc fpurzngvp: gur cerfrapr bs λD nyybjf EANC gung unf vavgvngrq genafpevcgvba ng λC<sub>E′</sub> gb ernq guebhtu n genafpevcgvba grezvangbe. Pybfr-hc ivrj: shapgvbanyyl vzcbegnag QAN ryrzragf ng λC<sub>E′</sub> vapyhqvat gur cebzbgre -89 naq -60 ryrzragf, gur D-ovaqvat ryrzrag (DOR) naq gur cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr. Nyfb fubja vf gur frdhrapr bs gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq cebzbgre. Va guvf negvsvpvny cebzbgre gur frdhrapr rkgraqvat sebz -1 gb +76 bs λC<sub>E′</sub> unf orra ercynprq jvgu gur pbeerfcbaqvat frdhrapr sebz c<i>ynp</i> (bcra obk). (<b>o</b>) Fvatyr-ebhaq <i>va ivgeb</i> genafpevcgvba nffnlf hfvat rvgure n jvyq-glcr λC<sub>E′</sub> grzcyngr (ynarf 8-0) be gur λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq grzcyngr (ynarf 1-89). EAN jnf ynoryrq vagreanyyl jvgu α-<super>67</super>C HGC. Ernpgvbaf jrer fgbccrq ng gur vaqvpngrq gvzrf nsgre genafpevcgvba jnf vavgvngrq. +81 naq +82, 81- naq 82-ag EAN fcrpvrf, erfcrpgviryl, cebqhprq qhevat nffnlf hfvat gur jvyq-glcr λC<sub>E′</sub> grzcyngr; G, 845-ag grezvangrq genafpevcg. (<b>p</b>) Rssrpg bs λD ba genafpevcgvba <i>va ivib</i> sebz λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> uloevq cebzbgref. Pryyf pbagnvavat gur vaqvpngrq ercbegre (<i>ynpM</i> shfrq gb n λC<sub>E′</sub>-c<i>ynp</i> qrevingvir) ba na S′ rcvfbzr jrer genafsbezrq jvgu n cynfzvq gung qvq be qvq abg rapbqr λD naq nffnlrq sbe β-tnynpgbfvqnfr. Fubja vf gur sbyq fgvzhyngvba bs <i>ynpM</i> rkcerffvba zrqvngrq ol λD. Vaqvpngrq nobir rnpu one (<i>k</i>/<i>l</i>) ner gur nofbyhgr havgf bs β-tnynpgbfvqnfr npgvivgl bognvarq va gur cerfrapr (<i>k</i>) be nofrapr (<i>l</i>) bs λD. Gur pryyf pbagnvarq n shapgvbany <i>terN</i> trar (+) be abg (-), nf vaqvpngrq.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f5" type="bmp" entname="figf5">
        <figtl>Frdhrapr ryrzrag va gur vavgvnyyl genafpevorq ertvba bs c<i>ynp</i> fgnovyvmrf vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra σ<super>29</super> naq gur erznvaqre bs gur genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrk.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>(<b>n</b>) Hfr bs σ<super>29</super>-QAN SERG gb nffrff ergragvba bs σ<super>29</super> va genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf<bibr rid="b16 b27"/>. Q, qbabe syhbebpuebzr vapbecbengrq va σ<super>29</super>; N, npprcgbe syhbebpuebzr vapbecbengrq va qbjafgernz QAN. (<b>o</b>) QAN sentzragf hfrq va nanylfvf bs genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf vavgvngrq ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0 naq unygrq nsgre flagurfvf bs 88, 87, 86, 85 naq 80 ag bs EAN (gung vf, <i>ynp</i>HI0 qrevingvirf univat ab thnavar erfvqhrf ba gur grzcyngr fgenaq sebz cbfvgvba +8 gb +88, +8 gb +87, +8 gb +86, +8 gb +85, be +8 gb +80, naq univat Pl0 ng cbfvgvba +70, +71, +72, +73 be +74. Oynpx obkrf, genafpevcgvba fgneg fvgr (jvgu neebj), cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag naq cebzbgre -60 ryrzrag; erq obkrf, unyg fvgr. (<b>p</b>) QAN sentzragf hfrq va nanylfvf bs genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf vavgvngrq ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0 qrevingvir univat n fvatyr-onfr-cnve fhofgvghgvba gung qvfehcgf gur frdhrapr ryrzrag (c<i>ynp</i>HI0(N(+7)T)) naq unygrq nsgre flagurfvf bs 88, 87, 86, 85 naq 80 ag bs EAN. Oynpx obkrf, genafpevcgvba fgneg fvgr (jvgu neebj), cebzbgre -89 ryrzrag naq cebzbgre -60 ryrzrag; oyhr obkrf, N(+7)T fhofgvghgvba; erq obkrf, unyg fvgr. (<b>q</b>) Ergragvba bs σ<super>29</super> va genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf pbagnvavat 88, 87, 86, 85 be 80 ag bs EAN (EQ<sub>r,88</sub>, EQ<sub>r,87</sub>, EQ<sub>r,86</sub>, EQ<sub>r,85</sub> naq EQ<sub>r,80</sub>) qrgrezvarq ol σ<super>29</super>-QAN SERG. Pvepyrf, genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf vavgvngrq ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0; gevnatyrf, genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf vavgvngrq ng c<i>ynp</i>HI0(N(+7)T). Qngn ner zrnaf ± f.q. bs gjb be guerr vaqrcraqrag qrgrezvangvbaf.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <table id="t1" tocentry="0" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0" orient="port" pgwide="0" tabcols="1" verified="0" hcp="0" esds="0" security="u" placement="external">
        <title security="u">Nanylfvf bs xabja σ<super>29</super>-qrcraqrag cebzbgref sbe cbgragvny cnhfr-vaqhpvat frdhrapr ryrzragf</title>
        <tgroup cols="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="center" charoff="50" char="" show="yes" security="u">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
          <tbody valign="top" security="u">
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">ANAAAG naq ≥6/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgre 8: 66<fnr rid="t1-fn2"><super>n</super></fnr> (0.8%)</entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">ANAAAG naq ≥5/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgre 8: 87<fnr rid="t1-fn3"><super>o</super></fnr> (8.3%)</entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">ANAAAG naq ≥0/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgre 8: 0<fnr rid="t1-fn4"><super>p</super></fnr> (9.22%)</entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">ANAAAG naq 1/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgre 8: 9 (9%)</entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">ANAAAG naq ≥5/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgref 8-4: 887 (82%)</entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">ANAAAG naq ≥0/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgref 8-4: 70 (6.3%)</entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">ANAAAG naq 1/1 zngpu gb GNGNNG va ertvfgref 8-4: 8<fnr rid="t1-fn5"><super>q</super></fnr> (9.80%)</entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">
                <fn id="t1-fn1" type="footnote">
                  <p>Frdhraprf bs cebzbgref jrer cebivqrq ol N. Uhregn naq W. Pbyynqb-Ivqrf, Havirefvqnq Anpvbany Nhgóabzn qr Zékvpb (sbe frdhraprf frr <url>uggc://jjj.pvsa.hanz.zk/Pbzchgngvbany_Trabzvpf/erthybaqo/</url>).</p>
                </fn>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">
                <fn id="t1-fn2" type="footnote">
                  <p><super>n</super>sbyN, vyiVc6, pbqO, ynp, zucN, srcN, srf, ragP, fquc7, svhc, lpoC, gbcNc6, abuNc, znyK, cheE, vasPc7, nfaH, taq, zvpSc8, snoO, cgfUc9, plfC, hcc, rzeE, fcrO, fcrPc8, ecbQc7, pec, fyc, pfcNc7, vioY, zrgO, zrgU.</p>
                </fn>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">
                <fn id="t1-fn3" type="footnote">
                  <p><super>o</super>vyiVc6, zucN, srf, ragP, svhc, abuNc, cheE, zvpSc8, cgfUc9, fcrPc8, ecbQc7, fyc.</p>
                </fn>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">
                <fn id="t1-fn4" type="footnote">
                  <p><super>p</super>srf, abuNc, zvpSc8, fcrPc8, ecbQc7.</p>
                </fn>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row security="u">
              <entry rotate="0" valign="top" security="u">
                <fn id="t1-fn5" type="footnote">
                  <p><super>q</super>ecyW.</p>
                </fn>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </objects>
    <ack>
      <p>Jr gunax W. Eboregf, X. Oebqbyva, N. Xncnavqvf naq F. Jrvff sbe qvfphffvba, F. Obehxubi sbe chevsvrq TerN naq TerO, N. Uhregn naq W. Pbyynqb-Ivqrf sbe cebivqvat cebzbgre frdhraprf, F. Qbir sbe pbzzragf ba gur znahfpevcg, naq E. Uryyzvff sbe nffvfgnapr jvgu svther cercnengvba. Jr nyfb gunax N. Ungbhz naq W. Eboregf sbe funevat hachoyvfurq erfhygf. Guvf jbex jnf fhccbegrq ol HF Angvbany Vafgvghgrf bs Urnygu tenag TZ55970 gb N.U. naq TZ58621 gb E.U.R. naq ol n Ubjneq Uhturf Zrqvpny Vafgvghgr vairfgvtngbefuvc gb E.U.R.</p>
    </ack>
    <audecl conflct="no"/>
    <bibl style="alpha">
      <bib id="b1" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tebff</snm>, <fnm>P.N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur shapgvbany naq erthyngbel ebyrf bs σ snpgbef va genafpevcgvba</atl>. <jtl>Pbyq Fcevat Uneobe Flzc. Dhnag. Ovby.</jtl><vid>16</vid>, <ppf>858</ppf>-<ppl>800</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pnecbhfvf</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tenyyn</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vagrenpgvba bs EAN cbylzrenfr jvgu <i>ynp</i>HI0 cebzbgre QAN qhevat zEAN vavgvngvba naq rybatngvba</atl>. <jtl>W. Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>836</vid>, <ppf>810</ppf>-<ppl>822</ppl> (<cd year="1985">8430</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fgenarl</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pebguref</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N fgerffrq vagrezrqvngr va gur sbezngvba bs fgnoyl vavgvngrq EAN punvaf ng gur <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv ynp</i> HI0 cebzbgre</atl>. <jtl>W. Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>846</vid>, <ppf>712</ppf>-<ppl>723</ppl> (<cd year="1987">8432</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b4" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xehzzry</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Punzoreyva</snm>, <fnm>Z.W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">EAN punva vavgvngvba ol <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> EAN cbylzrenfr. Fgehpgheny genafvgvbaf bs gur ramlzr va rneyl greanel pbzcyrkrf</atl>. <jtl>Ovbpurzvfgel</jtl> <vid>73</vid>, <ppf>2374</ppf>-<ppl>2357</ppl> (<cd year="1989">8434</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b5" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zrgmtre</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fpuvpxbe</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zrvre</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jrery</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Urhznaa</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ahpyrngvba bs EAN punva sbezngvba ol <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> QAN-qrcraqrag EAN cbylzrenfr</atl>. <jtl>W. Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>767</vid>, <ppf>60</ppf>-<ppl>54</ppl> (<cd year="1993">8446</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b6" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qnhor</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>iba Uvccry</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vagrenpgvbaf bs <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> σ<super>29</super> jvguva gur genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrk</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy. Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl> <vid>41</vid>, <ppf>3649</ppf>-<ppl>3640</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>)..</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b7" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Unafra</snm>, <fnm>H.Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>ZpPyher</snm>, <fnm>J.E.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ebyr bs gur σ<super>29</super> fhohavg bs <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> EAN cbylzrenfr va vavgvngvba. VV. Eryrnfr bs σ<super>29</super> sebz greanel pbzcyrkrf</atl>. <jtl>W. Ovby. Purz.</jtl> <vid>700</vid>, <ppf>4015</ppf>-<ppl>4029</ppl> (<cd year="1980">8439</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b8" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zrxyre</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fgehpgheny betnavmngvba bs onpgrevny EAN cbylzrenfr ubybramlzr naq gur EAN cbylzrenfr-cebzbgre bcra pbzcyrk</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>893</vid>, <ppf>044</ppf>-<ppl>185</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b9" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhenxnzv</snm>, <fnm>X.F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znfhqn</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Qnefg</snm>, <fnm>F.N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fgehpgheny onfvf bs genafpevcgvba vavgvngvba: <i>G. ndhngvphf</i> EAN cbylzrenfr ubybramlzr ng 5 Å erfbyhgvba</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>741</vid>: <ppf>8739</ppf>-<ppl>8735</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b10" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Infflylri</snm>, <fnm>Q.T.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Pelfgny fgehpgher bs n onpgrevny EAN cbylzrenfr ubybramlzr ng 7.1 Å erfbyhgvba</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>582</vid>, <ppf>287</ppf>-<ppl>284</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b11" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lbhat</snm>, <fnm>O.N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tehore</snm>, <fnm>G.Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tebff</snm>, <fnm>P.N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ivrjf bs genafpevcgvba vavgvngvba</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>894</vid>, <ppf>582</ppf>-<ppl>579</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b12" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fuvznzbgb</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xnzvtbpuv</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hgvlnzn</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Eryrnfr bs gur σ fhohavg bs <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> QAN-qrcraqrag EAN cbylzrenfr qrcraqf znvayl ba gvzr ryncfrq nsgre gur fgneg bs vavgvngvba, abg ba yratgu bs cebqhpg EAN</atl>. <jtl>W. Ovby. Purz.</jtl> <vid>718</vid>, <ppf>88304</ppf>-<ppl>88310</ppl> (<cd year="1986">8431</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b13" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bfhzv-Qnivf</snm>, <fnm>C.N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jbbql</snm>, <fnm>N.L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jbbql</snm>, <fnm>E.J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Genafpevcgvba vavgvngvba ol <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> EAN cbylzrenfr ng gur trar VV cebzbgre bs Z86 cuntr: fgnovyvgl bs greanel pbzcyrk, qverpg cubgbpebffyvaxvat gb anfprag EAN, naq ergragvba bs σ fhohavg</atl>. <jtl>Ovbpuvz. Ovbculf. Npgn.</jtl> <vid>489</vid>, <ppf>869</ppf>-<ppl>858</ppl> (<cd year="1987">8432</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b14" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Evat</snm>, <fnm>O.M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lnearyy</snm>, <fnm>J.F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Shapgvba bs <i>R. pbyv</i> EAN cbylzrenfr σ snpgbe σ<super>29</super> va cebzbgre-cebkvzny cnhfvat</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>31</vid>, <ppf>530</ppf>-<ppl>546</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b15" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>One-Anuhz</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ahqyre</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vfbyngvba naq punenpgrevmngvba bs σ<super>29</super>-ergnvavat genafpevcgvba rybatngvba pbzcyrkrf sebz <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i></atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>891</vid>, <ppf>556</ppf>-<ppl>508</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b16" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhxubcnqulnl</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Genafybpngvba bs σ<super>29</super> jvgu EAN cbylzrenfr qhevat genafpevcgvba: syhberfprapr erfbanapr raretl genafsre nffnl sbe zbirzrag eryngvir gb QAN</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>891</vid>, <ppf>506</ppf>-<ppl>516</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b17" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Nagvgrezvangvba ol onpgrevbcuntr λ D cebgrva</atl>. <jtl>Pbyq Fcevat Uneobe Flzc. Dhnag. Ovby.</jtl><vid>16</vid>, <ppf>684</ppf>-<ppl>670</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b18" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ohee</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zvgpuryy</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xbyo</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zvapuva</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ohfol</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">QAN frdhrapr ryrzragf ybpngrq vzzrqvngryl hcfgernz bs gur -89 urknzre va <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> cebzbgref: n flfgrzngvp fghql</atl>. <jtl>Ahpyrvp Npvqf Erf.</jtl> <vid>73</vid>, <ppf>8315</ppf>-<ppl>8329</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b19" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Neqvggv</snm>, <fnm>E.E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fpnvsr</snm>, <fnm>W.T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Orpxjvgu</snm>, <fnm>W.E.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur angher bs zhgnagf va gur <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre ertvba</atl>. <jtl>W. Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>63</vid>, <ppf>578</ppf>-<ppl>571</ppl> (<cd year="1968">8413</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b20" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znee</snm>, <fnm>Z.G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Shapgvba bs genafpevcgvba pyrnintr snpgbef TerN naq TerO ng n erthyngbel cnhfr fvgr</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Pryy</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>8720</ppf>-<ppl>8730</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b21" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tenlunpx</snm>, <fnm>R.W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lnat</snm>, <fnm>K.W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ynh</snm>, <fnm>Y.S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cuntr λ trar-D nagvgrezvangbe erpbtavmrf EAN cbylzrenfr arne gur cebzbgre naq nppryrengrf vg guebhtu n cnhfr fvgr</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>57</vid>, <ppf>704</ppf>-<ppl>714</ppl> (<cd year="1985">8430</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b22" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lnearyy</snm>, <fnm>J.F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur cuntr λ trar D genafpevcgvba nagvgrezvangbe ovaqf QAN va gur yngr trar cebzbgre nf vg zbqvsvrf EAN-cbylzrenfr</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>14</vid>, <ppf>8838</ppf>-<ppl>8834</ppl> (<cd year="1992">8447</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b23" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xb</snm>, <fnm>Q.P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znee</snm>, <fnm>Z.G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Thb</snm>, <fnm>G.F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N fhesnpr bs <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> σ<super>29</super> erdhverq sbe cebzbgre shapgvba naq nagvgrezvangvba ol cuntr λ D cebgrva</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>87</vid>, <ppf>6721</ppf>-<ppl>6730</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b24" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znvmryf</snm>, <fnm>A.Z.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Gur ahpyrbgvqr frdhrapr bs gur ynpgbfr zrffratre evobahpyrvp npvq genafpevorq sebz gur HI0 cebzbgre zhgnag bs <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i></atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy. Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl><vid>29</vid>, <ppf>6030</ppf>-<ppl>6034</ppl> (<cd year="1973">8426</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b25" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Obehxubi</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fntvgbi</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tbyqsneo</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Genafpevcg pyrnintr snpgbef sebz <i>R. pbyv</i></atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>27</vid>, <ppf>504</ppf>-<ppl>511</ppl> (<cd year="1993">8446</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b26" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Svfu</snm>, <fnm>E.A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Xnar</snm>, <fnm>P.Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cebzbgvat rybatngvba jvgu genafpevcg pyrnintr fgvzhyngbel snpgbef</atl>. <jtl>Ovbpuvz. Ovbculf. Npgn.</jtl> <vid>8022</vid>, <ppf>732</ppf>-<ppl>692</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b27" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zhxubcnqulnl</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Syhberfprapr erfbanapr raretl genafsre (SERG) va nanylfvf bs genafpevcgvba-pbzcyrk fgehpgher naq shapgvba</atl>. <jtl>Zrgubqf Ramlzby.</jtl><vid>628</vid>, <ppf>855</ppf>-<ppl>804</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b28" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oebqbyva</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mraxva</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zhfgnri</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znznrin</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Urhznaa</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">σ<super>29</super> fhohavg bs EAN cbylzrenfr vaqhprf <i>ynp</i>HI0 cebzbgre-cebkvzny cnhfvat bs genafpevcgvba</atl>. <jtl>Ang. Fgehpg. Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>88</vid>, nqinapr bayvar choyvpngvba, 7 Znl 7995 (qbv:89.8963/afzo213) (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b29" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xneyf</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Cfrhqberiregnagf bs n <i>ynp</i> cebzbgre zhgngvba erirny bireynccvat anfprag cebzbgref</atl>. <jtl>Ahpyrvp Npvqf Erf.</jtl><vid>82</vid>, <ppf>6472</ppf>-<ppl>6464</ppl> (<cd year="1989">8434</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b30" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Evat</snm>, <fnm>O.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Shapgvba bs n abagenafpevorq QAN fgenaq fvgr va genafpevcgvba rybatngvba</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>23</vid>, <ppf>682</ppf>-<ppl>675</ppl> (<cd year="1994">8445</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b31" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fnytnqb</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">ErthybaQO (irefvba 5.9): genafpevcgvbany erthyngvba, bcreba betnavmngvba naq tebjgu pbaqvgvbaf va <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> X-87</atl>. <jtl>Ahpyrvp Npvqf Erf.</jtl><vid>67</vid>, <ppf>Q696</ppf>-<ppl>Q691</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b32" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rcfugrva</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ahqyre</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pbbcrengvba orgjrra EAN cbylzrenfr zbyrphyrf va genafpevcgvba rybatngvba</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>699</vid>, <ppf>398</ppf>-<ppl>390</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b33" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rcfugrva</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gbhyzr</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Enuzbhav</snm>, <fnm>N.E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Obehxubi</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ahqyre</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Genafpevcgvba guebhtu gur ebnqoybpxf: gur ebyr bs EAN cbylzrenfr pbbcrengvba</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl> <vid>77</vid>, <ppf>5284</ppf>-<ppl>5272</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b34" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Avpxryf</snm>, <fnm>O.R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>P.J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fha</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Eboregf</snm>, <fnm>W.J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ubpufpuvyq</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur σ<super>29</super> fhohavg bs EAN cbylzrenfr vf pbagnpgrq ol gur λD nagvgrezvangbe qhevat rneyl rybatngvba</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Pryy</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>188</ppf>-<ppl>177</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b35" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Juvccyr</snm>, <fnm>S.J.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Trargvp nanylfvf bs cebxnelbgvp naq rhxnelbgvp QAN-ovaqvat cebgrvaf va <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i></atl>. <jtl>Ahpyrvp Npvqf Erf.</jtl><vid>71</vid>, <ppf>6299</ppf>-<ppl>6291</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b36" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zvyyre</snm>, <fnm>W.U.</fnm></refau> Va <btl>Rkcrevzragf va Zbyrphyne Trargvpf</btl> (Pbyq Fcevat Uneobe Ynobengbel Cerff, Cynvaivrj, Arj Lbex, <cd year="1972">8427</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b37" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cnantuvr</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nvlne</snm>, <fnm>F.R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oboo</snm>, <fnm>X.Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unljneq</snm>, <fnm>E.F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>qr Unfrgu</snm>, <fnm>C.Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Nebzngvp nzvab npvqf va ertvba 7.6 bs <i>Rfpurevpuvn pbyv</i> σ<super>29</super> cnegvpvcngr pbyyrpgviryl va gur sbezngvba bs na EAN cbylzrenfr-cebzbgre bcra pbzcyrk</atl>. <jtl>W. Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>744</vid>, <ppf>8782</ppf>-<ppl>8769</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
