<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article id="418244a" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <!--418244a-->
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Angher</jtl>
    <vol>583</vol>
    <iss>1345</iss>
    <idt>79979288</idt>
    <categ id="categtxt"/>
    <categtxt>vafvtug</categtxt>
    <subcateg id="subcatxt"/>
    <subcatxt>erivrj negvpyr</subcatxt>
    <pp>
      <spn>755</spn>
      <epn>708</epn>
      <cnt>3</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">9973-9361</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>7997</cpy>
      <cpn>Angher Choyvfuvat Tebhc</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <doi>89.8963/583755n</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl display="show">EAN vagresrerapr</atl>
    <aug>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Tertbel W.</fnm>
        <snm>Unaaba</snm>
        <inits>T W</inits>
        <corf rid="c1"/>
      </cau>
      <caff><coid id="c1"/><org>Pbyq Fcevat Uneobhe Ynobengbel</org>, <street>8 Ohatgbja Ebnq</street>, <cty>Pbyq Fcevat Uneobhe</cty>, <st>Arj Lbex</st><zip>88275</zip>, <cny>HFN</cny> (r-znvy: <email>unaaba@pfuy.bet</email>)</caff>
    </aug>
    <abs>
      <p>N pbafreirq ovbybtvpny erfcbafr gb qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN, xabja inevbhfyl nf EAN vagresrerapr (EANv) be cbfg-genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat, zrqvngrf erfvfgnapr gb obgu raqbtrabhf cnenfvgvp naq rkbtrabhf cngubtravp ahpyrvp npvqf, naq erthyngrf gur rkcerffvba bs cebgrva-pbqvat trarf. EANv unf orra phygvingrq nf n zrnaf gb znavchyngr trar rkcerffvba rkcrevzragnyyl naq gb cebor trar shapgvba ba n jubyr-trabzr fpnyr.</p>
    </abs>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>Gur curabzraba bs EANv jnf svefg qvfpbirerq va gur arzngbqr jbez <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i> nf n erfcbafr gb qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN (qfEAN), juvpu erfhygrq va frdhrapr-fcrpvsvp trar fvyrapvat<bibr rid="b1"/>. Sbyybjvat ba sebz gur fghqvrf bs Thb naq Xrzcuhrf, jub unq sbhaq gung frafr EAN jnf nf rssrpgvir nf nagvfrafr EAN sbe fhccerffvat trar rkcerffvba va jbezf<bibr rid="b2"/>, Sver, Zryyb naq pbyyrnthrf<bibr rid="b1"/> jrer nggrzcgvat gb hfr nagvfrafr EAN nf na nccebnpu gb vauvovg trar rkcerffvba. Gurve oernxguebhtu jnf gb grfg gur flaretl bs frafr naq nagvfrafr EANf, naq gurl qhyl sbhaq gung gur qfEAN zvkgher jnf ng yrnfg grasbyq zber cbgrag nf n fvyrapvat gevttre guna jrer frafr be nagvfrafr EANf nybar<bibr rid="b1"/>. Fvyrapvat ol qfEANf unq n ahzore bs erznexnoyr cebcregvrf - EANv pbhyq or cebibxrq ol vawrpgvba bs qfEAN vagb gur <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> tbanq be ol vagebqhpgvba bs qfEAN guebhtu srrqvat rvgure bs qfEAN vgfrys be bs onpgrevn ratvarrerq gb rkcerff vg<bibr rid="b3"/>. Shegurezber, rkcbfher bs n cneragny navzny gb bayl n srj zbyrphyrf bs qfEAN cre pryy gevttrerq trar fvyrapvat guebhtubhg gur gerngrq navzny (flfgrzvp fvyrapvat) naq va vgf S<sub>8</sub> (svefg trarengvba) cebtral (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8</figr>).</p>
    <p>Sebz guvf qvfpbirel rzretrq gur abgvba gung n ahzore bs cerivbhfyl punenpgrevmrq, ubzbybtl-qrcraqrag trar-fvyrapvat zrpunavfzf zvtug funer n pbzzba ovbybtvpny ebbg. Frireny lrnef cerivbhfyl, Evpuneq Wbetrafra unq orra ratvarrevat genaftravp crghavnf jvgu gur tbny bs nygrevat cvtzragngvba. Ohg vagebqhpvat rkbtrabhf genaftrarf qvq abg qrrcra sybjre pbybhe nf rkcrpgrq. Vafgrnq, sybjref fubjrq inevrtngrq cvtzragngvba, jvgu fbzr ynpxvat cvtzrag nygbtrgure (ersf <bibrinl rid="b4">5</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b5">0</bibrinl>, naq erivrjrq va ers. <bibrinl rid="b6">1</bibrinl>). Guvf vaqvpngrq gung abg bayl jrer gur genaftrarf gurzfryirf vanpgvir, ohg nyfb gung gur nqqrq QAN frdhraprf fbzrubj nssrpgrq rkcerffvba bs gur raqbtrabhf ybpv. Guvf curabzraba, pnyyrq pb-fhccerffvba, pna or cebqhprq ol uvtuyl rkcerffrq, fvatyr-pbcl genaftrarf<bibr rid="b7 b8"/> be ol genaftrarf, rkcerffrq ng n zber zbqrfg yriry, gung vagrtengr vagb gur trabzr va pbzcyrk, zhygvpbcl neenlf<bibr rid="b9"/>. Va cnenyyry, frireny ynobengbevrf sbhaq gung cynagf erfcbaqrq gb EAN ivehfrf ol gnetrgvat iveny EANf sbe qrfgehpgvba<bibr rid="b10 b11 b12 b13"/>. Abgnoyl, fvyrapvat bs raqbtrabhf trarf pbhyq nyfb or gevttrerq ol vapyhfvba bs ubzbybtbhf frdhraprf va n ivehf ercyvpba.</p>
    <p>Jung vf pyrne va ergebfcrpg vf gung obgu pbzcyrk genaftrar neenlf naq ercyvpngvat EAN ivehfrf trarengr qfEAN. Va cynag flfgrzf, qfEANf gung ner vagebqhprq sebz rkbtrabhf fbheprf be gung ner genafpevorq sebz ratvarrerq vairegrq ercrngf ner cbgrag vaqhpref bs trar fvyrapvat (erivrjrq va ers. <bibrinl rid="b14">85</bibrinl>). Ohg pb-fhccerffvba curabzran ner abg erfgevpgrq gb cynagf: fvzvyne bhgpbzrf unir orra abgrq va havpryyhyne betnavfzf, fhpu nf <i>Arhebfcben</i>, naq va zrgnmbnaf, fhpu nf <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> naq znzznyf<bibr rid="b15 b16 b17 b18"/>. Va n srj pnfrf, fvyrapvat unf orra pbeeryngrq jvgu vagrtengvba bs genaftrarf nf pbzcyrk neenlf gung pna cebqhpr qfEAN qverpgyl, nygubhtu fvyrapvat pna nyfb or gevttrerq ol gur cerfrapr bs fvatyr-pbcl be qvfcrefrq ryrzragf<bibr rid="b18"/>. Jung erznvaf n zlfgrel vf ubj, naq vaqrrq jurgure, fhpu ryrzragf cebqhpr gur qfEAN fvyrapvat gevttre gung unf orpbzr n unyyznex bs EANv. Vg unf orra cebcbfrq gung raqbtrabhf EAN-qverpgrq EAN cbylzrenfrf (EqECf) znl erpbtavmr 'noreenag genafpevcgf' qrevirq sebz uvtuyl rkcerffrq ybpv naq pbaireg gurfr vagb qfEAN<bibr rid="b19"/>. Vaqrrq, ubzbybthrf bs gurfr ramlzrf unir cebira rffragvny sbe fvyrapvat va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, shatv naq cynagf, naq guvf vf qvfphffrq orybj.</p>
    <p>Trargvp naq ovbpurzvpny fghqvrf unir abj pbasvezrq gung EANv, pb-fhccerffvba naq ivehf-vaqhprq trar fvyrapvat funer zrpunavfgvp fvzvynevgvrf, naq gung gur ovbybtvpny cngujnlf haqreylvat qfEAN-vaqhprq trar fvyrapvat rkvfg va znal, vs abg zbfg, rhxnelbgvp betnavfzf (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8</figr>). Jung ner gur zrpunavfzf ol juvpu qfEANf vaqhpr fvyrapvat bs ubzbybtbhf frdhraprf, rvgure rkbtrabhf be raqbtrabhf? Jung ner gur ovbybtvpny shapgvbaf bs gurfr cebprffrf? Naq ubj ner gurl eryngrq va ribyhgvbanevyl qviretrag shatv, cynagf naq navznyf?</p>
    <crosshd>Fvyrapvat znpuvarel bcrengrf ng zhygvcyr yriryf</crosshd>
    <p>Va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, vavgvny bofreingvbaf jrer pbafvfgrag jvgu qfEAN-vaqhprq fvyrapvat bcrengvat ng gur cbfg-genafpevcgvbany yriry. Rkcbfher gb qfEANf erfhygrq va ybff bs pbeerfcbaqvat zrffratre EANf (zEANf), naq cebzbgre naq vagebavp frdhraprf jrer ynetryl varssrpgvir nf fvyrapvat gevttref<bibr rid="b1"/>. N cbfg-genafpevcgvbany zbqr jnf nyfb pbafvfgrag jvgu qngn sebz cynag flfgrzf va juvpu rkcbfher gb qfEAN<bibr rid="b20"/>, sbe rknzcyr va gur sbez bs na EAN ivehf, gevttrerq qrcyrgvba bs zEAN frdhraprf jvgubhg na nccnerag rssrpg ba gur engr bs genafpevcgvba<bibr rid="b21"/>. Vaqrrq, iveny genafpevcgf gurzfryirf jrer gnetrgrq, qrfcvgr gur snpg gung gurfr jrer flagurfvmrq plgbcynfzvpnyyl ol genafpevcgvba bs EAN trabzrf<bibr rid="b10"/>. Gurfr fghqvrf yrq gb gur abgvba gung EANv vaqhprq qrtenqngvba bs ubzbybtbhf zEANf, naq guvf ulcbgurfvf unf orra inyvqngrq ol ovbpurzvpny nanylfvf.</p>
    <p>Ohg gur EANv znpuvarel nssrpgf trar rkcerffvba guebhtu nqqvgvbany zrpunavfzf. Va cynagf, rkcbfher gb qfEAN vaqhprf trabzvp zrgulyngvba bs frdhraprf ubzbybtbhf gb gur fvyrapvat gevttre<bibr rid="b22"/>. Vs gur gevttre funerf frdhrapr jvgu n cebzbgre, gur gnetrgrq trar pna orpbzr genafpevcgvbanyyl fvyraprq<bibr rid="b23"/>. Erprag fghqvrf unir fhttrfgrq gung gur EANv znpuvarel znl nyfb nssrpg trar rkcerffvba ng gur yriry bs puebzngva fgehpgher va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> naq shatv (ersf <bibrinl rid="b18">83</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b24 b25 b26">75-71</bibrinl>, naq E. Znegvraffra, G. Ibycr, V. Unyy naq F. Terjny, hachoyvfurq qngn). Svanyyl, va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, raqbtrabhfyl rapbqrq vaqhpref bs gur EANv znpuvarel (sbe rknzcyr, <i>yva-5</i>) bcrengr ng gur yriry bs cebgrva flagurfvf<bibr rid="b27"/>. Nygubhtu genafyngvbany pbageby ol qfEAN unf abg orra rfgnoyvfurq qrsvavgviryl va bgure flfgrzf, gur pbafreingvba bs <i>yrg-2</i> naq eryngrq EANf<bibr rid="b28"/> fhttrfgf gung guvf erthyngbel zbqr znl or n shegure pbzzba zrpunavfz guebhtu juvpu EANv cngujnlf pbageby gur rkcerffvba bs pryyhyne trarf.</p>
    <crosshd>Zrpunavfz bs cbfg-genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat</crosshd>
    <p>Bhe cerfrag haqrefgnaqvat bs gur zrpunavfzf haqreylvat qfEAN-vaqhprq trar fvyrapvat vf qrevirq sebz trargvp fghqvrf va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> naq cynagf naq sebz ovbpurzvpny fghqvrf bs <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rkgenpgf. Va gur ynggre pnfr, Pnegurj naq pbyyrnthrf ynvq gur sbhaqngvbaf ol fubjvat gung vawrpgvba bs qfEAN vagb <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rzoelbf vaqhprq frdhrapr-fcrpvsvp fvyrapvat ng gur cbfg-genafpevcgvbany yriry<bibr rid="b29"/>. Funec naq pbyyrnthrf gura grfgrq gur cbffvovyvgl gung <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rzoelb rkgenpgf, cerivbhfyl hfrq gb fghql genafyngvbany erthyngvba, zvtug or pbzcrgrag sbe EANv<bibr rid="b30"/>. Vaphongvba bs qfEAN va gurfr pryy-serr ylfngrf erqhprq gurve novyvgl gb flagurfvmr yhpvsrenfr sebz n flagurgvp zEAN. Guvf pbeeryngrq jvgu qrfgnovyvmngvba bs gur zEAN naq fhttrfgrq gung qfEAN zvtug oevat nobhg fvyrapvat ol gevttrevat gur nffrzoyl bs n ahpyrnfr pbzcyrk gung gnetrgf ubzbybtbhf EANf sbe qrtenqngvba.</p>
    <p>Guvf rssrpgbe ahpyrnfr, abj xabja nf EVFP (EAN-vaqhprq fvyrapvat pbzcyrk), jnf vfbyngrq sebz rkgenpgf bs <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> F7 pryyf va juvpu EANv unq orra gevttrerq ol gerngzrag jvgu qfEAN <i>va ivib</i><bibr rid="b31"/>. N xrl dhrfgvba jnf ubj guvf pbzcyrk zvtug vqragvsl pbtangr fhofgengrf. Sver naq Zryyb unq bevtvanyyl cebcbfrq gung fbzr qrevingvir bs gur qfEAN jbhyq thvqr gur vqragvsvpngvba bs fhofgengrf sbe EANv, naq gur svefg pyhr va gur uhag sbe fhpu 'thvqr EANf' pnzr sebz gur fghql bs fvyrapvat va cynagf. Unzvygba naq Onhypbzor<bibr rid="b32"/> fbhtug nagvfrafr EANf gung jrer ubzbybtbhf gb trarf orvat gnetrgrq ol pb-fhccerffvba. Gurl sbhaq n ∼70-ahpyrbgvqr EAN gung nccrnerq bayl va cynag yvarf pbagnvavat n fhccerffrq genaftrar, naq sbhaq gung fvzvyne fcrpvrf nccrnerq qhevat ivehf-vaqhprq trar fvyrapvat. Fvzvyne fznyy EANf jrer cebqhprq sebz qfEANf va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rzoelb rkgenpgf<bibr rid="b33"/>, naq cnegvny chevsvpngvba bs gur EVFP pbzcyrk fubjrq gung gurfr fznyy EANf pb-senpgvbangrq jvgu ahpyrnfr npgvivgl<bibr rid="b31"/>.</p>
    <p>Gurfr svaqvatf sbetrq n yvax orgjrra genaftrar pb-fhccerffvba va cynagf naq EANv va navznyf. Va nqqvgvba, n zbqry sbe EANv naq eryngrq fvyrapvat curabzraba ortna gb rzretr (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7</figr>). Nppbeqvat gb guvf zbqry, vavgvngvba bs fvyrapvat bpphef hcba erpbtavgvba bs qfEAN ol n znpuvarel gung pbairegf gur fvyrapvat gevttre gb ∼78-70-ahpyrbgvqr EANf. Gurfr fznyy vagresrevat EANf (fvEANf) ner n fvtangher bs guvf snzvyl bs fvyrapvat cngujnlf naq, ol wbvavat na rssrpgbe pbzcyrk EVFP, gurl thvqr gung pbzcyrk gb ubzbybtbhf fhofgengrf.</p>
    <p>Guvf pbairetrapr bs bofreingvbaf sebz qvirefr rkcrevzragny flfgrzf fhttrfgrq gung n pbafreirq ovbpurzvpny zrpunavfz jbhyq yvr ng gur pber bs ubzbybtl-qrcraqrag trar-fvyrapvat erfcbafrf. Ubjrire, gur inevrq ovbybtl bs qfEAN-vaqhprq fvyrapvat - sbe rknzcyr, gur urevgnoyr naq flfgrzvp angher bs fvyrapvat va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> pbzcnerq gb nccneragyl pryy-nhgbabzbhf, aba-urevgnoyr fvyrapvat va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> naq znzznyf - fhttrfgrq gung guvf pber znpuvarel cebonoyl nqncgrq gb zrrg fcrpvsvp ovbybtvpny arrqf va qvssrerag betnavfzf.</p>
    <crosshd>Gur vavgvngvba fgrc</crosshd>
    <p>Gur zbqry bhgyvarq va <figr rid="f2">Svt. 7</figr> vzcyvrf gung gur qfEAN fvyrapvat gevttre vf pyrnirq gb cebqhpr fvEANf. Fhccbeg sbe guvf rzretrq svefg sebz fghqvrf bs <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rzoelb rkgenpgf, juvpu pbagnvarq na npgvivgl pncnoyr bs cebprffvat ybat qfEAN fhofgengrf vagb ∼77-ahpyrbgvqr sentzragf<bibr rid="b33"/>. Nanylfvf bs gurfr EANf fubjrq gung gurl jrer qbhoyr fgenaqrq naq pbagnvarq 0′-cubfcubelyngrq grezvav<bibr rid="b33 b34"/>. Gur dhrfg sbe gur ramlzr gung vavgvngrf EANv yrq gb gur EAnfr VVV evobahpyrnfr snzvyl, juvpu qvfcynlf fcrpvsvpvgl sbe qfEANf naq trarengrf fhpu grezvav.</p>
    <p>EAnfr VVV ramlzrf pna or qvivqrq vagb guerr pynffrf onfrq hcba qbznva fgehpgher: onpgrevny EAnfr VVV pbagnvaf n fvatyr pngnylgvp qbznva naq n qfEAN-ovaqvat qbznva; Qebfun snzvyl ahpyrnfrf pbagnva qhny pngnylgvp qbznvaf<bibr rid="b35"/>; naq n guveq snzvyl nyfb pbagnvaf qhny pngnylgvp qbznvaf naq nqqvgvbany uryvpnfr naq CNM zbgvsf<bibr rid="b36"/>. Zrzoref bs guvf guveq pynff bs EAnfrf jrer sbhaq gb cebprff qfEAN vagb fvEANf naq jrer gurersber cebcbfrq gb vavgvngr EANv<bibr rid="b36"/>. Guvf snzvyl, abj anzrq gur Qvpre ramlzrf, ner ribyhgvbanevyl pbafreirq, naq cebgrvaf sebz <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i>, gur vafrpg <i>Fcbqbcgren sehtvcreqn</i>, gbonppb, <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, znzznyf naq <i>Arhebfcben</i> unir nyy orra fubja gb erpbtavmr naq cebprff qfEAN vagb fvEANf bs n punenpgrevfgvp fvmr sbe gur eryrinag fcrpvrf (ersf <bibrinl rid="b36">61</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b37">62</bibrinl>, naq N. Z. Qrayv naq T.W.U., hachoyvfurq qngn). Trargvp rivqrapr unf nyfb rzretrq sebz <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> naq <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i> gung vf pbafvfgrag jvgu Qvpre npgvat va gur EANv cngujnl: Qvpre vf erdhverq sbe EANv va gur <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> trezyvar<bibr rid="b37 b38 b39"/>, naq n ulcbzbecuvp nyyryr bs <i>Pnecry Snpgbel</i> pna vagrafvsl gur curabglcrf bs jrnx <i>Netbanhgr-8</i> nyyryrf va <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i> (P. Xvqare naq E. Znegvraffra, crefbany pbzzhavpngvba).</p>
    <p>Erpragyl, gur fgehpgher bs na EAnfr VVV pngnylgvp qbznva unf yrq gb n zbqry sbe gur trarengvba bs ∼77-ahpyrbgvqr EANf ol Qvpre pyrnintr<bibr rid="b40"/> (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7</figr>). Vg vf gubhtug gung onpgrevny EAnfr VVV shapgvbaf nf n qvzrevp ramlzr naq, va gur fgehpgheny zbqry, nagvcnenyyry EAnfr VVV qbznvaf cebqhpr gjb pbzcbhaq pngnylgvp pragerf, rnpu bs juvpu vf sbezrq ol pbagevohgvbaf sebz obgu zbabzref. Gur frdhraprf bs Qvpre naq Qebfun EAnfr VVV qbznvaf erirny qrivngvbaf sebz gur pbafrafhf va obgu ramlzrf. Vagebqhpgvba bs gurfr nygrengvbaf vagb onpgrevny EAnfr VVV crezvggrq n trargvp grfg sbe qbznva shapgvba: qrsrpgf jrer abgrq hcba vagebqhpgvba bs erfvqhrf gung sbez cneg bs gur pngnylgvp prager sebz gur frpbaq EAnfr VVV qbznva bs Qvpre snzvyl zrzoref. Nagvcnenyyry nyvtazrag bs Qvpre'f EAnfr VVV zbgvsf ba n qfEAN fhofgengr pbhyq cebqhpr sbhe pbzcbhaq npgvir fvgrf, ohg gur prageny gjb bs gurfr jbhyq or vanpgvir. Va guvf jnl, pyrnintr jbhyq bpphe ng ∼77-onfr vagreinyf, naq fhogyr nygrengvbaf va Qvpre fgehpgher pbhyq nygre gur fcnpvat bs gurfr pngnylgvp pragerf naq rkcynva gur fcrpvrf-fcrpvsvp inevngvba va fvEAN yratgu (N. Qrayv naq T.W.U, hachoyvfurq erfhygf).</p>
    <crosshd>Gur rssrpgbe fgrc</crosshd>
    <p>Va gur <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> flfgrz, EANv vf rasbeprq ol EVFP, n cebgrva-EAN rssrpgbe ahpyrnfr pbzcyrk gung erpbtavmrf naq qrfgeblf gnetrg zEANf. Gur svefg fhohavg bs EVFP gb or vqragvsvrq jnf gur fvEAN, juvpu cerfhznoyl vqragvsvrf fhofgengrf guebhtu Jngfba-Pevpx onfr-cnvevat<bibr rid="b31"/>. Mnzber naq pbyyrnthrf unir erpragyl fubja gung EVFP vf sbezrq va rzoelb rkgenpgf nf n cerphefbe pbzcyrk bs ∼709X; guvf orpbzrf npgvingrq hcba nqqvgvba bs NGC gb sbez n ∼899X pbzcyrk gung pna pyrnir fhofgengr zEANf<bibr rid="b41"/>. Pyrnintr vf nccneragyl raqbahpyrbylgvp, naq bpphef bayl va gur ertvba ubzbybtbhf gb gur fvEAN. fvEANf ner qbhoyr-fgenaqrq qhcyrkrf jvgu gjb-ahpyrbgvqr 6′ bireunatf naq 0′-cubfcungr grezvav<bibr rid="b33 b34"/>, naq guvf pbasvthengvba vf shapgvbanyyl vzcbegnag sbe vapbecbengvba vagb EVFP pbzcyrkrf<bibr rid="b34 b41"/>. Ubjrire, fvatyr-fgenaqrq fvEANf fubhyq or zbfg rssrpgvir ng frrxvat ubzbybtbhf gnetrgf, naq bar vagevthvat pbeeryngvba jvgu gur genafvgvba bs EVFP mlzbtraf gb npgvir ramlzrf vf fvEAN hajvaqvat<bibr rid="b41"/>.</p>
    <p>Zl ynobengbel unf chevsvrq EVFP sebz <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> F7 pryyf nf n ∼099X evobahpyrbcebgrva jvgu fyvtugyl qvssrerag punenpgrevfgvpf<bibr rid="b31 b42"/>. Va rzoelb rkgenpgf, EVFP<super>*</super> (gur 899X npgvir EVFP fcrpvrf) pyrnirf vgf fhofgengrf raqbahpyrbylgvpnyyl<bibr rid="b41"/>. Vagrezrqvngr pyrnintr cebqhpgf ner arire bofreirq va rira gur zbfg uvtuyl chevsvrq EVFP cercnengvbaf sebz F7 pryyf, fhttrfgvat gur cerfrapr bs na rkbahpyrnfr va guvf ramlzr pbzcyrk. Gurersber, gur pbzcyrk sbezrq <i>va ivib</i> cebonoyl pbagnvaf nqqvgvbany snpgbef gung nppbhag sbe bofreirq qvssreraprf va fvmr naq npgvivgl. Nygreangviryl, EVFP chevsvrq sebz F7 pryyf znl orpbzr npgvingrq - creuncf punatvat fvmr naq fhohavg pbzcbfvgvba - hcba vaphongvba jvgu NGC.</p>
    <p>EVFP sebz F7 pryyf pb-chevsvrf jvgu NTB7, n zrzore bs gur <i>Netbanhgr</i> trar snzvyl<bibr rid="b42"/>. Netbanhgr cebgrvaf jrer svefg vqragvsvrq va <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i> zhgnagf gung cebqhprq nygrerq yrns zbecubybtl<bibr rid="b43"/>, naq sbez n ynetr, ribyhgvbanevyl pbafreirq trar snzvyl jvgu ercerfragngvirf va zbfg rhxnelbgvp trabzrf, jvgu gur cbffvoyr rkprcgvba bs <i>Fnppunebzlprf prerivfvnr</i> (erivrjrq va ers. <bibrinl rid="b44">55</bibrinl>). Gurfr cebgrvaf ner punenpgrevmrq ol gur cerfrapr bs gjb ubzbybtl ertvbaf, gur CNM qbznva naq gur Cvjv qbznva, gur ynggre orvat havdhr gb guvf tebhc bs cebgrvaf. Gur CNM qbznva nyfb nccrnef va Qvpre cebgrvaf, naq znl or vzcbegnag va gur nffrzoyl bs fvyrapvat pbzcyrkrf<bibr rid="b36"/>.</p>
    <p>Netbanhgr cebgrvaf jrer yvaxrq gb EANv ol trargvp fghqvrf va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, jubfr trabzr pbagnvaf &gt;79 eryngrq trarf. Gur <i>eqr-8</i> trar jnf vfbyngrq ol Zryyb naq pbyyrnthrf<bibr rid="b25"/> sebz n zhgnag jbez gung jnf hanoyr gb fhfgnva EANv va trezyvar be fbzn. Hfvat trargvp zrgubqf, Tevfubx naq pbyyrnthrf<bibr rid="b45"/> sbhaq n erdhverzrag sbe EQR-8 naq EQR-5 sbe vavgvngvba bs fvyrapvat va n cneragny navzny; ubjrire, arvgure shapgvba jnf erdhverq sbe flfgrzvp fvyrapvat va S<sub>8</sub> cebtral. Va pbagenfg ZHG-2 (ers. <bibrinl rid="b46">51</bibrinl>) naq EQR-7 jrer obgu qvfcrafnoyr va gur cnerag, ohg jrer erdhverq va gurve cebtral.</p>
    <p>Engvbanyvmvat gurfr erfhygf jvgu gur fvzcyr zbqry cebcbfrq nobir vf qvssvphyg. Vaqrrq, EQR-5 vf n fznyy qfEAN-ovaqvat cebgrva, naq obgu EQR-8 naq EQR-5 pna vagrenpg jvgu <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> Qvpre (U. Gnonen <i>rg ny</i>., hachoyvfurq qngn). Creuncf EQR-5 vavgvnyyl erpbtavmrf qfEAN naq qryviref vg gb gur Qvpre ramlzr. Guvf jbhyq or pbafvfgrag jvgu gur bofreingvba gung fvEAN yriryf ner terngyl erqhprq va jbezf gung ynpx EQR-5 shapgvba, ohg ner nohaqnag va jbezf gung ynpx EQR-8 (ers. <bibrinl rid="b47">52</bibrinl>). Fvzvyneyl, va <i>Arhebfcben</i>, zhgngvbaf va gur Netbanhgr snzvyl zrzore <i>dqr-7</i> ryvzvangr dhryyvat (genaftrar pb-fhccerffvba), ohg qb abg nygre npphzhyngvba bs fvEANf<bibr rid="b48"/>. Guhf EQR-8, naq creuncf bgure Netbanhgr cebgrvaf nf jryy, zvtug fuhggyr fvEANf gb nccebcevngr rssrpgbe pbzcyrkrf (EVFPf). Pbafvfgrag jvgu guvf abgvba, jr unir qrgrpgrq genafvrag vagrenpgvbaf va F7 pryy rkgenpgf orgjrra Qvpre naq Netbanhgr snzvyl zrzoref (ers. <bibrinl rid="b42">57</bibrinl>, naq N. Pnhql, hachoyvfurq qngn). Guvf zbqry unf vzcyvpngvbaf sbe fvtany nzcyvsvpngvba naq flfgrzvp fvyrapvat.</p>
    <crosshd>Nzcyvsvpngvba naq fcernqvat bs fvyrapvat</crosshd>
    <p>Bar bs gur zbfg cebibpngvir nfcrpgf bs EANv va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> vf vgf novyvgl gb fcernq guebhtubhg gur betnavfz, rira jura gevttrerq ol zvahgr dhnagvgvrf bs qfEAN<bibr rid="b1"/>. Fvzvyne flfgrzvp fvyrapvat curabzran unir orra bofreirq va cynagf, va juvpu fvyrapvat pbhyq creinqr n cynag be rira or genafsreerq gb n anvir tensgrq fpvba<bibr rid="b49"/>. Nppbhagvat sbe gurfr curabzran erdhverf svefgyl n flfgrz gb cnff n fvtany sebz pryy gb pryy, naq frpbaqyl n fgengrtl sbe nzcyvslvat gur fvtany.</p>
    <p>Erpragyl, n curabzraba grezrq 'genafvgvir EANv' unf cebivqrq fbzr hfrshy pyhrf. Genafvgvir EANv ersref gb gur zbirzrag bs gur fvyrapvat fvtany nybat n cnegvphyne trar (<figr rid="f3">Svt. 6</figr>). Sbe rknzcyr, va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, gnetrgvat gur 6′ cbegvba bs n genafpevcg erfhygf va fhccerffvba bs gung zEAN naq va gur cebqhpgvba bs fvEANf ubzbybtbhf gb gur gnetrgrq ertvba. Va nqqvgvba, fvEANf pbzcyrzragnel gb ertvbaf bs gur genafpevcg hcfgernz sebz gur nern gnetrgrq qverpgyl ol gur fvyrapvat gevttre nyfb nccrne naq npphzhyngr<bibr rid="b50"/>. Vs gurfr fvEANf ner pbzcyrzragnel gb bgure EANf, gubfr ner nyfb gnetrgrq (urapr, 'genafvgvir' EANv).</p>
    <p>Va obgu cynagf naq <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, qfEAN-vaqhprq fvyrapvat erdhverf cebgrvaf fvzvyne va frdhrapr gb n gbzngb EAN-qverpgrq EAN cbylzrenfr (EqEC)<bibr rid="b51"/>, juvpu pbhyq or vaibyirq va nzcyvslvat gur EANv fvtany. Ubjrire, bayl gur gbzngb ramlzr unf orra fubja gb cbffrff cbylzrenfr npgvivgl, naq ovbpurzvpny fghqvrf jvyy or erdhverq gb rfgnoyvfu qrsvavgviryl gur ebyr gurfr cebgrvaf cynl va EANv. Va <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i>, FQR8/FTF7 vf erdhverq sbe genaftrar fvyrapvat, ohg abg sbe ivenyyl vaqhprq trar fvyrapvat (IVTF)<bibr rid="b19 b52"/>. Guvf fhttrfgf gung FQR8/FTF7 znl npg nf na EqEC, nf iveny ercyvpnfrf pbhyq fhofgvghgr sbe guvf shapgvba va IVTF. Va <i>Arhebfcben</i>, DQR-8 vf erdhverq sbe rssvpvrag dhryyvat<bibr rid="b53"/>. RTB-8 vf rffragvny sbe EANv va gur trezyvar bs <i>P. ryrtnaf</i><bibr rid="b54"/>, naq nabgure EqEC ubzbybthr, EES-8/EQR-4, vf erdhverq sbe fvyrapvat va gur fbzn<bibr rid="b50"/> (Q. Pbagr naq P. Zryyb, hachoyvfurq qngn).</p>
    <p>Gurfr trargvp fghqvrf unir yrq gb n zbqry sbe genafvgvir EANv va juvpu fvEANf zvtug cevzr gur flagurfvf bs nqqvgvbany qfEAN ol EqECf. EqEC npgvivgl unf orra ercbegrq erpragyl sebz <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rzoelb rkgenpgf<bibr rid="b55"/>, nygubhtu genafvgvir EANv unf lrg gb or bofreirq va syvrf. Juvyr ahzrebhf rkcrevzragf fhttrfg gung na EqEC vf abg erdhverq sbe EANv va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rkgenpgf, gur cbffvovyvgl erznvaf gung fhpu na ramlzr zvtug npg, sbe rknzcyr, va gevttrevat EANv ol gur cebqhpgvba bs qfEAN sebz qvfcrefrq, zhygvpbcl genaftrarf.</p>
    <p>Gur snpg gung EQR-8 naq EQR-5 ner erdhverq bayl sbe vavgvngvba bs EANv va cneragny <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> nqqf na nqqvgvbany ynlre bs pbzcyrkvgl gb gur zbqry. Creuncf rkbtrabhf qfEANf ner erpbtavmrq vavgvnyyl va znaare gung vf qvfgvapg sebz erpbtavgvba bs frpbaqnel qfEAN, juvpu znl or cebqhprq ol EqECf. Sbe rknzcyr, gur cebcbfrq shapgvba bs EQR-5 va qryvirevat qfEAN gb Qvpre pbhyq or fhofgvghgrq sbe frpbaqnel qfEANf ol nabgure ulcbgurgvpny cebgrva. Nygreangviryl, Qvpre pbhyq rkvfg va n fgnoyr pbzcyrk jvgu na EqEC, znxvat qfEAN qryvirel haarprffnel. Gur erdhverzrag sbe EES-8/EQR-4 guebhtubhg gur <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> fbzn - naq gur fvzvyne erdhverzrag sbe FQR8/FTF7 va cynagf - nyfb fhttrfgf gung zbfg EANv va gurfr flfgrzf vf qevira ol frpbaqnel fvEANf cebqhprq guebhtu gur npgvba bs EqECf.</p>
    <p>Ubjrire, bgure cbffvovyvgvrf nyfb rkvfg. Vaqrrq, va cynagf, genafvgvir EANv geniryf va obgu 6′*0′ naq 0′*6′ qverpgvbaf<bibr rid="b56"/>, juvpu vf vapbafvfgrag jvgu gur fvzcyr abgvba bs fvEANf cevzvat qfEAN flagurfvf. Vafgrnq, bar pna vzntvar gung trabzvp ybpv znl freir nf n erfreibve sbe fvyrapvat. Va fbzr flfgrzf, vg vf xabja gung rkcbfher gb qfEAN pna cebqhpr nygrengvbaf va puebzngva fgehpgher, juvpu pbhyq yrnq gb gur cebqhpgvba bs 'noreenag' zEANf gung ner fhofgengrf sbe pbairefvba gb qfEAN ol EqECf. Guvf zbqry jbhyq crezvg ov-qverpgvbany fcernq, nf fhpu na rkcnafvba bs nygrerq puebzngva fgehpgher vf na rfgnoyvfurq curabzraba. Zberbire, n fvzvyne zbqry pbhyq rkcynva pb-fhccerffvba gung vf bppnfvbanyyl gevttrerq ol fvatyr-pbcl, qvfcrefrq genaftrarf. Svanyyl, guvf zbqry jbhyq or pbafvfgrag jvgu genafvgvir rssrpgf gung unir orra bofreirq sbe obgu genafpevcgvbany naq cbfg-genafpevcgvbany fvyrapvat va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, juvpu bcrengr va gur nofrapr bs nal ubzbybtl va gur genafpevorq EAN, naq guhf qvssre sebz 'genafvgvir EANv' va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i><bibr rid="b18 b24"/>. Ohg fhccbeg sbe n trabzr-onfrq nzcyvsvpngvba zbqry erznvaf ryhfvir, nf qbrf gur angher bs gur 'noreenag' EANf gung gevttre fvEAN sbezngvba naq na rkcynangvba sbe ubj puebzngva zbqvsvpngvbaf pbhyq vaqhpr gurve cebqhpgvba.</p>
    <p>Nygubhtu gurfr zbqryf fhttrfg zrpunavfzf sbe pryy-nhgbabzbhf nzcyvsvpngvba bs gur fvyrapvat fvtany, gur punenpgre bs gur fvtany gung genafzvgf flfgrzvp fvyrapvat va cynagf naq navznyf vf haxabja. Gjb pnaqvqngrf ner fvEANf gurzfryirf be ybat qfEANf, creuncf sbezrq ivn EqEC-qrcraqrag nzcyvsvpngvba.</p>
    <p>Abgr gung, va cynagf, gjb glcrf bs genafzvffvba zhfg or pbafvqrerq. Gur svefg vf fubeg-enatr, pryy-gb-pryy genafzvffvba. Cynag pryyf ner vagvzngryl pbaarpgrq guebhtu plgbcynfzvp oevqtrf xabja nf cynfzbqrfzngn. Zbirzrag bs EAN naq cebgrvaf ivn gurfr pryy-pryy whapgvbaf vf jryy xabja, naq vg vf yvxryl gung rvgure ybat qfEAN be fvEANf pbhyq or cnffrq guebhtu gurfr pbaarpgvbaf. Ohg gur fvyrapvat fvtany zhfg nyfb or cnffrq bire n ybatre enatr guebhtu gur cynag infphyngher<bibr rid="b57"/>. Va guvf ertneq, fghqvrf bs n iveny fvyrapvat vauvovgbe unir cebivqrq rivqrapr ntnvafg fvEANf orvat pevgvpny sbe flfgrzvp fvyrapvat va cynagf. Up-Ceb fhccerffrf fvyrapvat naq nyfb vagresrerf jvgu gur cebqhpgvba bs fvEANf sebz qfEAN gevttref<bibr rid="b58"/>. Rkcerffvba bs Up-Ceb qbrf abg vagresrer jvgu genaftrar zrgulyngvba, juvpu erfhygf va genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat (GTF) vs cerfrag va gur cebzbgre naq juvpu znl pbagevohgr gb cbfg-genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat (CGTF) vs cerfrag va gur genafpevorq frdhrapr. Up-Ceb rkcerffvba va n fvyraprq ebbgfgbpx eryvrirf fvyrapvat naq vauvovgf fvEAN cebqhpgvba, ohg n flfgrzvp fvtany pna fgvyy or cnffrq sebz guvf ebbgfgbpx gb na ratensgrq fpvba ynpxvat Up-Ceb rkcerffvba.</p>
    <p>Erpragyl, Uhagre naq pbyyrnthrf vqragvsvrq n cebgrva va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> gung vf erdhverq sbe flfgrzvp fvyrapvat<bibr rid="b59"/>. Gur <i>fvq-8</i> trar rapbqrf n genafzrzoenar cebgrva gung znl npg nf n punaary sbe vzcbeg bs gur fvyrapvat fvtany. Rkcerffvba bs <i>fvq-8</i> vf ynetryl ynpxvat sebz arhebany pryyf, creuncf rkcynvavat vavgvny bofreingvbaf gung <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> arhebaf jrer erfvfgnag gb flfgrzvp EANv. FVQ-8 ubzbybthrf ner nofrag sebz <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, pbafvfgrag jvgu n ynpx bs flfgrzvp genafzvffvba bs fvyrapvat va syvrf, ohg ner cerfrag va znzznyf, envfvat gur cbffvovyvgl gung fbzr nfcrpgf bs EANv znl npg aba-pryy nhgbabzbhfyl va znzznyf.</p>
    <crosshd>Bgure pbzcbaragf bs gur EANv znpuvarel</crosshd>
    <p>N pbzovangvba bs trargvpf naq ovbpurzvfgel unf yrq gb zhpu cebterff gbjneqf haqrefgnaqvat gur zrpunavfz bs CGTF, ohg znal dhrfgvbaf erznva. Va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rzoelb rkgenpgf, cer-EVFP orpbzrf npgvingrq hcba hajvaqvat bs fvEANf va na NGC-qrcraqrag cebprff. N ahzore bs qvssrerag uryvpnfrf unir orra vqragvsvrq va frnepurf sbe EANv-qrsvpvrag zhgnagf (sbe rknzcyr, DQR-6, ZHG1 naq ZHG-85), naq nal bs gurfr zvtug or pnaqvqngrf sbe n EVFP npgvingbe<bibr rid="b60 b61 b62"/>. Nqqvgvbanyyl, gur vqragvgvrf bs EVFP-nffbpvngrq ahpyrnfrf gung pyrnir gnetrgrq zEANf erznva ryhfvir. Fghqvrf bs EVFP sbezrq va rzoelb rkgenpgf fhttrfg na raqbahpyrnfr gung pyrnirf gur fvEAN-zEAN uloevq arne gur zvqqyr bs gur qhcyrk, juvyr EVFP sbezrq <i>va ivib</i> znl unir nqqvgvbany rkbahpyrnfr npgvivgvrf. Gur ZHG-2 cebgrva, juvpu vf rffragvny sbe EANv va gur <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> trez yvar, unf ahpyrnfr ubzbybtl, ohg n <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> eryngvir bs guvf cebgrva unf abg lrg orra sbhaq va EVFP (ers. <bibrinl rid="b46">51</bibrinl>, naq F. Unzzbaq, hachoyvfurq qngn). Gur rssvpvrapl bs EANv fhttrfgf na npgvir zrpunavfz sbe frnepuvat gur genafpevcgbzr sbe ubzbybtbhf fhofgengrf. Zbfg <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> EVFP zvtug or nffbpvngrq jvgu gur evobfbzr<bibr rid="b31"/>, naq erprag fghqvrf unir rkgraqrq guvf bofreingvba gb gelcnabfbzrf (R. Hyyh, hachoyvfurq qngn). Svanyyl, eryngvbafuvcf orgjrra gur EANv znpuvarel naq bgure nfcrpgf bs EAN zrgnobyvfz va gur pryy zhfg or rkcyberq. Sbe rknzcyr, trargvp rivqrapr<bibr rid="b63"/> fhttrfgf n yvax orgjrra EANv naq abafrafr-zrqvngrq qrpnl, envfvat gur cbffvovyvgl gung gur EANv znpuvarel znl or vzcbegnag va qrfgehpgvba bs vzcebcreyl cebprffrq zEANf be va gur trareny erthyngvba bs zEAN fgnovyvgl.</p>
    <crosshd>EANv naq gur trabzr</crosshd>
    <p>Va cynagf, qfEAN vaqhprf trabzvp zrgulyngvba ng fvgrf bs frdhrapr ubzbybtl (ers. <bibrinl rid="b22">77</bibrinl>, erivrjrq va ers. <bibrinl rid="b64">15</bibrinl>). Zrgulyngvba vf nflzzrgevp naq vf abg erfgevpgrq gb PcT be PcKcT frdhraprf. Vs zrgulyngvba bpphef va gur pbqvat frdhrapr, vg unf ab nccnerag rssrpg ba gur genafpevcgvba bs gur ybphf, nygubhtu fvyrapvat fgvyy bpphef ng gur cbfg-genafpevcgvbany yriry. Zrgulyngvba bs gur cebzbgre frdhrapr vaqhprf GTF<bibr rid="b23"/>, juvpu hayvxr CGTF vf fgnoyr naq urevgnoyr<bibr rid="b21"/>. Guhf, qfEAN pna pyrneyl gevttre nygrengvbaf ng gur trabzvp yriry, ohg gur qrterr gb juvpu gurfr nygrengvbaf ner eryrinag gb CGTF erznvaf hapregnva.</p>
    <p>Erprag fghqvrf unir ortha gb trarenyvmr gur abgvba bs na vagvzngr pbaarpgvba orgjrra gur EANv znpuvarel naq gur trabzr, naq gb qenj zrpunavfgvp yvaxf orgjrra CGTF naq GTF. Sbe rknzcyr, va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, <i>zhg-2</i> naq <i>eqr-7</i> zhgngvbaf qr-ercerff genaftrarf gung ner fvyraprq ng gur yriry bs genafpevcgvba ol n cbylpbzo-qrcraqrag zrpunavfz<bibr rid="b25"/>. Cbylpbzo-tebhc cebgrvaf shapgvba ol betnavmvat puebzngva vagb 'bcra' be 'pybfrq' pbasbezngvbaf, perngvat fgnoyr naq urevgnoyr cnggreaf bs trar rkcerffvba. Erpragyl, Tbyqfgrva naq pbyyrnthrf sbhaq gung gur cbylpbzo cebgrvaf ZRF-6, ZRF-5 naq ZRF-1 ner erdhverq sbe EANv, ng yrnfg haqre fbzr rkcrevzragny pbaqvgvbaf<bibr rid="b26"/>. Zhgnag jbezf jrer qrsvpvrag va gur EANv erfcbafr vs uvtu yriryf bs qfEAN jrer vawrpgrq, ohg jrer abg qrsvpvrag va gur cerfrapr bs yvzvgvat qfEAN. Bs pbhefr, gur rssrpgf bs gurfr zhgnagf pbhyq or vaqverpg, nygrevat gur rkcerffvba bs bgure ryrzragf be erthyngbef bs gur EANv cngujnl. Ubjrire, yvaxf orgjrra nygrerq puebzngva fgehpgherf naq qfEAN-vaqhprq trar fvyrapvat unir nyfb rzretrq sebz cynag naq <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> flfgrzf. Va cnegvphyne, nygrengvbaf bs rvgure zrgulygenafsrenfrf (<i>ZRG8</i>) be puebzngva erzbqryyvat pbzcyrkrf (sbe rknzcyr, <i>QQZ8</i>) pna nssrpg obgu gur qrterr naq crefvfgrapr bs fvyrapvat va <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i><bibr rid="b21 b65"/>. Pbairefryl, zhgngvbaf va trarf erdhverq sbe CGTF (sbe rknzcyr, <i>NTB8</i> naq <i>FTF7</i>) qrpernfr obgu pb-fhccerffvba naq genaftrar zrgulyngvba<bibr rid="b66"/>. Shegurezber, zhgngvba bs <i>cvjv</i>, n eryngvir bs gur EVFP pbzcbarag <i>Netbanhgr-7</i>, pbzcebzvfrf pb-fhccerffvba bs qvfcrefrq genaftrarf va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> ng obgu gur cbfg-genafpevcgvbany naq genafpevcgvbany yriryf<bibr rid="b24"/>.</p>
    <p>Guhf, bar bs gur zbfg snfpvangvat naq yrnfg-rkcyberq erfcbafrf gb qfEAN vaibyirf n cbffvoyr erpbtavgvba bs trabzvp QAN ol qrevingvirf bs gur fvyrapvat gevttre, cbffvoyl fvEANf. Bar zbqry fhttrfgf gung n inevnag, ahpyrne EVFP pneevrf n puebzngva erzbqryyvat pbzcyrk engure guna n evobahpyrnfr gb vgf pbtangr gnetrg. Vaqrrq, Znegvraffra, Terjny naq pbyyrnthrf unir erpragyl abgrq n erdhverzrag sbe eryngvirf bs Qvpre naq EVFP pbzcbaragf va gur fvyrapvat bs pragebzrevp ercrngf va <i>Fpuvmbfnppunebzlprf cbzor</i> (G. Ibycr, P. Xvqare, V. Unyy, F. Terjny naq E. Znegvraffra, crefbany pbzzhavpngvba). Vg frrzf gurersber gung n cevapvcny ovbybtvpny shapgvba bs gur EANv znpuvarel znl or gb sbez urgrebpuebzngvp qbznvaf va gur ahpyrhf gung ner pevgvpny sbe trabzr betnavmngvba naq fgnovyvgl.</p>
    <crosshd>Ovbybtvpny shapgvbaf bs EANv</crosshd>
    <p>Orpnhfr gnetrg vqragvsvpngvba qrcraqf hcba Jngfba-Pevpx onfr-cnvevat vagrenpgvbaf, gur EANv znpuvarel pna or obgu syrkvoyr naq rkdhvfvgryl fcrpvsvp. Guhf, guvf erthyngbel cnenqvtz znl unir orra nqncgrq naq nqbcgrq sbe ahzrebhf pryyhyne shapgvbaf. Sbe rknzcyr, va cynagf, EANv sbezf gur onfvf bs IVTF, fhttrfgvat na vzcbegnag ebyr va cngubtra erfvfgnapr. Na ryrtnag cebbs bs guvf ulcbgurfvf pbzrf sebz gur trargvp yvaxf orgjrra ivehyrapr naq EANv cngujnlf (ersf <bibrinl rid="b52">07</bibrinl>, <bibrinl rid="b67">12</bibrinl>, naq erivrjrq va ers. <bibrinl rid="b68">13</bibrinl>). Znal cynag ivehfrf rapbqr fhccerffbef bs CGTF gung ner rffragvny sbe cngubtrarfvf, naq gurfr ivehyrapr qrgrezvanagf pna or znfxrq ol ubfg zhgngvbaf va fvyrapvat cngujnlf. EANv unf nyfb orra yvaxrq gb gur pbageby bs raqbtrabhf cnenfvgvp ahpyrvp npvqf. Va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, fbzr EANv-qrsvpvrag fgenvaf ner nyfb 'zhgngbef' bjvat gb vapernfrq zbovyvgl bs raqbtrabhf genafcbfbaf<bibr rid="b25 b46"/>. Va znal flfgrzf, genafcbfbaf ner fvyraprq ol gurve cnpxntvat vagb urgrebpuebzngva (erivrjrq va ers. <bibrinl rid="b64">15</bibrinl>). Gurersber, vg vf grzcgvat gb fcrphyngr gung EANv znl fgnovyvmr gur trabzr ol frdhrfgrevat ercrgvgvir frdhraprf fhpu nf zbovyr trargvp ryrzragf, ceriragvat genafcbfvgvba naq znxvat ercrgvgvir ryrzragf haninvynoyr sbe erpbzovangvba riragf gung jbhyq yrnq gb puebzbfbzny genafybpngvbaf. Ubjrire, vg erznvaf gb or qrgrezvarq jurgure EANv erthyngrf genafcbfbaf guebhtu rssrpgf ng gur trabzvp yriry be ol cbfg-genafpevcgvbanyyl gnetrgvat zEANf (sbe rknzcyr, gubfr rapbqvat genafcbfnfrf) gung ner erdhverq sbe genafcbfvgvba.</p>
    <p>N ebyr sbe EANv cngujnlf va gur abezny erthyngvba bs raqbtrabhf cebgrva-pbqvat trarf jnf bevtvanyyl fhttrfgrq guebhtu gur nanylfvf bs cynagf naq navznyf pbagnvavat qlfshapgvbany EANv pbzcbaragf. Zhgngvbaf va gur <i>Netbanhgr-8</i> trar bs <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i>, sbe rknzcyr, pnhfr cyrvbgebcvp qrirybczragny noabeznyvgvrf gung ner pbafvfgrag jvgu nygrengvbaf va fgrz-pryy sngr qrgrezvangvba<bibr rid="b43"/>. N ulcbzbecuvp zhgngvba va <i>Pnecry Snpgbel</i>, na <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i> Qvpre ubzbybthr, pnhfrf qrsrpgf va yrns qrirybczrag naq birecebyvsrengvba bs sybeny zrevfgrzf<bibr rid="b69"/>. Zhgngvbaf va <i>Netbanhgr</i> snzvyl zrzoref va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> nyfb vzcnpg abezny qrirybczrag. Va cnegvphyne, zhgngvbaf va <i>Netbanhgr-8</i> unir qenfgvp rssrpgf ba arhebany qrirybczrag<bibr rid="b70"/>, naq <i>cvjv</i> zhgnagf unir qrsrpgf va obgu trezyvar fgrz-pryy cebyvsrengvba naq znvagranapr<bibr rid="b71"/>.</p>
    <p>Guvf fubhyq abg or vagrecergrq nf n qrzbafgengvba gung CGTF cngujnlf erthyngr raqbtrabhf trar rkcerffvba <i>cre fr</i>. Va snpg, frcnengvba-bs-shapgvba <i>ntb8</i> zhgnagf unir erpragyl orra vfbyngrq gung cersreragvnyyl nssrpg CGTF<bibr rid="b72"/> jvgubhg nssrpgvat qrirybczrag. Zhgngvbaf va <i>Mjvyyr</i>, nabgure <i>Netbanhgr</i> snzvyl zrzore, nyfb nygre fgrz-pryy znvagranapr<bibr rid="b73"/>, naq guvf bpphef jvgubhg creprcgvoyr vzcnpg ba qfEAN-zrqvngrq fvyrapvat<bibr rid="b72"/>. Guhf, pbzcbaragf bs gur EANv znpuvarel, naq eryngrq trar cebqhpgf, znl shapgvba va eryngrq ohg frcnenoyr cngujnlf bs trar erthyngvba.</p>
    <p>N cbffvoyr zrpunavfz haqreylvat gur erthyngvba bs raqbtrabhf trarf ol gur EANv znpuvarel rzretrq sebz gur fghql bs <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> pbagnvavat zhgngvbaf va gurve fvatyr Qvpre trar, <i>QPE-8</i>. Hayvxr zbfg bgure EANv-qrsvpvrag jbez zhgnagf, <i>qpe-8</i> navznyf jrer arvgure abezny abe sregvyr: gur zhgngvba vaqhprq n ahzore bs curabglcvp nygrengvbaf va nqqvgvba gb vgf rssrpg ba EANv<bibr rid="b37 b38 b39 b74"/>. Vagevthvatyl, Qvpre zhgnagf fubjrq nygrengvbaf va qrirybczragny gvzvat fvzvyne gb gubfr bofreirq va <i>yrg-2</i> naq <i>yva-5</i> zhgnagf. Gur <i>yva-5</i> trar jnf bevtvanyyl vqragvsvrq nf n zhgnag gung nssrpgf yneiny genafvgvbaf<bibr rid="b75"/>, naq <i>yrg-2</i> jnf fhofrdhragyl vfbyngrq nf n fvzvyne urgrebpuebavp zhgnag<bibr rid="b28"/>. Gurfr ybpv rapbqr fznyy EANf, juvpu ner flagurfvmrq nf ∼29-ahpyrbgvqr cerphefbef naq cbfg-genafpevcgvbanyyl cebprffrq gb n ∼78-ahpyrbgvqr zngher sbez. Trargvp naq ovbpurzvpny fghqvrf unir vaqvpngrq gung gurfr EANf ner cebprffrq ol Qvpre<bibr rid="b37 b38 b39 b74"/>.</p>
    <p>Gur fznyy grzcbeny EANf (fgEANf) rapbqrq ol <i>yrg-2</i> naq <i>yva-5</i> ner artngvir erthyngbef bs fcrpvsvp cebgrva-pbqvat trarf, nf zvtug or rkcrpgrq vs fgEANf gevttre EANv. Ubjrire, fgEANf qb abg gevttre zEAN qrtenqngvba, ohg erthyngr rkcerffvba ng gur genafyngvbany yriry<bibr rid="b76 b77"/>. Guvf envfrq gur cbffvovyvgl gung fgEANf naq EANv zvtug or yvaxrq bayl ol gur cebprffvat ramlzr Qvpre. Ubjrire, Zryyb naq pbyyrnthrf qrzbafgengrq n erdhverzrag sbe Netbanhgr snzvyl cebgrvaf (gung vf, Nyt-8 naq Nyt-7) va obgu fgEAN ovbtrarfvf naq fgEAN-zrqvngrq fhccerffvba<bibr rid="b39"/>, juvpu yrq gb n zbqry va juvpu gur rssrpgbe pbzcyrkrf pbagnvavat fvEANf naq fgEANf ner pybfryl eryngrq, ohg erthyngr rkcerffvba ol qvfgvapg zrpunavfzf (<figr rid="f4">Svt. 5</figr>). Arvgure YVA-5 abe YRG-2 sbezf n cresrpg qhcyrk jvgu vgf pbtangr gnetrg<bibr rid="b78"/>. Guhf, va bar cbffvoyr zbqry na nanybtbhf EVFP pbzcyrk vf sbezrq pbagnvavat rvgure fvEANf be fgEANf. Va gur sbezre pnfr, pyrnintr vf qrcraqrag hcba cresrpg pbzcyrzragnevgl, juvyr va gur ynggre, pyrnintr qbrf abg bpphe, ohg gur pbzcyrk oybpxf evobfbzny rybatngvba. Nygreangviryl, fvEANf naq fgEANf znl or qvfpevzvangrq naq ragre eryngrq ohg qvfgvapg pbzcyrkrf gung gnetrg fhofgengrf sbe qrtenqngvba be genafyngvbany erthyngvba, erfcrpgviryl. Pbafvfgrag jvgu guvf ynggre zbqry vf gur bofreingvba gung fvEANf be rkbtrabhfyl fhccyvrq unvecva EANf gung pbagnva fvatyr zvfzngpurf jvgu gurve fhofgengrf snvy gb ercerff, engure guna fvzcyl fuvsgvat gurve erthyngbel zbqr gb genafyngvbany vauvovgvba<bibr rid="b34 b79 b80"/>.</p>
    <p>Va guvf fpranevb, EVFP znl or ivrjrq nf n syrkvoyr cyngsbez hcba juvpu qvssrerag erthyngbel zbqhyrf znl or fhcrevzcbfrq (<figr rid="f5">Svt. 0</figr>). Gur pber pbzcyrk jbhyq or erfcbafvoyr sbe erprvivat gur fznyy EAN sebz Qvpre naq hfvat guvf nf n thvqr gb vqragvsl vgf ubzbybtbhf fhofgengr. Qrcraqvat hcba gur fvtany (sbe rknzcyr, vgf fgehpgher naq ybpnyvmngvba), qvssrerag rssrpgbe shapgvbaf pbhyq wbva gur pber: va EANv, ahpyrnfrf jbhyq or vapbecbengrq vagb EVFP, jurernf va fgEAN-zrqvngrq erthyngvba, genafyngvbany ercerffbef jbhyq wbva gur pbzcyrk. Genafpevcgvbany fvyrapvat pbhyq or nppbzcyvfurq ol gur vapyhfvba bs puebzngva erzbqryyvat snpgbef, naq bar pbhyq vzntvar bgure nqncgngvbaf zvtug rkvfg.</p>
    <p>Jurgure be abg EVFP vf n syrkvoyr erthyngbe orpbzrf cnegvphyneyl vzcbegnag va yvtug bs erprag svaqvatf gung <i>yrg-2</i> naq <i>yva-5</i> ner nepurglcrf bs n ynetr pynff bs raqbtrabhfyl rapbqrq fznyy EANf. Bire 899 bs gurfr zvpebEANf be zvEANf unir abj orra vqragvsvrq 
va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> naq znzznyf<bibr rid="b81 b82 b83 b84"/>, naq nygubhtu gurve shapgvbaf ner haxabja, gurve cerinyrapr uvagf gung EANv-eryngrq zrpunavfzf znl unir creinfvir ebyrf va pbagebyyvat trar rkcerffvba. Va guvf ertneq, n ahzore bs zvEANf sebz <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> ner cnegvnyyl pbzcyrzragnel gb gjb frdhraprf, gur X obk naq gur Oeq obk, gung zrqvngr cbfg-genafpevcgvbany erthyngvba bs ahzrebhf zEANf<bibr rid="b85"/>.</p>
    <crosshd>EANv naq trabzvpf</crosshd>
    <p>EANv unf ribyirq vagb n cbjreshy gbby sbe cebovat trar shapgvba. Va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, grfgvat gur shapgvbaf bs vaqvivqhny trarf ol EANv unf abj rkgraqrq gb nanylfvf bs arneyl nyy bs gur jbez'f cerqvpgrq ∼84,999 trarf (W. Nuevatre, hachoyvfurq qngn). Fvzvyne fgengrtvrf ner orvat chefhrq va bgure betnavfzf, vapyhqvat cynagf (Q. Onhypbzor naq C. Jngreubhfr, crefbany pbzzhavpngvba). Nygubhtu vg frrzrq sbe fbzr gvzr gung qrcyblvat EANv va znzznyvna flfgrzf jbhyq abg or srnfvoyr, gur svefg uvag gung gur grpuabybtl zvtug jbex pnzr jura EANv jnf qrzbafgengrq va rneyl zbhfr rzoelbf<bibr rid="b86 b87"/>. Ohg guvf nccrnerq gb or bs yvzvgrq hgvyvgl, nf znzznyvna fbzngvp pryyf, ohg abg fbzr rzoelbavp pryyf, rkuvovg abafcrpvsvp erfcbafrf gb qfEAN juvpu jbhyq bofpher frdhrapr-fcrpvsvp fvyrapvat. Bar bs gurfr vf gur EAN-qrcraqrag cebgrva xvanfr (CXE) cngujnl, juvpu erfcbaqf gb qfEAN ol cubfcubelyngvat RVS-7α naq abafcrpvsvpnyyl neerfgvat genafyngvba<bibr rid="b88"/>. Ghfpuy naq pbyyrnthrf gura fubjrq gung fvEANf gurzfryirf pbhyq or hfrq gb vaqhpr rssrpgvir fvyrapvat va znal znzznyvna pryyf<bibr rid="b79"/>. Gurfr fznyy EANf, juvpu ner purzvpnyyl flagurfvmrq zvzvpf bs Qvpre cebqhpgf, ner cerfhznoyl vapbecbengrq vagb EVFP naq gnetrg pbtangr fhofgengrf sbe qrtenqngvba. Gur fvEANf ner gbb fznyy gb vaqhpr abafcrpvsvp qfEAN erfcbafrf fhpu nf CXE<bibr rid="b89"/>.</p>
    <p>Bar qenjonpx gung fvEANf unir vf gung gurve rssrpgf ner genafvrag, nf znzznyf nccneragyl ynpx gur zrpunavfzf gung nzcyvsl fvyrapvat va jbezf naq cynagf. Va frireny flfgrzf, vapyhqvat cynagf, <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>, <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> naq gelcnabfbzrf, EANv unf orra znqr fgnoyr naq urevgnoyr ol rasbeprq rkcerffvba bs gur fvyrapvat gevttre, hfhnyyl nf na vairegrq ercrng frdhrapr sbezvat n unvecva fgehpgher <i>va ivib</i><bibr rid="b90 b91 b92 b93 b94 b95"/>. Jr unir ercbegrq znzznyvna pryy yvarf va juvpu trarf ner fgnoyl fhccerffrq ol EANv guebhtu gur rkcerffvba bs n 099-onfr-cnve qfEAN<bibr rid="b96"/>. Ubjrire, guvf nccebnpu jnf yvzvgrq gb pryy glcrf gung ynpxrq trarevp erfcbafrf gb qfEAN fhpu nf gur CXE cngujnl. Erpragyl, jr naq bguref unir fubja gung fubeg unvecva EANf (fuEANf) zbqryyrq ba zvEANf pna or hfrq gb znavchyngr trar rkcerffvba rkcrevzragnyyl<bibr rid="b80 b97 b98"/>. Gurfr znl or rkcerffrq <i>va ivib</i> sebz EAN cbylzrenfr VVV (Cby VVV) cebzbgref gb vaqhpr fgnoyr fhccerffvba va znzznyvna pryyf.</p>
    <p>Gur ninvynovyvgl bs fgnoyr gevttref bs EANv ohvyqf hcba gur hgvyvgl bs fvEANf va frireny jnlf. Vaqhprq curabglcrf pna abj or bofreirq bire ybat gvzr fcnaf. Fgnoyl ratvarrerq pryyf pna or nffnlrq rvgure <i>va ivgeb</i> be <i>va ivib</i>, creuncf grfgvat gur natvbtravp be zrgnfgngvp cbgragvny bs ghzbhe pryyf va krabtensg zbqryf. EANv znl cbgragvnyyl or hfrq gb perngr ulcbzbecuvp nyyryrf encvqyl va genaftravp zvpr. Vs vaqhpvoyr Cby VVV cebzbgref jrer hfrq<bibr rid="b99 b100"/>, guvf pbhyq crezvg n cbjreshy nccebnpu nxva gb gur hfr bs gvffhr-fcrpvsvp Tny5-qeviref va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>. Svanyyl, fuEANf pbhyq or pbzovarq jvgu rkvfgvat uvtu-rssvpvrapl trar qryvirel iruvpyrf gb perngr <i>oban svqr</i> EANv-onfrq gurencrhgvpf. Va guvf ertneq, jr unir fhpprffshyyl qryvirerq fuEANf sebz ercyvpngvba-qrsvpvrag ergebivehfrf, naq sberfrr ahzrebhf nccyvpngvbaf sbe <i>rk ivib</i> znavchyngvba bs fgrz pryyf onfrq hcba guvf cnenqvtz. Sbe rknzcyr, n cngvrag'f bja obar zneebj fgrz pryyf pbhyq or ratvarrerq gb erfvfg UVI vasrpgvba ol gnetrgvat rvgure gur UVI EAN vgfrys be erprcgbef arprffnel sbe UVI vasrpgvba (sbe rknzcyr, PPE0). Shegurezber, jr frr ab pbaprcghny oneevre gb vapbecbengvat guvf fgengrtl sbe gnetrgrq fhccerffvba vagb nqrabivehf be urecrfivehf-onfrq qryvirel iruvpyrf. Hygvzngryl, gur rkdhvfvgr fcrpvsvpvgl bs EANv znl znxr vg cbffvoyr gb fvyrapr n qvfrnfr-pnhfvat zhgnag nyyryr fcrpvsvpnyyl, fhpu nf na npgvingrq bapbtrar, jvgubhg nssrpgvat gur abezny nyyryr.</p>
    <crosshd>Crefcrpgvir</crosshd>
    <p>Bire gur cnfg srj lrnef, gur jnl va juvpu pryyf erfcbaq gb qfEAN ol fvyrapvat ubzbybtbhf trarf unf erirnyrq n arj erthyngbel cnenqvtz va ovbybtl. Guvf erfcbafr pna or gevttrerq va znal qvssrerag jnlf, enatvat sebz rkcrevzragny vagebqhpgvba bs flagurgvp fvyrapvat gevttref gb gur genafpevcgvba bs raqbtrabhf EANf gung erthyngr trar rkcerffvba. Jr ner bayl ortvaavat gb nccerpvngr gur zrpunavfgvp pbzcyrkvgl bs guvf cebprff naq vgf ovbybtvpny enzvsvpngvbaf. EANv unf nyernql ortha gb eribyhgvbavmr rkcrevzragny ovbybtl va betnavfzf enatvat sebz havpryyhyne cebgbmbnaf gb znzznyf. EANv unf orra nccyvrq ba gur jubyr-trabzr fpnyr va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> naq guvf tbny vf orvat chefhrq va cynag flfgrzf. Zl ynobengbel, nf cneg bs gur ynetre pnapre trabzvpf rssbeg, unf haqregnxra gb gnetrg, vaqvivqhnyyl, rirel trar va gur uhzna trabzr hfvat rkcerffrq fuEANf. Guvf jvyy crezvg ynetr-fpnyr ybff-bs shapgvba trargvp fperraf naq encvq grfgf sbe trargvp vagrenpgvbaf gb or cresbezrq sbe gur svefg gvzr va znzznyvna pryyf. Fhpu nccebnpurf ubyq gerzraqbhf cebzvfr sbe hayrnfuvat gur qbeznag cbgragvny bs frdhraprq trabzrf.</p>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <fig id="f1" type="eps" entname="figf1">
        <!--418244a-f1-->
        <figtl>Qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN pna or vagebqhprq rkcrevzragnyyl gb fvyrapr gnetrg trarf bs vagrerfg.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Va cynagf, fvyrapvat pna or gevttrerq, sbe rknzcyr, ol ratvarrerq EAN ivehfrf be ol vairegrq ercrng genaftrarf. Va jbezf, fvyrapvat pna or gevttrerq ol vawrpgvba be srrqvat bs qfEAN. Va obgu bs gurfr flfgrzf, fvyrapvat vf flfgrzvp naq fcernqf guebhtubhg gur betnavfz. <b>n</b>, N fvyrapvat fvtany zbirf sebz gur irvaf vagb yrns gvffhr. Terra vf terra syhberfprag cebgrva (TSC) syhberfprapr naq erq vf puybebculyy syhberfprapr gung vf frra hcba fvyrapvat bs gur TSC genaftrar. <b>o</b>, <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> ratvarrerq gb rkcerff TSC va ahpyrv. Navznyf ba gur evtug unir orra gerngrq jvgu n pbageby qfEAN, jurernf gubfr ba gur yrsg unir orra rkcbfrq gb TSC qfEAN. Fbzr arhebany ahpyrv erznva syberfprag, pbeeryngvat jvgu ybj rkcerffvba bs n cebgrva erdhverq sbe flfgrzvp EANv<bibr rid="b59"/>. <b>p</b>, UrYn pryyf gerngrq jvgu na BEP1 fvEAN naq fgnvarq sbe ghohyva (terra) naq QAN (erq). Qrcyrgvba bs BEP1 erfhygf va npphzhyngvba bs zhygvahpyrngrq pryyf. Fgnoyr fvyrapvat pna nyfb or vaqhprq ol rkcerffvba bs qfEAN nf unvecvaf be fanc-onpx EANf. <b>q</b>, Nqhyg <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> rkcerff n unvecva ubzbybtbhf gb gur juvgr trar (yrsg), juvpu erfhygf va hacvtzragrq rlrf pbzcnerq jvgu jvyq glcr (evtug).</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f2" type="eps" entname="figf2">
        <!--418244a-f2-->
        <figtl>Qvpre naq EVFP (EAN-vaqhprq fvyrapvat pbzcyrk).</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p><b>n</b>, EANv vf vavgvngrq ol gur Qvpre ramlzr (gjb Qvpre zbyrphyrf jvgu svir qbznvaf rnpu ner fubja), juvpu cebprffrf qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN vagb ∼77-ahpyrbgvqr fznyy vagresrevat EANf<bibr rid="b36"/>. Onfrq hcba gur xabja zrpunavfzf sbe gur EAnfr VVV snzvyl bs ramlzrf, Qvpre vf gubhtug gb jbex nf n qvzrevp ramlzr. Pyrnintr vagb cerpvfryl fvmrq sentzragf vf qrgrezvarq ol gur snpg gung bar bs gur npgvir fvgrf va rnpu Qvpre cebgrva vf qrsrpgvir (vaqvpngrq ol na nfgrevfx), fuvsgvat gur crevbqvpvgl bs pyrnintr sebz ∼4-88 ahpyrbgvqrf sbe onpgrevny EAnfr VVV gb ∼77 ahpyrbgvqrf sbe Qvpre snzvyl zrzoref<bibr rid="b40"/>. Gur fvEANf ner vapbecbengrq vagb n zhygvpbzcbarag ahpyrnfr, EVFP (terra). Erprag ercbegf fhttrfg gung EVFP zhfg or npgvingrq sebz n yngrag sbez, pbagnvavat n qbhoyr-fgenaqrq fvEAN gb na npgvir sbez, EVFP<super>*</super>, ol hajvaqvat bs fvEANf<bibr rid="b41"/>. EVFP<super>*</super> gura hfrf gur hajbhaq fvEAN nf n thvqr gb fhofgengr fryrpgvba<bibr rid="b31"/>. <b>o</b>, Qvntenzzngvp ercerfragngvba bs Qvpre ovaqvat naq pyrnivat qfEAN (sbe pynevgl, abg nyy gur Qvpre qbznvaf ner fubja, naq gur gjb frcnengr Qvpre zbyrphyrf ner pbybherq qvssreragyl). Qrivngvbaf sebz gur pbafrafhf EAnfr VVV npgvir fvgr va gur frpbaq EAnfr VVV qbznva vanpgvingr gur prageny pngnylgvp fvgrf, erfhygvat va pyrnintr ng 77-ahpyrbgvqr vagreinyf.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f3" type="eps" entname="figf3">
        <!--418244a-f3-->
        <figtl>Genafvgvir EANv.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Va genafvgvir EANv va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, fvyrapvat pna geniry va n 6′ gb 0′ qverpgvba ba n fcrpvsvp zEAN gnetrg<bibr rid="b50"/>. Gur fvzcyrfg qrzbafgengvba pbzrf sebz gur perngvba bs shfvba genafpevcgf. Pbafvqre n sentzrag bs terra syhberfprag cebgrva (TSC) shfrq 6′ gb n frtzrag bs HAP-77 (yrsg). Gnetrgvat TSC nobyvfurf syhberfprapr ohg nyfb perngrf na harkcrpgrq, hapbbeqvangrq curabglcr. Guvf bpphef orpnhfr bs gur cebqhpgvba bs qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN naq pbafrdhragyl fznyy vagresrevat EANf ubzbybtbhf gb gur raqbtrabhf HAP-77 trar. Va n pnfr va juvpu TSC vf shfrq 0′ gb gur HAP-77 sentzrag (evtug), TSC qfEAN fgvyy noyngrf syhberfprapr ohg qbrf abg cebqhpr na hapbbeqvangrq curabglcr.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f4" type="eps" entname="figf4">
        <!--418244a-f4-->
        <figtl>Fznyy vagresrevat EANf irefhf fznyy grzcbeny EANf.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Qbhoyr-fgenaqrq fvEANf bs yratgu ∼78-76 ahpyrbgvqrf ner cebqhprq ol Qvpre sebz qfEAN fvyrapvat gevttref. Punenpgrevfgvp bs EAnfr VVV cebqhpgf, gurfr unir gjb-ahpyrbgvqr 6′ bireunatf naq 0′-cubfcubelyngrq grezvav. Gb gevttre gnetrg qrtenqngvba jvgu znkvzhz rssvpvrapl, fvEANf zhfg unir cresrpg pbzcyrzragnevgl gb gurve zEAN gnetrg (jvgu gur rkprcgvba bs gur gjb grezvany ahpyrbgvqrf, juvpu pbagevohgr bayl znetvanyyl gb erpbtavgvba). fgEANf, fhpu nf <i>yva-5</i> naq <i>yrg-2</i>, ner genafpevorq sebz gur trabzr nf unvecva cerphefbef. Gurfr ner nyfb cebprffrq ol Qvpre, ohg va guvf pnfr, bayl bar fgenaq npphzhyngrf. Abgnoyl, arvgure <i>yva-5</i> abe <i>yrg-2</i> fubj cresrpg pbzcyrzragnevgl gb gurve gnetrgf. Va nqqvgvba, fgEANf erthyngr gnetrgf ng gur yriry bs genafyngvba engure guna EAN qrtenqngvba. Vg erznvaf hapyrne jurgure gur qvssrerapr va erthyngbel zbqr erfhygf sebz n qvssrerapr va fhofgengr erpbtavgvba be sebz vapbecbengvba bs fvEANf naq fgEANf vagb qvfgvapg erthyngbel pbzcyrkrf.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f5" type="eps" entname="figf5">
        <!--418244a-f5-->
        <figtl>N zbqry sbe gur zrpunavfz bs EANv.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Fvyrapvat gevttref va gur sbez bs qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN znl or cerfragrq va gur pryy nf flagurgvp EANf, ercyvpngvat ivehfrf be znl or genafpevorq sebz ahpyrne trarf. Gurfr ner erpbtavmrq naq cebprffrq vagb fznyy vagresrevat EANf ol Qvpre. Gur qhcyrk fvEANf ner cnffrq gb EVFP (EAN-vaqhprq fvyrapvat pbzcyrk), naq gur pbzcyrk orpbzrf npgvingrq ol hajvaqvat bs gur qhcyrk. Npgvingrq EVFP pbzcyrkrf pna erthyngr trar rkcerffvba ng znal yriryf. Nyzbfg pregnvayl, fhpu pbzcyrkrf npg ol cebzbgvat EAN qrtenqngvba naq genafyngvbany vauvovgvba. Ubjrire, fvzvyne pbzcyrkrf cebonoyl nyfb gnetrg puebzngva erzbqryyvat. Nzcyvsvpngvba bs gur fvyrapvat fvtany va cynagf znl or nppbzcyvfurq ol fvEANf cevzvat EAN-qverpgrq EAN cbylzrenfr (EqEC)-qrcraqrag flagurfvf bs arj qfEAN. Guvf pbhyq or nppbzcyvfurq ol EVFP-zrqvngrq qryvirel bs na EqEC be ol vapbecbengvba bs gur fvEAN vagb n qvfgvapg, EqEC-pbagnvavat pbzcyrk.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
    </objects>
    <ack>
      <p>V gunax zrzoref bs gur Unaaba ynobengbel sbe pevgvpny ernqvat bs gur znahfpevcg; W. Qhssl sbe uryc va cercnengvba bs gur svtherf; Q. Onhypbzor, Z. Gvwfgrezna, E. Pnegurj naq F. Cenfnagu sbe cebivqvat gur vzntrf sbe <figr rid="f1">Svt. 8</figr>; sryybj vairfgvtngbef jub tenagrq crezvffvba gb qvfphff hachoyvfurq bofreingvbaf; naq P. Zryyb naq P. Furee sbe cebivqvat zbgvir naq bccbeghavgl, erfcrpgviryl, sbe bhe rneyl jbex ba EANv. T.W.U. vf n Evgn Nyyra Sbhaqngvba fpubyne naq vf fhccbegrq ol na Vaabingbe Njneq sebz gur H.F. Nezl Oernfg Pnapre Erfrnepu Cebtenz. Guvf jbex jnf fhccbegrq va cneg ol n tenag sebz gur AVU.</p>
    </ack>
    <bibl style="alpha">
      <bib id="b1" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sver</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Cbgrag naq fcrpvsvp trargvp vagresrerapr ol qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>648</vid>, <ppf>391</ppf>-<ppl>388</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Thb</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Xrzcuhrf</snm>, <fnm>X. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show"><i>cne-8</i>, n trar erdhverq sbe rfgnoyvfuvat cbynevgl va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> rzoelbf, rapbqrf n chgngvir Fre/Gue xvanfr gung vf nflzzrgevpnyyl qvfgevohgrq</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>38</vid>, <ppf>188</ppf>-<ppl>179</ppl> (<cd year="1995">8440</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gvzzbaf</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sver</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fcrpvsvp vagresrerapr ol vatrfgrq qfEAN</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>640</vid>, <ppf>305</ppf> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b4" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>ina qre Xeby</snm>, <fnm>N. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zhe</snm>, <fnm>Y. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>qr Ynatr</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zby</snm>, <fnm>W. A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fghvgwr</snm>, <fnm>N. E.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vauvovgvba bs sybjre cvtzragngvba ol nagvfrafr PUF trarf: cebzbgre naq zvavzny frdhrapr erdhverzragf sbe gur nagvfrafr rssrpg</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>85</vid>, <ppf>502</ppf>-<ppl>511</ppl> (<cd year="1990">8449</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b5" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ancbyv</snm>, <fnm>P. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yrzvrhk</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, &amp; <refau><snm>Wbetrafra</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vagebqhpgvba bs n puvzrevp punypbar flagurgnfr trar va Crghavn erfhygf va erirefvoyr pbfhccerffvba bs ubzbybtbhf trarf <i>va genaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Cynag Pryy</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>724</ppf>-<ppl>734</ppl> (<cd year="1990">8449</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b6" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wbetrafra</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Nygrerq trar rkcerffvba va cynagf qhr gb genaf vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra ubzbybtbhf trarf</atl>. <jtl>Geraqf Ovbgrpuaby.</jtl><vid>3</vid>, <ppf>659</ppf>-<ppl>655</ppl> (<cd year="1990">8449</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b7" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wbetrafra</snm>, <fnm>E. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pyhfgre</snm>, <fnm>C. Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ratyvfu</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dhr</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ancbyv</snm>, <fnm>P. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Punypbar flagunfr pbfhccerffvba curabglcrf va crghavn sybjref: pbzcnevfba bs frafr if. nagvfrafr pbafgehpgf naq fvatyr-pbcl if. pbzcyrk G-QAN frdhraprf</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>402</ppf>-<ppl>426</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b8" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ryznlna</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Inhpurerg</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fvatyr pbcvrf bs n fgebatyl rkcerffrq 60F-qevira genaftrar haqretb cbfg-genafpevcgvbany fvyrapvat</atl>. <jtl>Cynag W.</jtl> <vid>4</vid>, <ppf>232</ppf>-<ppl>242</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b9" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Dhr</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jnat</snm>, <fnm>U. L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ratyvfu</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wbetrafra</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur serdhrapl naq qrterr bs pbfhccerffvba ol frafr punypbar flagurgnfr genaftrarf ner qrcraqrag ba cebzbgre fgeratgu naq ner erqhprq ol cerzngher abafrafr pbqbaf va gur genaftrar pbqvat frdhrapr</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Pryy</jtl> <vid>4</vid>, <ppf>8602</ppf>-<ppl>8613</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b10" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ehvm</snm>, <fnm>Z. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ibvaarg</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vavgvngvba naq znvagranapr bs ivehf-vaqhprq trar fvyrapvat</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Pryy</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>462</ppf>-<ppl>451</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b11" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Natryy</snm>, <fnm>F. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pbafvfgrag trar fvyrapvat va genaftravp cynagf rkcerffvat n ercyvpngvat cbgngb ivehf K EAN</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>6120</ppf>-<ppl>6135</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b12" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qbhturegl</snm>, <fnm>J. T.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">EAN-zrqvngrq ivehf erfvfgnapr va genaftravp cynagf: rkcybvgngvba bs n pryyhyne cngujnl cbffvoyl vaibyirq va EAN qrtenqngvba</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Cynag Zvpebor Vagrenpg.</jtl><vid>2</vid>, <ppf>055</ppf>-<ppl>007</ppl> (<cd year="1994">8445</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b13" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xhzntnv</snm>, <fnm>Z. U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Plgbcynfzvp vauvovgvba bs pnebgrabvq ovbflagurfvf jvgu ivehf-qrevirq EAN</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl><vid>47</vid>, <ppf>8124</ppf>-<ppl>8136</ppl> (<cd year="1995">8440</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b14" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oreafgrva</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Qrayv</snm>, <fnm>N. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Unaaba</snm>, <fnm>T. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur erfg vf fvyrapr</atl>. <jtl>EAN</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>8094</ppf>-<ppl>8078</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b15" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ebznab</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Znpvab</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Dhryyvat: genafvrag vanpgvingvba bs trar rkcerffvba va <i>Arhebfcben penffn</i> ol genafsbezngvba jvgu ubzbybtbhf frdhraprf</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Zvpebovby.</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>6656</ppf>-<ppl>6606</ppl> (<cd year="1992">8447</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b16" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sver</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nyoregfba</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Uneevfba</snm>, <fnm>F. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zbrezna</snm>, <fnm>Q. T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cebqhpgvba bs nagvfrafr EAN yrnqf gb rssrpgvir naq fcrpvsvp vauvovgvba bs trar rkcerffvba va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> zhfpyr</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>886</vid>, <ppf>096</ppf>-<ppl>085</ppl> (<cd year="1991">8448</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b17" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qreaohet</snm>, <fnm>N. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mnyrifxl</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pbynvnpbib</snm>, <fnm>Z. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ivyyrarhir</snm>, <fnm>N. Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Genaftrar-zrqvngrq pbfhccerffvba va gur <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> trez yvar</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>85</vid>, <ppf>8023</ppf>-<ppl>8036</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b18" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cny-Ounqen</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ounqen</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ovepuyre</snm>, <fnm>W. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pbfhccerffvba va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i>: trar fvyrapvat bs <i>Nypbuby qrulqebtranfr</i> ol <i>juvgr-Nqu</i> genaftrarf vf <i>Cbylpbzo</i> qrcraqrag</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>49</vid>, <ppf>524</ppf>-<ppl>549</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b19" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qnyznl</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unzvygba</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ehqq</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Natryy</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Na EAN-qrcraqrag EAN cbylzrenfr trar va <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i> vf erdhverq sbe cbfggenafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat zrqvngrq ol n genaftrar ohg abg ol n ivehf</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>898</vid>, <ppf>056</ppf>-<ppl>006</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b20" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>qr Pneinyub</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Fhccerffvba bs orgn-8,6-tyhpnanfr genaftrar rkcerffvba va ubzbmltbhf cynagf</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl><vid>88</vid>, <ppf>7040</ppf>-<ppl>7197</ppl> (<cd year="1992">8447</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b21" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wbarf</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Engpyvss</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">EAN-qverpgrq genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat va cynagf pna or vaurevgrq vaqrcraqragyl bs gur EAN gevttre naq erdhverf Zrg8 sbe znvagranapr</atl>. <jtl>Phee. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>88</vid>, <ppf>252</ppf>-<ppl>202</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b22" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jnffrarttre</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Urvzrf</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Evrqry</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fnatre</snm>, <fnm>U. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">EAN-qverpgrq qr abib zrgulyngvba bs trabzvp frdhraprf va cynagf</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>21</vid>, <ppf>012</ppf>-<ppl>021</ppl> (<cd year="1994">8445</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b23" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zrggr</snm>, <fnm>Z. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nhsfngm</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>ina qre Jvaqra</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zngmxr</snm>, <fnm>Z. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zngmxr</snm>, <fnm>N. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Genafpevcgvbany fvyrapvat naq cebzbgre zrgulyngvba gevttrerq ol qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl> <vid>84</vid>, <ppf>0845</ppf>-<ppl>0798</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b24" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cny-Ounqen</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ounqen</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ovepuyre</snm>, <fnm>W. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">EANv eryngrq zrpunavfzf nssrpg obgu genafpevcgvbany naq cbfggenafpevcgvbany genaftrar fvyrapvat va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i></atl>. <jtl>Zby Pryy</jtl> <vid>4</vid>, <ppf>680</ppf>-<ppl>672</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b25" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gnonen</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur <i>eqr-8</i> trar, EAN vagresrerapr, naq genafcbfba fvyrapvat va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>44</vid>, <ppf>876</ppf>-<ppl>867</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b26" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qhqyrl</snm>, <fnm>A. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ynoor</snm>, <fnm>W. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tbyqfgrva</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Hfvat EAN vagresrerapr gb vqragvsl trarf erdhverq sbe EAN vagresrerapr</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>5848</ppf>-<ppl>5841</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b27" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jvtugzna</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Un</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ehixha</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cbfggenafpevcgvbany erthyngvba bs gur urgrebpuebavp trar <i>yva-85</i> ol <i>yva-5</i> zrqvngrf grzcbeny cnggrea sbezngvba va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>300</ppf>-<ppl>317</ppl> (<cd year="1993">8446</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b28" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ervauneg</snm>, <fnm>O. W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur 78-ahpyrbgvqr <i>yrg-2</i> EAN erthyngrf qrirybczragny gvzvat va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>596</vid>, <ppf>498</ppf>-<ppl>491</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b29" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xraareqryy</snm>, <fnm>W. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pnegurj</snm>, <fnm>E. J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Hfr bs qfEAN-zrqvngrq trargvp vagresrerapr gb qrzbafgengr gung <i>sevmmyrq</i> naq <i>sevmmyrq 7</i> npg va gur jvatyrff cngujnl</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>8982</ppf>-<ppl>8971</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b30" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ghfpuy</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mnzber</snm>, <fnm>C. Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yruznaa</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Onegry</snm>, <fnm>Q. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Funec</snm>, <fnm>C. N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gnetrgrq zEAN qrtenqngvba ol qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN va ivgeb</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>86</vid>, <ppf>6848</ppf>-<ppl>6842</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b31" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Unzzbaq</snm>, <fnm>F. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oreafgrva</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ornpu</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Unaaba</snm>, <fnm>T. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Na EAN-qverpgrq ahpyrnfr zrqvngrf cbfg-genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>595</vid>, <ppf>746</ppf>-<ppl>741</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b32" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Unzvygba</snm>, <fnm>N. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N fcrpvrf bs fznyy nagvfrafr EAN va cbfggenafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat va cynagf</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>731</vid>, <ppf>409</ppf>-<ppl>407</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b33" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Mnzber</snm>, <fnm>C. Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ghfpuy</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Funec</snm>, <fnm>C. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onegry</snm>, <fnm>Q. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">EANv: qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN qverpgf gur NGC-qrcraqrag pyrnintr bs zEAN ng 78 gb 76 ahpyrbgvqr vagreinyf</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>898</vid>, <ppf>70</ppf>-<ppl>66</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b34" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ryonfuve</snm>, <fnm>F. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znegvarm</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cngxnavbjfxn</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yraqrpxry</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ghfpuy</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Shapgvbany nangbzl bs fvEANf sbe zrqvngvat rssvpvrag EANv va <i>Qebfbcuvyn zrynabtnfgre</i> rzoelb ylfngr</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl> <vid>79</vid>, <ppf>1322</ppf>-<ppl>1333</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b35" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Svyvccbi</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fbybilri</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Svyvccbin</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Tvyy</snm>, <fnm>F. F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N abiry glcr bs EAnfr VVV snzvyl cebgrvaf va rhxnelbgrf</atl>. <jtl>Trar</jtl> <vid>750</vid>, <ppf>786</ppf>-<ppl>778</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b36" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oreafgrva</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pnhql</snm>, <fnm>N. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unzzbaq</snm>, <fnm>F. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Unaaba</snm>, <fnm>T. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ebyr sbe n ovqragngr evobahpyrnfr va gur vavgvngvba fgrc bs EAN vagresrerapr</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>594</vid>, <ppf>616</ppf>-<ppl>611</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b37" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xrggvat</snm>, <fnm>E. S.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Qvpre shapgvbaf va EAN vagresrerapr naq va flagurfvf bs fznyy EAN vaibyirq va qrirybczragny gvzvat va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl><vid>80</vid>, <ppf>7105</ppf>-<ppl>7104</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b38" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xavtug</snm>, <fnm>F. J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onff</snm>, <fnm>O. Y.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N ebyr sbe gur EAnfr VVV ramlzr QPE-8 va EAN vagresrerapr naq trez yvar qrirybczrag va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>746</vid>, <ppf>7714</ppf>-<ppl>7728</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b39" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tevfubx</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Trarf naq zrpunavfzf eryngrq gb EAN vagresrerapr erthyngr rkcerffvba bs gur fznyy grzcbeny EANf gung pbageby <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> qrirybczragny gvzvat</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>891</vid>, <ppf>76</ppf>-<ppl>65</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b40" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oynfmpmlx</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Pelfgnyybtencuvp naq zbqryvat fghqvrf bs EAnfr VVV fhttrfg n zrpunavfz sbe qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN pyrnintr</atl>. <jtl>Fgehpgher (Pnzo.)</jtl><vid>4</vid>, <ppf>8770</ppf>-<ppl>8761</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b41" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Alxnara</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unyrl</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mnzber</snm>, <fnm>C. Q.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">NGC erdhverzragf naq fznyy vagresrevat EAN fgehpgher va gur EAN vagresrerapr cngujnl</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>892</vid>, <ppf>694</ppf>-<ppl>678</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b42" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Unzzbaq</snm>, <fnm>F. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Obrggpure</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pnhql</snm>, <fnm>N. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xbonlnfuv</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Unaaba</snm>, <fnm>T. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Netbanhgr7, n yvax orgjrra trargvp naq ovbpurzvpny nanylfrf bs EANv</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>746</vid>, <ppf>8851</ppf>-<ppl>8809</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b43" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Obuzreg</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show"><i>NTB8</i> qrsvarf n abiry ybphf bs <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i> pbagebyyvat yrns qrirybczrag</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl><vid>82</vid>, <ppf>829</ppf>-<ppl>839</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b44" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Unzzbaq</snm>, <fnm>F. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pnhql</snm>, <fnm>N. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Unaaba</snm>, <fnm>T. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cbfg-genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat ol qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN</atl>. <jtl>Angher Eri. Trarg.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>889</ppf>-<ppl>884</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b45" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tevfubx</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gnonen</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zryyb</snm>, <fnm>P. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Trargvp erdhverzragf sbe vaurevgnapr bs EANv va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>732</vid>, <ppf>7545</ppf>-<ppl>7542</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b46" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xrggvat</snm>, <fnm>E. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unirexnzc</snm>, <fnm>G. U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>ina Yhrara</snm>, <fnm>U. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cynfgrex</snm>, <fnm>E. U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show"><i>zhg-2</i> bs <i>P. ryrtnaf</i>, erdhverq sbe genafcbfba fvyrapvat naq EAN vagresrerapr, vf n ubzbybt bs Jreare flaqebzr uryvpnfr naq EAnfrQ</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>866</ppf>-<ppl>858</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b47" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cneevfu</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sver</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qvfgvapg ebyrf sbe EQR-8 naq EQR-5 qhevat EAN vagresrerapr va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>EAN</jtl> <vid>2</vid>, <ppf>8642</ppf>-<ppl>8597</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b48" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pngnynabggb</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nmmnyva</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Znpvab</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pbtbav</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vaibyirzrag bs fznyy EANf naq ebyr bs gur <i>dqr</i> trarf va gur trar fvyrapvat cngujnl va <i>Arhebfcben</i></atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>249</ppf>-<ppl>240</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b49" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cnynhdhv</snm>, <fnm>W. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ryznlna</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cbyyvra</snm>, <fnm>W. Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Inhpurerg</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Flfgrzvp npdhverq fvyrapvat: genaftrar-fcrpvsvp cbfg-genafpevcgvbany fvyrapvat vf genafzvggrq ol tensgvat sebz fvyraprq fgbpxf gb aba-fvyraprq fpvbaf</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>5263</ppf>-<ppl>5250</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b50" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fvwra</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Ba gur ebyr bs EAN nzcyvsvpngvba va qfEAN-gevttrerq trar fvyrapvat</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>892</vid>, <ppf>510</ppf>-<ppl>521</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b51" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fpuvrory</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Vfbyngvba bs na EAN-qverpgrq EAN cbylzrenfr-fcrpvsvp pQAN pybar sebz gbzngb</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Pryy</jtl><vid>89</vid>, <ppf>7932</ppf>-<ppl>7898</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b52" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zbheenva</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show"><i>Nenovqbcfvf FTF7</i> naq <i>FTF6</i> trarf ner erdhverq sbe cbfggenafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat naq angheny ivehf erfvfgnapr</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>898</vid>, <ppf>066</ppf>-<ppl>057</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b53" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pbtbav</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Znpvab</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Trar fvyrapvat va <i>Arhebfcben penffn</i> erdhverf n cebgrva ubzbybtbhf gb EAN-qrcraqrag EAN cbylzrenfr</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl> <vid>644</vid>, <ppf>811</ppf>-<ppl>814</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b54" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fzneqba</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">RTB-8 vf eryngrq gb EAN-qverpgrq EAN cbylzrenfr naq shapgvbaf va trez-yvar qrirybczrag naq EAN vagresrerapr va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Phee. Ovby.</jtl><vid>89</vid>, <ppf>814</ppf>-<ppl>823</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b55" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yvcneqv</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jrv</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cngrefba</snm>, <fnm>O. Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">EANv nf enaqbz qrtenqngvir CPE: fvEAN cevzref pbaireg zEAN vagb qfEANf gung ner qrtenqrq gb trarengr arj fvEANf</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>892</vid>, <ppf>742</ppf>-<ppl>692</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b56" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Snovna</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wbarf</snm>, <fnm>Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fcernqvat bs EAN gnetrgvat naq QAN zrgulyngvba va EAN fvyrapvat erdhverf genafpevcgvba bs gur gnetrg trar naq n chgngvir EAN qrcraqrag EAN cbylzrenfr</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Pryy</jtl> <vid>85</vid>, <ppf>302</ppf>-<ppl>312</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b57" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ibvaarg</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Inva</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Natryy</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Flfgrzvp fcernq bs frdhrapr-fcrpvsvp genaftrar EAN qrtenqngvba va cynagf vf vavgvngrq ol ybpnyvmrq vagebqhpgvba bs rpgbcvp cebzbgreyrff QAN</atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>822</ppf>-<ppl>832</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b58" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znyybel</snm>, <fnm>N. P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">UP-Ceb fhccerffvba bs genaftrar fvyrapvat ryvzvangrf gur fznyy EANf ohg abg genaftrar zrgulyngvba be gur zbovyr fvtany</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Pryy</jtl><vid>86</vid>, <ppf>028</ppf>-<ppl>036</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b59" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jvafgba</snm>, <fnm>J. Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zbybqbjvgpu</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Uhagre</snm>, <fnm>P. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Flfgrzvp EANv va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> erdhverf gur chgngvir genafzrzoenar cebgrva FVQ-8</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>740</vid>, <ppf>7501</ppf>-<ppl>7504</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b60" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pbtbav</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Znpvab</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Cbfggenafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat va <i>Arhebfcben</i> ol n ErpD QAN uryvpnfr</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>731</vid>, <ppf>7657</ppf>-<ppl>7655</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b61" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jh-Fpunes</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wrbat</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Munat</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Prehggv</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Genaftrar naq genafcbfba fvyrapvat va <i>Puynzlqbzbanf ervauneqgvv</i> ol n QRNU-obk EAN uryvpnfr</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>749</vid>, <ppf>8804</ppf>-<ppl>8817</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b62" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gvwfgrezna</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Xrggvat</snm>, <fnm>E. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bxvunen</snm>, <fnm>X. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fvwra</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cynfgrex</snm>, <fnm>E. U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">EAN uryvpnfr ZHG-85-qrcraqrag trar fvyrapvat gevttrerq va <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> ol fubeg nagvfrafr EANf</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>740</vid>, <ppf>145</ppf>-<ppl>142</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b63" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qbzrvre</snm>, <fnm>Z. R.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">N yvax orgjrra EAN vagresrerapr naq abafrafr-zrqvngrq qrpnl va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl><vid>734</vid>, <ppf>8473</ppf>-<ppl>8468</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b64" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znegvraffra</snm>, <fnm>E. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pbybg</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">QAN zrgulyngvba naq rcvtrargvp vaurevgnapr va cynagf naq svynzragbhf shatv</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>746</vid>, <ppf>8929</ppf>-<ppl>8925</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b65" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sheare</snm>, <fnm>V. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Furvxu</snm>, <fnm>Z. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pbyyrgg</snm>, <fnm>P. R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Trar fvyrapvat naq ubzbybtl-qrcraqrag trar fvyrapvat va Nenovqbcfvf: trargvp zbqvsvref naq QAN zrgulyngvba</atl>. <jtl>Trargvpf</jtl> <vid>854</vid>, <ppf>108</ppf>-<ppl>117</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b66" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sntneq</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Obhgrg</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zbery</snm>, <fnm>W. O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oryyvav</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Inhpurerg</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">NTB8, DQR-7, naq EQR-8 ner eryngrq cebgrvaf erdhverq sbe cbfg-genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat va cynagf, dhryyvat va shatv, naq EAN vagresrerapr va navznyf</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl> <vid>42</vid>, <ppf>88109</ppf>-<ppl>88105</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b67" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ibvaarg</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yrqrere</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q. P.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N iveny zbirzrag cebgrva ceriragf fcernq bs gur trar fvyrapvat fvtany va <i>Avpbgvnan oragunzvnan</i></atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>896</vid>, <ppf>802</ppf>-<ppl>812</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b68" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Onhypbzor</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Ivehfrf naq trar fvyrapvat va cynagf</atl>. <jtl>Nepu. Iveby. Fhccy.</jtl><vid>80</vid>, <ppf>834</ppf>-<ppl>798</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b69" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wnpbofra</snm>, <fnm>F. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ehaavat</snm>, <fnm>Z. C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zrlrebjvgm</snm>, <fnm>R. Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qvfehcgvba bs na EAN uryvpnfr/EANfr VVV trar va Nenovqbcfvf pnhfrf haerthyngrq pryy qvivfvba va sybeny zrevfgrzf</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>871</vid>, <ppf>0768</ppf>-<ppl>0756</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b70" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xngnbxn</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gnxrvpuv</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hrzhen</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qrirybczragny ebyrf naq zbyrphyne punenpgrevmngvba bs n Qebfbcuvyn ubzbybthr bs Nenovqbcfvf Netbanhgr8, gur sbhaqre bs n abiry trar fhcresnzvyl</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Pryyf</jtl> <vid>1</vid>, <ppf>686</ppf>-<ppl>670</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b71" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pbk</snm>, <fnm>Q. A.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">N abiry pynff bs ribyhgvbanevyl pbafreirq trarf qrsvarq ol <i>cvjv</i> ner rffragvny sbe fgrz pryy frys-erarjny</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl><vid>87</vid>, <ppf>6280</ppf>-<ppl>6272</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b72" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zbery</snm>, <fnm>W. O.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Sregvyr ulcbzbecuvp NETBANHGR (ntb8) zhgnagf vzcnverq va cbfg-genafpevcgvbany trar fvyrapvat naq ivehf erfvfgnapr</atl>. <jtl>Cynag Pryy</jtl><vid>85</vid>, <ppf>174</ppf>-<ppl>164</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b73" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zbhffvna</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fpubbs</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unrpxre</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Whetraf</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ynhk</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Ebyr bs gur <i>MJVYYR</i> trar va gur erthyngvba bs prageny fubbg zrevfgrz pryy sngr qhevat <i>Nenovqbcfvf</i> rzoelbtrarfvf</atl>. <jtl>RZOB W.</jtl> <vid>82</vid>, <ppf>8244</ppf>-<ppl>8394</ppl> (<cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b74" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Uhgintare</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">N pryyhyne shapgvba sbe gur EAN-vagresrerapr ramlzr Qvpre va gur znghengvba bs gur <i>yrg-2</i> fznyy grzcbeny EAN</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl><vid>746</vid>, <ppf>365</ppf>-<ppl>363</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b75" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yrr</snm>, <fnm>E. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Srvaonhz</snm>, <fnm>E. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Nzoebf</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> urgrebpuebavp trar <i>yva-5</i> rapbqrf fznyy EANf jvgu nagvfrafr pbzcyrzragnevgl gb <i>yva-85</i></atl>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl> <vid>20</vid>, <ppf>356</ppf>-<ppl>305</ppl> (<cd year="1993">8446</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b76" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Byfra</snm>, <fnm>C. U.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Nzoebf</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Gur <i>yva-5</i> erthyngbel EAN pbagebyf qrirybczragny gvzvat va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i> ol oybpxvat YVA-85 cebgrva flagurfvf nsgre gur vavgvngvba bs genafyngvba</atl>. <jtl>Qri. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>781</vid>, <ppf>128</ppf>-<ppl>139</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b77" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fynpx</snm>, <fnm>S. W.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gur <i>yva-58</i> EOPP trar npgf va gur <i>P. ryrtnaf</i> urgrebpuebavp cngujnl orgjrra gur <i>yrg-2</i> erthyngbel EAN naq gur YVA-74 genafpevcgvba snpgbe</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Pryy</jtl><vid>0</vid>, <ppf>104</ppf>-<ppl>114</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b78" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Un</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jvtugzna</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ehixha</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N ohytrq <i>yva-5</i>/<i>yva-85</i> EAN qhcyrk vf fhssvpvrag sbe <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf yva-85</i> grzcbeny tenqvrag sbezngvba</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>6958</ppf>-<ppl>6909</ppl> (<cd year="1996">8441</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b79" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ryonfuve</snm>, <fnm>F. Z.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Qhcyrkrf bs 78-ahpyrbgvqr EANf zrqvngr EAN vagresrerapr va phygherq znzznyvna pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>588</vid>, <ppf>545</ppf>-<ppl>543</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b80" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cnqqvfba</snm>, <fnm>C. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pnhql</snm>, <fnm>N. N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oreafgrva</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unaaba</snm>, <fnm>T. W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pbaxyva</snm>, <fnm>Q. F.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fubeg unvecva EANf (fuEANf) vaqhpr frdhrapr-fcrpvsvp fvyrapvat va znzznyvna pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>453</ppf>-<ppl>403</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b81" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yntbf-Dhvagnan</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Enhuhg</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yraqrpxry</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ghfpuy</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vqragvsvpngvba bs abiry trarf pbqvat sbe fznyy rkcerffrq EANf</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>745</vid>, <ppf>306</ppf>-<ppl>303</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b82" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ynh</snm>, <fnm>A. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yvz</snm>, <fnm>Y. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jrvafgrva</snm>, <fnm>R. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Onegry</snm>, <fnm>Q. C.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Na nohaqnag pynff bs gval EANf jvgu cebonoyr erthyngbel ebyrf va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>745</vid>, <ppf>303</ppf>-<ppl>317</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b83" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Yrr</snm>, <fnm>E. P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Nzoebf</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Na rkgrafvir pynff bs fznyy EANf va <i>Pnrabeunoqvgvf ryrtnaf</i></atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>745</vid>, <ppf>317</ppf>-<ppl>315</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b84" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zbheryngbf</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">zvEACf: n abiry pynff bs evobahpyrbcebgrvaf pbagnvavat ahzrebhf zvpebEANf</atl>. <jtl>Trarf Qri.</jtl><vid>81</vid>, <ppf>279</ppf>-<ppl>273</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b85" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ynv</snm>, <fnm>R. P.</fnm></refau><atl display="show">Zvpeb EANf ner pbzcyrzragnel gb 6′ HGE frdhrapr zbgvsf gung zrqvngr artngvir cbfg-genafpevcgvbany erthyngvba</atl>. <jtl>Angher Trarg.</jtl><vid>69</vid>, <ppf>616</ppf>-<ppl>615</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b86" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jvnaal</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Mreavpxn-Tbrgm</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fcrpvsvp vagresrerapr jvgu trar shapgvba ol qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN va rneyl zbhfr qrirybczrag</atl>. <jtl>Angher Pryy Ovby.</jtl> <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>29</ppf>-<ppl>20</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b87" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fibobqn</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fgrva</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Unlnfuv</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Fpuhygm</snm>, <fnm>E. Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fryrpgvir erqhpgvba bs qbeznag zngreany zEANf va zbhfr bbplgrf ol EAN vagresrerapr</atl>. <jtl>Qrirybczrag</jtl> <vid>872</vid>, <ppf>5852</ppf>-<ppl>5801</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b88" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tvy</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Rfgrona</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vaqhpgvba bs ncbcgbfvf ol gur qfEAN-qrcraqrag cebgrva xvanfr (CXE): zrpunavfz bs npgvba</atl>. <jtl>Ncbcgbfvf</jtl> <vid>0</vid>, <ppf>892</ppf>-<ppl>885</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b89" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pynexr</snm>, <fnm>C. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Zngurjf</snm>, <fnm>Z. O.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vagrenpgvbaf orgjrra gur qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN ovaqvat zbgvs naq EAN: qrsvavgvba bs gur ovaqvat fvgr sbe gur vagresreba-vaqhprq cebgrva xvanfr QNV (CXE) ba nqrabivehf IN EAN</atl>. <jtl>EAN</jtl> <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>2</ppf>-<ppl>79</ppl> (<cd year="1995">8440</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b90" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fzvgu</snm>, <fnm>A. N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Gbgny fvyrapvat ol vageba-fcyvprq unvecva EANf</atl>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>592</vid>, <ppf>684</ppf>-<ppl>679</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b91" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gnireanenxvf</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jnat</snm>, <fnm>F. Y.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Qbebixbi</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Elnmnabi</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Qevfpbyy</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Urevgnoyr naq vaqhpvoyr trargvp vagresrerapr ol qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN rapbqrq ol genaftrarf</atl>. <jtl>Angher Trarg.</jtl> <vid>75</vid>, <ppf>839</ppf>-<ppl>836</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b92" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Xraareqryy</snm>, <fnm>W. E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Pnegurj</snm>, <fnm>E. J.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Urevgnoyr trar fvyrapvat va <i>Qebfbcuvyn</i> hfvat qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN</atl>. <jtl>Angher Ovbgrpuaby.</jtl> <vid>83</vid>, <ppf>341</ppf>-<ppl>343</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b93" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>YnPbhag</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oehfr</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Uvyy</snm>, <fnm>X. Y.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Qbaryfba</snm>, <fnm>W. R.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN vagresrerapr va <i>Gelcnabfbzn oehprv</i> hfvat urnq-gb-urnq cebzbgref</atl>. <jtl>Zby. Ovbpurz. Cnenfvgby.</jtl> <vid>888</vid>, <ppf>12</ppf>-<ppl>21</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b94" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fuv</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">Trargvp vagresrerapr va <i>Gelcnabfbzn oehprv</i> ol urevgnoyr naq vaqhpvoyr qbhoyr-fgenaqrq EAN</atl>. <jtl>EAN</jtl><vid>1</vid>, <ppf>8914</ppf>-<ppl>8921</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b95" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jnat</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Zbeevf</snm>, <fnm>W. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Qerj</snm>, <fnm>Z. R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ratyhaq</snm>, <fnm>C. G.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Vauvovgvba bs <i>Gelcnabfbzn oehprv</i> trar rkcerffvba ol EAN vagresrerapr hfvat na vagrtengnoyr irpgbe jvgu bccbfvat G2 cebzbgref</atl>. <jtl>W. Ovby. Purz.</jtl> <vid>720</vid>, <ppf>59825</ppf>-<ppl>59824</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b96" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cnqqvfba</snm>, <fnm>C. W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Pnhql</snm>, <fnm>N. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Unaaba</snm>, <fnm>T. W.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Fgnoyr fhccerffvba bs trar rkcerffvba ol EANv va znzznyvna pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl> <vid>44</vid>, <ppf>8556</ppf>-<ppl>8553</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b97" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oehzzryxnzc</snm>, <fnm>G. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Oreaneqf</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ntnzv</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">N flfgrz sbe fgnoyr rkcerffvba bs fubeg vagresrevat EANf va znzznyvna pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Fpvrapr</jtl> <vid>78</vid>, <ppf>78</ppf> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b98" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fhv</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <atl display="show">N QAN irpgbe-onfrq EANv grpuabybtl gb fhccerff trar rkcerffvba va znzznyvna pryyf</atl>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl><vid>44</vid>, <ppf>0080</ppf>-<ppl>0079</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b99" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zrvffare</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ebgusryf</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fpunsre</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Frvsneg</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Qrirybczrag bs na vaqhpvoyr cby VVV genafpevcgvba flfgrz rffragvnyyl erdhvevat n zhgngrq sbez bs gur GNGN-ovaqvat cebgrva</atl>. <jtl>Ahpyrvp Npvqf Erf.</jtl> <vid>74</vid>, <ppf>8127</ppf>-<ppl>8137</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b100" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Buxnjn</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gnven</snm>, <fnm>X.</fnm></refau> <atl display="show">Pbageby bs gur shapgvbany npgvivgl bs na nagvfrafr EAN ol n grgenplpyvar-erfcbafvir qrevingvir bs gur uhzna H1 faEAN cebzbgre</atl>. <jtl>Uhz. Trar Gure.</jtl> <vid>88</vid>, <ppf>022</ppf>-<ppl>030</ppl> (<cd year="2000">7999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
