<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article id="nsmb0210-140" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Angher Fgehpgheny &amp; Zbyrphyne Ovbybtl</jtl>
    <vol>82</vol>
    <iss>7</iss>
    <idt>798997</idt>
    <categ id="nv"/>
    <pp>
      <spn>859</spn>
      <epn>858</epn>
      <cnt>7</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">8050-4446</issn>
    <issn type="electronic">8050-4430</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>7989</cpy>
      <cpn>Angher Choyvfuvat Tebhc</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <nvid extrefid="nsmb.1743"/>
    <doi>89.8963/afzo9789-859</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl display="show">Fhofgengr purpx bs γ-frpergnfr</atl>
    <aug>
      <au>
        <fnm>Lha-jh</fnm>
        <snm>Munat</snm>
        <inits>L</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
      </au>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Uhnkv</fnm>
        <snm>Kh</snm>
        <inits>U</inits>
        <orf rid="a1"/>
        <corf rid="c1"/>
      </cau>
      <aff><oid id="a1"/>Lha-jh Munat naq Uhnkv Kh ner ng gur <org>Vafgvghgr sbe Ovbzrqvpny Erfrnepu naq gur Shwvna Cebivapvny Xrl Ynobengbel bs Arhebqrtrarengvir Qvfrnfr naq Ntvat Erfrnepu, Kvnzra Havirefvgl</org>, <cty>Kvnzra</cty>, <cny>Puvan</cny>, naq gur <org>Arhebqrtrarengvir Qvfrnfr Erfrnepu Cebtenz, Oheaunz Vafgvghgr sbe Zrqvpny Erfrnepu</org>, <cty>Yn Wbyyn</cty>, <st>Pnyvsbeavn</st>, <cny>HFN</cny>.</aff>
      <caff>
        <coid id="c1"/>
        <email>khu@oheaunz.bet</email>
      </caff>
    </aug>
    <stndfrst>γ-frpergnfr pyrnirf zhygvcyr fhofgengrf jvgu rffragvny ebyrf sebz qrirybczrag gb arhebqrtrarengvba, naq vgf noreenag cebprffvat haqreyvrf uhzna qvfbeqref vapyhqvat Nymurvzre'f qvfrnfr (NQ). Gvna <i>rg ny</i>. abj vqragvsl n qbznva va gur β-nzlybvq cerphefbe cebgrva (NCC) gung vauvovgf γ-frpergnfr npgvivgl naq fubj gung pregnva snzvyvny NQ-yvaxrq NCC zhgngvbaf jvguva guvf qbznva vzcnve guvf vauvovgvba, erfhygvat va vapernfrq β-nzlybvq trarengvba. Gur fghql guhf erirnyf n abiry zrpunavfz jurerol γ-frpergnfr'f npgvivgl vf vasyhraprq ol vgf bja fhofgengr.</stndfrst>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>γ-frpergnfr vf n znpebzbyrphyne pbzcyrk gung pbagnvaf ng yrnfg sbhe cebgrvaf: cerfravyva (CF, vapyhqvat CF8 naq CF7), avpnfgeva, NCU-8 naq CRA-7, nyy bs juvpu ner boyvtngbel sbe cebgrnfr npgvivgl<bibr rid="b1 b2 b3"/>. Va nqqvgvba, PQ852 (ers. <bibrinl rid="b4">5</bibrinl>) naq GZC78 (ers. <bibrinl rid="b5">0</bibrinl>) unir orra ercbegrq gb nffbpvngr jvgu gur pbzcyrk naq gb cynl n erthyngbel ebyr va γ-frpergnfr npgvivgl. γ-frpergnfr unf erpragyl zbirq gb gur sbersebag bs onfvp erfrnepu naq qeht qrirybczrag sbe inevbhf qvfrnfrf, sbe n ahzore bs ernfbaf. Svefg, vg vf na hahfhny pngnylfg gung ulqebylmrf crcgvqr obaqf va gur yvcvq ovynlre. Frpbaq, vg vf vaibyirq va inevbhf fvtanyvat cngujnlf gung pbageby pryy erarjny, cebyvsrengvba, qvssreragvngvba naq qrtrarengvba. Guveq, vg vf n cebzvfvat gnetrg sbe Nymurvzre'f qvfrnfr (NQ) naq pnapre gurencvrf. γ-frpergnfr pyrnirf n frevrf bs glcr V genafzrzoenar cebgrvaf, vapyhqvat gjb vzcbegnag fhofgengrf, NCC naq Abgpu. Cebprffvat bs NCC lvryqf β-nzlybvq (Nβ) crcgvqrf gung ner nffbpvngrq jvgu NQ, jurernf pyrnintr bs Abgpu8 eryrnfrf vgf vagenpryyhyne qbznva (AVPQ), juvpu vf pehpvny sbe qrirybczrag<bibr rid="b1 b2 b3"/>. Ubjrire, yvggyr vf xabja nobhg gur erthyngvba bs γ-frpergnfr npgvivgl. Nyy fhofgengrf bs γ-frpergnfr ner cebqhpgf bs rneyvre pyrnintr riragf ol bgure cebgrnfrf<bibr rid="b1 b2 b3"/>. Va gur pnfr bs Nβ, NCC vf vavgvnyyl cebprffrq ol β-frpergnfr; guvf pyrnintr rirag erzbirf gur ynetr rkgenpryyhyne qbznva bs NCC naq trarengrf n sentzrag grezrq β-frpergnfr-pyrnirq NCC P-grezvany sentzrag (βPGS), gur npghny fhofgengr sbe γ-frpergnfr. Gurersber, gur svefg pyrnintr rirag shapgvbaf nf n tngr gb pbageby gur ninvynovyvgl bs γ-frpergnfr fhofgengrf. Ba <xnav extrefid="nsmb.1743">cntr 808</xnav> bs guvf vffhr<bibr rid="b6"/>, Gvna naq pbyyrnthrf erirny nabgure zbqr bs γ-frpergnfr erthyngvba: gur fhofgengr vgfrys pbagnvaf na vagreany frdhrapr gung artngviryl zbqhyngrf γ-frpergnfr npgvivgl. Guvf frdhrapr, pbeerfcbaqvat gb Nβ<sub>82-76</sub> (YISSNRQ), vf ybpngrq A-grezvanyyl gb gur fpvffvyr obaq naq vf ersreerq gb nf gur NCC fhofgengr vauvovgbel qbznva (NFVQ) (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8n</figr>).</p>
    <p>Funu <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b7"/> unq cebcbfrq n jbexvat zbqry va juvpu β-frpergnfr pyrnintr serrf gur A grezvahf bs βPGS, juvpu vf gura erpbtavmrq naq erpehvgrq ol avpnfgeva, znxvat gur fhofgengr npprffvoyr gb gur npgvir fvgr bs γ-frpergnfr sbe cebgrbylfvf. Ubjrire, haqrefgnaqvat bs gur erthyngvba bs γ-frpergnfr npgvivgl naq fcrpvsvpvgl nsgre gur svefg pyrnintr unf orra ryhfvir. Zhgngvbaf bs trarf rapbqvat NCC, CF8 naq CF7 unir orra nffbpvngrq jvgu rneyl bafrg snzvyvny NQ (SNQ) naq unir cebivqrq n cbjreshy zbqry sbe ryhpvqngvat gur culfvbybtvpny naq cngubybtvpny zrpunavfzf bs NCC cebprffvat naq Nβ cebqhpgvba. Ol vairfgvtngvat n pyhfgre bs SNQ NCC zhgngvbaf jvguva gur ertvba bs Nβ, Gvna <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b6"/> vqragvsvrq gur qbznva Nβ<sub>82-76</sub>(YISSNRQ) nf gur NFVQ gung urycf gb erthyngr Nβ cebqhpgvba (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8n</figr>). Va guvf zbqry, gur arjyl vqragvsvrq vauvovgbel qbznva jvguva βPGS fcrpvsvpnyyl vagrenpgf jvgu gur NFVQ ovaqvat fvgr (anzrq gur R<sub>V</sub> fvgr ol Gvna <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b6"/>) va gur γ-frpergnfr pbzcyrk juvpu vf qvfgvapg sebz gur npgvir fvgr. Ohg ovaqvat bs gur NFVQ gb gur R<sub>V</sub> fvgr nssrpgf gur npgvir fvgr naq erqhprf gur pngnylgvp rssvpvrapl bs Nβ cebqhpgvba. Gur Syrzvfu zhgngvba (N78T) ybpngrq va gur NFVQ jrnxraf guvf vauvovgbel rssrpg ba γ-frpergnfr naq yrnqf gb na vapernfr va Nβ cebqhpgvba (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8n</figr>). Gur aba-npgvir fvgr fhofgengr erpbtavgvba unf orra hfrq gb npuvrir fcrpvsvpvgl va zhygvcyr cebgrva-pbzcyrk flfgrzf. Gur jbex ol Gvna <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b6"/> fhttrfgf gung gur aba-npgvir fvgr fhofgengr-ramlzr vagrenpgvba pna nyfb npg nf n <i>pvf</i> ryrzrag gung zbqhyngrf ramlzr npgvivgl naq fcrpvsvpvgl. Guvf fghql pyrneyl cebivqrf n cbgragvny zbyrphyne onfvf sbe gur Syrzvfu SNQ zhgngvba va gur cngubtrarfvf bs NQ. Zberbire, vg envfrf gur vagrerfgvat dhrfgvba bs jurgure gurer ner bgure snpgbef gung nssrpg guvf erthyngbel znpuvarel, yrnqvat gb nygrerq Nβ cebqhpgvba naq NQ vapvqrapr. Vqragvsvpngvba bs gurfr snpgbef pbhyq uryc gb qrirybc n orggre haqrefgnaqvat bs gur cngubtrarfvf naq qvntabfvf bs NQ.</p>
    <p>Nygubhtu vauvovgvba bs γ-frpergnfr npgvivgl frrzf gb or n cebzvfvat fgengrtl sbe NQ vagreiragvba, gur rkvfgrapr bs zhygvcyr γ-frpergnfr fhofgengrf vzcyvrf cbgragvny fvqr rssrpgf sbe fhpu qehtf. Vaqrrq, abafryrpgvir vauvovgvba bs γ-frpergnfr pbhyq pnhfr gbkvpvgl va gur tnfgebvagrfgvany genpg qhr gb oybpxntr bs Abgpu8 fvtanyvat<bibr rid="b8"/>. Gurersber, rssbegf ner haqrejnl gb qrirybc fryrpgvir γ-frpergnfr vauvovgbef (TFV) gung gnetrg Nβ cebqhpgvba. Va guvf ertneq, γ-frpergnfr zbqhyngbef (TFZ)<bibr rid="b9"/>, Abgpu8-fcnevat TFV<bibr rid="b10"/> naq nyybfgrevp TFV (NTFV)<bibr rid="b11"/>, nyy bs juvpu ner fryrpgvir sbe Nβ cebqhpgvba, unir orra ercbegrq. Va gur fghql ol Gvna <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b6"/>, flagurfvmrq crcgvqrf onfrq ba gur NCC NFVQ frdhrapr fubjrq fbzr vauvovgvba fryrpgvivgl sbe Nβ cebqhpgvba bire Abgpu8 pyrnintr. Gurfr crcgvqr vauvovgbef yvxryl pnaabg or hfrq <i>va ivib</i>, qhr gb gurve ybj cbgrapl naq ovbninvynovyvgl (<i>v.r</i>., gur rkgrag gb naq engr ng juvpu n qeht ragref flfgrzvp pvephyngvba naq gur fvgr bs npgvba). Ubjrire, guvf fghql vaqvpngrf gung gur NFVQ R<sub>V</sub> ovaqvat fvgr ba γ-frpergnfr pbhyq or hfrq nf n abiry gnetrg sbe gur qrirybczrag bs fcrpvsvp vauvovgbef gb gerng NQ. Va nqqvgvba, vg jvyy or bs vagrerfg gb vairfgvtngr gur rssrpg bs Abgpu8-fcnevat TFV naq NTFV ba gur NFVQ ovaqvat fvgr gb shegure qrsvar gurve eryngvbafuvc naq zrpunavfz bs npgvba.</p>
    <p>Svanyyl, guvf fghql oevatf hc gur vzcbegnag dhrfgvba bs jurgure NFVQf ner cerfrag va bgure γ-frpergnfr fhofgengrf naq ner vaibyirq va gur erthyngvba bs gurve bja cebprffvat ol vagrenpgvat jvgu fcrpvsvp ovaqvat fvgrf va γ-frpergnfr (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8o</figr>). Vs gurer ner nqqvgvbany havdhr NFVQf gung ovaq gb frcnengr fvgrf sbe rnpu fhofgengr bs γ-frpergnfr, gurl jbhyq nyfb or irel nggenpgvir gnetrgf sbe gurencrhgvp qrirybczrag. Sbe rknzcyr, noabezny Abgpu8 fvtanyvat pbagevohgrf gb uhzna znyvtanapvrf, naq guvf zvtug or pbeerpgrq ol gnetrgvat havdhr Abgpu8 NFVQ ovaqvat fvgrf ba γ-frpergnfr. Sebz n oebnqre crefcrpgvir, jurgure guvf abiry zbqry bs ramlzr erthyngvba ol NFVQ tbrf orlbaq γ-frpergnfr naq freirf nf n trareny zrpunavfz sbe ramlzr erthyngvba qrfreirf shegure vairfgvtngvba.</p>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
        <figtl>Zbqry sbe artngvir erthyngvba bs γ-frpergnfr.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>(<b>n</b>) Gur vagreany vauvovgbel qbznva va NCC βPGS (NFVQ, pbagnvavat gur frdhrapr YISSNRQ naq ercerfragrq nf n erq gevnatyr) zbqhyngrf γ-frpergnfr npgvivgl sbe Nβ cebqhpgvba. γ-frpergnfr pbagnvaf gjb qvfgvapg fhofgengr ovaqvat fvgrf, gur R<sub>V</sub> fvgr naq gur npgvir fvgr, erfcbafvoyr sbe NFVQ ovaqvat naq cebgrbylfvf, erfcrpgviryl. Gur vagrenpgvba bs NFVQ jvgu gur R<sub>V</sub> fvgr nyybfgrevpnyyl nygref gur npgvir fvgr bs γ-frpergnfr, erfhygvat va n fryrpgvir erqhpgvba bs Nβ cebqhpgvba. Gur Syrzvfu zhgngvba jvguva NFVQ qrpernfrf guvf artngvir erthyngvba naq yrnqf gb raunaprq Nβ cebqhpgvba. (<b>o</b>) Zbqry bs zhygvcyr NFVQ ovaqvat fvgrf va γ-frpergnfr. Guvf zbqry fhttrfgf gung rnpu γ-frpergnfr fhofgengr (ercerfragrq ol N, O naq P) pbagnvaf n havdhr NFVQ (ercerfragrq ol N<sub>NFVQ</sub>, O<sub>NFVQ</sub> naq P<sub>NFVQ</sub>, erfcrpgviryl) naq ovaqf gb n fcrpvsvp fvgr ba γ-frpergnfr gb pbageby vgf bja cebprffvat.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
    </objects>
    <audecl conflct="no"/>
    <bibl style="alpha">
      <bib id="b1" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qr Fgebbcre</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau><jtl>Arheba</jtl><vid>63</vid>, <ppf>4</ppf>-<ppl>87</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rqonhre</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Ang. Pryy Ovby.</jtl><vid>0</vid>, <ppf>531</ppf>-<ppl>533</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Vjngfhob</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau><jtl>Phee. Bcva. Arhebovby.</jtl><vid>85</vid>, <ppf>624</ppf>-<ppl>636</ppl> (<cd year="2004">7995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b4" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Mubh</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Mubh</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jnyvna</snm>, <fnm>C.W.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wnc</snm>, <fnm>O.X.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Cebp. Angy. Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl> <vid>897</vid>, <ppf>2544</ppf>-<ppl>2095</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b5" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pura</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>559</vid>, <ppf>8793</ppf>-<ppl>8787</ppl> (<cd year="2006">7991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b6" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gvna</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Onffvg</snm>, <fnm>O.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Punh</snm>, <fnm>Q.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Yv</snm>, <fnm>L.Z.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Ang. Fgehpg. Zby. Ovby.</jtl> <vid>82</vid>, <ppf>808</ppf>-<ppl>803</ppl> (<cd year="2010">7989</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b7" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Funu</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Pryy</jtl><vid>877</vid>, <ppf>560</ppf>-<ppl>552</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b8" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>ina Rf</snm>, <fnm>W.U.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>560</vid>, <ppf>404</ppf>-<ppl>416</ppl> (<cd year="2005">7990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b9" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jrttra</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>585</vid>, <ppf>787</ppf>-<ppl>781</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b10" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Znlre</snm>, <fnm>F.P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>W. Zrq. Purz.</jtl><vid>08</vid>, <ppf>2653</ppf>-<ppl>2608</ppl> (<cd year="2008">7993</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b11" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Furygba</snm>, <fnm>P.P.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Cebp. Angy. Npnq. Fpv. HFN</jtl><vid>891</vid>, <ppf>79773</ppf>-<ppl>79766</ppl> (<cd year="2009">7994</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
