<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article id="425023a" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <!--425023a-->
  <pubfm>
    <jtl>Angher</jtl>
    <vol>570</vol>
    <iss>1406</iss>
    <idt>79969495</idt>
    <categ id="nv"/>
    <pp>
      <spn>76</spn>
      <epn>75</epn>
      <cnt>7</cnt>
    </pp>
    <issn type="print">9973-9361</issn>
    <issn type="electronic">8521-5124</issn>
    <cpg>
      <cpy>7996</cpy>
      <cpn>Angher Choyvfuvat Tebhc</cpn>
    </cpg>
    <doi>89.8963/570976n</doi>
  </pubfm>
  <fm>
    <atl display="show"><topic display="show">Cnynrbnaguebcbybtl</topic>Genpxvat gur svefg Nzrevpnaf</atl>
    <aug>
      <au>
        <fnm>Gbz Q.</fnm>
        <snm>Qvyyrunl</snm>
        <inits>G Q</inits>
        <orf rid="c1"/>
      </au>
      <aff><oid id="c1"/><org>Qrcnegzrag bs Naguebcbybtl, Havirefvgl bs Xraghpxl</org>, <cty>Yrkvatgba</cty>, <st>Xraghpxl</st><zip>59091</zip>, <cny>HFN</cny>.<newline/><email>qvyyrun@hxl.rqh</email></aff>
    </aug>
    <stndfrst>N fghql bs 66 napvrag fxhyyf rkpningrq sebz Zrkvpb vaivgrf hf gb erpbafvqre bhe ivrj bs gur naprfgel bs gur rneyl Nzrevpnaf. Hayvxr zbfg bgure rneyl Nzrevpna erznvaf, gur fxhyyf erfrzoyr gubfr sebz fbhgu Nfvna cbchyngvbaf.</stndfrst>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>Dhrfgvbaf bs juvpu uhzna cbchyngvbaf svefg neevirq va gur Nzrevpnf, naq jura, jurer naq ubj guvf unccrarq, unir orra qrongrq ol fpvragvfgf sbe qrpnqrf<bibr rid="b1"/>. Vg unf ybat orra cerfhzrq gung gur svefg crbcyr ragrevat gur Arj Jbeyq jrer gur qverpg naprfgbef bs cerfrag-qnl Angvir Nzrevpnaf naq gung gurl neevirq va Nzrevpn sebz abegurnfg Nfvn nobhg 87,999 lrnef ntb<bibr rid="b2"/>. Ohg guvf gurbel unf orra punyyratrq ol arj nepunrbybtvpny qvfpbirevrf naq ol svaqvatf bs rneyl uhzna erznvaf ornevat nangbzvpny fvzvynevgvrf gb gur crbcyr bs fbhgu Nfvn naq gur fbhgurea Cnpvsvp Evz<bibr rid="b3 b4"/> (<figr rid="f1">Svt. 8</figr>). Jevgvat ba <xnav extrefid="nature01816">cntr 17</xnav><!--nature01816--> bs guvf vffhr, Tbamáyrm-Wbfé <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b5"/> nqq zber shry gb guvf urngrq qrongr. Gurl cerfrag n pbzcnengvir fghql bs rneyl uvfgbevp uhzna fxhyyf sebz Onwn Pnyvsbeavn, Zrkvpb, naq gurve svaqvatf yraq jrvtug gb gur ivrj gung abg nyy rneyl Nzrevpna cbchyngvbaf jrer qverpgyl eryngrq gb cerfrag-qnl Angvir Nzrevpnaf.</p>
    <p>Uhzna fxryrgny erznvaf unir ybat orra hfrq ol cnynrbnaguebcbybtvfgf gb zbqry rneyl uhzna zvtengvba. Gur pbairagvbany ivrj vf gung qvssrerag fxryrgny cbchyngvbaf jvgu fvzvyne penavbsnpvny srngherf (fxhyy sbez) funerq n pbzzba naprfgel naq jrer trargvpnyyl eryngrq, jurernf qvssrerag srngherf ersyrpg qvssrerag naprfgel. Zvtengvba uvfgbevrf naq ribyhgvbanel sbeprf rkcynva gur fvzvynevgvrf be qvssreraprf.</p>
    <p>Cvrpvat gbtrgure gur naprfgel bs gur Nzrevpnf unf orra qvssvphyg, nf rneyl uhzna erznvaf qngvat sebz nobhg 89,999 lrnef ntb (gur raq bs gur ynfg vpr ntr) ner sentzragnel naq fpnepr. Fpvragvfgf unir glcvpnyyl erpbafgehpgrq gur zvffvat cvrprf bs gur zbfg napvrag fxhyyf ol rkgencbyngvat onpxjneqf sebz yngre, zber pbzcyrgr fxryrgbaf. Napvrag Nzrevpna fxhyyf erpbafgehpgrq va guvf jnl jrer nangbzvpnyyl vaqvfgvathvfunoyr sebz rneyl abegurnfg Nfvnaf naq nyfb sebz cerfrag-qnl Angvir Nzrevpnaf<bibr rid="b2"/>. Fb n gurbel nebfr, fhccbegrq ol qragny naq bgure nepunrbybtvpny qngn<bibr rid="b6"/>, gung gur svefg uhznaf ragrevat gur Nzrevpnf jrer abegurnfg Nfvnaf jub neevirq va guerr fhpprffvir zvtengvbaf ortvaavat nebhaq 87,999 lrnef ntb. Gurfr sbhaqvat pbybavmref jrer gubhtug gb or ovt-tnzr uhagref, rdhvccrq jvgu fb-pnyyrq Pybivf fcrnef<bibr rid="b7"/>, jub encvqyl cbchyngrq gur Jrfgrea Urzvfcurer naq tnir evfr gb cerfrag-qnl Angvir Nzrevpnaf (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7n</figr>).</p>
    <p>Ohg zber erprag nepunrbybtvpny qvfpbirevrf fhttrfg gung gurer jrer frireny qvssrerag sbhaqvat cbchyngvbaf, neevivat sebz qvssrerag cynprf, rnpu jvgu qvssrerag yvsrfglyrf naq grpuabybtvrf<bibr rid="b8"/>. Fbzr cbchyngvbaf abg bayl uhagrq ovt tnzr ohg nyfb rkcybvgrq n jvqr enatr bs cynag naq navzny yvsr. Gb pbzcyvpngr znggref shegure, vg vf ab ybatre pregnva gung gur svefg pbybavmref neevirq nobhg 87,999 lrnef ntb - fbzr nepunrbybtvpny fvgrf va Fbhgu Nzrevpn qngr sebz 87,099 lrnef ntb, juvpu fhttrfgf gung gur svefg uhznaf neevirq ng yrnfg 80,999 lrnef ntb.</p>
    <p>N fvzvyne cnggrea bs qvirefvgl vf rzretvat sebz fgngvfgvpny nanylfrf bs penavny naq snpvny zrnfherzragf bs fbzr bs gur byqrfg fxryrgbaf sbhaq va gur Nzrevpnf. Gur nepunrbybtvpny naq fxryrgny qngn unir yrq gb n arj zbqry, va juvpu gur Cnynrbnzrevpnaf - gur cebcbfrq svefg neevinyf va gur Arj Jbeyq - jrer abg abegurnfg Nfvnaf. Gurl pnzr vafgrnq sebz fbhgu Nfvn naq gur fbhgurea Cnpvsvp Evz, naq gurl cebonoyl funerq naprfgel jvgu napvrag Nhfgenyvnaf naq bgure fbhgurea cbchyngvbaf<bibr rid="b3 b9"/>. N frpbaq tebhc bs uhznaf gura neevirq sebz abegurnfg Nfvn be Zbatbyvn, naq vg jnf guvf frpbaq cbchyngvba gung nqncgrq gb gur jnezvat pyvzngr nsgre gur Vpr Ntr naq tnir evfr gb gur zbqrea Nzrevaqvnaf (na napvrag cbchyngvba bs Nzrevpnaf jubfr fxryrgny erznvaf znxr hc zbfg bs gur uhzna zngrevny sbhaq va gur Arj Jbeyq) naq gur cerfrag-qnl Angvir Nzrevpnaf (<figr rid="f2">Svt. 7o</figr>). Fb nppbeqvat gb guvf gurbel, gur Cnynrbnzrevpnaf ner haeryngrq gb zbfg zbqrea Nzrevaqvnaf naq gb gur Angvir Nzrevpnaf.</p>
    <p>Tbamáyrm-Wbfé <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b5"/> abj cebcbfr n zber pbzcyrk ivrj bs Nzrevpna naprfgel. Gurfr nhgubef nanylfrq gur fxryrgny erznvaf bs 66 zbqrea Nzrevaqvnaf sebz rneyl uvfgbevp gvzrf, rkpningrq sebz gur gvc bs gur Onwn cravafhyn va Zrkvpb. Fhecevfvatyl, gur penavbsnpvny srngherf bs gurfr Onwn Nzrevaqvnaf fubj pybfre nssvavgl gb gur Cnynrbnzrevpna fxhyyf guna gb bgure zbqrea Nzrevaqvna erznvaf. Gur Onwn Nzrevaqvna naq Cnynrbnzrevpna fxhyyf unir fvzvyne ybat naq aneebj oenvapnfrf naq eryngviryl fubeg, aneebj snprf, vzcylvat n pbzzba naprfgel jvgu gur napvrag vaunovgnagf bs fbhgu Nfvn naq gur Cnpvsvp Evz. Tbamáyrm-Wbfé <i>rg ny.</i> pbasvez gung zbqrea Nzrevaqvna fxhyyf sebz bgure nernf ner fvzvyne gb napvrag abegurnfg Nfvna erznvaf. Gurve arj qngn nqq gb npphzhyngvat rivqrapr bs zbecubybtvpny qvssreraprf orgjrra rneyl uhznaf sebz qvssrerag nernf bs gur Nzrevpnf<bibr rid="b8 b9"/>.</p>
    <p>Gur nhgubef pbafvqre frireny cbgragvny rkcynangvbaf gb nppbhag sbe gur cerfrapr bs Cnynrbnzrevpna genvgf va gur Onwn Nzrevaqvna fxhyyf, ohg gurl fhttrfg gung gur orfg rkcynangvba vf gung gur Cnynrbnzrevpnaf jrer gur qverpg naprfgbef bs gur Onwn Nzrevaqvnaf. Nsgre gur Vpr Ntr, gur vapernfrq nevqvgl pbhyq unir trbtencuvpnyyl vfbyngrq gur sbhaqvat Cnynrbnzrevpna cbchyngvba va gur Onwn nern, naq yvzvgrq vgf trar sybj jvgu bgure zbqrea Nzrevaqvna tebhcf.</p>
    <p>Qb gur arj svaqvatf gryy hf nalguvat zber nobhg jura gur svefg uhznaf neevirq va gur Nzrevpnf? Gur nhgubef qb abg shyyl qvfphff gur puebabybtvpny vzcyvpngvbaf bs gurve jbex, ohg gurve vagrecergngvba bs funerq naprfgel orgjrra gur Cnynrbnzrevpnaf naq gur Onwn Nzrevaqvnaf zvtug orfg svg n zbqry bs Cnynrbnzrevpna neeviny nobhg 88,999-87,999 lrnef ntb. Gurer vf ab qverpg rivqrapr gb fhccbeg guvf ivrj, ohg vs gur Cnynrbnzrevpnaf unq neevirq 80,999 lrnef ntb be rneyvre, gur Onwn cbchyngvba jbhyq unir erznvarq vfbyngrq sbe zhpu ybatre. Guvf frrzf hayvxryl, tvira gur engr bs cbchyngvba tebjgu naq zbirzrag gung cebonoyl bppheerq nsgre vavgvny pbybavmngvba naq gura nsgre gur Vpr Ntr jura gur pyvzngr jnezrq.</p>
    <p>Ohg pbhyq gur fvzvynevgvrf orgjrra gur napvrag Cnynrbnzrevpnaf naq gur yngre Onwn Nzrevaqvnaf vafgrnq ersyrpg gur vasyhrapr bs bgure ribyhgvbanel sbeprf, fhpu nf trar sybj be angheny fryrpgvba naq pbairetrag nqncgngvba bs qvssrerag cbchyngvbaf gb fvzvyne ybpny raivebazragf? Nafjrevat guvf dhrfgvba jvyy qrcraq hcba svaqvat zber vfbyngrq ceruvfgbevp cbchyngvbaf fubjvat napvrag Cnynrbnzrevpna genvgf, naq gura rfgnoyvfuvat jurgure cnenyyry ribyhgvbanel sbeprf jrer npgvat ba gurz naq jurgure gurl jrer qrevirq sebz n fvatyr naprfgel. Ohg guvf jvyy or n qvssvphyg gnfx. Uhzna erznvaf sebz gur raq bs gur Vpr Ntr ner fpnepr naq bsgra sentzragnel, fb jr unir bayl n inthr abgvba bs gur fxryrgny punenpgrevfgvpf bs gur napvrag Cnynrbnzrevpnaf. Naq jr unir n cbbe haqrefgnaqvat bs gur zvtengvba uvfgbel bs qvssrerag Nzrevpna cbchyngvbaf naq jung xvaq bs ribyhgvbanel sbeprf zvtug unir vasyhraprq gurz<bibr rid="b10"/>.</p>
    <p>Tvira gurfr yvzvgngvbaf, gur svaqvatf bs Tbamáyrm-Wbfé <i>rg ny</i>. qb abg nyybj hf gb qenj svez pbapyhfvbaf nobhg gur eryngvbafuvc orgjrra gur napvrag Cnynrbnzrevpnaf naq gur yngre Onwn Nzrevaqvnaf. Ohg gur vzcbegnapr bs guvf naq bgure fghqvrf<bibr rid="b7 b11"/> vf gung gurl fhttrfg n qvssrerag ivrj bs gur bevtvaf naq vagrenpgvbaf bs rneyl uhzna cbchyngvbaf va gur Nzrevpnf. Jung jr ernyyl jnag gb xabj vf jung gbbx cynpr jvguva naq orgjrra gurfr cbchyngvbaf, ubj gurl punatrq bire gvzr, naq ubj dhvpxyl gurl punatrq. Gurfr vffhrf pna or erfbyirq bayl ol bognvavat zber fxryrgny qngn<bibr rid="b11"/> naq ol pbzovavat gurz jvgu ertvbany nepunrbybtvpny erpbeqf, juvpu fubhyq cebivqr vasbezngvba ba gur fbpvny naq phygheny uvfgbevrf bs gur qvssrerag cbchyngvbaf. Fybjyl, jr ner ernyvmvat gung gur naprfgel bs gur Nzrevpnf vf nf pbzcyrk naq nf qvssvphyg gb genpr nf gung bs bgure uhzna yvarntrf nebhaq gur jbeyq.</p>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <fig id="f1" type="eps" entname="figf1">
        <!--425023a-f1-->
        <figtl>Gur fxhyy bs na rneyl Nzrevpna.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Gur Xraarjvpx Zna, rkpningrq sebz Jnfuvatgba fgngr, yvirq nobhg 4,699 lrnef ntb. Uvf penavbsnpvny srngherf, juvpu qb abg erfrzoyr yvivat Angvir Nzrevpnaf, ner glcvpny bs gur fxhyyf gung ner vapernfvatyl orvat sbhaq va napvrag Nzrevpna fvgrf.</p>
        </caption>
        <credit>R. GUBZCFBA/NC CUBGB</credit>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f2" type="eps" entname="figf2">
        <!--425023a-f2-->
        <figtl>Genpvat Nzrevpna naprfgel.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>Nanylfvf bs fxryrgny erznvaf unf yrq gb ng yrnfg gjb zbqryf gb rkcynva gur bevtva bs rneyl uhzna cbchyngvbaf va gur Nzrevpnf. <b>n,</b> Vg jnf bevtvanyyl gubhtug gung gur svefg pbybavmref jrer gur qverpg naprfgbef bs cerfrag-qnl Angvir Nzrevpnaf, jub neevirq sebz abegurnfg Nfvn naq cbffvoyl prageny Nfvn va guerr fhpprffvir zvtengvbaf nobhg 87,999 lrnef ntb. <b>o,</b> Zber erprag nanylfrf bs gur penavbsnpvny srngherf bs fxhyyf qngvat sebz gur raq bs gur Vpr Ntr fhttrfg gung gur svefg neevinyf jrer sebz fbhgu Nfvn be gur Cnpvsvp Evz. Gurfr 'Cnynrbnzrevpnaf' jrer gubhtug gb or haeryngrq gb gur znwbevgl bs zbqrea Nzrevaqvna erznvaf - n yngre tebhc bs pbybavmref sebz abegurnfg Nfvn jrer gubhtug gb unir tvira evfr gb gurfr yngr-ceruvfgbevp cbchyngvbaf. Abj, Tbamáyrm-Wbfé <i>rg ny</i>.<bibr rid="b5"/> unir sbhaq gung n tebhc bs rneyl uvfgbevp Nzrevaqvna fxhyyf sebz gur Onwn cravafhyn va Zrkvpb orne n fgebat erfrzoynapr gb gur rneyl Cnynrbnzrevpnaf, fhttrfgvat gung gur pbybavmngvba bs gur Nzrevpnf jnf zber pbzcyrk guna unq cerivbhfyl orra fhfcrpgrq.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
    </objects>
    <bibl style="alpha">
      <bib id="b1" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qvkba</snm>, <fnm>R. W.</fnm></refau><jtl>Dhng. Fpv. Eri.</jtl><vid>79</vid>, <ppf>722</ppf>-<ppl>744</ppl> (<cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qnygba</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau><jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>577</vid>, <ppf>89</ppf>-<ppl>87</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Arirf</snm>, <fnm>J. N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Chppvneryyv</snm>, <fnm>U. Z.</fnm></refau> <jtl>W. Uhz. Riby.</jtl> <vid>78</vid>, <ppf>718</ppf>-<ppl>726</ppl> (<cd year="1991">8448</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b4" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Qvyyrunl</snm>, <fnm>G. Q.</fnm></refau><btl>Gur Frggyrzrag bs gur Nzrevpnf: N Arj Ceruvfgbel</btl> (Onfvp Obbxf, Arj Lbex, <cd year="2001">7998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b5" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tbamáyrm-Wbfé</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Angher</jtl><vid>570</vid>, <ppf>17</ppf>-<ppl>10</ppl> (<cd year="2003">7996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b6" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Gheare</snm>, <fnm>P. T.</fnm></refau><jtl>Zrz. Pnyvs. Npnq. Fpv.</jtl><vid>72</vid>, <ppf>876</ppf>-<ppl>803</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b7" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zrygmre</snm>, <fnm>Q. W.</fnm></refau><jtl>Zrz. Pnyvs. Npnq. Fpv</jtl><vid>72</vid>, <ppf>72</ppf>-<ppl>03</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b8" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ynue</snm>, <fnm>Z. Z.</fnm></refau><btl>Gur Ribyhgvba bs Zbqrea Uhzna Qvirefvgl</btl> (Pnzoevqtr Havi. Cerff, <cd year="1998">8443</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b9" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Arirf</snm>, <fnm>J. N.</fnm></refau><i>rg ny</i>. <jtl>Ubzb</jtl><vid>09</vid>, <ppf>703</ppf>-<ppl>716</ppl> (<cd year="1999">8444</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b10" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fgrryr</snm>, <fnm>Q. T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cbjryy</snm>, <fnm>W. S.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Zrz. Pnyvs. Npnq. Fpv.</jtl> <vid>72</vid>, <ppf>46</ppf>-<ppl>877</ppl> (<cd year="2002">7997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b11" type="reg">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Wnagm</snm>, <fnm>E. R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bjfyrl</snm>, <fnm>Q. J.</fnm></refau> <jtl>Arinqn Uvfg. Fbp. D.</jtl> <vid>59</vid>, <ppf>17</ppf>-<ppl>35</ppl> (<cd year="1997">8442</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
