<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "NPG_XML_Article.dtd">
<article id="newbio246107a0">
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature New Biology</jtl>
<vol>246</vol>
<iss>152</iss>
<idt>19731128</idt>
<categ id="lt"/>
<pp><spn>107</spn><epn>109</epn><cnt>3</cnt></pp>
<issn>0090-0028</issn>
<cpg><cpy>1973</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group</cpn></cpg>
<doi>10.1038/newbio246107a0</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Quantitative Differences between N-terminal Methionyl Nascent Globin Chains of Human and Rabbit Reticulocytes</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>HARUO</fnm><snm>SUZUKI</snm><inits>H.</inits><aufnr rid="n1" refchar="asterisk"/></au>
<au><fnm>HARVEY A.</fnm><snm>ITANO</snm><inits>H. A.</inits></au>
<aff>Department of Pathology, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, Calif ornia 92037</aff></aug>
<aufn id="n1" refchar="asterisk">Present address: Institute for Developmental Research, Aichi Prefectural Colony, Aichi, Japan. Address reprint requests to H. A. I.</aufn>
<hst>
<re year="1973" month="07" day="23"/>
<rv year="1973" month="09" day="21"/></hst></fm>
<bdy>
<fp><p>INCORPORATION of methionine as N-terminal residue initiates biosynthesis of a globin chain in rabbit reticulocytes<super>1&ndash;7</super>. After initiation, elongation of the chain proceeds with successive additions of amino acid residues; therefore a population of actively synthesising polysomes contains nascent peptide chains of all stages of elongation<super>8</super>. The initial methionine residue is removed before completion of the chain; consequently methionine is the N-terminal residue of short nascent chains, and valine, the second amino acid incorporated, is the N-terminal residue of long nascent chains. When these chains are digested with trypsin, long nascent chains yield the same N-terminal tryptic peptides as haemoglobin, &alpha;T1 of &alpha; chain and &beta;T1 of &beta; chain, which have N-terminal valine and are composed of seven and eight amino acid residues, respectively<super>9, 10</super>. The N-terminal tryptic peptides of short nascent chains are longer by one residue, namely the N-terminal methionine. Thus all but very short nascent chains contain either the methionyl or the valyl N-terminal tryptic peptide, and the ratio of yields of these peptides from a tryptic digest is a measure of the relative numbers of the two types of nascent chains in a polysomal preparation.</p></fp>
<p>Fig. 1 Column chromatographic analyses of synthetic Metf3Tl(A) and f3Tl(A). In both a and b, a mixture of peptides was applied to a column and eluted with a linear gradient of 250 ml each of pH 3.1 and 5.0 pyridine-acetic acid buffers18. One-tenth of the effluent was reacted with ninhydrin and its transmittance at 570 nm recorded continuously, and the remainder of the effluent was collected in 3 ml fractions. a, A mixture of 125 nmol of Metf3Tl(A) and 160 nmol of 3T1(A) was applied to a 0.9&times;19.2cm column of Aminex AS. The left and right peaks are MetIlTl(A) and IIT1(A), respectively. b, A mixture of 62 nmol of MetflTl(A) and 80 nmol of f3Tl(A) was applied to a 0.9&times;12.0 cm column of AG5OWX-2. Chromatography on this column does not separate these peptides but is useful as a step in their purification from other peptides of tryptic digests.
Recently we found that synthesis of the chains of haemoglobin S in sickle-cell anaemia reticulocytes is also initiated with methionine, but that the relative yields of the methionyl N-terminal tryptic peptides of both a chain and /3 chain are higher than in rabbit reticulocytes". To determine whether the higher yields are associated generally with human reticulocytes or specifically with sickle cell anaemia reticulocytes, we have examined cells that synthesise haemoglobin A (HbA), the normal form of human adult haemoglobin.
The N-terminal tryptic peptide f3Tl(A) of the /3 chain of HbA and the corresponding methionyl peptide Met/31(A), were synthesised chemically12 and were used to determine conditions for column chromatographic separation and identification. These peptides are: /3T1(A), Val-His-Leu-ThrPro-Glu-Glu-Lys 13'14 Met/31(A), Met-Val-His-Leu-Thr-ProGlu-Glu-Lys. Column chromatography of these synthetic peptides is shown in Fig. 1 . HbA has the same a chain as haemoglobin S (HbS), and the N-terminal trypic peptide aTl of this chain is identical to that of rabbit a chain9'13'15. This peptide and MetaTl were synthesised chemically and characterised chromatographically in our study. Reticulocyte-rich blood samples were obtained from anaemic patients. The presence of HbA as the preponderant species in these samples was ascertained by electrophoresis on cellulose acetate strips. Published procedures for incubation, digestion, chromatography, and counting were used1'8.
Table I Incorporation of 3H-Iabelled Amino Acids into N-terminal Tryptic Peptides of Nascent f3 Chains&ast;
3H-amino acids
MetI3Tl
Sample
Exp.
incorporated
Metf3Tl &plus; 13T1
Normal human
1
2
3
Lys
Lys, Leu, Val
Leu, His
0.38
0.34
0.35
Sickle cell 1 Rabbits
Mean
Lys; Lys, Val Lys
0.36&plusmn; 0.02 (3)
0.31 &plusmn; 0.02 (3)
0.19&plusmn;0.01 (3)
&ast; Mean &plusmn; s.d. (No. of experiments).
t Haemoglobin A.
Haemoglobin S.
&sect; Data from ref. 11.
Fig. 2 Chromatographic purification and radioactive counting of 3H-labelled Metf3Tl(A) and f3Tl(A). A 50 ml sample of blood with 24% reticulocytes was incubated with 200 jiCi of 3H-histidine and 200 jiCi of 3H-leucine for 10 mm at 37&deg; C. The polysomal fraction was incubated with 65 jig of bovine pancreatic RNase; then 20 mg of globin prepared from haemoglobin A was added, and the resulting mixture was digested with 200 ig of trypsin for 4 h at 37&deg; C. a, The tryptic digest was analysed on Aminex AS as in Fig. la. b, Fractions 38 to 56 of the analysis of Fig. 2a were collected and analysed on AG5OW-X2 as in Fig. lb. c, Fractions 33 to 50 of the analysis of Fig. 2b were collected and reanalysed on Aminex AS as in Fig. la. One ml of each fraction in 10 ml of Aquasol (New England Nuclear Corp.) was counted, and background of 40 c.p.m. was deducted. The peaks at fractions 42 and 48 were radioactive peptides MetI3Tl(A) and 13T1(A), respectively.
Incorporation of 3H-labelled valine, histidine, leucine, and lysine in various combinations into Met/3T1(A) and f3Tl(A) of nascent chains of HbA was determined in three different samples of blood. Chromatographic purification of these peptides in one of the experiments is shown in Fig. 2. Radioactivity of the purified peptides was counted, and the fraction Metf3Tl &ast;/(Met/3T1&ast; &plus; /3T1 &ast;) was calculated for each experiment. Values obtained are shown in Table 1 together with our values for the same ratio from rabbit and sickle-cell anaemia reticulocytes.
Two samples were incubated with 35S-methionine, and incorporation of radioactivity into N-terminal methionyl peptides and internal methionine-containing tryptic peptides was measured. Chromatographic separations of these pep- tides are shown in Fig. 3. Incorporation of radioactivity into purified fractions to MetaTl, aT5, Met/3T1, and f3T5 was counted, and the ratios of counts MetaTl &ast; / aT5&ast; and MetfTl &ast;//3T5&ast; were calculated. These values are listed in Table 2 together with our values of the same ratios from nascent chains of rabbit and sickle-cell anaemia reticulocytes.
Figure 3 shows that radioactive fractions with the same chromatographic properties as chemically synthesised Met/3T1(A) and MetaTl are present in tryptic digests of nascent globin chains from normal human reticulocytes and absent in digests of globin prepared from post-ribosomal haemoglobin of the same cells. The data 'of Tables 1 and 2 indicate that the fraction of methionyl nascent chains in reticulocytes that synthesise HbA does not differ significantly from this fraction in reticulocytes that synthesise HbS; therefore nascent chains from both human sources have a higher proportion of N-terminal methionine than nascent chains of rabbit reticulocytes.
Table 2 Incorporation
of
Nas
35S-Methionine into cent Globin Chains&ast;
Tryptic Peptides
Experiment
MetctTl/aT5
Metf3T1/3T5
Normal human t
W.
0.48
0.83
W. G.
0.35
0.80
Mean
0.42 &plusmn; 0.06 (2)
0.82 &plusmn; 0.01 (2)
Sickle cell
0.46 &plusmn; 0.08 (3)
0.86 &plusmn; 0.08 (3)
Rabbits
0.15
0.19
&ast; Mean &plusmn; s.d. (No. of experiments).
t Haemoglobin A.
Haemoglobin S.
&sect; Data from ref. 11.
The relative yields of methionyl and valyl N-terminal tryptie peptides from a digest of nascent chains can be used to calculate the stage of elongation at which methionine is removed. There are 146 amino acid residues in the /3 chain of rabbit or human haemoglobin'&deg;"3'14 therefore reticulocyte polysomes contain 146 possible kinds of nascent 1 chains of increasing length from the dipeptide Met-Val to the corn- pleted but unreleased /3 chain. If y is the length in amino acid residues of the longest nascent chain with N-terminal methionine, the number of kinds of nascent chain retaining this residue is y - 1 . Because seven of these chains are shorter than Met/3Tl, the number of kinds of nascent chains that contain Met/3T1 is y- 8, and the total number of kinds of nascent chains that contain either Met/3T1 or /3T1 is 146-7=139. Rate of elongation of rabbit globin chains is uniform'6'19 consequently nascent chains of each length are present in equal numbers during steady-state synthesis; therefore (y - 8) / 1 39= Met/3T1 &ast; / (Met/3T1 &ast; &plus;/3Tl &ast;), where Metf3Tl &ast; and /3T1 &ast; are the yields of radioactive peptides from a digest of uniformly labelled nascent chains. Thus the length of the longest nascent chain with N-terminal methionine is y=8 &plus; 1 39[Met/3T1 &ast;/(Metf3Tl &ast; &plus;f3Tl &ast;)]. Derivation of the method of calculation of the same parameter from the data of Table 2 was given in our previous report11.
The residue lengths of nascent chains at the time of removal of N-terminal methionine, calculated from the data of Tables 1 and 2, are shown in Table 3. The calculated maximum lengths of rabbit nascent methionyl chains are in approximate agreement with previous estimates45 and the calculated lengths of corresponding human chains are roughly 1.5 to 3 times as great. Results from the data of Table 2 show little if any difference in residue length between human a chain and either of the human /3 chains. Each of the two independent sets of experiments represented in Tables 1 and 2 yielded nearly equal values for the residue lengths of nascent methionyl /3 chains of HbA and HbS.
Thus the substitution of glutamic acid near the N terminus of the /3 chain of HbA by valine in HbS (ref. 20) has little if any effect on removal of the initiating methionine residue. The fact that human nascent a and /3 chains both have a higher proportion of N-terminal methionine than corresponding rabbit nascent chains may suggest a species difference in some supernatant activity in reticulocytes, such as enzymatic activity toward hydrolysis of the methionyl peptide bond21. Species differences in uniformity of elongation or in folding of nascent chains have also been suggested as possible mechanisms for the observed differences'1.
Fig. 3 Chromatographic purification and radioactive counting of 35S-methionine-labelled cryptic peptides from haemoglobin A. a, A tryptic digest of the ribosomal fraction was loaded on an Aminex A5 column (0.9&times;19.2 cm). The column was first washed with 60 ml ofpH 2.5 pyridine-acetic acid buffer18, then eleted with same buffer gradient as in Fig. 1. Aliquots of 0.3 ml from each 3 ml fraction were counted in 10 ml Aquasol. Background of 35 c.p.m. was deducted. Arrows indicate, from left to right, the elution positions of peptides 3T5, ciT5, and MetflTl(A). b, A tryptic digest of globin prepared from the postribosomal supernatant fraction was chromatographed as in Fig. 3a. Aliquots of 0.4 mt of each fraction were counted in 10 ml of Aquasol, and background of 40 c.p.m. was deducted. Arrows indicate the same peptide fractions as Fig. 3a. MetflTl(A) is absent. c, Fractions 33 to 43 from the analysis of Fig. 3a were collected, loaded on a column of AG5OW-X2 (0.9&times;12.0 cm) and eluted with same buffer gradient as in Fig. 1. Aliquots of 2 ml of each fraction in 10 ml Aquasol were counted, and background of 70 c.p.m. was deducted. The arrows indicate MektTl and xT5. d, Fractions 32 to 45 from the analysis of Fig. 3b were reanalysed as in Fig. 3c. Aliquots of 1 ml of each fraction in 10 ml of Aquasol were counted, and background of 70 c.p m. was deducted. Arrows indicate the same peptide positions as Fig. 3c, and MetaTl is missing.
Table 3 Maximum Number of Amino Acid Residues in N-terminal Methionyl Nascent Chains of Haemoglobin&ast;
a
b
c
x Chain
Normal human
50&plusmn;7 (2)
41&plusmn;6 (2)
-
Sickle cell
54&plusmn;7 (3)
44 &plusmn; 6 (3)
-
Rabbitt
23
19
30
13 Chain
Normal human
Sickle cell
Rabbit
80 &plusmn; 2 (2)
84&plusmn;6 (3)
27
46&plusmn;1 (2)
49&plusmn;3 (3)
 17
58 &plusmn; 3 (3)
51&plusmn;3 (3)
34&plusmn;1 (3)
&ast; Mean&plusmn; s.d. (No. of experiments), calculated with the equations of ref. 1 1 . Columns a and b: data of Table 2 were used for these calculations. Yields of peptides were taken to be equal in column a; yields of peptides MetcJl, aT5, MetflTl(S), 13T5(S), Met13Tl(A), and 13T5(A) were taken to be 63, 50, 75, 40, 80, and 42% respectively22 in column b. Column c: data of Table 1 were used for these calculations; yields of Met13Tl and 13T1 were assumed to be equal.
t The value for rabbit a chain was calculated from the result of Wilson and Dintzis'.
We thank Drs M. Goulian, I. Mendelsohn, R. J. Ugoretz, H. Wohl, and H. Koenig for their help in obtaining blood samples. This work was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health.</p></bdy>
<bm>
<bibl>
<bib id="b1" number="1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wilson</snm>, <fnm>D. B.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Dintzis</snm>, <fnm>H. M.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl>, <vid>66</vid>, <ppf>1282</ppf> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2" number="2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bhaduri</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Chatterjee</snm>, <fnm>N. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bose</snm>, <fnm>K. K.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Gupta</snm>, <fnm>N. K.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Biochem. biophys. Res. Commun.</jtl>, <vid>40</vid>, <ppf>402</ppf> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3" number="3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Housman</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Jacobs-Lorena</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rajbhandary</snm>, <fnm>U. L.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Lodish</snm>, <fnm>H. F.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Nature</jtl>, <vid>227</vid>, <ppf>913</ppf> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4" number="4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jackson</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Hunter</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Nature</jtl>, <vid>227</vid>, <ppf>672</ppf> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5" number="5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yoshida</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Watanabe</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Morris</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl>, <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>1600</ppf> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6" number="6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hunter</snm>, <fnm>A. R.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Jackson</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Eur. J. Biochem.</jtl>, <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>316</ppf> (<cd year="1971">1971</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7" number="7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Crystal</snm>, <fnm>R. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shafritz</snm>, <fnm>D. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Prichard</snm>, <fnm>P. M.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Anderson</snm>, <fnm>W. F.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl>, <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>1810</ppf> (<cd year="1971">1971</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8" number="8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Dintzis</snm>, <fnm>H. M.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl>, <vid>47</vid>, <ppf>247</ppf> (<cd year="1961">1961</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9" number="9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Flamm</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Best</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Braunitzer</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Hoppe-Seyler&apos;s Z. physiol. Chem.</jtl>, <vid>352</vid>, <ppf>885</ppf> (<cd year="1971">1971</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10" number="10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Best</snm>, <fnm>J. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Flamm</snm>, <fnm>U.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Braunitzer</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Hoppe-Sey1er&apos;s Z. physiol. Chem.</jtl>, <vid>350</vid>, <ppf>563</ppf> (<cd year="1969">1969</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11" number="11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Suzuki</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Itano</snm>, <fnm>H. A.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Proc. natn. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</jtl>, <vid>70</vid>, <ppf>2059</ppf> (<cd year="1973">1973</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12" number="12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Merrifield</snm>, <fnm>R. B.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>J. Am. chem. Soc.</jtl>, <vid>85</vid>, <ppf>2149</ppf> (<cd year="1963">1963</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13" number="13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Braunitzer</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gehring-M&uuml;ller</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hilschmann</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hilse</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hobom</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Rudloff</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Wittman-Liebold</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Hoppe-Seyler&apos;s Z. physiol. Chem.</jtl>, <vid>325</vid>, <ppf>283</ppf> (<cd year="1961">1961</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14" number="14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Konigsberg</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Goldstein</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Hill</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl>, <vid>238</vid>, <ppf>2028</ppf> (<cd year="1963">1963</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15" number="15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Konigsberg</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Hill</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl>, <vid>237</vid>, <ppf>3157</ppf> (<cd year="1962">1962</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16" number="16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hunt</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hunter</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Munro</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>J. molec. Biol.</jtl>, <vid>36</vid>, <ppf>31</ppf> (<cd year="1968">1968</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17" number="17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Del Monte</snm>, <fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Kazazian</snm>, <fnm>H. H.</fnm>, <suff>jun.</suff></refau>, <jtl>J. molec. Biol.</jtl>, <vid>56</vid>, <ppf>429</ppf> (<cd year="1971">1971</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18" number="18"><reftxt><refau><snm>Jones</snm>, <fnm>R. T.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Meth. biochem. Analysis</jtl>, <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>205</ppf> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19" number="19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Luppis</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bargellesi</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Conconi</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Biochemistry</jtl>, <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>4175</ppf> (<cd year="1970">1970</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20" number="20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ingram</snm>, <fnm>V. M.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>Nature</jtl>, <vid>180</vid>, <ppf>326</ppf>, (<cd year="1957">1957</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21" number="21"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yoshida</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Lin</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl>, <vid>247</vid>, <ppf>952</ppf> (<cd year="1972">1972</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22" number="22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Guidotti</snm>, <fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hill</snm>, <fnm>R. J.</fnm></refau>, and <refau><snm>Konigsberg</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau>, <jtl>J. biol. Chem.</jtl>, <vid>237</vid>, <ppf>2184</ppf> (<cd year="1962">1962</cd>).</reftxt></bib></bibl></bm></article>
