<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN" "NPG_XML_Article.dtd" [
<!ENTITY figf1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2396-F1//EN" "nsmb.2396-F1" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf2 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2396-F2//EN" "nsmb.2396-F2" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf3 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2396-F3//EN" "nsmb.2396-F3" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf4 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2396-F4//EN" "nsmb.2396-F4" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY figf5 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2396-F5//EN" "nsmb.2396-F5" NDATA ITEM>
<!ENTITY tbl1 PUBLIC "-//NatureAmerica//FICI nsmb.2396-T1//EN" "nsmb.2396-T1" NDATA ITEM>
]>
<article id="nsmb.2396" language="eng" relation="no">
<pubfm>
<jtl>Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology</jtl>
<vol>19</vol>
<iss>11</iss>
<idt>201211</idt>
<categ id="af"/>
<pp><spn>1176</spn><epn>1181</epn><cnt>6</cnt></pp>
<issn type="print">1545-9993</issn>
<issn type="electronic">1545-9985</issn>
<cpg><cpy>2012</cpy><cpn>Nature Publishing Group, a division of Macmillan Publishers Limited. All Rights Reserved.</cpn></cpg>
<suppinfo id="S1">
<suppobj extrefid="nsmb.2396-S1" format="pdf" filesize="4M"><title>Supplementary Text and Figures</title>
<descrip><p>Supplementary Figure 1</p></descrip></suppobj>
</suppinfo>
<subject code="npg_subject_470"/>
<subject code="npg_subject_143"/>
<doi>10.1038/nsmb.2396</doi></pubfm>
<fm>
<atl>Crystal structure of adenovirus <named-entity id="named-entity-1">E3-19K</named-entity> bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-2">HLA-A2</named-entity> reveals mechanism for immunomodulation</atl>
<aug>
<au><fnm>Lenong</fnm><snm>Li</snm><inits>L</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<au><fnm>Yasameen</fnm><snm>Muzahim</snm><inits>Y</inits><orf rid="a1"/></au>
<cau><fnm>Marlene</fnm><snm>Bouvier</snm><inits>M</inits><orf rid="a1"/><corf rid="c1"/></cau>
<aff><oid id="a1"/><org>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Illinois at Chicago</org>, <cty>Chicago</cty>, <st>Illinois</st> <cny>USA</cny>.</aff>
<caff><coid id="c1"/><email>mbouvier@uic.edu</email></caff>
</aug>
<hst>
<re year="2012" month="05" day="05"/>
<acc year="2012" month="08" day="30"/>
<pubdate type="aop" year="2012" month="10" day="07"/></hst>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="aop">
<title/>
<p>Adenovirus infection can suppress antigen presentation by MHC I, by the action of transmembrane protein E3-19K, whose N-terminal domain localizes to the ER lumen and binds MHC I luminal domain. Now the crystal structure of E3-19K in complex with MHC I molecule HLA-A2 is presented, providing atomic-level insight into this interaction.</p></edsumm>
<edsumm type="standfirst" publish="issue">
<title/>
<p>Adenovirus infection can suppress antigen presentation by MHC I, by the action of transmembrane protein E3-19K, whose N-terminal domain localizes to the ER lumen and binds MHC I luminal domain. Now the crystal structure of E3-19K in complex with MHC I molecule HLA-A2 is presented, providing atomic-level insight into this interaction.</p></edsumm>
<abs><p><named-entity id="named-entity-3">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to and retains MHC class I molecules in the endoplasmic reticulum, suppressing anti-adenovirus activities of T cells. We determined the structure of the adenovirus serotype 2 (Ad2, species C) <named-entity id="named-entity-4">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-5">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex to 1.95-&#xC5; resolution. Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-6">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to the N terminus of the <named-entity id="named-entity-7">HLA-A2</named-entity> groove, contacting the &#x3B1;1, &#x3B1;2 and &#x3B1;3 domains and <named-entity id="named-entity-8">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity>. Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-9">E3-19K</named-entity> has a unique structure comprising a large N-terminal domain, formed by two partially overlapping &#x3B2;-sheets arranged in a V shape, and a C-terminal &#x3B1;-helix and tail. The structure reveals determinants in <named-entity id="named-entity-10">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-11">HLA-A2</named-entity> that are important for complex formation; conservation of some of these determinants in <named-entity id="named-entity-12">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins of different species and MHC I molecules of different loci suggests a universal binding mode for all <named-entity id="named-entity-13">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins. Our structure is important for understanding the immunomodulatory function of <named-entity id="named-entity-14">E3-19K</named-entity>.</p></abs></fm>
<bdy>
<p>Adenoviruses are widespread in the human population, with at least 51 known serotypes (Ad1&#x2013;Ad51) classified into six species (A&#x2013;F)<bibr rid="b1"/>. Adenoviruses cause a number of infections that are linked to respiratory, gastrointestinal and ocular diseases<bibr rid="b2"/>. Although primary adenovirus infection elicits antiviral cytotoxic T lymphocyte (CTL) immune responses, these responses are usually insufficient to clear the virus. Consequently, adenoviruses cause lifelong asymptomatic infections in healthy individuals and can be fatal in children and immunocompromised patients.</p>
<p>Large DNA viruses such as adenoviruses have evolved strategies for evading antiviral immune responses<bibr rid="b3 b4"/>. It was shown in the late 1980s that the <named-entity id="named-entity-15">E3-19K</named-entity> protein of adenovirus binds to and retains MHC class I molecules in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) of infected cells, preventing their egress to the cell surface<bibr rid="b5 b6 b7"/>. As a consequence, adenovirus-infected cells are less susceptible to lysis by adenovirus-specific CTLs<bibr rid="b6 b8 b9 b10"/>. At that time, this represented the first example of a viral protein capable of interfering with MHC I antigen presentation. It was also shown that when the lungs of cotton rats are infected with wild-type adenovirus, immunopathological responses are less severe than when the lungs are infected with a mutant adenovirus containing a deletion of the <i><named-entity id="named-entity-16">E3-19K</named-entity></i> gene<bibr rid="b11"/>. It was suggested that the absence of <i><named-entity id="named-entity-17">E3-19K</named-entity></i> in the mutant virus activated CTLs as part of the host inflammatory response to the virus<bibr rid="b11"/>. It is thought that <named-entity id="named-entity-18">E3-19K</named-entity>, through its association with MHC I, enables adenoviruses to establish persistence in host cells<bibr rid="b4 b11 b12"/>.</p>
<p><named-entity id="named-entity-19">E3-19K</named-entity> is a type I transmembrane glycoprotein that comprises an N-terminal ER-lumenal domain, a transmembrane domain and a C-terminal cytosolic tail. The ER-lumenal domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-20">E3-19K</named-entity> associates with the ER-lumenal domain of MHC class I molecules<bibr rid="b8 b13 b14 b15 b16"/>, whereas the <named-entity id="named-entity-21">dilysine</named-entity> motif in the cytosolic tail of <named-entity id="named-entity-22">E3-19K</named-entity> provides the signal for localization of the <named-entity id="named-entity-23">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;MHC I complex in the ER<bibr rid="b8 b17 b18"/>. An analysis of immunoprecipitates from Ad2-, Ad5- and Ad19-infected mammalian cells suggested that <named-entity id="named-entity-24">E3-19K</named-entity> displays differential affinity with MHC I<bibr rid="b19 b20 b21"/>. Using recombinant, soluble <named-entity id="named-entity-25">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins of species B, C, D and E and <named-entity id="named-entity-26">HLA-A</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-27">HLA-B</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-28">HLA-C</named-entity> molecules, we showed that <named-entity id="named-entity-29">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins associate with MHC I in a locus-specific manner<bibr rid="b22 b23"/>: <named-entity id="named-entity-30">E3-19K</named-entity> associates with <named-entity id="named-entity-31">HLA-A</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-32">HLA-B</named-entity> but displays essentially no affinity for <named-entity id="named-entity-33">HLA-C</named-entity>. We also showed that <named-entity id="named-entity-34">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins of species B, C and E associate with <named-entity id="named-entity-35">HLA-A</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-36">HLA-B</named-entity> in an HLA allele&#x2013;dependent manner<bibr rid="b22 b23"/>.</p>
<p>The ER-lumenal domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-37">E3-19K</named-entity> has been subdivided into three regions<bibr rid="b24 b25"/>: (i) residues 1 to ~78&#x2013;81 are rather variable between <named-entity id="named-entity-38">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins of different species; (ii) residues ~79&#x2013;82 to ~98 are rather conserved between <named-entity id="named-entity-39">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins of different species; and (iii) residues ~99 to 107 act as a linker between the ER-lumenal domain and the transmembrane domain. Secondary-structure predictions of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-40">E3-19K</named-entity> have provided some insights into potential architectural elements<bibr rid="b26 b27 b28"/>. Structure-function relationship studies have identified specific residues in both the variable and conserved regions of <named-entity id="named-entity-41">E3-19K</named-entity> that are critical for its MHC I&#x2013;binding function<bibr rid="b22 b23 b25 b27 b29"/>. Evidence from several studies has suggested that <named-entity id="named-entity-42">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to the peptide-binding groove of MHC I<bibr rid="b13 b14 b22 b23"/>. We proposed recently a model of interaction in which <named-entity id="named-entity-43">E3-19K</named-entity> has contact sites on MHC I at the N-terminal end of the &#x3B1;1 helix and at the C-terminal end of the &#x3B1;2 helix<bibr rid="b23"/>. To date, more than 20 years after the discovery of <named-entity id="named-entity-44">E3-19K</named-entity> as the first viral immunomodulatory protein, lack of knowledge of its three-dimensional structure when alone or in complex with MHC I severely limits understanding of its immunomodulatory function. Progress has been hampered largely by the fact that <named-entity id="named-entity-45">E3-19K</named-entity> is a protein recalcitrant to crystallization.</p>
<p>We set out to determine the X-ray three-dimensional structure of soluble recombinant Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-46">E3-19K</named-entity> bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-47">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-48">Tax</named-entity> peptide. We describe a new rescue refolding strategy that allowed formation of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-49">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-50">HLA-A2</named-entity>, from which we generated crystals diffracting to 1.95-&#xC5; resolution. Our structure offers precise explanations for the mechanism by which <named-entity id="named-entity-51">E3-19K</named-entity> modulates antiviral cellular immunity.</p>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Results</sectitle>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Structure of the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-52">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-53">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex</sectitle>
<p>The ER-lumenal domain of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-54">E3-19K</named-entity> has two N-linked glycans (Asn12 and Asn61)<bibr rid="b30"/>. In previous studies, we showed that treatment of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-55">E3-19K</named-entity> with the glycan-cleaving enzymes <named-entity id="named-entity-56">PNGase F</named-entity> and Endo H<bibr rid="b31"/> leads to precipitation of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-57">E3-19K</named-entity>. This suggested an important role for the glycans in the stabilization of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-58">E3-19K</named-entity>. When Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-59">E3-19K</named-entity> is bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-60">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-61">Tax</named-entity>, it can more easily withstand hydrolysis of its glycans; crystallization trials of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-62">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-63">HLA-A2</named-entity> treated with <named-entity id="named-entity-64">PNGase F</named-entity> and Endo H failed to produce crystals (data not shown).</p>
<p>The expression of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-65">E3-19K</named-entity> in <i>Escherichia coli</i> led to the production of inclusion bodies from which we were unable to refold <named-entity id="named-entity-66">E3-19K</named-entity> (discussed in ref. <bibrinl rid="b31">31</bibrinl>). In marked contrast, the addition of submolar amounts of folded <named-entity id="named-entity-67">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-68">Tax</named-entity> in the oxidative refolding buffer containing <named-entity id="named-entity-69">urea</named-entity>-solubilized inclusion bodies of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-70">E3-19K</named-entity> generated the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-71">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-72">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex in solution. Most likely, upon refolding, Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-73">E3-19K</named-entity> can bind immediately to <named-entity id="named-entity-74">HLA-A2</named-entity> and form a stable Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-75">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-76">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex before it can aggregate.</p>
    <p>Using this strategy, we determined the structure of the complex between the ER-lumenal domains of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-77">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-78">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-79">Tax</named-entity> to 1.95-&#xC5; resolution by molecular replacement (Online <ancref rid="an1">Methods</ancref> and <tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr>). Only minor differences were observed between the two molecules of <named-entity id="named-entity-80">E3-19K</named-entity> in the asymmetric unit (r.m.s. deviation of 0.52 &#xC5; for 97 equivalent C&#x3B1; atoms), so only chain G will be discussed further. Clear electron density was observed for nearly all residues of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-81">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-82">HLA-A2</named-entity>; residues 2&#x2013;100 of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-83">E3-19K</named-entity>, residues 1&#x2013;275 of <named-entity id="named-entity-84">HLA-A2</named-entity> heavy chain, residues 0&#x2013;99 of <named-entity id="named-entity-85">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>-microglobulin</named-entity> (<named-entity id="named-entity-86">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity>) and the HTLV-1 <named-entity id="named-entity-87">Tax</named-entity> peptide (LLFGYPVYV). The overall structure of the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-88">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-89">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex is shown in <figr rid="f1">Figure 1a</figr>.</p>
<p>The structure of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-90">E3-19K</named-entity> contains a large N-terminal domain that forms two antiparallel &#x3B2;-sheets defined by &#x3B2;-strands A, B and E and &#x3B2;-strands C, C&#x2032;, F and G (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr>). The C terminus of this domain is connected to an &#x3B1;-helix and a tail (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1b</figr>). The two &#x3B2;-sheets of the N-terminal domain overlap with each other only partially, with an angle of approximately 30&#xB0; between each other, such that overall this domain resembles a V-shaped structure. The apex of the V shape is formed by contact between &#x3B2;-strands C&#x2032; and E, and the opening is defined by &#x3B2;-strands A and G. This unusual relative arrangement of &#x3B2;-sheets confines the hydrophobic core to the deepest part of the V shape. The hydrophobic core comprises residues of &#x3B2;-strands B (Cys22, Thr24, Ile26 and Cys28) and E (Val48 and Ala50) of the ABE &#x3B2;-sheet and &#x3B2;-strands C (Leu35, Ile37 and His39), C&#x2032; (Gly44) and F (Val62 and Val64) of the CC&#x2032;FG &#x3B2;-sheet (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1c</figr>); only one residue of the edge &#x3B2;-strand A (Val13), and none of the edge &#x3B2;-strand G, is part of the hydrophobic core. Other residues including Pro9 and Trp52 of the large N-terminal domain, Phe79 and Met87 of the &#x3B1;-helix and Trp96 of the tail also participate in forming the hydrophobic core (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1c</figr>).</p>
<p>In addition to those within the hydrophobic core, a number of interactions keep the &#x3B1;-helix packed against the N-terminal domain. These include the disulfide bond between Cys83 and Cys22 and also several mostly water-mediated (water G271) hydrogen bonds between Ser90 (&#x3B1;-helix) and Ser17 (&#x3B2;-strand A) and Asn20 (AB loop, the loop connecting &#x3B2;-strands A and B). The well-ordered electron density of the N-terminal residues Lys2&#x2013;Pro9 reveals that main chain atoms of Lys7, Glu8 and Pro9 form water-mediated hydrogen bonds (water G231, G224 and G237, respectively) with the side chains of Thr30 and Glu31 (BC-loop). Similarly, the side chain of Trp96 participates in a water-mediated (water G202) hydrogen bond network that contributes to the well-defined backbone curvature of the tail. Overall, the presence of important hydrogen bonds at the N and C termini and of a hydrophobic core along the entire length of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-91">E3-19K</named-entity> appear to provide structural rigidity to the protein. Finally, it is clear that the strategically positioned disulfide bonds that link &#x3B2;-strands A to B (Cys11-Cys28) and the &#x3B1;-helix to the N-terminal domain (Cys22-Cys83) are critical structural features of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-92">E3-19K</named-entity>, consistent with results from mutational analysis of <named-entity id="named-entity-93">cysteine</named-entity> residues in Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-94">E3-19K</named-entity><bibr rid="b32"/>.</p>
<p>The coordinates of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-95">E3-19K</named-entity> were submitted to the DALI server<bibr rid="b33"/> to establish how <named-entity id="named-entity-96">E3-19K</named-entity> might be related to other proteins of known structure in the Protein Data Bank (PDB). The search revealed a relatively low degree of structural similarity with <named-entity id="named-entity-97">gp130</named-entity>. The closest structural relative is D2 of D2D3 <named-entity id="named-entity-98">gp130</named-entity> (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">1PVH</accession>, r.m.s. deviation of 3.4 &#xC5;), with a <i>Z</i> score of 6.6. The next two best matches are D1 of D1D2 <named-entity id="named-entity-99">gp130</named-entity> (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">1BQU</accession>, r.m.s. deviation of 3.5 &#xC5;) and D2 of D1D2D3 <named-entity id="named-entity-100">gp130</named-entity> (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">1I1R</accession>, r.m.s. deviation of 3.7 &#xC5;), with <i>Z</i> scores of 6.5 and 6.4, respectively. These domains adopt fibronectin type III folds. The superposition of these <named-entity id="named-entity-101">gp130</named-entity>-based structures onto the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-102">E3-19K</named-entity> structure revealed that similarities are limited to one or two &#x3B2;-strands of the CC&#x2032;FG &#x3B2;-sheet; no protein could be identified that aligned well with <named-entity id="named-entity-103">E3-19K</named-entity> in its entirety. No closely related structures were also found with the SSM server<bibr rid="b34"/>. We conclude that the <named-entity id="named-entity-104">E3-19K</named-entity> protein has a unique tertiary structure.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>The <named-entity id="named-entity-105">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-106">HLA-A2</named-entity> binding interface</sectitle>
<p>Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-107">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to the N terminus of the &#x3B1;1-helix on <named-entity id="named-entity-108">HLA-A2</named-entity>, also contacting the C terminus of the &#x3B1;2 helix and prominent loops of the &#x3B1;3 domain and <named-entity id="named-entity-109">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). The <named-entity id="named-entity-110">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-111">HLA-A2</named-entity> binding interface shields a molecular surface area of 1,929 &#xC5;<super>2</super> from solvent. The shape-complementarity coefficient, <i>S</i><sub>c</sub>, of the complex was determined to be 0.68 (<i>S</i><sub>c</sub> = 1 for perfect geometrical fits<bibr rid="b35"/>).</p>
<p>Each interaction site (referred to as sites 1, 2, 3 and 4) is discussed separately (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). Site 1 is located at the N terminus of the &#x3B1;1 helix on <named-entity id="named-entity-112">HLA-A2</named-entity> and contributes 36% to the total buried surface area. The site features a salt bridge between Lys27 (&#x3B2;-strand B) of <named-entity id="named-entity-113">E3-19K</named-entity> and Glu53 of <named-entity id="named-entity-114">HLA-A2</named-entity> as well as hydrogen bond interactions involving Lys16 and Tyr49 (&#x3B2;-strands A and E, respectively) of <named-entity id="named-entity-115">E3-19K</named-entity> and Arg48 and Gln54 of <named-entity id="named-entity-116">HLA-A2</named-entity>, respectively. These interactions are supplemented by a number of solvent-mediated hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic contacts. Site 2 is located at the C terminus of the &#x3B1;2 helix on <named-entity id="named-entity-117">HLA-A2</named-entity> and occupies 16% of the total buried surface area. The key interaction at site 2 is a salt bridge between Lys42 (&#x3B2;-strand C&#x2032;) of <named-entity id="named-entity-118">E3-19K</named-entity> and Glu177 of <named-entity id="named-entity-119">HLA-A2</named-entity>. Site 3 involves prominent loops of <named-entity id="named-entity-120">E3-19K</named-entity> and the &#x3B1;3 domain of <named-entity id="named-entity-121">HLA-A2</named-entity> and contributes 17% of the total buried surface area. The interface at that site is defined by a number of mostly water-mediated hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic contacts. Site 4 involves the &#x3B1;-helix of <named-entity id="named-entity-122">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-123">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> and represents 31% of the total buried surface area. Interactions at site 4 include mostly hydrogen bonds involving Gln92 and Tyr93 of <named-entity id="named-entity-124">E3-19K</named-entity> and several residues (Lys19, Ser20 and Asn21) of <named-entity id="named-entity-125">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> as well as a number of hydrophobic contacts. Overall, interactions at sites 1, 2, 3 and 4 define a novel binding surface on MHC I. No large conformational changes were observed in the polypeptide backbone of <named-entity id="named-entity-126">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-127">Tax</named-entity> upon complex formation; the r.m.s. deviation between free (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">1HHK</accession>) and bound <named-entity id="named-entity-128">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-129">Tax</named-entity> is 0.66 &#xC5; for 384 equivalent C&#x3B1; atoms.</p>
<p>The complementarity of charges at each interaction surface is shown in <figr rid="f3">Figure 3</figr>. The binding interface at site 1 includes a highly electropositive region, contributed by <named-entity id="named-entity-130">E3-19K</named-entity>, that targets an electronegative region on <named-entity id="named-entity-131">HLA-A2</named-entity>. Similarly, the interface region at site 2 is largely electropositive in nature for Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-132">E3-19K</named-entity> and complementarily electronegative for <named-entity id="named-entity-133">HLA-A2</named-entity>. Site 3, in contrast, is formed by areas of electronegativity and electropositivity on both <named-entity id="named-entity-134">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-135">HLA-A2</named-entity>. Finally, site 4, which involves the &#x3B1;-helix of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-136">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-137">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity>, is the most apolar region of the overall binding interface.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Residues in <named-entity id="named-entity-138">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins conserved across adenovirus species</sectitle>
<p>A sequence alignment of <named-entity id="named-entity-139">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins of different species reveals residues that have been maintained by evolution as strictly and highly conserved (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>). These residues were mapped in the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-140">E3-19K</named-entity> structure (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). The analysis shows that several strictly conserved residues are clustered in the N-terminal domain, particularly in the central &#x3B2;-strands B and F (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). The N terminus of the &#x3B1;-helix and tail both also contain several strictly conserved residues. Strict conservation is also observed for four <named-entity id="named-entity-141">cysteine</named-entity> residues that form the two disulfide bonds (Cys11, Cys28 and Cys22, Cys83).</p>
<p>Notably, nine strictly conserved (Cys22, Ile26, Cys28, Ile37, Trp52, Val62, Val64, Phe79 and Trp96) and four highly conserved (Val13, Leu35, Val48 and Met87) residues (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>) are part of the hydrophobic core (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1c</figr> compared to <figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). Thus, several residues have been maintained evolutionarily because of their key role in the structural integrity of the <named-entity id="named-entity-142">E3-19K</named-entity> fold. Other strictly conserved (Lys27) and highly conserved (Glu18, Leu25, Lys42, Met89, Gln92, Tyr93 and Leu95) residues have been maintained because of the important part that they play in the MHC I&#x2013;binding function of <named-entity id="named-entity-143">E3-19K</named-entity> (residues marked in red in <sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir> and side chains indicated in <figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). These residues mediate hydrophilic and hydrophobic interactions with <named-entity id="named-entity-144">HLA-A2</named-entity> at site 1 (Glu18, Leu25, Lys27), site 2 (Glu18 and Lys42), site 3 (Leu95) and site 4 (Met89, Gln92 and Tyr93). Notably, sequence alignment reveals strict conservation of the WPP motif (residues 96&#x2013;98) (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1)</sir>. Trp96 is part of the hydrophobic core (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1c</figr> compared to <figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>) and participates in a network of solvent-mediated hydrogen bonds, as mentioned above. This effect, together with the exceptional conformational rigidity of <named-entity id="named-entity-145">proline</named-entity> residues, suggests that the WPP motif has an important structural role.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Conserved MHC I residues at the binding interface</sectitle>
<p>A sequence alignment of consensus <named-entity id="named-entity-146">HLA-A</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-147">HLA -B</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-148">HLA-C</named-entity> heavy chains at each of the three interaction sites on the <named-entity id="named-entity-149">HLA-A2</named-entity> heavy chain is shown in <figr rid="f5">Figure 5</figr>. The analysis shows that Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-150">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to conserved residues of the <named-entity id="named-entity-151">HLA-A2</named-entity> heavy chain at sites 1 and 2 but to polymorphic residues at site 3. Site 4, which involves <named-entity id="named-entity-152">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity>, is obviously strictly conserved in HLA molecules. Overall, our structure shows that Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-153">E3-19K</named-entity> interacts largely with conserved residues of <named-entity id="named-entity-154">HLA-A2</named-entity>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Discussion</sectitle>
<p>It was previously speculated that the <named-entity id="named-entity-155">E3-19K</named-entity> protein resembles an immunoglobulin-like domain<bibr rid="b26"/>; however, our structure shows that this is not the case. Structural-alignment searches against the DALI and SSM servers did not identify any structures that aligned well with Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-156">E3-19K</named-entity> in its entirety, which indicated a unique tertiary structure.</p>
<p><named-entity id="named-entity-157">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins share relatively low levels of sequence homology in their N-terminal 100 residues (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>). In spite of this, several residues in this region that are part of the hydrophobic core are strictly or highly conserved (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>). This includes residue Trp96, which together with Pro97 and Pro98 likely provides conformational rigidity to the tail region of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-158">E3-19K</named-entity>. Such rigidity of the tail should restrict conformational freedom of the membrane-anchored ER-lumenal domain. The strictly conserved WPP motif may thus be important for correctly aligning <named-entity id="named-entity-159">E3-19K</named-entity> onto MHC I. It is of note that a mutation of Trp96 in Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-160">E3-19K</named-entity> decreased interaction with MHC I<bibr rid="b27"/>. Thus, it is clear that the conservation of key structural determinants in <named-entity id="named-entity-161">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins reflects a strong evolutionary pressure to maintain a function-specific tertiary structure, which is consistent with our knowledge that all <named-entity id="named-entity-162">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins display an MHC I&#x2013;binding function.</p>
<p>The characterization of interaction in <named-entity id="named-entity-163">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;MHC I pairs is important because of the role that this association has in adenovirus pathogenesis. We suggest that Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-164">E3-19K</named-entity> residues Lys27 (site 1), which is strictly conserved (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>), and Lys42 (site 2), which is conserved by charge, are key determinants of the MHC I&#x2013;binding function of <named-entity id="named-entity-165">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins. We showed previously the importance of the electrostatic interaction mediated by Lys42 from a mutation of E177K in <named-entity id="named-entity-166">HLA-A</named-entity>*1101, which abolished interaction with <named-entity id="named-entity-167">E3-19K</named-entity> of species B, C, D and E<bibr rid="b23"/>. Furthermore, we suggest that the highly conserved Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-168">E3-19K</named-entity> residues Gln92 and Tyr93 (site 4) (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>) are important determinants of interaction in <named-entity id="named-entity-169">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;MHC I pairs. Consistent with this, we showed that a Y93G mutation in Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-170">E3-19K</named-entity> abolished interaction with <named-entity id="named-entity-171">HLA-A</named-entity> molecules<bibr rid="b29"/>. We and others have also shown that mutation of noncontact Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-172">E3-19K</named-entity> residues such as Met87 and Lys91 (site 4) destabilized Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-173">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;MHC I interaction<bibr rid="b23 b27"/>. Because the shape complementarity is high at site 4 (<i>S</i><sub>c</sub> = 0.81), any mutations that affect the geometrical fit between the &#x3B1;-helix of <named-entity id="named-entity-174">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-175">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> is expected to disrupt the interconnected network of interactions at that site (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). We have evidence in support of this view from studies in which we showed that for a given MHC class I molecule, Ad37 <named-entity id="named-entity-176">E3-19K</named-entity> of species D displays the weakest binding affinities relative to those of species B, C and E<bibr rid="b23"/>. <named-entity id="named-entity-177">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins of species D are not only most divergent at site 4 (<sir rid="S1" refobjid="nsmb.2396-S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</sir>) but also carry nonconserved substitutions at each of the three contact residues: M89V, Q92L and Y93H. Taken together, this analysis suggests that the binding mode of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-178">E3-19K</named-entity> onto <named-entity id="named-entity-179">HLA-A2</named-entity> is likely to represent a universal mode of interaction for all <named-entity id="named-entity-180">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins. Finally, site 3 is a region of the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-181">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-182">HLA-A2</named-entity> interface where the consensus sequences of HLA heavy chains are most divergent (<figr rid="f5">Fig. 5</figr>), and it also lacks the kind of key interaction involving conserved residues that are present at the other three sites. As such, interactions at site 3 are expected to be responsible for the variability in binding affinities that <named-entity id="named-entity-183">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins display for MHC I.</p>
<p>There are many particular features of the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-184">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-185">HLA-A2</named-entity> structure (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1a</figr>) that exemplify the fine-tuned nature of the <named-entity id="named-entity-186">E3-19K</named-entity> immunomodulatory function. First, <named-entity id="named-entity-187">E3-19K</named-entity> ensures 'cross-reactivity' with MHC I by binding largely to conserved MHC residues. Second, <named-entity id="named-entity-188">E3-19K</named-entity> has evolved to circumvent peptide specificity by binding away from the groove. Third, and importantly, <named-entity id="named-entity-189">E3-19K</named-entity> displays high-affinity interaction with MHC I<bibr rid="b22 b23"/>. Fourth, Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-190">E3-19K</named-entity> has evolved an elongated structure that permits contacts over the entire length of <named-entity id="named-entity-191">HLA-A2</named-entity>, including the heavy chain and <named-entity id="named-entity-192">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity>. In this regard, we showed that the first N-terminal 93 residues of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-193">E3-19K</named-entity> are sufficient to maintain high-affinity interaction with <named-entity id="named-entity-194">HLA-A</named-entity>*1101 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b29">29</bibrinl>), which is in perfect agreement with our structure. Finally, <named-entity id="named-entity-195">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to the N terminus, rather than the C terminus, of the groove. The C terminus of the groove is thought to represent the binding region for the class I assembly proteins onto immature MHC I<bibr rid="b36"/>. Thus, in targeting the N terminus of the groove, <named-entity id="named-entity-196">E3-19K</named-entity> likely ensures that it can maintain an association with both immature (peptide-free) and mature (peptide-filled) forms of MHC I. In support of this, we showed that Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-197">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to both peptide-free and peptide-filled <named-entity id="named-entity-198">HLA-A</named-entity>*1101 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b31">31</bibrinl>).</p>
<p>The conformationally sensitive monoclonal antibody (mAb) 64-3-7, which is specific for 'open' MHC I<bibr rid="b37"/>, was shown to bind to a region of MHC I comprising Arg48 and Pro50 (site 1 in <figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). Because 64-3-7 can distinguish between open and 'closed' MHC I, it was suggested that the region of the groove to which 64-3-7 binds is folded differently in these two forms of MHC I<bibr rid="b37"/>. In the context of our structure, this is entirely consistent with our findings that Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-199">E3-19K</named-entity> displays differential binding affinities for peptide-free (open) and peptide-filled (closed) <named-entity id="named-entity-200">HLA-A</named-entity>*1101 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b31">31</bibrinl>). It is also consistent with a previous report showing that <named-entity id="named-entity-201">E3-19K</named-entity> cannot be co-immunoprecipitated with 64-3-7 (ref. <bibrinl rid="b38">38</bibrinl>). Taken together, this evidence suggests that the stretch of MHC residues between Arg48 to Glu58 is likely to undergo major peptide-induced conformational changes, reinforcing the notion that peptide-induced conformational changes occur at the N terminus of the groove<bibr rid="b37 b39"/>.</p>
<p>We showed previously that <named-entity id="named-entity-202">E3-19K</named-entity> proteins bind to <named-entity id="named-entity-203">HLA-A</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-204">HLA-B</named-entity> molecules but show no avidity for <named-entity id="named-entity-205">HLA-C</named-entity> molecules<bibr rid="b22 b23"/>. Other immunomodulatory proteins of large DNA viruses display the same locus specificity<bibr rid="b40 b41 b42"/>. An analysis of interaction between Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-206">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-207">HLA-A2</named-entity> at site 3 (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>), in the context of the crystal structure of free <named-entity id="named-entity-208">HLA-Cw</named-entity>*0403 (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">1QQD</accession>), suggests that residues Glu183 and Gly207 in <named-entity id="named-entity-209">HLA-Cw</named-entity>*0403 cannot mediate interactions shown at site 3. We therefore suggest that these two residues have a role in the inability of <named-entity id="named-entity-210">E3-19K</named-entity> to bind <named-entity id="named-entity-211">HLA-C</named-entity>. Notably, we have new data showing that Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-212">E3-19K</named-entity> and Ad4 <named-entity id="named-entity-213">E3-19K</named-entity> are unable to associate with <named-entity id="named-entity-214">HLA-E</named-entity> (data not shown). <named-entity id="named-entity-215">HLA-E</named-entity> carries Glu183 and Gly207, and in the context of the structure of free <named-entity id="named-entity-216">HLA-E</named-entity>*0103 (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">3BZE</accession>), both of these residues also cannot mediate interactions shown at site 3. This lends further support to the idea that MHC residues Glu183 and Gly207 modulate the inability of <named-entity id="named-entity-217">E3-19K</named-entity> to associate with <named-entity id="named-entity-218">HLA-C</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-219">HLA-E</named-entity>.</p>
<p>Because of the effects that <named-entity id="named-entity-220">E3-19K</named-entity> has on suppressing the expression of the MHC I homologs <named-entity id="named-entity-221">MICA</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-222">MICB</named-entity> on adenovirus-infected cells<bibr rid="b43"/>, it is presumed that <named-entity id="named-entity-223">E3-19K</named-entity> binds to <named-entity id="named-entity-224">MICA</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-225">MICB</named-entity> and that <named-entity id="named-entity-226">E3-19K</named-entity> residues Thr14 and Met82 play a part in this interaction<bibr rid="b27"/>. We have mapped the position of the side chains of Thr14 and Met82 in the structure of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-227">E3-19K</named-entity> (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). The implication of this analysis is that <named-entity id="named-entity-228">E3-19K</named-entity> likely uses a different surface to sequester <named-entity id="named-entity-229">MICA</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-230">MICB</named-entity> from its MHC I binding surface (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). Furthermore, that mutation of Thr14 and Met82 in Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-231">E3-19K</named-entity> had essentially no effect on the MHC I binding function of <named-entity id="named-entity-232">E3-19K</named-entity><bibr rid="b27"/> is entirely consistent with our structure (<figr rid="f1">Figs. 1</figr> and <figr rid="f4">4</figr>).</p>
<p>In conclusion, the structure of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-233">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-234">HLA-A2</named-entity> represents an example of coevolution between a viral immunomodulatory protein and its host MHC I ligand. Our studies provide structural explanations for how <named-entity id="named-entity-235">E3-19K</named-entity> achieves promiscuous and high-affinity binding to <named-entity id="named-entity-236">HLA-A</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-237">HLA-B</named-entity> and give insights into its inability to engage with <named-entity id="named-entity-238">HLA-C</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-239">HLA-E</named-entity>. Notably, a comparison of our structure with that of <named-entity id="named-entity-240">US2</named-entity> immunomodulatory protein from human cytomegalovirus bound to <named-entity id="named-entity-241">HLA-A2</named-entity> (ref. <bibrinl rid="b44">44</bibrinl>) shows that both proteins have common contact residues on <named-entity id="named-entity-242">HLA-A2</named-entity> at site 3 (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). This has implications for understanding the molecular basis of co-infection of the same host cell by two different persistent viruses.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle><anchor id="an1"/>Methods</sectitle>
<online-methods>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Cloning and protein expression.</sectitle>
<p>The cDNA encoding the ER-lumenal domain (residues 1&#x2013;100) of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-243">E3-19K</named-entity> (referred to as <named-entity id="named-entity-244">E3-19K</named-entity>) was generated by polymerase chain reaction. This was carried out using the plasmid <i>pBS-Ad2E3-19K</i> (gift from H.-G. Burgert, University of Warwick, Coventry, UK) containing the cDNA of full-length Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-245">E3-19K</named-entity> as a template and the appropriate forward and reverse primers. The amplified cDNA was ligated into the PLM1 vector (gift from D.C. Wiley, deceased) by using the BamH1 and EcoR1 restriction sites. Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-246">E3-19K</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-247">HLA-A2</named-entity> heavy chain (residues 1&#x2013;275) and <named-entity id="named-entity-248">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> (residues 0&#x2013;99) were expressed in the <i>Escherichia coli</i> strain BL21(DE3)pLysS (Stratagene) as inclusion bodies. Inclusion bodies were isolated, purified from cell pellets and solubilized as described previously<bibr rid="b46"/>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Assembly of <named-entity id="named-entity-249">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-250">Tax</named-entity> and Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-251">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-252">HLA-A2</named-entity>.</sectitle>
<p><named-entity id="named-entity-253">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-254">Tax</named-entity> was reconstituted <i>in vitro</i> from the <named-entity id="named-entity-255">urea</named-entity>-solubilized inclusion bodies of <named-entity id="named-entity-256">HLA-A2</named-entity> heavy chain (1 &#x3BC;M) and <named-entity id="named-entity-257">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> (2 &#x3BC;M) in the presence of the <named-entity id="named-entity-258">Tax</named-entity> peptide (LLFGYPVYV) (10 &#x3BC;M) in an oxidative refolding buffer<bibr rid="b46"/>. Stock solutions of purified <named-entity id="named-entity-259">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-260">Tax</named-entity> (10&#x2013;30 mg ml<super>&#x2212;1</super>) in 20 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-261">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 150 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-262">NaCl</named-entity> were kept at &#x2013;80 &#xB0;C. The Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-263">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-264">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex was assembled by using a modified version of this approach. The <named-entity id="named-entity-265">urea</named-entity>-solubilized inclusion bodies of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-266">E3-19K</named-entity> were added at 4 &#xB0;C, under rapid stirring, to a final concentration of 1 &#x3BC;M to an oxidative refolding buffer consisting of 50 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-267">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 8.0, 1 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-268">EDTA</named-entity>, 400 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-269"><sc>L</sc>-arginine</named-entity>, 5 mM reduced <named-entity id="named-entity-270">glutathione</named-entity>, 0.5 mM oxidized <named-entity id="named-entity-271">glutathione</named-entity>, 1 &#x3BC;M <named-entity id="named-entity-272">phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride</named-entity> and submolar amounts (0.2 &#x3BC;M) of refolded, purified <named-entity id="named-entity-273">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-274">Tax</named-entity>. The presence of refolded <named-entity id="named-entity-275">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-276">Tax</named-entity> in the buffer of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-277">E3-19K</named-entity> was absolutely essential for formation of the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-278">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-279">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex. The refolding mixture was incubated at 4 &#xB0;C. After 24 h, the mixture was concentrated in an Amicon stirred cell and then purified on a Superdex 200 HR 10-30 column in 20 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-280">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-281">NaCl</named-entity>. The purified Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-282">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-283">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex generated from this rescue refolding strategy was characterized by SDS-PAGE and native PAGE. Stock solutions of purified Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-284">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-285">HLA-A2</named-entity> (20&#x2013;40 mg ml<super>&#x2212;1</super>) in 20 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-286">Tris-HCl</named-entity>, pH 7.5, 100 mM <named-entity id="named-entity-287">NaCl</named-entity> were kept at &#x2013;80 &#xB0;C. The rescue refolding strategy described here is applicable to other complexes involving recalcitrant proteins such as Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-288">E3-19K</named-entity>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Crystallization and data collection.</sectitle>
<p>Crystallization conditions of the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-289">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-290">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex were searched with the aid of a Tecan Freedom EVO 200 robot using sitting drops. Complex solution (1 &#x3BC;l, 10 mg ml<super>&#x2212;1</super>) was dispensed into each well of a Corning 96-well plate, mixed with an identical volume of precipitant solution and equilibrated against 100 &#x3BC;l of reservoir solution. The plates were incubated at 17 &#xB0;C. The initial crystallization condition was found by using Crystal Screen Index (Hampton Research) as solution no. 22, 0.8 M <named-entity id="named-entity-291">succinic acid</named-entity>, pH 7.0. Optimization of the crystallization condition was carried out by using the Additive Screen (Hampton Research) and the hanging-drop vapor-diffusion method. Crystals used for data collection were grown by mixing 2 &#x3BC;l of 10 mg ml<super>&#x2212;1</super> protein complex solution with 2 &#x3BC;l of 0.8 M <named-entity id="named-entity-292">succinic acid</named-entity>, pH 7.0, and 0.2 &#x3BC;l of 0.1 M <named-entity id="named-entity-293">calcium chloride dihydrate</named-entity> as additive. Crystals grew over 20 d to dimensions of ~400 &#xD7; 200 &#xD7; 100 &#x3BC;m. Prior to data collection, the crystals were soaked for about 1&#x2013;2 min in mineral oil (Sigma) as the cryoprotectant and then flash frozen in liquid nitrogen. X-ray diffraction data for the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-294">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-295">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex was collected to 1.95-&#xC5; resolution with a MAR-225 CCD detector at SER-CAT beamline 22-BM-D of the Advanced Photon Source (Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Illinois). The space group was determined to be <i>I</i>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub> (<i>a</i> = 113.19 &#xC5;, <i>b</i> = 133.67 &#xC5;, <i>c</i> = 196.72 &#xC5;). Data were processed and scaled with the HKL-2000 program package<bibr rid="b47"/>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="2">
<sectitle>Structure determination and refinement.</sectitle>
<p>The structure of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-296">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-297">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex was determined by molecular replacement in AMoRe<bibr rid="b48"/> by using free <named-entity id="named-entity-298">HLA-A2</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-299">Tax</named-entity> (PDB <accession type="pdb" status="secondary">1HHK</accession>) as a search model. Two solutions were identified for both the rotation and translation functions, corresponding to two molecules of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-300">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-301">HLA-A2</named-entity> in the asymmetric unit. After molecular replacement, the electron density maps were calculated, initial refinements were examined manually and residues with a poor fit to the electron density map were omitted from the model. The electron density improved with use of the DM program from the CCP4 package<bibr rid="b49"/>. Subsequent model rebuilding was carried out in Coot<bibr rid="b50"/>. The extended model was then refined using simulated annealing, energy minimization and restrained individual B factor in CNS<bibr rid="b51"/>. In the first refinement cycles, noncrystallographic symmetry (NCS) restraints were applied to the main chain atoms (loops excluded), using data to 3.0 &#xC5;, resulting in <i>R</i><sub>free</sub> and <i>R</i><sub>work</sub> values of 0.43 and 0.39, respectively. In the final refinement cycles, NCS restraints were released, and a composite omit map was calculated to eliminate model bias. Water molecules were added by using the CNS program<bibr rid="b51"/> and were checked with the <i>F</i><sub>o</sub> &#x2013; <i>F</i><sub>c</sub> electron density map (&gt;3&#x3C3;) at 3.5 &#xC5; or less from hydrogen bond donors or acceptors. A total of 472 water molecules were added to the model. Throughout refinement, agreement between the model and the observed data was monitored by calculating <i>R</i><sub>free</sub> on the basis of 10% of the reflections. The final <i>R</i><sub>work</sub> and <i>R</i><sub>free</sub> values (with a bulk solvent correction) are 21.0% and 24.1%, respectively, for all reflections between 37.06 and 1.95 &#xC5; (<tablr rid="t1">Table 1</tablr>). In the final model, the structural geometry was checked by using PROCHECK<bibr rid="b52"/>. All backbone <i>&#x3C6;</i>&#x2212;<i>&#x3C8;</i> torsion angles of the model were within allowed regions of the Ramachandran plot. Because of poor quality or missing electron density, the final model lacks residue 1 of chain G and residues 1, 99 and 100 of chain H. Buried surface areas were calculated with the program AreaIMol in the CCP4 package, using a probe radius of 1.4 &#xC5;. All structural figures were prepared using PyMOL (<url>http://www.pymol.org</url>)<super>53</super>.</p>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Accession codes.</sectitle>
<p>The atomic coordinates and structure factors of the Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-302">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-303">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex have been deposited in the PDB with ID code <accession type="pdb" status="primary">4E5X</accession>.</p></sec>
</online-methods>
</sec>
<sec level="1">
<sectitle>Author contributions</sectitle>
<p>L.L., crystallographic and biochemical studies and manuscript preparation; Y.M., biochemical studies; M.B., project supervisor and manuscript preparation and principal manuscript author.</p></sec></bdy>
<bm>
<objects>
<fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
<figtl>The structure of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-306">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-307">HLA-A2</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>(<b>a</b>) Ribbon representation of the structure of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-308">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-309">HLA-A2</named-entity>. <named-entity id="named-entity-310">E3-19K</named-entity>, cyan; heavy chain (&#x3B1;1, &#x3B1;2 and &#x3B1;3 domains), yellow; <named-entity id="named-entity-311">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity>, green; HTLV-1 <named-entity id="named-entity-312">Tax</named-entity> (LLFGYPVYV) peptide, orange; disulfide bond, magenta. The N and C termini of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-313">E3-19K</named-entity> are labeled. (<b>b</b>) Ribbon representation of the structure of ligand-bound Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-314">E3-19K</named-entity> (top) and its topology diagram (below). The N-terminal domain (residues 1&#x2013;78), &#x3B1;-helix (residues 79&#x2013;93) and tail (residues 94&#x2013;100) are indicated. The disulfide bonds are shown in magenta. The &#x3B2; strands A, B, C, C&#x2032;, E, F and G and the N (residue 1) and C (residue 100) termini are labeled. The &#x3B2; strands are represented by arrows, and the &#x3B1;-helix is shown as a cylinder. The two disulfide bonds are indicated by dashed lines. (<b>c</b>) Hydrophobic core of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-315">E3-19K</named-entity>. Ribbon representation of the structure of ligand-bound Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-316">E3-19K</named-entity> showing the side chain of the core-forming residues (magenta) (some side chains are labeled for clarity). Core-forming residues (&gt;90% buried) were determined by using SPDBV<bibr rid="b45"/>. The &#x3B2; strands A, B, C, C&#x2032;, E, F and G, and N and C termini are labeled.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
<figtl>Interaction surface between Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-317">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-318">HLA-A2</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>Interaction sites 1, 2, 3 and 4 of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-319">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-320">HLA-A2</named-entity> are shown in separate panels, using the same color code as in <figr rid="f1">Figure 1a</figr>. Nitrogen, oxygen and sulfur atoms are colored blue, red and light orange, respectively. Hydrogen bonds (distance &#x2264;3.5 &#xC5;) and salt bridges are indicated by dashed green lines; hydrophobic contacts (distance &lt;4.0 &#xC5;) are represented by dashed magenta lines. Water molecules are shown as red spheres. The &#x3B2; strands of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-321">E3-19K</named-entity> and &#x3B1;1, &#x3B1;2 and &#x3B1;3 domains of the heavy chain are labeled. Arg48-O and Ile43-O denote interactions involving the backbone oxygen atoms of these residues.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
<figtl>Electrostatic properties of interacting surfaces in Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-322">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-323">HLA-A2</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>Electrostatic surfaces of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-324">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-325">HLA-A2</named-entity> at interaction sites 1, 2, 3 and 4 (marked by dashed lines), shown as electronegative (red, &#x2013;1.000 <i>k</i>T<i>e</i><super>&#x2212;1</super>), electropositive (blue, +1.000 <i>k</i>T<i>e</i><super>&#x2212;1</super>) and apolar (white). Conserved contact residues in Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-326">E3-19K</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-327">HLA-A2</named-entity> at site 1 (Lys27 and Glu53, respectively) and site 2 (Lys42 and Glu177, respectively) that form salt bridges are labeled. The &#x3B1;1, &#x3B1;2 and &#x3B1;3 domains of the heavy chain and <named-entity id="named-entity-328">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> are labeled.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
<figtl>Conserved residues in Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-329">E3-19K</named-entity>.</figtl>
<caption><p>Strictly (blue) and highly (cyan) conserved residues are mapped on the structure of Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-330">E3-19K</named-entity>. The side chains of strictly and highly conserved residues at sites 1 (Glu18, Leu25, Lys27), 2 (Glu18, Lys42), 3 (Leu95) and 4 (Met89, Gln92, Tyr93) are indicated; nitrogen, oxygen and sulfur atoms are colored blue, red and light orange, respectively. The positions of Thr14 and Met82 side chains, which are important for <named-entity id="named-entity-331">MICA</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-332">MICB</named-entity> interaction<bibr rid="b27"/>, are indicated by dashed arrows. The &#x3B2; strands A, B, C, C&#x2032;, E, F and G and the N and C termini are labeled.</p></caption></fig>
<fig id="f5" type="bmp" entname="figf5">
<figtl>Amino acid sequence alignment at the four interaction sites.</figtl>
<caption><p>Alignment of <named-entity id="named-entity-333">HLA-A2</named-entity> and consensus <named-entity id="named-entity-334">HLA-A</named-entity>, <named-entity id="named-entity-335">HLA-B</named-entity> and <named-entity id="named-entity-336">HLA-C</named-entity> heavy chain sequences at sites 1, 2 and 3. Interaction site 4 on <named-entity id="named-entity-337">&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub>m</named-entity> is also indicated. Capital letters designate contact residues at each of the four sites (indicated in legend of <figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). Consensus sequences were obtained from the IMGT-HLA Sequence Database (<url>http://www.ebi.ac.uk/imgt/hla/align.html</url>).</p></caption></fig>
<table id="t1" tocentry="0" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0" orient="port" pgwide="0" tabcols="2">
<title>Data collection and refinement statistics</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="center">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<spanspec namest="1" nameend="2" spanname="1to2"/>
<thead valign="top">
<row rowsep="1"><entry/>
<entry align="center">Ad2 <named-entity id="named-entity-304">E3-19K</named-entity>&#x2013;<named-entity id="named-entity-305">HLA-A2</named-entity> complex</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody valign="top">
<row><entry><b>Data collection</b><fnr rid="t1-fn1"><super>a</super></fnr></entry>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>Space group</entry>
<entry align="center"><i>I</i>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub></entry></row>
<row><entry>Cell dimensions</entry>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;<i>a</i>, <i>b</i>, <i>c</i> (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">113.19, 133.67, 196.72</entry></row>
<row><entry>Resolution (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">50.00&#x2013;1.95 (2.02&#x2013;1.95)<fnr rid="t1-fn2"><super>b</super></fnr></entry></row>
<row><entry><i>R</i><sub>merge</sub></entry>
<entry align="center">0.148 (0.540)</entry></row>
<row><entry><i>I</i> / &#x3C3;<i>I</i></entry>
<entry align="center">15.97 (3.20)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Completeness (%)</entry>
<entry align="center">99.7 (97.4)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Redundancy</entry>
<entry align="center">11.0 (7.1)</entry></row>
<row><entry><b>Refinement</b></entry>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>Resolution (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">37.06&#x2013;1.95</entry></row>
<row><entry>No. reflections</entry>
<entry align="center">102,933</entry></row>
<row><entry><i>R</i><sub>work</sub> / <i>R</i><sub>free</sub></entry>
<entry align="center">0.210 / 0.241</entry></row>
<row><entry>No. atoms</entry>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Protein</entry>
<entry align="center">7,968</entry></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Water</entry>
<entry align="center">472</entry></row>
<row><entry><i>B</i> factors</entry>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Protein</entry>
<entry align="center">35.6</entry></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Water</entry>
<entry align="center">34.4</entry></row>
<row><entry>R.m.s. deviations</entry>
<entry/></row>
<row><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Bond lengths (&#xC5;)</entry>
<entry align="center">0.006</entry></row>
<row rowsep="1"><entry>&#x2003;&#x2003;Bond angles (&#xB0;)</entry>
<entry align="center">1.3</entry></row>
<row>
<entry spanname="1to2" align="left"><fn id="t1-fn1" type="footnote"><p><super>a</super>Data were collected from a single crystal.</p></fn></entry></row>
<row>
<entry spanname="1to2" align="left"><fn id="t1-fn2" type="footnote"><p><super>b</super>Values in parentheses are for highest-resolution shell.</p></fn></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>
</objects>
<ack><p>This work was supported, in whole or in part, by the US National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases grants R01 AI045070 and R56 AI102468 (to M.B.). We thank B. Santarsiero for help with X-ray data collection. Technical support by L. Qian for cell culture and protein purification is also acknowledged.</p></ack>
<audecl conflct="no"/>
<bibl><bib id="b1"><reftxt><refau><snm>Berk</snm>, <fnm>A.J.</fnm></refau> <atl>Adenoviruses. in</atl> <jtl>Fields Virology</jtl> 5th edn. (eds. Knipe, D.M., Howley, P.M., Griffin, D.E. &amp; Lamb, R.A.) <ppf>2395</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2436</ppl> (Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, <cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b2"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wold</snm>, <fnm>W.S.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Horwitz</snm>, <fnm>M.S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Adenoviridae: the viruses and their replication</atl>. in <jtl>Fields Virology</jtl>, 5th edn. (eds. Knipe, D.M., Howley, P.M., Griffin, D.E. &amp; Lamb, R.A.) <ppf>2355</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2394</ppl> (Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins, <cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b3"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hansen</snm>, <fnm>T.H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bouvier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>MHC class I antigen presentation: learning from viral evasion strategies</atl>. <jtl>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>503</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>513</ppl> (<cd year="2009">2009</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b4"><reftxt><refau><snm>Burgert</snm>, <fnm>H.-G.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Subversion of host defense mechanisms by adenoviruses</atl>. in <jtl>Viral Proteins Counteracting Host Defenses</jtl> (eds. Koszinowski, U.H. &amp; Hengel, H.) 273&#x2013;318 (Springer, 2002).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b5"><reftxt><refau><snm>Andersson</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Paabo</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Nilsson</snm>, <fnm>T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Peterson</snm>, <fnm>P.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Impaired intracellular transport of class I MHC antigens as a possible means for adenoviruses to evade immune surveillance</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>43</vid>, <ppf>215</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>222</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b6"><reftxt><refau><snm>Andersson</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>McMichael</snm>, <fnm>A.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Peterson</snm>, <fnm>P.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Reduced allorecognition of adenovirus-2 infected cells</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>138</vid>, <ppf>3960</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3966</ppl> (<cd year="1987">1987</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b7"><reftxt><refau><snm>Burgert</snm>, <fnm>H.G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kvist</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>An adenovirus type 2 glycoprotein blocks cell surface expression of human histocompatibility class I antigens</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>41</vid>, <ppf>987</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>997</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b8"><reftxt><refau><snm>Burgert</snm>, <fnm>H.-G.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kvist</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>The E3/19K protein of adenovirus type 2 binds to the domains of histocompatibility antigens required for CTL recognition</atl>. <jtl>EMBO J.</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>2019</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2026</ppl> (<cd year="1987">1987</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b9"><reftxt><refau><snm>Flomenberg</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Piaskowski</snm>, <fnm>V.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Truitt</snm>, <fnm>R.L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Casper</snm>, <fnm>J.T.</fnm></refau> <atl>Human adenovirus-specific CD8+ T-cell responses are not inhibited by E3&#x2013;19K in the presence of gamma interferon</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>70</vid>, <ppf>6314</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>6322</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b10"><reftxt><refau><snm>Rawle</snm>, <fnm>F.C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tollefson</snm>, <fnm>A.E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wold</snm>, <fnm>W.S.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gooding</snm>, <fnm>L.R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Mouse anti-adenovirus cytoxic T lymphocytes</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>143</vid>, <ppf>2031</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2037</ppl> (<cd year="1989">1989</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b11"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ginsberg</snm>, <fnm>H.S.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Role of early region 3 (E3) in pathogenesis of Adenovirus disease</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>86</vid>, <ppf>3823</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3827</ppl> (<cd year="1989">1989</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b12"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wold</snm>, <fnm>W.S.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Gooding</snm>, <fnm>L.R.</fnm></refau> <atl>Adenovirus regions E3 proteins that prevent cytolysis by cytotoxic T cells and tumor necrosis factor</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Biol. Med.</jtl> <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>433</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>452</ppl> (<cd year="1989">1989</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b13"><reftxt><refau><snm>Feuerbach</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Identification of amino acids within the MHC molecule important for the interaction with the adenovirus protein E3/19K</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>153</vid>, <ppf>1626</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1636</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b14"><reftxt><refau><snm>Flomenberg</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gutierrez</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Hogan</snm>, <fnm>K.T.</fnm></refau> <atl>Identification of class I MHC regions which bind to the adenovirus E3&#x2013;19K protein</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>31</vid>, <ppf>1277</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1284</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b15"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gabathuler</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Levy</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kvist</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau> <atl>Requirement for the association of adenovirus type 2 E3&#x2013;19K wild-type and mutant proteins with HLA antigens</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>64</vid>, <ppf>3679</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3685</ppl> (<cd year="1990">1990</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b16"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hermiston</snm>, <fnm>T.W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tripp</snm>, <fnm>R.A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sparer</snm>, <fnm>R.A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gooding</snm>, <fnm>L.R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wold</snm>, <fnm>W.S.M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Deletion mutation analysis of the adenovirus type 2 E3-gp19K protein: identification of sequences within the endoplasmic reticulum lumenal domain that are required for class I antigen binding and protection from adenovirus-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>5289</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5298</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b17"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cox</snm>, <fnm>J.H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bennink</snm>, <fnm>J.R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Yewdell</snm>, <fnm>J.W.</fnm></refau> <atl>Retention of adenovirus E19 glycoprotein in the endoplasmic reticulum is essential to its ability to block antigen presentation</atl>. <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl> <vid>174</vid>, <ppf>1629</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1637</ppl> (<cd year="1991">1991</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b18"><reftxt><refau><snm>P&#xE4;&#xE4;bo</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bhat</snm>, <fnm>B.M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wold</snm>, <fnm>W.S.M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Peterson</snm>, <fnm>P.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>A short sequence in the COOH-terminus makes an adenovirus membrane glycoprotein a resident of the endoplasmic reticulum</atl>. <jtl>Cell</jtl> <vid>50</vid>, <ppf>311</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>317</ppl> (<cd year="1987">1987</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b19"><reftxt><refau><snm>Severinsson</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Martens</snm>, <fnm>I.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Peterson</snm>, <fnm>P.A.</fnm></refau> <atl>Differential association between two human MHC class I antigens and an adenoviral glycoprotein</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>137</vid>, <ppf>1003</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1009</ppl> (<cd year="1986">1986</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b20"><reftxt><refau><snm>Deryckere</snm>, <fnm>F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Burgert</snm>, <fnm>H.-G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Early region 3 of adenovirus type 19 (subgroup D) encodes an HLA-binding protein distinct from that of subgroups B and C</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>70</vid>, <ppf>2832</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2841</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b21"><reftxt><refau><snm>K&#xF6;rner</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Burgert</snm>, <fnm>H.-G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Down-regulation of HLA antigens by the adenovirus type 2 E3/19K protein in a T-lymphoma cell line</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>1442</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1448</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b22"><reftxt><refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fu</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bouvier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Allele- and locus-specific recognition of class I MHC molecules by the immunomodulatory E3&#x2013;19K protein from adenovirus</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>178</vid>, <ppf>4567</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>4575</ppl> (<cd year="2007">2007</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b23"><reftxt><refau><snm>Fu</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Li</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bouvier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Adenovirus E3&#x2013;19K proteins of different serotypes and subgroups have similar, yet distinct, immunomodulatory functions towards major histocompatibility class I molecules</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>286</vid>, <ppf>17631</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>17639</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b24"><reftxt><refau><snm>Hermiston</snm>, <fnm>T.W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tripp</snm>, <fnm>R.A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sparer</snm>, <fnm>R.A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gooding</snm>, <fnm>L.R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wold</snm>, <fnm>W.S.M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Deletion mutation analysis of the adenovirus type 2 E3-gp19K protein: identification of sequences within the endoplasmic reticulum lumenal domain that are required for class I antigen binding and protection from adenovirus-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>67</vid>, <ppf>5289</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5298</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b25"><reftxt><refau><snm>Flomenberg</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Szmulewicz</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Gutierrez</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Lupatkin</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau> <atl>Role of the adenovirus E3&#x2013;19K conserved region in binding major histocompatibility complex class I molecules</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>66</vid>, <ppf>4778</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>4783</ppl> (<cd year="1992">1992</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b26"><reftxt><refau><snm>Chatterjee</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Maizel</snm>, <fnm>J.V.</fnm></refau> <atl>Homology of adenoviral E3 glycoprotein with HLA-DR heavy chain</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>81</vid>, <ppf>6039</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>6043</ppl> (<cd year="1984">1984</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b27"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sester</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Conserved amino acids within the adenovirus 2 E3/19K protein differentially affect downregulation of MHC class I and MICA/B proteins</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>184</vid>, <ppf>255</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>267</ppl> (<cd year="2010">2010</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b28"><reftxt><refau><snm>Menz</snm>, <fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Sester</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Koebernick</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Schmid</snm>, <fnm>R.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Burgert</snm>, <fnm>H.-G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Structural analysis of the adenovirus type 2 E3-/19K protein using mutagenesis and a panel of conformation-sensitive monoclonal antibodies</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>46</vid>, <ppf>16</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>26</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b29"><reftxt><refau><snm>Fu</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bouvier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Determinants of the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) lumenal-domain of the Adenovirus serotype 2 E3&#x2013;19K protein for association with and ER-retention of major histocompatibility complex class I molecules</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>48</vid>, <ppf>532</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>538</ppl> (<cd year="2011">2011</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b30"><reftxt><refau><snm>Wold</snm>, <fnm>W.S.M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cladaras</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Deutscher</snm>, <fnm>S.L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Kapoor</snm>, <fnm>Q.S.</fnm></refau> <atl>The 19-kDa glycoprotein coded by region E3 of adenovirus. Purification, characterization, and structural analysis</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>260</vid>, <ppf>2424</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2431</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b31"><reftxt><refau><snm>Liu</snm>, <fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Stafford</snm>, <fnm>W.F.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Bouvier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>The endoplasmic reticulum lumenal domain of the adenovirus type 2 E3&#x2013;19K binds to peptide-filled and peptide-deficient HLA-A*1101 molecules</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>79</vid>, <ppf>13317</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>13325</ppl> (<cd year="2005">2005</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b32"><reftxt><refau><snm>Sester</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Burgert</snm>, <fnm>H.-G.</fnm></refau> <atl>Conserved cysteine residues within the E3/19K protein of adenovirus type 2 are essential for binding to major histocompatibility complex antigens</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>68</vid>, <ppf>5423</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5432</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b33"><reftxt><refau><snm>Holm</snm>, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Sander</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau> <atl>Touring protein fold space with Dali/FSSP. Nucleic Acids Res</atl>. <vid>26</vid>, <ppf>316</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>319</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b34"><reftxt><refau><snm>Krissinel</snm>, <fnm>E.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Henrick</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Secondary-structure matching (SSM), a new tool for fast protein structure alignment in three-dimension</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>60</vid>, <ppf>2256</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2268</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b35"><reftxt><refau><snm>Lawrence</snm>, <fnm>M.C.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Colman</snm>, <fnm>P.M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Shape complementarity at protein/protein interfaces</atl>. <jtl>J. Mol. Biol.</jtl> <vid>234</vid>, <ppf>946</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>950</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b36"><reftxt><refau><snm>Bouvier</snm>, <fnm>M.</fnm></refau> <atl>Accessory proteins and the assembly of human class I MHC molecules. A molecular and structural perspective</atl>. <jtl>Mol. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>39</vid>, <ppf>697</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>706</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b37"><reftxt><refau><snm>Yu</snm>, <fnm>Y.Y.L.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Definition and transfer of a serological epitope specific for peptide-empty forms of MHC class I</atl>. <jtl>Int. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>1897</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1906</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b38"><reftxt><refau><snm>Morris</snm>, <fnm>C.R.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The amyloid precursor-like protein 2 and the adenoviral E3/19K protein both bind to a conformational site on H-2Kd and regulate H-2Kd expression</atl>. <jtl>J. Biol. Chem.</jtl> <vid>278</vid>, <ppf>12618</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>12623</ppl> (<cd year="2003">2003</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b39"><reftxt><refau><snm>Mage</snm>, <fnm>M.G.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The peptide-receptive transition state of MHC class I molecules: insight from structure and molecular dynamics</atl>. <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl> <vid>189</vid>, <ppf>1391</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>1399</ppl> (<cd year="2012">2012</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b40"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gewurz</snm>, <fnm>B.E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>E.W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Tortorella</snm>, <fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Schust</snm>, <fnm>D.J.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Ploegh</snm>, <fnm>H.L.</fnm></refau> <atl>Human cytomegalovirus US2 endoplasmic reticulum-lumenal domain dictates association with major histocompatibility complex class I in a locus-specific manner</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>75</vid>, <ppf>5197</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5204</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b41"><reftxt><refau><snm>Ishido</snm>, <fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wang</snm>, <fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lee</snm>, <fnm>B.-S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Cohen</snm>, <fnm>G.B.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Jung</snm>, <fnm>J.U.</fnm></refau> <atl>Downregulation of major histocompatibility complex class I molecules by Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus K3 and K5 proteins</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>74</vid>, <ppf>5300</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>5309</ppl> (<cd year="2000">2000</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b42"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cohen</snm>, <fnm>G.B.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>The selective downregulation of class I major histocompatibility complex proteins by HIV-1 protects HIV-infected cells from NK cells</atl>. <jtl>Immunity</jtl> <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>661</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>671</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b43"><reftxt><refau><snm>McSharry</snm>, <fnm>B.P.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Adenovirus E3/19K promotes evasion of NK cell recognition by intracellular sequestration of the NKG2D ligands major histocompatibility complex class I chain-related proteins A and B</atl>. <jtl>J. Virol.</jtl> <vid>82</vid>, <ppf>4585</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>4594</ppl> (<cd year="2008">2008</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b44"><reftxt><refau><snm>Gewurz</snm>, <fnm>B.E.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Antigen presentation subverted: structure of the human cytomegalovirus protein US2 bound to the class I molecule HLA-A2</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>98</vid>, <ppf>6794</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>6799</ppl> (<cd year="2001">2001</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b45"><reftxt><refau><snm>Guex</snm>, <fnm>N.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Peitsch</snm>, <fnm>M.C.</fnm></refau> <atl>SWISS-MODEL and the Swiss-PdbViewer: An environment for comparative protein modeling</atl>. <jtl>Electrophoresis</jtl> <vid>18</vid>, <ppf>2714</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2723</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b46"><reftxt><refau><snm>Garboczi</snm>, <fnm>D.N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hung</snm>, <fnm>D.T.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Wiley</snm>, <fnm>D.C.</fnm></refau> <atl>HLA-A2-peptide complexes: refolding and crystallization of molecules expressed in <i>Escherichia coli</i> and complexed with single antigenic peptides</atl>. <jtl>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> <vid>89</vid>, <ppf>3429</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>3433</ppl> (<cd year="1992">1992</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b47"><reftxt><refau><snm>Otwinowski</snm>, <fnm>Z.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Minor</snm>, <fnm>W.</fnm></refau> <atl>Processing of X-ray diffraction data collected in oscillation mode</atl>. <jtl>Methods Enzymol.</jtl> <vid>276</vid>, <ppf>307</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>326</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b48"><reftxt><refau><snm>Navaza</snm>, <fnm>J.</fnm></refau> <atl>AMoRe: an automated package for molecular replacement</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. A</jtl> <vid>50</vid>, <ppf>157</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>163</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b49"><reftxt><refau><snm>Cowtan</snm>, <fnm>K.D.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Main</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> <atl>Improvement of macromolecular electron-density maps by the simultaneous application of real and reciprocal space constraints</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>49</vid>, <ppf>148</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>157</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b50"><reftxt><refau><snm>Emsley</snm>, <fnm>P.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Cowtan</snm>, <fnm>K.</fnm></refau> <atl>Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>60</vid>, <ppf>2126</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>2132</ppl> (<cd year="2004">2004</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b51"><reftxt><refau><snm>Br&#xFC;nger</snm>, <fnm>A.T.</fnm></refau> <i>et al</i>. <atl>Crystallography &amp; NMR system: a new software suite for macromolecular structure determination</atl>. <jtl>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>54</vid>, <ppf>905</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>921</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
<bib id="b52"><reftxt><refau><snm>Laskowski</snm>, <fnm>R.A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>MacArthur</snm>, <fnm>M.W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Moss</snm>, <fnm>D.S.</fnm></refau> &amp; <refau><snm>Thornton</snm>, <fnm>J.M.</fnm></refau> <atl>PROCHECK: a program to check the stereochemical quality of protein structures</atl>. <jtl>J. Appl. Crystallogr.</jtl> <vid>26</vid>, <ppf>283</ppf>&#x2013;<ppl>291</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt></bib>
</bibl></bm></article>
