<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article id="35005508" language="eng" publish="issue" relation="no" origsrc="yes">
  <!--402d006A0-->
  <suppfm supptype="reprint">
    <suppmast>
      <jtl>Nature</jtl>
      <suppttl>Immunology</suppttl>
      <vol>402</vol>
      <iss>6763supp</iss>
      <idt>19991216</idt>
    </suppmast>
    <parent>
      <jtl>Nature</jtl>
      <vol>402</vol>
      <iss>6763</iss>
      <idt>19991216</idt>
      <issn type="print">0028-0836</issn>
      <cpg>
        <cpy>1999</cpy>
        <cpn>Macmillan Magazines Ltd.</cpn>
      </cpg>
    </parent>
    <sponsor type="com">BIOGEN</sponsor>
    <categ id="rv"/>
    <pp>
      <spn>6</spn>
      <epn>13</epn>
      <cnt>8</cnt>
    </pp>
  </suppfm>
  <fm>
    <atl>Selecting and maintaining a diverse T-cell repertoire</atl>
    <aug>
      <au>
        <fnm>Ananda W.</fnm>
        <snm>Goldrath</snm>
        <inits>A W</inits>
      </au>
      <cau>
        <fnm>Michael J.</fnm>
        <snm>Bevan</snm>
        <inits>M J</inits>
        <corf rid="c1"/>
      </cau>
      <aff><org>Department of Immunology and Howard Hughes Medical Institute, University of
          Washington</org>, <cty>Seattle</cty>, <st>Washington</st>
        <zip>98195</zip>, <cny> USA</cny></aff>
      <caff><coid id="c1"/>Correspondence should be addressed to M.J.B. (e-mail: <email>
          mbevan@u.washington.edu</email>).<newline/><newline/></caff>
    </aug>
    <abs>
      <p>To provide a T-cell population that will respond promptly to foreign antigen, the immune
        system looks inward, using the variety of self-antigens to select and maintain a diverse
        repertoire of receptors. A protective immune system must include a T-lymphocyte population
        that is poised to respond to foreign antigenic peptides presented by self-major
        histocompatibility complex molecules. As the organism cannot predict the precise
        pathogen-derived antigens that will be encountered, the system uses the diverse array of
        self-peptides bound to self-major histocompatibility complex molecules, not only to select a
        receptor repertoire in the thymus, but also to keep nainodot; uml;ve T cells alive and
        lsquo;ready for actionrsquo; in the periphery.</p>
    </abs>
  </fm>
  <bdy>
    <p>Originally published as <cite id="n1"><jtl>Nature</jtl>
        <vid>402</vid>, <ppf> 255</ppf>ndash;<ppl>262</ppl>; <cd year="1999">1999</cd></cite></p>
    <p>The revelation that T lymphocytes recognize foreign antigen only when presented by major
      histocompatibility complex (MHC) molecules was made 25 years ago and remains the cornerstone
      of our understanding of cellular immunity<bibr rid="b1"/>. The nature of antigen presentation
      was unknown for more than a decade until it became clear that foreign antigen has to be
      processed into peptides that can bind stably to the groove of an MHC molecule to allow
      recognition by the T-cell receptor (TCR)<bibr rid="b2 b3"/>. MHC genes are extremely
      polymorphic and the various allelic products bind a broad spectrum of different peptides,
      explaining MHC restriction of T-cell recognition. During T-cell development, immature T cells
      are chosen to mature on the basis of the ability of their clonally expressed TCR to interact
      weakly with self-MHC molecules expressed in the thymus. During this process of positive
      selection, self-peptides bound in the MHC groove are also recognized. Thus, the selection of
      the TCR repertoire is not based solely on the recognition of one or a few self-MHC structures,
      but on the recognition of those structures modified by the binding of an enormous diversity of
      self-peptides. Low-affinity interactions between the newly expressed TCRs and
      self-peptidendash;MHC molecules select a diverse repertoire that will be fine-tuned to react
      strongly to pathogen-derived peptides bound to the same MHC in the periphery. Even after
      maturing and leaving the thymus, T cells continue to depend on survival signals transmitted by
      the interaction of the TCR with self-peptidendash;MHC complexes. The long-term homeostasis of
      nainodot; uml;ve T cells depends on continuous tickling of the TCR, and the rebound of the
      size and complexity of the peripheral lymphocyte pool after any marked loss in cell numbers
      involves recognition of self-peptidendash;MHC complexes. Infection often results in massive
      clonal expansion and development of effector function that initially overrides the balance of
      lymphocyte pools. When the pathogen is cleared, balance is restored: effector cells are
      eliminated and a long veteran's retirement is guaranteed for the surviving memory cells, which
      are no longer dependent on recognition of self-antigen. The veterans may be recalled to action
      quickly by a subsequent infection with the same pathogen. To provide protection against both
      unknown new pathogens and the recurrence of old infections, the immune system must maintain
      separate populations of nainodot; uml;ve cells and memory cells. In addition, the system
      must retain an appropriate mixture of CD4<super>+</super> helper T cells and CD8<super>
        +</super> cytotoxic T cells in both nainodot; uml;ve and memory pools.</p>
    <sec level="1">
      <sectitle>Thymocyte development</sectitle>
      <p>Bone marrow stem cells enter the thymus and commit to the T lineage in response to signals
        from the microenvironment<bibr rid="b4"/>. The stages of development of the major lineages
        of T cells are delineated by the surface expression of the co-receptor molecules CD4 and
        CD8. The earliest precursors are CD4<super>-</super>CD8<super>-</super> double negative (DN)
        in phenotype, comprising about 3% of the total thymocyte numbers. These proliferate
        extensively and become CD4<super>+</super>CD8<super>+</super> double positive (DP) cells,
        which are still immature and are the targets for TCR-based selection events. The MHC
        molecules expressed by the epithelial elements of the thymus are critically involved in the
        process of positive selection, which allows a small fraction of the DP population to mature
        into single positive CD4 lineage or CD8 lineage T cells<bibr rid="b5 b6"/>.</p>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Assembling the TCR</sectitle>
        <p> As is the case for antibodies, functional TCR genes are assembled from separate V, D and
          J region segments by genetic recombination<bibr rid="b7"/>. For T cells expressing
          alpha;beta; receptors, this process of gene rearrangement occurs in the thymus. Mice and
          humans carry in their germline a large number of V gene segments, which encode roughly the
          first 90 residues of a mature TCRalpha; or TCRbeta; chain. The TCRbeta; chain gene is
          assembled at the DN stage of T-cell development. A short D gene segment is juxtaposed to a
          short J segment and this is followed by rearrangement of a V segment to the assembled
          downstream DJ segment. In the case of TCRalpha; chains which rearrange later at the DP
          stage there are no D segments; a large number of Valpha; segments may rearrange to a
          large number of J segments. The immunoglobulin-like fold of the TCR chains positions three
          loops or complementarity determining regions (CDRs) from each chain in close proximity to
          each other, creating a binding face that will contact antigen. Two of these CDR loops,
          namely 1 and 2, are encoded by the V gene segment and have only the diversity provided by
          the number of germline V region gene segments, around 20ndash;70thinsp;Valpha; and
          Vbeta; segments in mice and humans. The third CDR loop is created by the juxtaposition of
          VJ or V(D)J segments and provides much more diversity, a result of the ability of each V
          segment to rearrange to any (D)J segment compounded by the fact that the joining of the
          coding sequences is imprecise. Nucleotides may be added or deleted at each of these
          junctions. If there were only 50thinsp;Valpha; and 50thinsp;Vbeta; genes to encode the
          TCR repertoire, combinatorial pairing would provide only <f>50 times; 50 = 2,500</f>
          TCRs. The addition of (D)J segments and the imprecision of joining boosts this number into
          the billions, with sequence diversity concentrated in the CDR3 loops.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>TCR interaction with ligand</sectitle>
        <p> Crystal structures of MHC class I and class II molecules have revealed their mode of
          function (<figr rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>). Although differing in detail, both MHC class I
          and class II molecules have peptide-binding grooves to present antigen to T cells<bibr
            rid="b8 b9 b10"/>. In each case, the groove is made up of a lsquo;floorrsquo; of
          beta;-sheets and lsquo;wallsrsquo; of long alpha;-helical regions. The most
          polymorphic residues in the MHC molecules protrude into the groove, thus altering the
          spectrum of peptides that can be bound. The remarkable feature of MHCndash;peptide
          binding is that it is both extremely stable yet promiscuous, allowing many different
          peptides to bind each allele. Many of the stabilizing interactions are between the
          backbone of the peptide and the MHC, whereas a few pockets in the groove select for
          certain side chains on the so-called lsquo;anchor residuesrsquo; of the peptide. MHC
          class I molecules load peptides soon after synthesis in the endoplasmic reticulum before
          trafficking to the cell surface. In contrast, the groove of MHC class II molecules is
          protected from peptide loading until the molecules reach endocytic vesicles. Once loaded
          with a peptide derived from lysosomal processing, the class-IIndash;peptide complex, like
          the class-Indash;peptide complex, is expressed stably at the cell surface.</p>
        <p>Mature T cells discriminate between self and foreign by recognition of peptides presented
          in the groove of self-MHC molecules. The membrane-distal face of the peptidendash;MHC
          complex that is presented to the T cell consists of a flat surface made up principally of
          the alpha;-helices of the MHC surrounding a central peptide. High-resolution structures
          of the TCR complexed with peptidendash;MHC ligand have shown how this is achieved (<figr
            rid="f1">Fig. 1</figr>). Crystal structures of a murine TCR interacting with MHC class I
          and peptide<bibr rid="b11 b12"/>, and two human TCRs complexed with the HLA-A2 class I
          molecule bound to the same viral peptide<bibr rid="b13 b14"/> have been solved, and all of
          the structures showed the same basic topology of interaction<bibr
            rid="b11 b12 b13 b14 b15 b16"/>. The TCR is positioned in a diagonal orientation over
          the face of the peptidendash;MHC complex with the CDR1 and CDR2 loops of the TCRalpha;
          chain lying over the N-terminal half of the peptide and the corresponding regions of the
          TCRbeta; chain lying over the C-terminal half. Many of the interactions of the V gene
          segment-encoded CDR1 and CDR2 regions of the TCR are actually with MHC residues. In
          particular, the CDR1 and CDR2 loops of the Valpha; chain have almost identical sites of
          interactions with peptidendash;MHC in all structures solved so far, and this match-up may
          be critical in establishing the overall configuration. The most variable loops of the TCR,
          namely the CDR3 regions of the TCRalpha; and TCRbeta; chains, lie centrally and have
          most contact with protruding peptide side chains. Thus, the most variable region of the
          TCR (CDR3 loops) has best access to the most variable region of the ligand (peptide).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>The unselected TCR repertoire</sectitle>
        <p> The lymphoid-specific components of immunoreceptor gene rearrangement, the
          recombinase-activating gene (RAG) products, are first expressed in thymocytes soon after
          entry in the thymus and operate initially on the TCRbeta; loci. Successful VDJ
          rearrangement resulting in the production of a functional, in-frame TCRbeta; chain is
          tested by assembly of the new gene product (TCRbeta;) along with an invariant surrogate
          TCRalpha; chain, pre-Talpha;, plus signalling components of the TCR, the CD3
            complex<bibr rid="b17"/>. Proper assembly of this complex with the newly generated
          TCRbeta; chain signals the CD4<super>-</super>CD8<super>-</super> pre-T-cell to switch
          off expression of RAG proteins, to go through several rounds of division and to proceed to
          the CD4<super>+</super>CD8<super>+</super> stage of thymocyte maturation. This check
          point, called beta;-selection, does not involve the recognition of any ligand by the
          pre-TCR, as truncated versions of TCRbeta; and pre-Talpha; lacking the extracellular
          domain can trigger progression to the DP compartment<bibr rid="b18"/>. The mere assembly
          of the CD3ndash;pre-Talpha;ndash;TCRbeta; complex appears to be sufficient to activate
          the downstream signalling pathway. It is possible, although perhaps unlikely, that some
          TCRbeta; chains are lost in this selection if they cannot assemble with CD3 and/or
          pre-Talpha;.</p>
        <p>At the DP stage of thymocyte differentiation, the RAG genes are expressed once again, and
          the cells now focus on rearranging TCR Valpha;. to Jalpha;. Production of a new
          TCRalpha; chain that can pair with the existing TCRbeta; chain allows surface expression
          of the TCRalpha;beta;ndash;CD3 complex. Co-expression of randomly rearranged
          TCRalpha;beta; at the DP cell surface is an expression of the germline, or unselected
          TCR repertoire. The repertoire that is allowed to leave the thymus for the peripheral
          lymphoid organs is only a subset of this larger pool. To complete maturation, the germline
          repertoire is positively and negatively selected for interactions with MHC molecules in
          the thymus. Ultimately, only about 5% of the DPs are allowed to emigrate. In a murine
          thymus that lacks expression of any MHC molecule, T-cell development is blocked at the DP
          stage. DP thymocytes from such a MHC-deficient environment are immature and unresponsive
          to conventional antigen, yet tricks have been used to study the specificity of their
          germline TCRs. In one case, maturation of the thymocytes was induced in foetal thymic
          organ culture by receptor engagement with anti-TCR antibodies<bibr rid="b19"/>. The mature
            CD4<super>+</super> T cells that developed were cloned as hybridomas to allow analysis
          of their TCR specificity. In another case, DP thymocytes from MHC-deficient mice were
          isolated and reaggregated with MHC wild-type thymus stromal cells. In such reaggregate
          cultures, the fraction of cells that respond to MHC class I or MHC class II could be
          scored by examining the upregulation of surface markers that are normally turned on during
          thymocyte selection<bibr rid="b20"/>. Both of these approaches showed that the germline
          TCR repertoire is skewed to the recognition of MHC molecules. Somewhere between 5 and 20%
          of the DP population from MHC-deficient mice was responsive to the set of MHC molecules
          expressed in any one mouse strain. This is a much higher frequency than would be expected
          by the generation of receptors through the random rearrangement of gene sequences that do
          not have an inherent predisposition for interactions with MHC. Evolution has shaped the
          TCR genes, presumably the CDR1 and CDR2 regions encoded by the V gene segments, so that
          their alpha;beta; product will preferentially match MHC molecules.</p>
        <p>Certain Valpha; gene segments have evolved to interact preferentially with either class
          I or class II molecules. TCRs bearing these Valpha; segments are preferentially selected
          into the CD8<super>+</super> (MHC class I reactive) or CD4<super>+</super> (MHC class II
          reactive) T-cell subset during normal thymocyte selection. Swapping individual residues in
          the CDR1 or CDR2 regions of the Valpha; gene is sufficient to change the selection of
          these TCRs from the CD4<super>+</super> to the CD8<super>+</super> subset<bibr rid="b21"
          />. Furthermore, certain mouse strains differ consistently in the ratio of CD4<super>
            +</super> to CD8<super>+</super> T cells in peripheral organs, and one of the loci
          controlling this phenotype maps with the TCRalpha; locus<bibr rid="b22"/>. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Positive selection of thymocytes</sectitle>
        <p> Even though they express a TCR at the surface, in the absence of MHC recognition
            CD4<super> +</super>CD8<super>+</super> thymocytes will undergo apoptotic death because
          of receptor neglect (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). During their approximate 3-day life
          span, the DP thymocytes will continue to express the RAG genes and continue to rearrange
          TCRalpha; chain genes. TCR engagement with MHC class I or class II molecules on the
          cortical thymic epithelial cells is required to rescue the cell from death by neglect and
          to switch off further TCRalpha; chain gene rearrangement. Only those DP thymocytes that
          bind self-MHC with sufficiently low affinity will be rescued. In contrast, DP cells that
          express a receptor that interacts with high affinity with MHC in the thymus will be
          eliminated in a process referred to as negative selection. Almost half of the cells
          reacting with self-MHC are lost through this mechanism<bibr rid="b23"/> (<figr rid="f2"
            >Fig. 2</figr>). The low-affinity recognition of self-MHC not only promotes thymocyte
          survival but also determines commitment of the DP thymocyte to either the CD4 or the CD8
            lineage<bibr rid="b5 b6 b24"/>. Recognition of MHC class I results in commitment to the
          CD8 lineage, whereas recognition of class II results in CD4<super>+</super> T cells. Thus,
          function and lineage are correlated with MHC class recognition. How positive selection on
          MHC class I versus class II is distinguished by the thymocyte is unknown. Lineage choice
          may be steered by qualitative or quantitative differences in signalling, or may be random
          but confirmed by later selective events.</p>
        <p>The molecular nature of the TCRndash;MHC recognition event in positive selection has
          been an area of active research. Initial experiments showed that mutations affecting only
          the inside of the groove of a murine class I molecule drastically altered the selected
          repertoire of CD8<super>+</super> T cells<bibr rid="b25 b26"/>. These experiments
          suggested strongly that self-peptides bound to the MHC groove are recognized by thymocytes
          and are critical for positive selection. Further analysis of this recognition required the
          use of an <i>in vitro</i> organ culture system, using thymus lobes from mice deficient in
          class I expression in which peptides could be added back to reconstitute positive
          selection. Disruption of the beta;<sub>2</sub>-microglobulin gene, encoding the light
          chain of class I molecules, or of the TAP genes encoding a transporter that delivers
          peptides to nascent class I molecules in the endoplasmic reticulum, leads to a drastic
          decrease in selection of CD8 lineage cells. Surface expression of MHC class I can be
          restored to some extent by the addition of single peptides or peptide mixtures to organ
          culture systems. Initial experiments using thymic lobes from mice that express a normal,
          germline TCR repertoire suggested that a complex mixture of peptides restored selection of
            CD8<super> +</super> T cells better than single peptides which bound and stabilized MHC
          to the same degree<bibr rid="b27 b28"/>. Follow-up experiments in this peptide add-back
          system using mice that express rearranged TCR transgenes of known ligand specificity
          suggested a stringent requirement for peptide recognition in the positive selection of CD8
          lineage T cells<bibr rid="b29 b30 b31"/>. Peptides that bind MHC class I and form a
          low-affinity ligand for the TCR induced the maturation of functional CD8<super>+</super>
          cytotoxic T cells most efficiently<bibr rid="b32"/>. The measured TCR affinities for
          foreign peptidendash;MHC ligands fall into the 1ndash;10thinsp;micro;M range<bibr
            rid="b33"/>. Compared with this, the affinities for ligands that can efficiently induce
          positive selection, but cannot induce negative selection, are only 5ndash;9-fold
            lower<bibr rid="b34"/>.</p>
        <p>Is a single self-peptide actually responsible for the maturation of a cohort of
          thymocytes? Or do a larger number of self-peptides select each TCR? Natural peptides
          eluted from MHC class I molecules can induce selection of certain TCR transgenic
          thymocytes when added back to TAP-deficient thymus lobes<bibr rid="b35 b36"/>, although
          whether these are expressed at the appropriate level in the thymus cortex is not known.
          Antibodies that react in a peptide-specific fashion with only a subset of class II
          molecules prevent the thymic selection of a specific subset of CD4<super>+</super> T
            cells<bibr rid="b37"/>. Certainly, it can be concluded that a subset of self-peptides,
          and possibly a single self-peptide, bound to self-MHC acts as the ligand that permits the
          maturation of each T cell. In this way, these self-peptides act as low-affinity mimics or
          lsquo;stand insrsquo; to prime the immune system to interact later in the periphery with
          high-affinity ligands for the TCR such as foreign peptide bound to the same MHC<bibr
            rid="b38"/>.</p>
        <p>In the study of CD4<super>+</super> T-cell selection in the thymus, researchers have
          generated mice in which all or a large fraction of the class II molecules in an individual
          mouse are occupied by the same peptide, and have asked how many T cells can one
          peptidendash;MHC ligand select. The invariant chain Ii is a chaperone for MHC class II
          that contains a region, CLIP, that occupies the class II groove in the endoplasmic
          reticulum and prohibits other peptides from binding until the molecules reach
          endosomal/lysosomal vesicles. At this site, CLIP is removed by the action of the peptide
          exchange catalyst, H2ndash;M. Mice deficient in H2ndash;M express near normal levels of
          class-IIndash;peptide on their surface, but in this case, most remain occupied by the
          CLIP peptide<bibr rid="b39 b40 b41"/>. Another strategy has been to generate a covalently
          linked class-IIndash;peptide construct that assembles with the single peptide lsquo;sewn
          inrsquo; to the MHC groove and to express these as transgenes in mice that lack wild-type
          MHC class II<bibr rid="b42 b43"/>.</p>
        <p>Initial results from these lsquo;single peptidersquo; systems were remarkable in
          showing that the mice developed a large and broad CD4<super>+</super> T-cell repertoire.
          They contained 20ndash;50% of the normal numbers of CD4<super> +</super> T cells, with
          diverse TCRs as assessed by Vbeta; and Valpha; usage. Could a single peptidendash;MHC
          complex select a near-normal CD4<super>+ </super> T-cell repertoire? More recent analysis
          has shown quite clearly that the repertoire in these animals is far from normal. First,
          none of the single-peptide mice can positively select TCRs of known specificity that are
          selected in normal mice<bibr rid="b44 b45 b46"/>. Second, closer analysis of the
          TCRalpha; chain usage in the mutant versus wild-type mice shows that the selected
          repertoire is markedly constrained in the mutants<bibr rid="b47"/>. Last, even when 95% of
          class II molecules are occupied by a single peptide, most of the CD4<super> +</super> T
          cells that emerge from the thymus are actually selected on the 5% of molecules that are
          occupied by a diverse mixture of unknown self-peptides. The CLIP region of Ii was replaced
          with a tight-binding peptide, so that in mice that were Ii-deficient, 95% of surface MHC
          class II molecules were occupied by the substituted sequence<bibr rid="b48"/>. Under these
          conditions, large numbers of CD4<super>+</super> T cells were selected. The critical
          experiment was to breed these mice to an H2ndash;M-deficient background which resulted in
          no apparent change in the level of MHC class II expression, but a 70% decline in the
          number of CD4<super>+</super> T cells selected. The simple conclusion is that the
          lsquo;backgroundrsquo; of diverse peptides bound to class II must have a major role in
          selection even though such complexes are present at extremely low levels.</p>
        <p>Positive selection of immature DP thymocytes by low-affinity interactions with
          self-peptidendash;MHC complexes implies that cells at this stage of development are more
          sensitive to low-affinity ligands than are their mature descendents. This has been shown
          to be the case, despite the fact that they express 10-fold less TCR on their surface<bibr
            rid="b49 b50"/>. Low-affinity ligands stimulated early activation events in DP
          thymocytes but not in mature T cells bearing the same TCR; however, from what we have
          learned recently about the homeostasis of peripheral T cells, we might assume that under
          certain circumstances, mature T cells can also respond to low-affinity self-ligands. </p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec level="1">
      <sectitle>Peripheral T-cell homeostasis</sectitle>
      <p>After the selection and maturation of T cells in the thymus, naive T cells enter the
        periphery where they circulate throughout the secondary lymphoid organs awaiting an
        encounter with antigen. The organization of the many cell types that make up the immune
        system requires complex homeostatic mechanisms to assure the production and survival of each
        cell type in appropriate numbers to maintain proper immune function. One can imagine many
        different mechanisms by which appropriate homeostasis of lymphocyte populations is
        maintained, including control of the rate of production, division of mature cells,
        trafficking and cell death.</p>
      <p>To maintain homeostasis of lymphocyte populations, the different cell types must be grouped
        and counted. Peripheral B- and T-cell populations appear to be independently regulated<bibr
          rid="b51"/>. This conclusion is based on the fact that similar numbers of mature B cells
        are found in the periphery of normal mice and in mice that lack T cells<bibr rid="b52"/>.
        Likewise, the number of T cells found in normal mice does not increase in B-cell-deficient
          mice<bibr rid="b53"/>. In addition, when small numbers of T cells are introduced into
        depleted hosts, they undergo expansion equivalently in mice deficient in both B and T cells
        and in mice deficient only in T cells<bibr rid="b54"/>. All these results suggest the
        independent homeostatic control of T-cell and B-cell numbers. </p>
      <p>The pool of peripheral T cells consists of nainodot; uml;ve T cells and previously
        activated antigen-experienced memory cells. Interestingly, nainodot; uml;ve and memory T
        cells appear to occupy separate homeostatic niches. After reconstitution of T-cell-deficient
        mice with memory cells, the transferred cells expand to equal the same total number of
        memory cells in normal mice. Furthermore, it is not possible to increase the size of the
        memory pool by transferring large numbers of memory T cells, indicating that there is a set
        point for memory T-cell number even when no nainodot; uml;ve T cells are present<bibr
          rid="b55"/>. The separate regulation of memory and nainodot; uml;ve pools makes
        teleological sense as it is vital to retain both a diverse nainodot; uml;ve repertoire
        that can respond to invasion by yet unknown pathogens and a memory pool that can respond
        rapidly to previously encountered pathogens. If these two populations were in competition
        for survival, the diverse repertoire of nainodot; uml;ve T cells could be replaced by
        rapidly expanding memory T cells or, conversely, new thymic emigrants could displace memory
        T cells resulting in the loss of immunological recall<bibr rid="b51"/>. </p>
      <p>Although CD4<super>+</super> and CD8<super>+</super> cells serve different functions in the
        immune system and recognize different MHC molecules, many results suggest that they occupy
        overlapping homeostatic niches<bibr rid="b51"/>. First, relatively normal numbers of total T
        cells are found in mice deficient in MHC class I or II or in the CD8 or CD4 co-receptors,
        and thus lacking one T-cell subset. Second, small numbers of mature peripheral T cells will
        expand when introduced into a T-cell-deficient host, and the co-transfer of large numbers of
        either CD4<super>+</super> or CD8<super>+</super> mature T cells can suppress this
          expansion<bibr rid="b56 b57"/>. Last, in TCR transgenic mice in which the T-cell
        population is skewed toward either the CD4<super>+</super> or CD8<super>+</super> subset,
        total T-cell numbers are typically near normal. Thus, CD4<super>+</super> and
          CD8<super>+</super> T cells appear to be counted together for purposes of maintaining the
        homeostasis of T-cell numbers. However, some distinction is clearly made between
          CD4<super>+</super> and CD8<super> +</super> T cells, as the ratio of CD4<super>+</super>
        to CD8<super>+</super> T cells is tightly regulated in normal mice and will rapidly readjust
        after transfer of large numbers of either subset<bibr rid="b56"/>.</p>
      <p>The size of the nainodot; uml;ve pool of T cells remains more or less constant in spite
        of the continuing contribution of recent thymic emigrants, the loss of T cells due to normal
        cell death, the expansion and waning of effector populations during immune responses, and
        the diversion of cells into the memory pool after an immune response. The size of the
        peripheral T-cell pool does not appear to influence the rate of thymocyte production or
        export of nainodot; uml;ve T cells, as changes in the number of peripheral T cells do not
        change the rate of thymocyte output<bibr rid="b58"/>. These data suggest that homeostatic
        control over the size of the nainodot; uml;ve peripheral pool is regulated by the loss of
        T cells in the periphery<bibr rid="b58"/>. How recent thymic emigrants are incorporated into
        the peripheral pool is not entirely understood. Clearly, recent thymic emigrants must
        displace other nainodot; uml;ve T cells to maintain homeostasis of the peripheral T-cell
        pool. Newly generated T cells could either randomly displace resident T cells in the
        periphery or selectively displace resident cells on the basis of a criterion such as
          age<bibr rid="b51 b58 b59"/>. Even in the absence of thymic export, the nainodot; uml;ve
        pool remains rather constant in size, indicating that the life span of nainodot; uml;ve T
        cells is under homeostatic control<bibr rid="b59 b60"/>.</p>
      <p>Relatively little is known about the mechanisms that determine life span, capacity for
        renewal and survival of nainodot; uml;ve T cells in the periphery in the absence of
        antigen. Nainodot; uml;ve T cells were considered to be quiescent lsquo;spore-likersquo;
        cells that persist indefinitely without antigenic stimulation<bibr rid="b61 b62 b63 b64 b65"
        />; however, evidence now suggests that nainodot; uml;ve T cells may require input signals
        to support their survival in the periphery. Expression of transcription factors such as lung
        Kruppel-like factor and NFAT4 are crucial for the maintenance of a resting, nainodot;
        uml;ve population of T cells<bibr rid="b66 b67"/>. In addition, cytokine signals influence
        the survival, homing and activation of nainodot; uml;ve T cells, which in turn alter the
        activation state and homeostasis of the nainodot; uml;ve compartment<bibr rid="b68 b69"/>.
        The bcl-2 family of molecules, which are intimately involved in the survival of many cell
        types, are also involved in the maintenance of the nainodot; uml;ve pool of T cells<bibr
          rid="b70"/>. Now it appears that TCR interactions with self-MHC direct a signal required
        for maintenance of nainodot; uml;ve T cells.</p>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>MHC in peripheral maintenance</sectitle>
        <p> Although self-peptidendash;MHC molecules are known to be crucial in the generation of a
          T-cell repertoire with a wide spectrum of specificities, only recently have data emerged
          that implicate TCR interaction with self-MHC in the survival and expansion of peripheral T
          cells (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>). Several groups have shown that MHC molecules are
          important in maintaining a peripheral pool of T cells<bibr rid="b71"/>. </p>
        <p>In many experimental systems, nainodot; uml;ve CD4<super>+</super> T cells demonstrate
          a requirement for MHC class II molecules for long-term survival<bibr rid="b72 b73 b74 b75"
          />. CD4<super>+</super> T cells were positively selected in MHC class-II-expressing
          thymuses and then assayed for survival in a periphery that was engineered to lack
          expression of the positively selecting MHC class II allele. In all cases,
            CD4<super>+</super> T cells declined in numbers in the absence of self-MHC class II. One
          report has shown that expression of MHC class II on dendritic cells is sufficient to
          support CD4<super>+</super> T cells in the periphery<bibr rid="b74"/>.</p>
        <p>An important role for MHC class I in maintaining nainodot; uml;ve CD8<super> +</super>
          T cells has been demonstrated by the transfer of TCR transgenic CD8<super>+</super> T
          cells into MHC class-I-deficient hosts<bibr rid="b76 b77"/>. Both studies showed that the
          nainodot; uml;ve CD8<super>+</super> T cells fade away in hosts that lack peripheral
          expression of MHC class I. Furthermore, the MHC class I allele that positively selected
          the T cell in the thymus is strictly required for nainodot; uml;ve T-cell survival<bibr
            rid="b76"/>. The inability of CD8<super>+</super> T cells to accumulate in mice
          expressing very low levels of MHC class I when grafted with a wild-type thymus further
          supports a role for TCR engagement by MHC in the periphery to permit survival of T
            cells<bibr rid="b78"/>. Although some differences were reported in these studies, the
          trend remains clear: the retention of both CD8<super>+</super> and CD4<super>+</super> T
          cells is enhanced when MHC class I and II, respectively, are expressed in the
          periphery.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>MHC in recovery of peripheral homeostasis</sectitle>
        <p> The nainodot; uml;ve T-cell pool consists mostly of resting cells compared with the
          memory pool in which cells turn over more rapidly<bibr rid="b63"/>. Upon close
          examination, however, low levels of division are observed in nainodot; uml;ve T-cell
          populations in the absence of conventional antigen stimulation<bibr rid="b61 b63"/>.
          Furthermore, even without conventional antigen stimulation, nainodot; uml;ve T cells
          have a great potential for division when transferred into hosts with low numbers of
            lymphocytes<bibr rid="b56 b60 b62 b65 b79 b80 b81 b82 b83"/>. This proliferation of
          nainodot; uml;ve cells after transfer into lymphopenic hosts has been speculated to
          involve cytokine release, the expression ofnbsp;environmental antigens or interactions
          with self-MHC molecules<bibr rid="b57 b65 b82 b84 b85 b86"/>. Recently, the molecular
          interactions that support the expansion of nainodot; uml;ve T cells in lymphopenic
          environments have become of significant interest, and several groups have studied the
          function of MHC in this process. There is a clear consensus that both CD4<super>+</super>
          and CD8<super>+</super> T cells require expression of MHC ligands for efficient
          homeostatic expansion in lymphopenic hosts<bibr rid="b54 b57 b77 b86 b87 b88 b89"/>.</p>
        <p>When polyclonal or TCR transgenic monoclonal CD4<super>+</super> T-cell populations are
          transferred into syngeneic hosts that have been T-cell depleted, they divide without
          direct antigenic stimulation. If the CD4<super>+</super> cells are transferred into class
          II-deficient hosts or hosts expressing MHC class II other than the positively selecting
          class II molecule, however, little division is observed<bibr rid="b54 b57 b86 b87"/>.
          Similarly, both polyclonal and TCR transgenic CD8<super>+</super> T cells expand in
          wild-type hosts expressing MHC class I, but minimally in hosts with low or no levels of
          MHC class I molecules<bibr rid="b77 b88 b89"/>. Thus, both CD8<super>+</super> and
            CD4<super>+</super> T cells proliferate much more efficiently in a lymphopenic host
          expressing MHC class I or MHC class II molecules, respectively. These data show that MHC
          recognition contributes to division of nainodot; uml;ve T cells responding to
          homeostatic signals.</p>
        <p>What is the specificity of the TCRndash;MHC interaction that promotes homeostasis-driven
          expansion? Experiments comparing CD4<super>+</super> T cells transferred into hosts with
          wild-type self-peptidendash;MHC class II or hosts expressing MHC class II bound to a
          limited repertoire of self-peptides show that CD4<super>+</super> T cells undergo
          expansion efficiently only when transferred into a host with a self-peptidendash;MHC
          class II repertoire from the background in which the T cells developed. Division of
          wild-type CD4<super>+</super> T cells was observed in T-cell-depleted wild-type hosts but
          only minimally in H2ndash;M-deficient hosts. As expected, CD4<super> +</super> T cells
          that were positively selected in the H2ndash;M-deficient background were able to divide
          when transferred into T-cell-depleted Hndash;2M-deficient hosts<bibr rid="b57 b86"/>.
          These data make a strong case that peptide-specific recognition of MHC class II complexes
          by T cells promotes division in T-cell-depleted environments<bibr rid="b57 b86"/>.
          Furthermore, they suggest that this recognition is specific for the same peptides that T
          cells previously recognized with low affinity during their positive selection in the
            thymus<bibr rid="b57 b86"/>. </p>
        <p>CD8<super>+</super> T cells also exhibit a requirement for specific recognition of
          peptidendash;MHC class I complexes to undergo homeostatic expansion. Proliferation of TCR
          transgenic CD8<super>+</super> T cells in TAP-deficient hosts expressing low levels of MHC
          class I was restored by the addition of a single MHC class-I-binding peptide<bibr
            rid="b89"/>. Recognition was peptide specific, as a low-affinity peptide known to
          positively select the TCR transgenic T cells promoted expansion, whereas a control peptide
          did not. Thus, the signal for homeostatic proliferation may be characterized by
          low-affinity TCR interactions with self-peptidendash;MHC complexes. This suggests that
          the specific recognition of self-peptidendash;MHC complexes drives homeostatic
          proliferation of peripheral T cells, and that this interaction has a specificity similar
          to the recognition of self-peptidendash;MHC during positive selection. It is possible
          that the positively selecting peptide(s) may not necessarily be expressed in the
          periphery, but that other ligands of similar affinity or avidity for the TCR function in
          this capacity (<figr rid="f2">Fig. 2</figr>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>The response to T-cell depletion</sectitle>
        <p> To what extent does homeostasis-driven proliferation of peripheral T cells in a
          self-peptidendash;MHC-specific manner contribute to a useful immune system? One
          possibility is that it ensures the diversity of the peripheral T-cell repertoire. It is
          appealing to consider that a requirement for peptide-specific recognition during
          homeostatic proliferation would reinforce the requirement for self-recognition established
          during positive selection for an individual clone to survive over time and contribute to
          the long-lived pool of peripheral T cells. Furthermore, the ability of a nainodot;
          uml;ve T cell to receive TCRndash;self-peptidendash;MHC signals may determine to what
          extent a given cell contributes to reconstitution after a decline in T-cell numbers. This
          could have important implications for peripheral homeostasis after a loss of peripheral T
          cells in adults, as the ability of the thymus to replenish a nainodot; uml;ve T-cell
          pool with diverse specificities may be insufficient to repopulate the periphery
            efficiently<bibr rid="b84"/>. The clinical relevancy of such a mechanism certainly
          exists for patients with T-cell immunodeficiencies resulting from infection (such as AIDS)
          or from therapeutic treatments (such as chemotherapy or irradiation).</p>
        <p>Until recently, it was thought that nainodot; uml;ve T cells did not recognize
          self-peptidendash;MHC ligands in the periphery. However, the existence of mechanisms for
          MHC-dependent homeostasis-driven proliferation and survival suggest that low-affinity
          interactions between the TCR of peripheral T cells and self-peptidendash;MHC complexes
          are involved in regulating homeostasis of peripheral T-cell populations. T cells
          proliferate in response to low-affinity self-ligands when T-cell numbers are reduced,
          which demonstrates that the sensitivity of the TCR or the response to TCR-mediated signals
          can be altered by global homeostatic signals. We can envisage at least three different
          mechanisms by which this could work (<figr rid="f3">Fig. 3</figr>). Under normal
          conditions, T cells crowding through lymph nodes may be competing for ligands on
          presenting cells. Competition may be for MHC itself or for some other growth factor;
          lymphopenia would decrease the competition. Alternatively, T cells may lsquo;countrsquo;
          their own numbers by sending inhibitory signals to each other, or by inhibiting the
          stimulatory properties of a presenting cell. Decreasing T-cell numbers would sensitize the
          T cell or activate the presenting cell (<figr rid="f3"> Fig. 3</figr>).</p>
        <p>One implication of nainodot; uml;ve T cells being induced to proliferate in
          T-cell-depleted environments is that what has previously been considered
          lsquo;maintenancersquo; is likely to be the sum of survival and proliferation. The
          decline of T cells in the absence of MHC may be partially due to their inability to
          undergo homeostatic proliferation. Thus, it is necessary at this point to re-evaluate our
          understanding of T-cell maintenance to accommodate a more complex regulation of T-cell
          homeostasis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>Maintenance of the memory T-cell pool</sectitle>
        <p> Memory T cells often divide in the periphery long after antigen stimulation, even
          without evidence for the persistence of antigen. Furthermore, the rules for the
          persistence of memory T cells appear to be different from those that nainodot; uml;ve
          T-cells obey. Recent studies have shown that CD4<super>+</super> and CD8<super> +</super>
          memory T cells have a much less stringent requirement for TCRndash;MHC interactions for
          survival and homeostatic proliferation compared with nainodot; uml;ve T cells.</p>
        <p>The survival of memory CD8<super>+</super> T cells is much less dependent on MHC class I
          than that of nainodot; uml;ve CD8<super>+</super> T cells. Both polyclonal and TCR
          transgenic memory CD8<super>+</super> T cells specific for lymphocytic choriomeningitis
          virus (LCMV) survive indefinitely in MHC-deficient hosts<bibr rid="b77"/>. Memory
            CD8<super>+</super> T cells, expressing the TCR transgene specific for the male antigen
          HY, survived and proliferated without a preference for the restricting allele<bibr
            rid="b76"/>. However, unlike the LCMV-specific memory T cells, the memory T cells
          specific for the HY antigen disappeared after transfer into mice expressing low levels of
          MHC class I<bibr rid="b76 b90"/>. In both experimental systems, CD8<super>+</super> memory
          T cells were able to proliferate in lymphopenic hosts even when MHC class I was not
          expressed, showing that homeostatic proliferation of memory CD8<super>+</super> T cells is
          MHC class I independent<bibr rid="b76 b77"/>. Although some differences in conclusions
          from these studies may be attributed to distinct experimental systems, the data with
          polyclonal CD8<super>+</super> T cells specific for many LCMV antigens present a
          convincing argument for MHC independence for homeostatic proliferation and survival of
          memory CD8<super> +</super> T cells<bibr rid="b77"/>. Similarly, memory
            CD4<super>+</super> T cells survive indefinitely in hosts that do not express their
          positively selecting MHC class II molecule<bibr rid="b91"/> or any class II molecules at
            all<bibr rid="b92"/>. Thus, CD4<super>+</super> memory T cells appear to have no
          requirement for the presence of self-MHC class II to support their long-term survival. An
          obvious corollary of these observations is that neither CD8<super>+</super> nor
            CD4<super>+</super> memory T cells need continuous exposure to their cognate antigen to
          survive, a subject of much previous debate.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec level="2">
        <sectitle>The response to infection</sectitle>
        <p>
          <?Pub Caret?>There is concern that certain infectious agents may overwhelm the immune
          system because of their high replicative potential; however, the opposite problem may
          arise. Analyses have shown that, in some cases, the specific immune response can threaten
          to overwhelm the lymphoid compartment. Use of peptidendash;MHC tetramers to stain T cells
          on the basis of TCR specificty, and of single-cell assays to detect interferon-gamma;
          secretion, have revolutionized our appreciation of the numerology of the
            CD8<super>+</super> T-cell response to infection<bibr rid="b93 b94"/>. For mice infected
          with the natural pathogen LCMV, total CD8<super> +</super> T-cell numbers increase
          2ndash;10-fold by eight days after exposure (<figr rid="f4">Fig. 4</figr>). Remarkably,
          most of the CD8<super>+</super> T-cell expansion is antigen-specific! The rare,
          antigen-specific, nainodot; uml;ve CD8<super>+</super> T cells present before infection
          can divide 13ndash;16 times in this time, so that their frequency may go from 1 in
            10<super>4</super>ndash;10<super> 5</super> to making up most of the
            CD8<super>+</super> T-cell population. Such rapid proliferation leads to the production
          of enormous numbers of effectors capable of killing infected cells and releasing cytokines
          upon antigen encounter. Such a massive CD8<super>+</super> T-cell response is not unique
          to LCMV infection, as large numbers of antigen-specific T cells are generated in other
          human and animal infections<bibr rid="b95 b96 b97 b98 b99"/>. In this case of a viral or
          bacterial pathogen in which multiple pathogen-derived epitopes are known and the specific
            CD8<super>+</super> T-cell response to each one can be quantitated by tetramer staining,
          the composition of the memory pool reflects the epitope specificity of the effector
            population<bibr rid="b94 b100"/>. The dominant epitopes in the initial response remain
          dominant in the memory repertoire. </p>
        <p>The problem for the immune system is how to revert to homeostasis from a situation at the
          height of response when over half of the CD8<super>+</super> T cells in the infected
          animal are effector cells specific for one pathogen. The system copes extremely well.
          During the few days after antigen has been cleared, 90ndash;99% of the effector cells
          die, leaving an expanded population of new memory cells. The original nainodot; uml;ve
            CD8<super>+</super> T-cell pool is left intact, except for the promotion of the
          pathogen-specific members, whereas the memory pool adds some new members (<figr rid="f4"
            >Fig. 4</figr>). A recent experiment in which memory T cells were irreversibly marked by
          the activation of a modified granzyme B promoter suggests that a specific subset of
          effector cells contributes to memory<bibr rid="b101"/>. What regulates the contraction of
          the overwhelming numbers of effector CD8<super>+</super> T cells into reasonable numbers
          of memory cells is unknown. There is no evidence that Fas/FasL or any other
          tumour-necrosis factor family member is involved in the massive apoptosis of the effector
            cells<bibr rid="b102"/>. Cessation of antigen stimulation and withdrawal of growth
          factors at the end of the response may lead to death. By whatever mechanism the immune
          system pulls it off, this represents a remarkable example of the recovery of homeostasis
          in the T-cell repertoire.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec level="1">
      <sectitle>The lives of a T cell</sectitle>
      <p>CD4<super>+</super> and CD8<super>+</super> T cells depend on TCR interactions with
        self-peptides presented by MHC molecules for both their maturation in the thymus and their
        maintenance in peripheral lymphoid organs. The signals delivered in the periphery through
        interactions with self maintain the homeostasis of the nainodot; uml;ve T-cell pool by
        keeping cells alive and by stimulating a low level of proliferation when the need arises.
        Low-affinity interactions with self-peptidendash;MHC may keep nainodot; uml;ve T cells
        alert and is a way for them to reaffirm their potential to respond to higher affinity
        interactions with foreign peptide. The recognition of self-peptidendash;MHC by developing
        thymocytes does more than simply deliver a survival signalmdash;it also allows the
        preferential selection of T cells on the basis of their ability to detect self-ligands with
        high specificity and low affinity. Because the composition of self-peptides bound to MHC is
        diverse, the specificity of T cells selected to mature is also diverse. The fact that
        peripheral T cells remain sensitive to self-peptidendash;MHC suggests that a continuum of
        self-recognition ensures diversity within the T-cell pool long after positive selection in
        the thymus is completed.</p>
      <p>The factors that govern the production and maintenance of the memory T-cell pool are a
        mystery. This issue is further compounded by the finding that memory T cells are
        heterogeneous and can be subclassified into those that retain receptors for entering
        secondary lymphoid organs and those that preferentially enter inflamed tissues and perform
        immediate effector function<bibr rid="b103"/>. In contrast to nainodot; uml;ve T cells, T
        cells that have responded to foreign antigen and graduated to the memory pool no longer
        require self-antigen stimulation to survive. An obvious rational for this is that once a T
        cell has responded to a first encounter with a pathogen, it does not need to reaffirm its
        usefulness in the memory pool. A pathogen that came once may certainly come again. Another
        reason why memory T cells should be less responsive to self-antigen is that they are
        potentially more dangerous than nainodot; uml;ve cells. Memory T cells are easier to
        trigger, faster to respond, and may enter tissues more readily than nainodot; uml;ve T
        cells, allowing them to see a broader range of self-antigens. Thus, compared with nainodot;
        uml;ve T cells, they pose an increased threat to upset the balance of discrimination
        between self and non-self. On the basis of this realization, one may propose a way in which
        a fraction of effector cells from a primary response is allowed to revert to memory status.
        The effector cells that have responded well to foreign antigen, yet are the least sensitive
        to low-affinity self-peptidendash;MHC interactions, may be the ones chosen to enter the
        memory pool. Their lower sensitivity to self-antigen would guard against a harmful
        autoimmune response due to unforeseen cross-reactivity with self. This lowered sensitivity
        to self may be based on the specificity of their TCR in a polyclonal population, or on some
        stochastic change in their ability to perceive low-affinity ligands in a monoclonal
        setting.</p>
      <p>The goal of vaccination is to induce long-lived memory cells. Understanding the
        developmental progression of T lymphocytes from the thymus, to nainodot; uml;ve peripheral
        cell, to effector cell to memory cell is a challenge for the future. Advances in the way
        that we are able to identify T cells on the basis of their specificity, and expanding
        knowledge of signalling pathways will allow rapid progress in this area.</p>
    </sec>
  </bdy>
  <bm>
    <objects>
      <fig id="f1" type="bmp" entname="figf1">
        <!--402d006AA-->
        <figtl>The nature of TCR interaction with peptidendash;MHC ligand.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p><b>a</b>, Positioning of the three CDR loops of the TCRalpha; and TCRbeta; chains in
            the ligand-binding face of the TCR. <b>b</b>,nbsp;Footprint of the TCR on the
            peptidendash;MHC complex. <b>c</b>, MHC class I molecule with bound peptide. The long
            alpha;-helices of MHC enclose the peptide. Reprinted with permission from Garcia <i>et
              al</i>.<bibr rid="b11"/>. The crystal structure of a TCR interaction with a MHC class
            II ligand has not been reported but is likely to follow the same rules.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f2" type="bmp" entname="figf2">
        <!--402d006AB-->
        <figtl>Consequences of TCR interactions with ligands of varying affinity in the thymus and
          periphery.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>TCRndash;MHC interactions may facilitate maturation, survival, proliferation or death.
            The consequences of TCR binding to peptidendash;MHC are dictated by the affinity of the
            interaction, as well as the maturation state of the T cell. Immature thymocytes require
            a positively selecting signal, which is delivered through low-affinity interactions of
            their newly rearranged TCR with self-peptidendash;MHC. If no signal is delivered to the
            thymocyte because of an inability of the TCR to interact with self-peptidendash;MHC
            complexes, it will undergo programmed cell death known as death by neglect.
            Alternatively, a thymocyte may express a TCR that has high affinity for
            self-peptidendash;MHC. These cells must be eliminated by negative selection as they are
            potentially autoreactive. In the periphery mature T cells require low-affinity
            interactions with self-peptidendash;MHC to ensure survival. Furthermore, low-affinity
            interactions with self-peptidendash;MHC allow nainodot; uml;ve T cells to expand when
            T-cell numbers are reduced. High-affinity interactions between a nainodot; uml;ve
            T-cell in the periphery and peptidendash;MHC typically initiate the immune response
            against a foreign antigen. This leads to rapid proliferation and the development of the
            effector function culminating in the emergence of a few antigen-experienced cells that
            join the pool of memory T cells to await a subsequent encounter with antigen.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f3" type="bmp" entname="figf3">
        <!--402d006AC-->
        <figtl>Possible mechanisms to explain the proliferation by nainodot; uml;ve T cells in
          response to low-affinity ligands following T-cell depletion.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>The lymphopenic state renders nainodot; uml;ve T cells capable of responding by
            proliferation to peptidendash;MHC complexes that are not stimulatory during normal
            conditions. <b>a</b>, Competition for niches or space on the antigen-presenting cell
            (APC) would be reduced when T-cell numbers are depleted, thereby allowing greater
            accessibility to ligands or growth factors. Such decreased competition for
            non-MHC-derived stimulatory signals such as growth factors or ligands could make signals
            accessible that would allow T cells to detect self-peptidendash;MHC complexes resulting
            in proliferation. It seems improbable that a decrease in direct competition for
            peptidendash;MHC complexes explains the ability of T cells to proliferate in response
            to self-peptidendash;MHC ligands because CD4<super>+</super> and CD8<super>+</super> T
            cells recognize distinct ligands yet appear to occupy largely overlapping homeostatic
            niches. <b>b</b>, T cells could somehow lsquo;sensersquo; a drop in T-cell number. T
            cell/T cell interactions could inhibit proliferation or decrease sensitivity to TCR
            signals. A release from autoinhibition during lymphopenia would allow T cells to receive
            a signal for proliferation following interactions with low-affinity ligands for the TCR.
              <b>c</b>, T-cell loss could be detected by another cell type that would upregulate the
            expression of a factor promoting T-cell division by influencing the T-cell response or
            sensitivity to TCR interactions with low-affinity peptidendash;MHC ligands.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f4" type="bmp" entname="figf4">
        <!--402d006AD-->
        <figtl>Response to infection and the recovery of homeostasis.</figtl>
        <caption>
          <p>The case of the murine CD8<super>+</super> T-cell response to LCMV is depicted. After
            viral infection, nainodot; uml;ve CD8<super>+</super> T cells that recognize LCMV
            epitopes may go through 13 or more divisions within 8 days, producing massive numbers of
            effector cells. When antigen is cleared, most of the effector cells die, leaving an
            expanded population of LCMV-specific T cells, which join the memory pool.</p>
        </caption>
      </fig>
    </objects>
    <bibl>
      <bib id="b1">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zinkernagel</snm>,<fnm>R. M.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Doherty</snm>,<fnm>P. C.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Restriction of <i>in vitro</i> T cell-mediated cytotoxicity in lymphocytic
            choriomeningitis within a syngeneic or semiallogeneic system.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid> 248</vid>, <ppf>701</ppf>ndash;<ppl>710</ppl> (<cd year="1974">1974</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b2">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Babbitt</snm>,<fnm>B. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Allen</snm>,<fnm>P.
              M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Matsueda</snm>,<fnm>G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Haber</snm>,<fnm>E.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Unanue</snm>,<fnm>E. R.
            </fnm></refau>
          <atl>Binding of immunogenic peptides to Ia histocompatibility molecules.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>317</vid>, <ppf>359</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 361</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b3">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Townsend</snm>,<fnm>A. R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Gotch</snm>,<fnm>F. M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Davey</snm>,<fnm>J.
            </fnm></refau>
          <atl>Cytotoxic T cells recognize fragments of the influenza nucleoprotein.</atl>
          <jtl>Cell</jtl>
          <vid>42</vid>, <ppf>457</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 467</ppl> (<cd year="1985">1985</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b4">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Shortman</snm>,<fnm>K.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Wu</snm>,<fnm>L.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Early T lymphocyte progenitors.</atl>
          <jtl> Annu. Rev. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>14</vid>, <ppf>29</ppf>ndash;<ppl>47</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b5">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jameson</snm>,<fnm>S. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Hogquist</snm>,<fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Bevan</snm>,<fnm> M.
              J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Positive selection of thymocytes.</atl>
          <jtl>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>13</vid>, <ppf>93</ppf>ndash;<ppl>126</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b6">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kisielow</snm>,<fnm>P.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm> von
              Boehmer</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Development and selection of T cells: facts and puzzles.</atl>
          <jtl>Adv. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>58</vid>, <ppf> 87</ppf>ndash;<ppl>209</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b7">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Davis</snm>,<fnm>M. M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Bjorkman</snm>,<fnm>P. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>T-cell antigen receptor genes and T-cell recognition.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>334</vid>, <ppf>395</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 402</ppl> (<cd year="1988">1988</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b8">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bjorkman</snm>,<fnm>P. J.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Structure of the human class I histocompatibility antigen,
            HLA-A2.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>329</vid>, <ppf>506</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 512</ppl> (<cd year="1987">1987</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b9">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Brown</snm>,<fnm>J. H.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Three-dimensional structure of the human class II histocompatibility
            antigen HLA-DR1.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>364</vid>, <ppf>33</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 39</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt>
        <natlink extrefid="00000"/>
        <!--364033a0-->
      </bib>
      <bib id="b10">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Scott</snm>,<fnm>C. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Peterson</snm>,<fnm>P. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Teyton</snm>,<fnm>L.
            </fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Wilson</snm>,<fnm>I. A.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> Crystal structures of two I-Ad-peptide complexes reveal that high affinity can be
            achieved without large anchor residues.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid> 8</vid>, <ppf>319</ppf>ndash;<ppl>329</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b11">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Garcia</snm>,<fnm>K. C.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>An alpha beta T cell receptor structure at 2.5thinsp;angst; and its
            orientation in the TCRndash;MHC complex.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid> 274</vid>, <ppf>209</ppf>ndash;<ppl>219</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b12">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Garcia</snm>,<fnm>K. C.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Structural basis of plasticity in T cell receptor recognition of a
            self peptidendash;MHC antigen.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid>279</vid>, <ppf> 1166</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1172</ppl> (<cd year="1998"
          >1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b13">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Garboczi</snm>,<fnm>D. N.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Structure of the complex between human T-cell receptor, viral peptide
            and HLA-A2.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>384</vid>, <ppf>134</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 141</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
        <natlink extrefid="00000"/>
        <!--384134a0-->
      </bib>
      <bib id="b14">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ding</snm>,<fnm>Y. H.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Two human T cell receptors bind in a similar diagonal mode to the
            HLA-A2/Tax peptide complex using different TCR amino acids.</atl>
          <jtl> Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>403</ppf>ndash;<ppl>411</ppl> (<cd year="1998"> 1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b15">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Garcia</snm>,<fnm>K. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Teyton</snm>,<fnm>L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Wilson</snm>,<fnm>I.
            A.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Structural basis of T cell recognition.</atl>
          <jtl> Annu. Rev. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>17</vid>, <ppf>369</ppf>ndash;<ppl>397</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b16">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Teng</snm>,<fnm>M. K.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Identification of a common docking topology with substantial variation
            among different TCRndash;peptidendash;MHC complexes.</atl>
          <jtl> Curr. Biol.</jtl>
          <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>409</ppf>ndash;<ppl>412</ppl> (<cd year="1998"> 1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b17">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fehling</snm>,<fnm>H. J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm> von
              Boehmer</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Early alpha beta T cell development in the thymus of normal and genetically altered
            mice.</atl>
          <jtl>Curr. Opin. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>263</ppf>ndash;<ppl>275</ppl> (<cd year="1997"> 1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b18">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Irving</snm>,<fnm>B. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Alt</snm>,<fnm>F.
              W.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Killeen</snm>,<fnm>N. </fnm></refau>
          <atl>Thymocyte development in the absence of pre-T cell receptor extracellular
            immunoglobulin domains.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid>280</vid>, <ppf> 905</ppf>ndash;<ppl>908</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b19">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zerrahn</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Held</snm>,<fnm>W.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Raulet</snm>,<fnm>D. H.
            </fnm></refau>
          <atl>The MHC reactivity of the T cell repertoire prior to positive and negative
            selection.</atl>
          <jtl>Cell</jtl>
          <vid>88</vid>, <ppf>627</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 636</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b20">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Merkenschlager</snm>,<fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>How many thymocytes audition for selection?</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>186</vid>, <ppf>1149</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1158</ppl> (<cd year="1997"
          >1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b21">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sim</snm>,<fnm>B. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Zerva</snm>,<fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Greene</snm>,<fnm>M. I.</fnm></refau>
          amp; <refau><snm>Gascoigne</snm>,<fnm>N. R. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Control of MHC restriction by TCR Valpha CDR1 and CDR2.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid> 273</vid>, <ppf>963</ppf>ndash;<ppl>966</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b22">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sim</snm>,<fnm>B. C.</fnm></refau>
          <i>et al</i>. <atl>Thymic skewing of the CD4/CD8 ratio maps with the T-cell receptor
            alphachain locus.</atl>
          <jtl>Curr. Biol.</jtl>
          <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>701</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 704</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b23">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>van Meerwijk</snm>,<fnm>J. P. M.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Quantitative impact of thymic clonal deletion on the T cell
            repertoire.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>185</vid>, <ppf>377</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 383</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b24">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Robey</snm>,<fnm>E.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Fowlkes</snm>,<fnm>B. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Selective events in T cell development. </atl>
          <jtl>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>12</vid>, <ppf>675</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 705</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b25">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Nikolic-Zugic</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Bevan</snm>,<fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Role of self-peptides in positively selecting the T-cell repertoire.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid> 344</vid>, <ppf>65</ppf>ndash;<ppl>67</ppl> (<cd year="1990">1990</cd>). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b26">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sha</snm>,<fnm>W. C.</fnm></refau>
          <i>et al</i>. <atl>Positive selection of transgenic receptor-bearing thymocytes by Kb
            antigen is altered by Kb mutations that involve peptide binding.</atl>
          <jtl> Proc. Natl Acad. Sci.</jtl>
          <vid>87</vid>, <ppf>6186</ppf>ndash;<ppl>6190 </ppl> (<cd year="1990"
          >1990</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b27">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Hogquist</snm>,<fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Gavin</snm>,<fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Bevan</snm>,<fnm>M.
            J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Positive selection of CD8<super>+</super> T cells induced by major histocompatibility
            complex binding peptides in fetal thymic organ culture.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>177</vid>, <ppf>1469</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 1473</ppl> (<cd year="1993"
          >1993</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b28">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ashton-Rickardt</snm>,<fnm>P. G.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Van
              Kaer</snm>,<fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Schumacher</snm>,<fnm>T.
            N.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Ploegh</snm>,<fnm>H. L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Tonegawa</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Peptide contributes to the specificity of positive selection of CD8<super>+</super> T
            cells in the thymus.</atl>
          <jtl> Cell</jtl>
          <vid>73</vid>, <ppf>1041</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1049</ppl> (<cd year="1993">
          1993</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b29">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ashton-Rickardt</snm>,<fnm>P. G.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Evidence for a differential avidity model of T cell selection in the
            thymus.</atl>
          <jtl>Cell</jtl>
          <vid>76</vid>, <ppf>651</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 663</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b30">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Hogquist</snm>,<fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>T cell receptor antagonist peptides induce positive selection. </atl>
          <jtl>Cell</jtl>
          <vid>76</vid>, <ppf>17</ppf>ndash;<ppl>27</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b31">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sebzda</snm>,<fnm>E.</fnm></refau>
          <i>et al</i>. <atl>Mature T cell reactivity altered by peptide agonist that induces
            positive selection.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>183</vid>, <ppf>1093 </ppf>ndash;<ppl>1104</ppl> (<cd year="1996"
          >1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b32">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Hogquist</snm>,<fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Jameson</snm>,<fnm>S. C.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Bevan</snm>,<fnm> M.
            J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Strong agonist ligands for the T cell receptor do not mediate positive selection of
            functional CD8<super>+</super> T cells. </atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>3</vid>, <ppf>79</ppf>ndash;<ppl>86</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b33">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Davis</snm>,<fnm>M. M.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Ligand recognition by alpha beta T cell receptors.</atl>
          <jtl> Annu. Rev. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>16</vid>, <ppf>523</ppf>ndash;<ppl>544</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b34">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Alam</snm>,<fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>T-cell-receptor affinity and thymocyte positive selection. </atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>381</vid>, <ppf>558</ppf>ndash;<ppl>559</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
        <natlink extrefid="00000"/>
        <!--381558a0-->
      </bib>
      <bib id="b35">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Hogquist</snm>,<fnm>K. A.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Specific recognition of thymic self-peptides induces the positive
            selection of cytotoxic T lymphocytes.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>7</vid>, <ppf> 221</ppf>ndash;<ppl>231</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b36">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Hu</snm>,<fnm>Q.</fnm></refau>
          <i>et al </i>. <atl>Specific recognition of thymic self-peptides induces the positive
            selection of cytotoxic T lymphocytes.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>7</vid>, <ppf> 221</ppf>ndash;<ppl>231</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b37">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Baldwin</snm>,<fnm>K. K.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Reay</snm>,<fnm>P.
              A.</fnm></refau>, <refau>Wu, <fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Farr</snm>,<fnm>A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Davis</snm>,<fnm>M. M.
            </fnm></refau>
          <atl>A T cell receptor-specific blockade of positive selection. </atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>189</vid>, <ppf>13</ppf>ndash;<ppl>24 </ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b38">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kersh</snm>,<fnm>G. J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Allen</snm>,<fnm>P. M.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Essential flexibility in the T-cell recognition of antigen.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>380</vid>, <ppf>495</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 498</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
        <natlink extrefid="00000"/>
        <!--380495a0-->
      </bib>
      <bib id="b39">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fung-Leung</snm>,<fnm>W. P.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Antigen presentation and T cell development in H2-M-deficient
            mice.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid>271</vid>, <ppf>1278</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 1281</ppl> (<cd year="1996"
          >1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b40">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Martin</snm>,<fnm>W. D.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>H2-M mutant mice are defective in the peptide loading of class II
            molecules, antigen presentation, and T cell repertoire selection.</atl>
          <jtl> Cell</jtl>
          <vid>84</vid>, <ppf>543</ppf>ndash;<ppl>550</ppl> (<cd year="1996"> 1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b41">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Miyazaki</snm>,<fnm>T.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Mice lacking H2-M complexes, enigmatic elements of the MHC class II
            peptide-loading pathway.</atl>
          <jtl>Cell</jtl>
          <vid>84</vid>, <ppf> 531</ppf>ndash;<ppl>541</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b42">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ignatowicz</snm>,<fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Kappler</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Marrack</snm>,<fnm>
            P.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>The repertoire of T cells shaped by a single MHC/peptide ligand.</atl>
          <jtl>Cell</jtl>
          <vid>84</vid>, <ppf>521</ppf>ndash;<ppl>541 </ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b43">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Fukui</snm>,<fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>
          <i>et al</i>. <atl>Positive and negative CD4<super>+</super> thymocyte selection by a
            single MHC class II/peptide ligand affected by its expression level in the thymus.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>6</vid>, <ppf>401</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 410</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b44">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Grubin</snm>,<fnm>C. E.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Kovats</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>deRoos</snm>,<fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
          amp; <refau><snm>Rudensky</snm>,<fnm>A. Y.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Deficient positive selection of CD4 T cells in mice displaying altered repertoires of
            MHC class II-bound self-peptides.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>197</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 208</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b45">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tourne</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
          <i>et al</i>. <atl>Selection of a broad repertoire of CD4<super>+</super> T cells in
            H-2Ma0/0 mice.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>187</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 195</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b46">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Surh</snm>,<fnm>C. D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Lee</snm>,<fnm>D.
              S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fung-Leung</snm>,<fnm>W. P. </fnm></refau>,
              <refau><snm>Karlsson</snm>,<fnm>L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Sprent</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Thymic selection by a single MHC/peptide ligand produces a semidiverse repertoire of
              CD4<super>+</super> T cells.</atl>
          <jtl> Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>209</ppf>ndash;<ppl>219</ppl> (<cd year="1997"> 1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b47">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sant'Angelo</snm>,<fnm>D. B.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>The imprint of intrathymic self-peptides on the mature T cell receptor
            repertoire.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>7</vid>, <ppf>517</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 524</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b48">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Barton</snm>,<fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Rudensky</snm>,<fnm>A. Y.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Requirement for diverse, low-abundance peptides in positive selection of T
            cells.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid> 283</vid>, <ppf>67</ppf>ndash;<ppl>70</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b49">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Davey</snm>,<fnm>G. M.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Preselection thymocytes are most sensitive to T cell receptor
            stimulation than mature T cells.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>188</vid>, <ppf> 1867</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1874</ppl> (<cd year="1998"
          >1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b50">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lucas</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Stefanova</snm>,<fnm>I.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Yasutomo</snm>,<fnm>K.
            </fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Dautigny</snm>,<fnm>N.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Germain</snm>,<fnm>R. N.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Divergent changes in the sensitivity of maturing T cells to structurally related
            ligands underlies formation of a useful T cell repertoire.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>10</vid>, <ppf> 367</ppf>ndash;<ppl>376</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b51">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tanchot</snm>,<fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Rosado</snm>,<fnm>M.
              M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Agenes</snm>,<fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Freitas</snm>,<fnm>A. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Rocha</snm>,<fnm>
            B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Lymphocyte homeostasis.</atl>
          <jtl>Semin. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid> 9</vid>, <ppf>331</ppf>ndash;<ppl>337</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b52">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Mombaerts</snm>,<fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Mutations in T-cell antigen receptor genes alpha and beta block
            thymocyte development at different stages.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid> 360</vid>, <ppf>225</ppf>ndash;<ppl>231</ppl> (<cd year="1992">1992</cd>). </reftxt>
        <natlink extrefid="00000"/>
        <!--360225a0-->
      </bib>
      <bib id="b53">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kitamura</snm>,<fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Roes</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kuhn</snm>,<fnm>R.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Rajewsky</snm>,<fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>A B-cell deficient mouse by targeted disruption of the membrane exon of the
            immunoglobulin mu chain gene.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>350</vid>, <ppf>423</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 426</ppl> (<cd year="1991">1991</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b54">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bender</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Mitchell</snm>,<fnm>T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Kappler</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
          amp; <refau><snm>Marrack</snm>,<fnm>P.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>CD4<super>+</super> T cell division in irradiated mice requires peptides distinct
            from those responsible for thymic selection.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>190</vid>, <ppf> 367</ppf>ndash;<ppl>374</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b55">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tanchot</snm>,<fnm>C.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Rocha</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>The peripheral T cell repertoire: independent homeostatic regulation of virgin and
            activated CD8<super>+</super> T cell pools.</atl>
          <jtl>Eur. J. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>25</vid>, <ppf>2127</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 2136</ppl> (<cd year="1995"
          >1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b56">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rocha</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Dautigny</snm>,<fnm>N.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Pereira</snm>,<fnm>
            P.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Peripheral T lymphocytes: expansion potential and homeostatic regulation of pool
            sizes and CD4/CD8 ratios <i>in vivo</i>.</atl>
          <jtl>Eur. J. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>19</vid>, <ppf>905</ppf>ndash;<ppl>911</ppl> (<cd year="1989">1989</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b57">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Ernst</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
            Lee</snm>,<fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
          <refau><snm>Chang</snm>,<fnm>J. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
            Sprent</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Surh</snm>,<fnm>C. D.
            </fnm></refau>
          <atl>The peptide ligands mediating positive selection in the thymus control T cell
            survival and homeostatic proliferation in the periphery. </atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>173</ppf>ndash;<ppl>181</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b58">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Berzins</snm>,<fnm>S. P.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Boyd</snm>,<fnm>R.
              L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Miller</snm>,<fnm>J. F. A. P.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>The role of the thymus and recent thymic migrants in the maintenance of the adult
            peripheral lymphocyte pool.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>187</vid>, <ppf>1839</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1848</ppl> (<cd year="1998"
          >1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b59">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tanchot</snm>,<fnm>C.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Rocha</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Peripheral selection of T cell repertoires: the role of continuous thymus
            output.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid> 186</vid>, <ppf>1099</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1106</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b60">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bell</snm>,<fnm>E. B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Sparshott</snm>,<fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Drayson</snm>,<fnm> M.
            T.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Ford</snm>,<fnm>W. L.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> The stable and permanent expansion of functional T lymphocytes in athymic nude rats
            after a single injection of mature T cells.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Immunol. </jtl>
          <vid>139</vid>, <ppf>1379</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1384</ppl> (<cd year="1987">
          1987</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b61">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sprent</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> Lifespans of naive, memory and effector lymphocytes.</atl>
          <jtl>Curr. Opin. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>433</ppf>ndash;<ppl>438</ppl> (<cd year="1993"> 1993</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b62">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sprent</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Schaefer</snm>,<fnm>M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Hurd</snm>,<fnm>M.</fnm></refau>,
              <refau><snm> Surh</snm>,<fnm>C. D.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Ron</snm>,<fnm>Y.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> Mature murine B and T cells transferred to SCID mice can survive indefinitely and
            many maintain a virgin phenotype.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid> 174</vid>, <ppf>717</ppf>ndash;<ppl>728</ppl> (<cd year="1991">1991</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b63">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tough</snm>,<fnm>D. F</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Sprent</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Turnover of naive- and memory-phenotype T cells.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>179</vid>, <ppf>1127</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 1135</ppl> (<cd year="1994"
          >1994</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b64">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>von Boehmer</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Hafen</snm>,<fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>The life span of naive alpha;/beta; T cells in secondary lymphoid organs.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>177</vid>, <ppf>891</ppf>ndash;<ppl>896</ppl> (<cd year="1993"> 1993</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b65">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bruno</snm>,<fnm>L.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> von
              Boehmer</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Kirberg</snm>,<fnm>
            J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Cell division in the compartment of naive and memory T lymphocytes.</atl>
          <jtl>Eur. J. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>26</vid>, <ppf>3179 </ppf>ndash;<ppl>3184</ppl> (<cd year="1996"
          >1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b66">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kuo</snm>,<fnm>C. T.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Veselitis</snm>,<fnm>M.
              L.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Leiden</snm>,<fnm> J. M.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>LKLF: a transcriptional regulator of single-positive T cell quiescence and
            survival.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid>277</vid>, <ppf> 1986</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1990</ppl> (<cd year="1997"
          >1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b67">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oukka</snm>,<fnm>M.</fnm></refau>
          <i>et al</i>. <atl>The transcription factor NFAT4 is involved in the generation and
            survival of T cells.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>295 </ppf>ndash;<ppl>304</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b68">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Lodolce</snm>,<fnm>J. P.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>IL-15 receptor maintains lymphoid homeostasis by supporting lymphocyte
            homing and proliferation.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>9</vid>, <ppf> 669</ppf>ndash;<ppl>676</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b69">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Nakajima</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Shores</snm>,<fnm>E.
              W.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Noguchi</snm>,<fnm>M.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Leonard</snm>,<fnm>W. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>The common cytokine receptor gamma;nbsp;chainnbsp;plays an essential role in
            regulating lymphoid homeostasis.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>185</vid>, <ppf>189</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 195</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b70">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Veis</snm>,<fnm>D. J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Sorenson</snm>,<fnm>C.
              M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Shutter</snm>,<fnm>J. R.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Korsmeyer</snm>,<fnm>S. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> Bcl-2-deficient mice demonstrate fulminant lymphoid apoptosis, polycystic kidneys,
            and hypopigmented hair.</atl>
          <jtl>Cell</jtl>
          <vid>75</vid>, <ppf> 229</ppf>ndash;<ppl>240</ppl> (<cd year="1993">1993</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b71">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Freitas</snm>,<fnm>A. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Rocha</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Peripheral T cell survival.</atl>
          <jtl> Curr. Opin. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>152</ppf>ndash;<ppl>156</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b72">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kirber</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Berns</snm>,<fnm>A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>von Boehmer</snm>,<fnm>
            H.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Peripheral T cell survival requires continual ligation of the T cell receptor to
            major histocompatibility complex-encoded molecules. </atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>186</vid>, <ppf>1269</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 1275</ppl> (<cd year="1997"
          >1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b73">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Takeda</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Rodewald</snm>,<fnm>H.-R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Arakawa</snm>,<fnm>H.
            </fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Bluethmann</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Shimizu</snm>,<fnm>T.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>MHC class II molecules are not required for survival of newly generated
              CD4<super>+</super> T cells, but affect their long-term life span.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>5</vid>, <ppf>217</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 228</ppl> (<cd year="1996">1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b74">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Brocker</snm>,<fnm>T.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> Survival of mature CD4 T lymphocytes is dependent on major histocompatibility
            complex class II-expressing dendritic cells.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid> 186</vid>, <ppf>1223</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1232</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b75">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Rooke</snm>,<fnm>R.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Waltzinger</snm>,<fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Benoist</snm>,<fnm>C.
            </fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Mathis</snm>,<fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> Targeted complementation of MHC class II deficiency by intrathymic delivery of
            recombinant adenoviruses.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>7</vid>, <ppf> 123</ppf>ndash;<ppl>134</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b76">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Tanchot</snm>,<fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Lemonnier</snm>,<fnm>F. A.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Perarnau</snm>,<fnm>
            B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Freitas</snm>,<fnm>A. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Rocha</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Differential requirements for survival and proliferation of CD8 naive or memory T
            cells.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl>
          <vid> 276</vid>, <ppf>2057</ppf>ndash;<ppl>2062</ppl> (<cd year="1997">1997</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b77">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Murali-Krishna</snm>,<fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Persistence of memory CD8 T cells in MHC class I deficient mice.</atl>
          <jtl>Science</jtl> (in the press). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b78">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Nesic</snm>,<fnm>D.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Vukmanovic</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>MHC class I is required for peripheral accumulation of CD8<super>+</super> thymic
            emigrants.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Immunol. </jtl>
          <vid>160</vid>, <ppf>3705</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3712</ppl> (<cd year="1998">
          1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b79">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bell</snm>,<fnm>E. B.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Sparshott</snm>,<fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Drayson</snm>,<fnm> M.
            T.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Hunt</snm>,<fnm>S. V.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> The origin of T cells in permanently reconstituted old athymic nude rats. Analysis
            using chromosome or allotype markers.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunology</jtl>
          <vid> 68</vid>, <ppf>547</ppf>ndash;<ppl>556</ppl> (<cd year="1989">1989</cd>). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b80">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>McDonagh</snm>,<fnm>M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Bell</snm>,<fnm>E. B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>The survival and turnover of mature and immature CD8 T cells.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunology</jtl>
          <vid>84</vid>, <ppf> 514</ppf>ndash;<ppl>520</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b81">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Pereira</snm>,<fnm>P.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Rocha</snm>,<fnm>B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Post-thymic <i>in vivo</i> expansion of mature alpha;beta; T cells.</atl>
          <jtl>Int. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>3</vid>, <ppf> 1077</ppf>ndash;<ppl>1080</ppl> (<cd year="1991">1991</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b82">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Oehen</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Brduscha-Riem</snm>,<fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Naive cytotoxic T lymphocytes spontaneously acquire effector function in
            lymphocytopenic recipients: A pitfall for T cell memory studies?</atl>
          <jtl>Eur. J. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>29</vid>, <ppf> 608</ppf>ndash;<ppl>614</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b83">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sprent</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Surh</snm>,<fnm>C.
              D.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Tough</snm>,<fnm>D. </fnm></refau>
          <atl>Fate of T and B cells transferred to SCID mice.</atl>
          <jtl> Res. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>145</vid>, <ppf>328</ppf>ndash;<ppl>331</ppl> (<cd year="1994">1994</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b84">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Bell</snm>,<fnm>E. B.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Sparshott</snm>,<fnm>S. M.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>The peripheral T-cell pool: regulation by non-antigen induced proliferation?</atl>
          <jtl>Semin. Immunol. </jtl>
          <vid>9</vid>, <ppf>347</ppf>ndash;<ppl>353</ppl> (<cd year="1997"> 1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b85">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Mackall</snm>,<fnm>C. L.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Thymic-independent T cell regeneration occurs via antigen-driven
            expansion of peripheral T cells resulting in a repertoire that is limited in diversity
            and prone to skewing.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>156</vid>, <ppf> 4609</ppf>ndash;<ppl>4616</ppl> (<cd year="1996"
          >1996</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b86">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Viret</snm>,<fnm>C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Wong</snm>,<fnm>F.
              S.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Janeway</snm>,<fnm> C. S.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Designing and maintaining the mature TCR repertoire: the continuum of
            self-peptide:self-MHC complex recognition.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity </jtl>
          <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>559</ppf>ndash;<ppl>568</ppl> (<cd year="1999"> 1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b87">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Beutner</snm>,<fnm>U.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              MacDonald</snm>,<fnm>H. R.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>TCRndash;MHC class II interaction is required for peripheral expansion of CD4 cells
            in a T cell-deficient host. </atl>
          <jtl>Int. Immun.</jtl>
          <vid>10</vid>, <ppf>305</ppf>ndash;<ppl>310 </ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b88">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Kieper</snm>,<fnm>W. C.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Jameson</snm>,<fnm>S. C.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Homeostatic expansion and phenotypic conversion of naive T cells in response to self
            peptide/MHC ligands.</atl>
          <jtl> Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</jtl> (in the press). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b89">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Goldrath</snm>,<fnm>A. W.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Bevan</snm>,<fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Low affinity ligands for the TCR drive proliferation of mature CD8<super>+</super> T
            cells in lymphopenic hosts.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>11</vid>, <ppf>183</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 190</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b90">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Markiewicz</snm>,<fnm>M. A.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Long-term T cells memory requires the surface expression of
            self-peptide/major histocompatibility complex molecules.</atl>
          <jtl>Proc. Natl Acad. Sic. USA</jtl>
          <vid>95</vid>, <ppf>3065</ppf>ndash;<ppl>3070</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b91">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Garcia</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              DiSanto</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Stockinger</snm>,<fnm>
            B.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Following the development of a CD4 T cell immune response <i> in vivo</i>: from
            activation to memory formation.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid> 11</vid>, <ppf>163</ppf>ndash;<ppl>171</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b92">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Swain</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
            Hui</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Huston</snm>,<fnm>G.</fnm></refau>
          <atl> Class II-independent generation of CD4 memory T cells from effectors.</atl>
          <jtl> Science</jtl> (in the press).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b93">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Butz</snm>,<fnm>E. A.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Bevan</snm>,<fnm>M. J.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Massive expansion of antigen-specific CD8<super>+</super> T cells during an acute
            virus infection.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity </jtl>
          <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>167</ppf>ndash;<ppl>175</ppl> (<cd year="1998"> 1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b94">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Murali-Krishna</snm>,<fnm>K.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Counting antigen-specific CD8 T cells: a reevaluation of bystander
            activation during viral infection.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>8</vid>, <ppf> 177</ppf>ndash;<ppl>187</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b95">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Busch</snm>,<fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Pilip</snm>,<fnm>I.
              M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Vijh</snm>,<fnm>S.</fnm></refau> amp;
              <refau><snm>Pamer</snm>,<fnm>E. G.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Coordinate regulation of complex T cell populations responding to bacterial
            infection.</atl>
          <jtl> Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>8</vid>, <ppf>353</ppf>ndash;<ppl>362</ppl> (<cd year="1998"> 1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b96">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Callan</snm>,<fnm>M. F.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Direct visualization of antigen-specific CD8<super>+</super> T cells
            during the primary immune response to Epsteinndash;Barr virus <i> in vivo</i>.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid>187</vid>, <ppf>1395</ppf>ndash;<ppl> 1402</ppl> (<cd year="1998"
          >1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b97">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Cose</snm>,<fnm>S. C.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm> Jones</snm>,<fnm>C.
              M.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Wallace</snm>,<fnm>M. E. </fnm></refau>,
              <refau><snm>Heath</snm>,<fnm>W. R.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Carbone</snm>,<fnm>F. R.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Antigen-specific CD8<super>+</super> T cell subset distribution in lymph nodes
            draining the site of herpes simplex virus infection.</atl>
          <jtl>Eur. J. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid>27</vid>, <ppf>2310 </ppf>ndash;<ppl>2316</ppl> (<cd year="1997"
          >1997</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b98">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Flynn</snm>,<fnm>K. J.</fnm></refau>
          <i> et al</i>. <atl>Virus-specific CD8<super>+</super> T cells in primary and secondary
            influenza pneumonia.</atl>
          <jtl>Immunity</jtl>
          <vid>8</vid>, <ppf> 683</ppf>ndash;<ppl>691</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b99">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Zimmermann</snm>,<fnm>C.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Pircher</snm>,<fnm>H.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>A novel approach to visualize polyclonal virus-specific CD8 T cells <i>in
            vivo</i>.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Immunol.</jtl>
          <vid> 162</vid>, <ppf>5178</ppf>ndash;<ppl>5182</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).
        </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b100">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Busch</snm>,<fnm>D. H.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Pilip</snm>,<fnm>I.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>Pamer</snm>,<fnm>E. G.
            </fnm></refau>
          <atl>Evolution of a complex T cell receptor repertoire during primary and recall bacterial
            infection.</atl>
          <jtl>J. Exp. Med.</jtl>
          <vid> 188</vid>, <ppf>61</ppf>ndash;<ppl>70</ppl> (<cd year="1998">1998</cd>). </reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b101">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Jacob</snm>,<fnm>J.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Baltimore</snm>,<fnm>D.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Modelling T-cell memory by genetic marking of memory T cells <i>in vivo</i>.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature</jtl>
          <vid>399 </vid>, <ppf>593</ppf>ndash;<ppl>597</ppl> (<cd year="1999">1999</cd>).</reftxt>
        <natlink extrefid="00000"/>
        <!--399593a0-->
      </bib>
      <bib id="b102">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Razvi</snm>,<fnm>E. S.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Jiang</snm>,<fnm>Z.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Woda</snm>,<fnm>B. A.</fnm></refau>
          amp; <refau><snm>Welsh</snm>,<fnm>R. M.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Lymphocyte apoptosis during the silencing of the immune response to acute viral
            infections in normal, Ipr, and Bcl-2-transgenic mice.</atl>
          <jtl>Am. J. Pathol.</jtl>
          <vid>147</vid>, <ppf> 79</ppf>ndash;<ppl>91</ppl> (<cd year="1995">1995</cd>).</reftxt>
      </bib>
      <bib id="b103">
        <reftxt><refau><snm>Sallusto</snm>,<fnm>F.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>
              Lenig</snm>,<fnm>D.</fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Fouml;rster</snm>,<fnm>R.
            </fnm></refau>, <refau><snm>Lipp</snm>,<fnm>M.</fnm></refau> amp; <refau><snm>
              Lanzavecchia</snm>,<fnm>A.</fnm></refau>
          <atl>Two subsets of memory T lymphocytes with distinct homing potentials and effector
            functions.</atl>
          <jtl>Nature </jtl>
          <vid>401</vid>, <ppf>708</ppf>ndash;<ppl>712</ppl> (<cd year="1999"> 1999</cd>).</reftxt>
        <natlink extrefid="00000"/>
        <!--401708a0-->
      </bib>
    </bibl>
  </bm>
</article>
<?Pub *0000094238?>
