<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">Characterization of human acid sphingomyelinase purified from the media of overexpressing Chinese hamster ovary cells</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Elsevier Science B.V.</publisher>
            <date>1999</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <licence>
                  <p>full-transfer</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename type="first">Xingxuan</forename>
                        <surname>He</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <affiliation>
                        <orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
                        <address>
                           <addrLine>Box 1498</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>1425 Madison Avenue</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Room 14-20A</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>New York</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>NY 10029</addrLine>
                           <country key="US">UNITED STATES</country>
                        </address>
                     </affiliation>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename type="first">Silvia R.P</forename>
                        <surname>Miranda</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <affiliation>
                        <orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
                        <address>
                           <addrLine>Box 1498</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>1425 Madison Avenue</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Room 14-20A</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>New York</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>NY 10029</addrLine>
                           <country key="US">UNITED STATES</country>
                        </address>
                     </affiliation>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename type="first">Xiaoling</forename>
                        <surname>Xiong</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <affiliation>
                        <orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
                        <address>
                           <addrLine>Box 1498</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>1425 Madison Avenue</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Room 14-20A</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>New York</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>NY 10029</addrLine>
                           <country key="US">UNITED STATES</country>
                        </address>
                     </affiliation>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename type="first">Arie</forename>
                        <surname>Dagan</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <affiliation>
                        <orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
                        <orgName type="institution">Hebrew University-Hadassah School of Medicine</orgName>
                        <address>
                           <addrLine>Jerusalem</addrLine>
                           <country key="IL">ISRAEL</country>
                        </address>
                     </affiliation>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename type="first">Shimon</forename>
                        <surname>Gatt</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <affiliation>
                        <orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry</orgName>
                        <orgName type="institution">Hebrew University-Hadassah School of Medicine</orgName>
                        <address>
                           <addrLine>Jerusalem</addrLine>
                           <country key="IL">ISRAEL</country>
                        </address>
                     </affiliation>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename type="first">Edward H</forename>
                        <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                     </persName>
                     <email>schuchman@msvax.mssm.edu</email>
                     <affiliation>
                        <orgName type="department">Department of Human Genetics</orgName>
                        <address>
                           <addrLine>Box 1498</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>1425 Madison Avenue</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>Room 14-20A</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>New York</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>NY 10029</addrLine>
                           <country key="US">UNITED STATES</country>
                        </address>
                     </affiliation>
                     <affiliation>
                        <orgName type="department">Institute for Gene Therapy and Molecular Medicine</orgName>
                        <orgName type="department">Mount Sinai School of Medicine</orgName>
                        <address>
                           <addrLine>New York</addrLine>
                           <addrLine>NY 10029</addrLine>
                           <country key="US">UNITED STATES</country>
                        </address>
                     </affiliation>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Characterization of human acid sphingomyelinase purified from the media of overexpressing Chinese hamster ovary cells</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j" type="abbrev">BBAPRO</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date type="Accepted" when="1999-03-11"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0167-4838(99)00069-2</idno>
               <idno type="PII">S0167-4838(99)00069-2</idno>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <abstract>
            <p>A rapid purification method was developed to isolate milligram quantities of human acid sphingomyelinase from the media of overexpressing Chinese hamster ovary cells.
                    The purified, recombinant enzyme (rhASM) had physical and kinetic characteristics that were consistent with those reported for the non-recombinant enzyme, including an acidic pH
                    optimum and sensitivity to sulfhydryl reducing reagents and the zinc specific chelator, 1,10-phenanthroline. A novel assay using fluorescently conjugated sphingomyelin was
                    developed to explore the substrate binding properties of rhASM. Substrate binding required a fatty acid chain length of at least six carbons and the presence of the phosphocholine
                    headgroup on sphingomyelin. Substrate binding also required an acidic pH, and was inhibited by pretreatment of the enzyme with sulfhydral reducing reagents or 1,10-phenanthroline.
                    rhASM was rapidly internalized by cultured skin fibroblasts from Niemann-Pick disease (NPD) patients, and ∼50% of this uptake was dependent on the mannose 6-phosphate
                    receptor system. Studies using FITC-labeled rhASM revealed that by 1 h the internalized enzyme was localized to acidic compartments and could degrade sphingomyelin, the first
                    demonstration that a lysosomal sphingolipid hydrolase can be fluorescently labeled and retain its biological activity. Intravenous injection of rhASM into ASM knock-out mice showed
                    that the <hi rend="italic">t</hi>
               <hi rend="subscript">1/2</hi> in the plasma was less than 5 min, and that the majority of the injected enzyme was taken up by the liver, followed by the
                    spleen. Thus, these studies lay the foundation for future structure/function investigations of ASM, further investigations into this enzyme’s role in ceramide mediated
                    signal transduction, and the evaluation of enzyme replacement therapy for NPD using the mouse model.</p>
            <p>A rapid purification method was developed to isolate milligram quantities of human acid sphingomyelinase from the media of overexpressing Chinese hamster ovary cells.
                    The purified, recombinant enzyme (rhASM) had physical and kinetic characteristics that were consistent with those reported for the non-recombinant enzyme, including an acidic pH
                    optimum and sensitivity to sulfhydryl reducing reagents and the zinc specific chelator, 1,10-phenanthroline. A novel assay using fluorescently conjugated sphingomyelin was
                    developed to explore the substrate binding properties of rhASM. Substrate binding required a fatty acid chain length of at least six carbons and the presence of the phosphocholine
                    headgroup on sphingomyelin. Substrate binding also required an acidic pH, and was inhibited by pretreatment of the enzyme with sulfhydral reducing reagents or 1,10-phenanthroline.
                    rhASM was rapidly internalized by cultured skin fibroblasts from Niemann-Pick disease (NPD) patients, and ∼50% of this uptake was dependent on the mannose 6-phosphate
                    receptor system. Studies using FITC-labeled rhASM revealed that by 1 h the internalized enzyme was localized to acidic compartments and could degrade sphingomyelin, the first
                    demonstration that a lysosomal sphingolipid hydrolase can be fluorescently labeled and retain its biological activity. Intravenous injection of rhASM into ASM knock-out mice showed
                    that the <hi rend="italic">t</hi>
               <hi rend="subscript">1/2</hi> in the plasma was less than 5 min, and that the majority of the injected enzyme was taken up by the liver, followed by the
                    spleen. Thus, these studies lay the foundation for future structure/function investigations of ASM, further investigations into this enzyme’s role in ceramide mediated
                    signal transduction, and the evaluation of enzyme replacement therapy for NPD using the mouse model.</p>
         </abstract>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>
                Lysosomal enzyme
            </term>
               <term>
                Niemann-Pick disease
            </term>
               <term>
                Knock-out mice
            </term>
               <term>
                Enzyme therapy
            </term>
               <term>
                Sphingomyelinase
            </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>
                ASM, acid sphingomyelinase
            </term>
               <term>
                ASMKO, acid sphingomyelinase knock-out mice
            </term>
               <term>
                bSmase, bacterial sphingomyelinase
            </term>
               <term>
                CHO, Chinese hamster ovary cells
            </term>
               <term>
                DTT, dithiothreitol
            </term>
               <term>
                Endo H, endoglycosylase H
            </term>
               <term>
                GC, glucosyl ceramide
            </term>
               <term>
                LR-SPM, lissamine rhodamine conjugated sphingomyelin
            </term>
               <term>
                L-SMase, intracellular, lysosomal sphingomyelinase
            </term>
               <term>
                M6P, mannose 6-phosphate
            </term>
               <term>
                NCM, nitrocellulose membrane
            </term>
               <term>
                NPD, Niemann-Pick disease
            </term>
               <term>
                PNG-F, peptide-<hi rend="italic">N</hi>-glycanase F
            </term>
               <term>
                rhASM, recombinant human acid sphingomyelinase
            </term>
               <term>
                S-SMase, secreted acid sphingomyelinase
            </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="1998-12-14">Received</change>
         <change when="1999-03-11">Revised</change>
         <change when="1999-03-11">Accepted</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="ElsevierSections">
            <div n="1">
               <head>Introduction</head>
               <p>Acid sphingomyelinase (sphingomyelin phosphodiesterase, E.C. 3.1.4.12; ASM) is the lysosomal enzyme which hydrolyzes sphingomyelin into ceramide and phosphocholine
                        <ref target="#BIB1 #BIB2">[1,2]</ref>. In man, a deficiency of this enzymatic activity leads to the type A and B forms of Niemann-Pick disease (NPD)
                        <ref target="#BIB3">[3]</ref>. Type A NPD is a severe, neuronopathic disorder which leads to death by 3 years of age. In contrast, patients with type B NPD have
                    little or no neurologic involvement and may survive into adolescence or adulthood. No treatment is available for either form of NPD. Mice in which the ASM gene has been inactivated
                    by gene targeting have been constructed (ASMKO mice), and the phenotype is intermediate between the human type A and B patients <ref target="#BIB4 #BIB5">[4,5]</ref>. Affected animals appear normal at birth, develop neurologic symptoms by 3–4 months of age, and usually die during the sixth or seventh
                    month.</p>
               <p>Human ASM has been purified from a variety of sources and extensively characterized (e.g. <ref target="#BIB6 #BIB7 #BIB8">[6–8]</ref>). The full-length
                    cDNA and genomic sequences encoding human and murine ASM also have been isolated and characterized <ref target="#BIB9 #BIB10 #BIB11 #BIB12">[9–12]</ref>. The
                    human cDNA sequence predicted a 629 amino acid polypeptide containing six <hi rend="italic">N</hi>-glycosylation sites. Site directed mutagenesis revealed that five of these sites
                    were utilized <ref target="#BIB13">[13]</ref>, predicting a molecular weight of ∼70 kDa for the fully glycosylated protein after cleavage of the signal
                    peptide region (assuming a molecular weight of ∼2 kDa per <hi rend="italic">N</hi>-linked oligosaccharide). Biosynthetic studies in cultured skin fibroblasts have suggested
                    that ASM is synthesized as a 75 kDa precursor that is processed into several smaller molecular weight species (e.g. 72, 67 and 57 kDa) within lysosomes <ref target="#BIB14">[14]</ref>. Small amounts of the precursor and 57 kDa forms also were immunoprecipitated from the culture medium. The precise subunit structure of ASM is
                    unknown.</p>
               <p>Until recently, it was assumed that ASM was released from cells at very low levels. However, Schissel et al. showed in 1996 that some cell types release ASM at high levels,
                    and that the secreted enzyme (also known as S-SMase) required zinc cations to become activated <ref target="#BIB15">[15]</ref>. This activity resembled the zinc
                    activated ASM activity described more than a decade ago in bovine and human serum <ref target="#BIB16">[16]</ref>. Interestingly, the addition of zinc to the
                    intracellular ASM (also known as L-SMase) had little or no effect on its activity. Despite these differences, both forms of the enzyme were derived from the same primary transcript
                    and both were deficient in cells from NPD patients. Subsequent studies confirmed these observations and showed that S-SMase had a distinct <hi rend="italic">N</hi>-glycosylation
                    pattern and N-terminal amino acid sequence as compared to L-SMase, and that L-SMase, while not stimulated by zinc, could be inactivated by treatment with the zinc-specific
                    chelator, 1,10-phenanthroline <ref target="#BIB17">[17]</ref>. A definitive role for S-SMase has not been established, however the existence of this enzyme form may
                    explain the data of several laboratories indicating that ASM is involved in ceramide mediated signal transduction events at or near the cell surface (e.g. <ref target="#BIB18 #BIB19">[18,19]</ref>).</p>
               <p>The current paper describes the purification and characterization of recombinant human ASM from the media of overexpressing CHO cells, as well as experiments carried out in
                    NPD cells and ASMKO mice suggesting that the secreted enzyme may be therapeutically useful for the treatment of NPD patients. These data provide important information concerning
                    the basic biology of this hydrolase and lay the foundation for the future structure/function studies and the development of enzyme replacement therapy for NPD.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
               <head>Materials and methods</head>
               <div n="2.1">
                  <head>Materials</head>
                  <p>Tissue culture media and other tissue culture reagents were purchased from either Life Technologies (Baltimore, MD) or Gibco-BRL (Gaithersburg, MD), with the exception of
                        fetal bovine serum (FBS), which was obtained from Hyclone Laboratories (Logan, UT). Tissue culture plasticware and all organic solvents were purchased from the Fisher
                        Scientific Co. (Springfield, NJ). DEAE Sephacel, concanavalin A- Sepharose, and Superose 12 were purchased from Pharmacia Biotech. (Piscataway, NJ). Precast 4–20%
                        gradient polyacrylamide gels were from Novex (San Diego, CA). Nitrocellulose membranes were from Schleicher and Schuell (Keene, NH). T-gel absorbent for purifying IgG was from
                        Pierce Chemical (Rockford, IL). Peroxidase conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG and the protein calibration kit were purchased from Boehringer Mannheim (Indianapolis, IN). A Western
                        blot chemiluminescence detection kit was from DuPont NEN (Boston, MA). The protein assay kit was purchased from Bio-Rad (Hercules, CA). All other biochemical reagents were from
                        Sigma (St. Louis, MO).</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2.2">
                  <head>Construction of CHO cells overexpressing human ASM</head>
                  <p>The full-length human ASM cDNA was inserted into the p91023(B) expression vector <ref target="#BIB20 #BIB21">[20,21]</ref>, kindly provided by Dr. Randall
                        Kaufmann. After electroporation into dihydrofolate reductase negative (<hi rend="italic">dhfr</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">−</hi>) DG44 Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells, stably
                        transfected clones were selected for their ability to grow in medium containing 10% dialyzed FBS, but lacking hypoxanthine (0.05 mM) and thymidine (0.008 mM). Non-transfected
                            <hi rend="italic">dhfr</hi>
                     <hi rend="superscript">−</hi> DG44 cells require these supplemental reagents in order to grow. Over 100 surviving colonies were isolated in this
                        manner, expanded, and then plated in medium containing 0.02 μM methotrexate. After 2 weeks of growth in this medium, surviving clones were isolated, expanded, and placed
                        into medium containing 0.1 μM methotrexate. A similar selection/expansion procedure was used to eventually isolate 15 clones which survived in medium containing 100
                        μM methotrexate. Of these, one clone, designated CHO 18, was selected for further analysis based on its high ASM activity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2.3">
                  <head>Purification of human ASM from the overexpressing CHO 18 medium</head>
                  <p>The procedure described below summarizes the typical purification of human ASM from 100 ml of CHO 18 medium harvested every 18–24 h from a CELLMAX 100 bioreactor
                        system (CellCo, Germantown, MD). In cases where the medium was collected over several days and pooled prior to purification (up to a total volume of 1 l), the materials
                        indicated below were increased proportionately.</p>
                  <div n="2.3.1">
                     <head>Step 1: DEAE Sephacel 1</head>
                     <p>100 ml of medium (CM-100) was centrifuged at 1000×<hi rend="italic">g</hi> to remove debris, and then slowly passed through a 50 ml DEAE Sephacel column
                            previously equilibrated with 10×bed volume of DEAE wash buffer (40 mM Tris-HCl, 0.1 mM ZnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, 0.1% Igepal CA-630, pH 7.2). The column was then
                            placed on a rocking platform for 90 min at room temperature. The unbound proteins were collected by allowing the solution to pass through the column by gravity, and then
                            stored at 4°C. An additional 20% bed volume of wash buffer was then passed through the column and this material was combined with the original eluate. The unbound
                            proteins were concentrated 5–10-fold (to a final concentration of ∼2 mg/ml) at 4°C using a Centriprep 30 column.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2.3.2">
                     <head>Step 2: DEAE Sephacel 2</head>
                     <p>The concentrated material was loaded onto a second DEAE Sephacel column (sample:bed volume ratio, 1:1) previously equilibrated with 10×bed volume of DEAE wash
                            buffer. The procedure described above was repeated, and the unbound proteins were again collected and stored at 4°C.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2.3.3">
                     <head>Step 3: concanavalin A-Sepharose (Con A)</head>
                     <p>The concentrated material was slowly added to a Con A column (sample:bed volume ratio, 1:2) which had been equilibrated with 10×bed volume of Con A wash buffer
                            (10 mM Tris-HCl, 500 mM NaCl, 1 mM CaCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, 1 mM MgCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, 1 mM MnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, 0.1% Igepal CA-630, and 0.02% NaN<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>, pH
                            7.2). The column was placed on a shaker platform for 90 min at room temperature, and then attached to an FPLC (FPLC-500; Pharmacia Biotech, Piscataway, NJ). The washing,
                            pre-elution and elution steps were carried out with Con A wash buffer, pre-elution buffer (Con A wash buffer containing 10 mM
                                methyl-α-<hi rend="smallCaps">d</hi>-glucopyranoside), and elution buffer (Con A wash buffer containing 1 M
                            methyl-α-<hi rend="smallCaps">d</hi>-glucopyranoside), respectively, and monitored using a UV detector. The flow rates were maintained at ∼60, 30 and 5
                            ml/h during the washing, pre-elution and elution steps, respectively. The protein peak was collected during the elution step, concentrated to less than 10 ml using a
                            Centriprep 30 column, and dialyzed overnight at 4°C against 20 mM Tris-HCl containing 0.1 mM ZnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, pH 7.2. The next day, the dialyzed material was
                            concentrated again to 2–3 ml and stored at 4°C.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2.3.4">
                     <head>Step 4: Superose 12 gel filtration</head>
                     <p>The dialyzed and concentrated Con A eluate was filtered (0.2 μm) and loaded onto a 106 ml Superose 12 column (1.6×53 cm, XK16/70, Pharmacia) equilibrated
                            with 5×bed volume of running buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1 mM ZnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, 0.02% NaN<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>, pH 7.2). The flow rate was maintained
                            at 0.2 ml/min. The eluate was collected in 1 ml fractions after the void volume (37 ml). The fractions were stored at 4°C and checked for ASM activity and protein
                            content before being pooled.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2.4">
                  <head>ASM and protein assays</head>
                  <p>ASM activity was routinely detected using a fluorescent sphingomyelin derivative, lissamine rhodamine sphingomyelin (LR12-SPM) <ref target="#BIB22">[22]</ref>. Cells were harvested and sonicated in 0.2% Triton X-100 on ice using three 10 s bursts with 1 min intervals (Sonifier Cell Disruptor 200; Branson
                        Sonic Power Company, CL). The homogenates were then centrifuged at 10 000×<hi rend="italic">g</hi> for 5 min. The standard 6 μl ASM assay mixture consisted
                        of 3 μl of this supernatant and 0.6 nmol of LR12 SPM suspended in 0.1 M sodium acetate buffer, pH 5.0, containing 0.6% Triton X-100 and 0.1 mM ZnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>.
                        Assays were generally carried out at 37°C for 30 min. After the reactions were complete, the assay mixtures were loaded onto thin layer chromatography (TLC) plates (TLC
                        LK6 D Silica gel 60, Whatman, Clifton, NJ), resolved in chloroform:methanol:water (80:19:1) for 15 min, dried, and visualized using a fluorescent lamp. Quantification was
                        carried out by determining the signal strength of the product (LR12-ceramide) using the NIH Image 1.68K software. Total protein was determined using the Bio-Rad protein assay
                        kit according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2.5">
                  <head>SDS-PAGE analysis and Western blotting procedure</head>
                  <p>Duplicate samples were boiled in loading buffer (12 mM Tris-HCl, 0.5% SDS, 5 mM β-mercaptoethanol, 5% glycerol, 0.02% bromophenol blue, pH 6.8) for 10 min, loaded
                        onto 4–20% gradient polyacrylamide gels, and electrophoresed in an XCELL II mini-cell apparatus (Novex, San Diego, CA) for 1 h. The voltage was maintained at 150 and the
                        running buffer contained 0.1% SDS. Following electrophoresis, one gel was stained in 0.1% Coomassie blue solution (methanol/glacial acetic acid/water, 9:2:9) for 5 min, and
                        then destained in methanol/glacial acetic acid/water (1:1:8). The other gel was electrotransferred to a nitrocellulose membrane (50 volts for 1 h) using a Blot Module apparatus
                        (Novex, San Diego, CA).</p>
                  <p>For immunoblotting, the nitrocellulose membrane was incubated overnight at 4°C with 5% nonfat dry milk in buffer A (4 mM Tris-HCl, 0.5 mM NaCl, pH 7.4), and then
                        incubated with rabbit anti-human ASM IgGs (1:5000 dilution) in buffer B (buffer A containing 3% nonfat dry milk, 0.1% Tween-20, and 0.1% bovine serum albumin) for 1 h at room
                        temperature. The anti-ASM antibodies were raised against a preparation of purified FLAG-tagged ASM, and have been reported previously <ref target="#BIB17">[17]</ref>. After washing four times with buffer A containing 0.1% Tween-20, the blot was incubated with horseradish peroxidase conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgGs
                        (1:2000 dilution) for 1 h in buffer B at room temperature. The membrane was subsequently washed twice with 0.3% Tween-20 in buffer A and then twice more with 0.1% Tween-20 in
                        buffer B. Finally, the blot was soaked in an enhanced chemiluminescence reagent (DuPont NEN) for 1 min and exposed to X-ray film for 10 s to 2 min.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2.6">
                  <head>Deglycosylation studies</head>
                  <p>To evaluate the effects of various glycosidases on the purified rhASM, 10 μg of the enzyme was added to a 50 μl reaction mixture containing endoglycosylase H
                        (Endo H) (10 mU), peptide-<hi rend="italic">N</hi>-glycanase F (PNG-F) (2000 mU), or sialidase (100 mU). Each reaction buffer was made up of 50 mM sodium acetate containing
                        0.1% <hi rend="italic">n</hi>-octylglucoside, with the pH adjusted to 5.0, 5.5, and 6.5, respectively for the three enzymes. After a 16 h incubation at 37°C, a small
                        portion of each reaction was removed to determine ASM activity (see above), while the remainder was boiled in SDS/dithiothreitol (DTT), electrophoresed on a 4–20%
                        Tris-glycine polyacrylamide gel, and stained with Coomassie blue.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2.7">
                  <head>Substrate binding assay</head>
                  <p>3 μg of purified rhASM was spotted onto a strip of nitrocellulose membrane (NCM) equilibrated with buffer C (20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.0). The air-dried NCM was then
                        rotated in blocking buffer (5% dry milk and 0.1% BSA in buffer C; see immunoblotting procedure, above) at room temperature for 30 min, washed with water twice, transferred to
                        0.2 M potassium acetate buffer (pH 4.0) containing 3 mM of the lissamine rhodamine derivatives (LR0, LR6, and LR12 SPM, and LR12-ceramide) and 0.2% Triton X-100, and incubated
                        at room temperature for 10 min. The NCM was then treated with washing buffer (0.2% Tween-20 in buffer A) at room temperature for at least 2 h, and the fluorescence signal was
                        quantified using the NIH Image 1.68K software. As negative controls, the NCM membranes were also spotted with either BSA or recombinant human β-glucosidase (Cerezyme,
                        Genzyme Corp.).</p>
                  <p>To evaluate the effects of DTT and 1,10-phenanthroline on substrate binding, 3 μg of purified human ASM was pretreated with 1 and 10 mM DTT or 1,10-phenanthroline
                        at 4°C for 2 h, respectively, prior to incubation with LR12 SPM. To evaluate the pH specificity of substrate binding, 3 μg of purified human ASM or a neutral
                        sphingomyelinase from <hi rend="italic">Bacillus cereus</hi> (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) were spotted onto the NCM, and the filters were then incubated with LR12-SPM in either 0.2 M
                        potassium acetate buffer, pH. 4.0 or 0.2 M Tris-HCl, pH 8.0 containing 0.2% Triton X-100.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2.8">
                  <head>Preparation of FITC-labeled ASM</head>
                  <p>500 μg of rhASM (in a total volume of 350 μl) was diluted with 1.4 ml of PBS at 4°C, and 1 mg of solid FITC (isomer I, Sigma, St. Louis, MO) was
                        added. The mixture was agitated slowly for 24 h at 4°C, lyophilized, and then resuspended in 1 ml of 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.0. After brief centrifugation
                            (1000×<hi rend="italic">g</hi> for 5 min), the protein was loaded onto a PD-10 column linked to an FPLC (Pharmacia Biotech., Piscataway, NJ). The protein peak was
                        monitored using a UV detector, collected and concentrated to ∼1 mg/ml using the Ultrafree-4 filtration system (Millipore, Bedford, MA). The optical density of the
                        concentrated protein was then measured using a spectrophotometer (Ultraspec 2000, Pharmacia Biotech., Piscataway, NJ) at a wavelength of 494 nm, and based on the molecular
                        extinction coefficient of FITC, it was determined that this solution contained 54 nmol/ml of FITC. Since it also contained 12 nmol/ml of rhASM, it could be estimated that each
                        mol of rhASM contained ∼4-5 mol of FITC.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2.9">
                  <head>Enzyme uptake studies</head>
                  <div n="2.9.1">
                     <head>Uptake of non-fluorescent ASM</head>
                     <p>Primary human fibroblast cultures from a type A NPD patient and a normal control were maintained in serum-free DMEM medium for 24 h. The medium was then changed to
                            DMEM containing 0.2% BSA and 10 μg of purified rhASM, with and without the addition of mannose 6-phosphate (M6P, 1, 10 or 100 mM) (Sigma, St Louis, MO). After 24 h,
                            the cells were trypsinized, washed three times in PBS, and homogenized in 0.2% Triton X-100 on ice using three 10-second bursts of a Potter-Elvehjem homogenizer (Thomas
                            Scientific, Sweedesboro, NJ). The total protein and ASM activity were measured as described above.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2.9.2">
                     <head>Uptake of fluorescent ASM and fluorescence microscopy</head>
                     <p>Primary mouse fibroblasts were grown on coverslips in DMEM containing 10% FBS. 0.1 nmol/ml (final concentration) of pH sensitive LR12-glucosyl ceramide (GC) or
                            LR12-SPM was added to the medium for 16 h. The medium was then removed, the cells were washed 3× with PBS, and medium containing 1.5 μg of FITC-ASM was added
                            for an additional 1 h. The use of these pH sensitive lipid derivatives that only fluoresce in acidic compartments has been described previously <ref target="#BIB23 #BIB24">[23,24]</ref>. The cells were washed 3× with PBS, fixed in 10% formalin for 10 min at room temperature, and mounted in antifade
                            medium (0.01 M Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, containing 20 mg of triethylenediamine. Fluorescence microscopy was performed using a Nikon fluorescence microscope.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2.10">
                  <head>In vivo enzyme uptake studies</head>
                  <p>Six ASMKO (6–8 weeks old) mice were injected intravenously with a single dose of the purified human ASM (2 μg/g of body weight). Peripheral blood was
                        obtained by retinal orbit bleeding at various time points after the enzyme injection, plasma was isolated, and the ASM activity was measured by the methods described above. At
                        the end of the 60 min blood sampling, the animals were killed by cervical dislocation, tissues were collected, and immediately frozen on dry ice for subsequent enzyme
                        analysis.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
               <head>Results</head>
               <div n="3.1">
                  <head>Purification of human ASM from overexpressing CHO cells</head>
                  <p>A clonal population of DG44 CHO cells overexpressing human ASM were obtained using the p91023(B) expression vector and methotrexate selection <ref target="#BIB20 #BIB21">[20,21]</ref>. This clone, designated CHO 18, had intracellular ASM activities that were up to ∼70-fold higher than those found in the
                        parental CHO cells, and activity in the medium that was up to 700-fold higher than the parental cells <ref target="#BIB15 #BIB17">[15,17]</ref>. The addition
                        of zinc cations was required to detect the markedly enhanced activity in the medium, but not in the cell extracts <ref target="#BIB15 #BIB17">[15,17]</ref>.</p>
                  <p>A purification method was developed to rapidly isolate the secreted, recombinant human ASM (rhASM) from the media of these cells (<ref target="#TBL1">Table
                            1</ref>
                     <ptr target="#TBL1"/>). The purification scheme consisted of four steps; the first two ion exchange chromatography steps were performed in
                        ‘batch’, i.e. by mixing the enzyme solutions with the gel matrix, followed by bulk elutions (see <ref target="#SEC1">Section 2</ref> for details).
                        The final two steps were performed using an FPLC. To obtain large amounts of enzyme, the cells were routinely grown in a CELLMAX 100 bioreactor system. ∼100 ml of medium
                        (CM-100) was harvested from the extracellular capillary space each day, ZnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> (final concentration 0.1 mM) was added, and the enzyme solution was then stored
                        at 4°C for up to 1 week. When ∼1 liter of medium was collected, the purification procedure was performed. ZnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> was routinely added to the medium
                        since it had been shown to enhance the secreted ASM enzymatic activity <ref target="#BIB15 #BIB17">[15,17]</ref>, and also stabilized the activity upon storage
                        at 4°C (not shown).</p>
                  <p>As can be seen in <ref target="#TBL1">Table 1</ref>, the final enrichment of the ASM enzymatic activity was ∼100-fold and the final yield was
                        ∼13%. The most efficient steps in this procedure used DEAE Sephacel; almost none of the rhASM bound to this matrix, while many other proteins in the media did, including
                        most of the serum albumin. Thus, more than a 30-fold enrichment of the enzyme could be achieved using these steps, with no loss of activity. Indeed, the amount of rhASM
                        activity detected after the two DEAE Sephacel steps was slightly higher than before, suggesting that either an inhibiting compound was removed by this procedure or a compound
                        which interfered with the assay system.</p>
                  <p>
                     <ref target="#FIG1">Fig. 1</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG1"/> depicts SDS-PAGE (panel A) and Western blotting (panel B) analyses at various stages of
                        purification. The degree of enrichment achieved throughout the purification procedure is evident, particularly from the Western blot. At the final stage of purification
                        (post-Superose 12), a single, ∼75 kDa Coomassie blue staining band was observed (<ref target="#FIG1">Fig. 1A</ref>), which cross-reacted with polyclonal
                        antibodies raised against a purified, FLAG tagged ASM <ref target="#BIB17">[17]</ref> (<ref target="#FIG1">Fig. 1B</ref>). A minor ∼60
                        kDa band also reacted with the antibodies in some of the rhASM preparations and could occasionally be seen after silver staining, but usually represented less than 2% of the
                        total protein. Using this purification procedure, ∼5 mg of rhASM could be routinely obtained from ∼1 l of culture medium within 3 days.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3.2">
                  <head>Physical and kinetic characterization of rhASM</head>
                  <p>The purified enzyme followed Michaelis-Menten kinetics using radioactive or fluorescent SPM as a substrate, and had a peak activity at pH 4.5 (not shown). Treatment of the
                        enzyme with sulfhydryl reducing reagents or the zinc specific chelator, 1,10-phenanthroline <ref target="#BIB25">[25]</ref>, led to a marked loss of enzymatic
                        activity in a concentration and time-dependent fashion (<ref target="#FIG2 #FIG3">Figs. 2 and 3</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG2"/>
                     <ptr target="#FIG3"/>). Treatment of the purified enzyme with Endo H, PNG-F or sialidase revealed the presence of complex or hybrid type oligosaccharide chains containing sialic
                        acid residues and the lack of high mannose containing oligosaccharides (<ref target="#FIG4">Fig. 4</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG4"/>). Similar results have
                        been reported previously for the ASM secreted from non-transfected CHO cells, while the carbohydrate chains on the L-SMase were mostly of the high mannose type <ref target="#BIB17">[17]</ref>. Together, these data confirm previous observations on the properties of this hydrolase and support the notion that the human enzyme
                        purified from the media of the overexpressing CHO cells is biologically active, resembles the native enzyme, and could be useful therapeutically in NPD patients (see
                        below).</p>
                  <p>To investigate the substrate binding properties of the purified enzyme further, we developed a novel assay using fluorescently conjugated SPM derivatives. We believe that
                        this assay system primarily measures substrate binding, as opposed to hydrolysis, since most of the experiment was carried out in water at room temperature (optimal hydrolysis
                        of SPM by rhASM requires a buffered solution around pH 4.5 and incubation at 37°C). Indeed, the enzyme and substrate were only incubated together at pH 4.5 for a short
                        time (10 min) at room temperature, precluding the possibility of significant hydrolysis. Moreover, the intensity of the fluorescent signal bound to the immobilized enzyme after
                        washing the NCM was similar to that observed after the initial preincubation with substrate (data not shown). If substantial hydrolysis had occurred during the 2 h wash period,
                        this signal would have been significantly decreased.</p>
                  <p>As shown in <ref target="#FIG5">Fig. 5A</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG5"/>, when LR12-SPM was incubated with purified rhASM which had been immobilized on
                        a nitrocellulose membrane, it bound tightly to the enzyme at pH 4.0, but not at pH 8.0, consistent with the fact that this substrate was readily degraded by rhASM at an acidic
                        pH. Similar findings were observed using several other fluorescent SPM substrates (data not shown), indicating that this result was not dependent on the fluorescent moiety. In
                        contrast, bacterial sphingomyelinase (bSMase), which has a neutral pH optimum, bound LR12-SPM at pH 8.0, but not pH 4.0 (<ref target="#FIG5">Fig.
                        5A</ref>).</p>
                  <p>The purified enzyme was then incubated at pH 4.0 with LR0-SPM, LR6-SPM, and LR12-ceramide (<ref target="#FIG5">Fig. 5B</ref>). Note that optimal binding
                        occurred with LR12-SPM, intermediate binding was observed with LR6-SPM, and no substrate binding was observed with LR0-SPM. This finding was consistent with the fact that
                        LR0-SPM could not be hydrolyzed by rhASM, and that the hydrolysis of LR6-SPM was less than that of LR12-SPM (data not shown). LR12-ceramide did not bind to the purified enzyme
                        as well. Interestingly, pretreated of rhASM with 1,10-phenanthroline or DTT inhibited binding of LR12-SPM in a concentration dependent fashion (<ref target="#FIG6">Fig.
                            6</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG6"/>), consistent with the inhibitory effects of these reagents on enzymatic activity. Thus, it likely that the reason
                        1,10-phenanthroline inhibits ASM activity is that zinc is required for efficient substrate binding. The specificity of this binding assay was further demonstrated by the fact
                        that the LR12-SPM could not bind to immobilized recombinant human β-glucosidase.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3.3">
                  <head>Enzyme uptake properties of rhASM</head>
                  <p>The uptake properties of the purified enzyme were examined using cultured type A NPD skin fibroblasts. As shown in <ref target="#FIG7">Fig.
                            7</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG7"/>, addition of rhASM to the medium of NPD cells led to a marked increase in intracellular enzymatic activity within 16 h.
                        Indeed, the amount of activity detected within these cells was almost 2–3-fold greater than that found in normal cells. Addition of M6P to the medium inhibited enzyme
                        uptake ∼50%.</p>
                  <p>To determine whether the purified enzyme that was taken up by cells could degrade SPM, rhASM was labeled with FITC by linking the fluorescent probe to free amino groups
                        (see <ref target="#SEC1">Section 2</ref> for details). This modified, fluorescent form of the enzyme retained all of its catalytic activity in an in vitro assay
                        system (not shown), and was added to cultured NPD skin fibroblasts alone, or to cells that had been preloaded with pH sensitive LR12-SPM or LR12-GC as a negative control
                            (<ref target="#FIG8">Fig. 8</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG8"/>). These substrates are readily taken up by cells and only fluoresce in acidic compartments
                            <ref target="#BIB23 #BIB24">[23,24]</ref>. Note that after 1 h of labeling both substrates can be seen in small vesicles spread throughout the cytoplasm.
                        Importantly, these vesicles appear yellow in cells that were treated with both the FITC-ASM and pH sensitive LR12-GC (which cannot be degraded by the recombinant ASM),
                        indicating colocalization to the same compartments. In cells colabeled with FITC-ASM and LR12-SPM, most of the vesicles appear green, indicating that the SPM has been degraded
                        by the recombinant enzyme and that the product, pH sensitive LR12-ceramide, translocated out of lysosomes to non-acidic compartments where it loses its fluorescence.</p>
                  <p>Based on these results, rhASM was injected intravenously into ASMKO mice (<ref target="#FIG9">Fig. 9</ref>
                     <ptr target="#FIG9"/>). Within 5 min,
                        almost all of the activity was absent from the plasma (<ref target="#FIG9">Fig. 9A</ref>). This was not due to inhibition of the enzyme by plasma components
                        since incubation with plasma from ASMKO mice for up to 1 h at 37°C had no effect on the enzymatic activity (<ref target="#FIG9">Fig. 9A</ref>, inset).
                        When tissues of the treated animals were analyzed for the presence of the ASM activity 1 h after the injection, most of the activity was found in the liver, followed by small
                        amounts in the spleen, heart, and kidney (<ref target="#FIG9">Fig. 9B</ref>).</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4">
               <head>Discussion</head>
               <p>Since it was first identified as the enzymatic defect in NPD in the late 1960s, ASM has been the subject of much research. While important progress has resulted from these
                    efforts, structural information is still lacking for this enzyme and essential features governing its catalytic activity remain unknown. In part, this is due to the fact that it is
                    expressed in low quantities in most natural sources, and highly purified enzyme has been difficult to obtain in large enough quantities to pursue many research goals. This same
                    limitation has also prevented the evaluation of enzyme replacement therapy for the treatment of NPD. The recent identification of ASM’s role in ceramide mediated signal
                    transduction has stimulated renewed interest in this hydrolase and highlighted the need for additional reagents to facilitate large-scale production, purification, and
                    characterization. This manuscript reports the development of such a reagent, and documents many features of the human enzyme secreted from genetically engineered CHO cells. A
                    recent report also has documented overexpression of rhASM in insect Sf21 cells <ref target="#BIB26">[26]</ref>.</p>
               <p>CHO 18 cells exhibited a remarkable degree of ASM overexpression in the media and in cells. A rapid and simple purification procedure was developed which permitted the
                    isolation of milligram quantities of rhASM from the CHO 18 medium within several days. ZnCl<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> was routinely added to the media and maintained in most of
                    purification buffers since zinc cations not only enhanced the activity of the secreted ASM, but also stabilized its activity upon storage at 4°C. This observation was
                    consistent with other reports studying secreted ASM (S-SMase) from several different cell types <ref target="#BIB15 #BIB17">[15,17]</ref>. SDS-PAGE analysis
                    revealed that the purified enzyme migrated as a single, diffuse band with an <hi rend="italic">M</hi>
                  <hi rend="subscript">r</hi> of ∼75 kDa. Occasionally, a minor ∼60 kDa band
                    representing 2% or less of the total protein also was visible by protein staining or on Western blots. The relative amount of this form increased depending on how long the medium
                    was stored at 4°C prior to purification (not shown), suggesting that it was a degradation product due to protease and/or glycosylase digestion.</p>
               <p>The focus of our efforts was to characterize the properties of the ASM secreted from the overexpressing cells, rather than the intracellular activity, since this form of the
                    enzyme was easily purified away from the medium components and could be obtained in large quantities for therapeutic evaluation. It should be noted that FLAG-tagged rhASM also has
                    been purified from the media of transfected CHO cells, as well as a lysosome enriched intracellular fraction <ref target="#BIB17">[17]</ref>. That work concluded
                    that the two enzyme forms (i.e. secreted and intracellular) underwent distinct trafficking events based on their unique N-terminal sequences and
                    <hi rend="italic">N</hi>-glycosylation patterns. It was further hypothesized that the intracellular, L-SMase was exposed to cellular zinc during trafficking to lysosomes or in
                    lysosomes (explaining why it was not zinc stimulated), while the S-SMase was sequestered from the cellular pools of zinc and therefore required exogenous zinc for complete
                    activation.</p>
               <p>The secreted rhASM characterized in this paper also was zinc-activated and had a molecular weight (∼75 kDa) similar to what has been reported previously for the
                    secreted FLAG-tagged rhASM. It also had many features of human ASM purified from natural sources, including an acidic pH optimum and cross-reactivity with anti-human ASM polyclonal
                    antibodies. The <hi rend="italic">M</hi>
                  <hi rend="subscript">r</hi> was slightly higher than that reported for human ASM purified from human urine and spleen (∼68–72 kDa), but
                    was consistent with the fact that the secreted enzyme was probably a precursor form. The secretion of such precursor forms has been reported previously for several other lysosomal
                    enzymes produced in similar overexpression systems (e.g. <ref target="#BIB27">[27]</ref>).</p>
               <p>To investigate the substrate specificity of the purified enzyme further, we developed a novel, substrate binding assay. Purified rhASM was immobilized on nitrocellulose
                    membranes and incubated with a fluorescent SPM derivative, LR12-SPM, a substrate which is known to be degraded efficiently by ASM from a variety of enzyme sources (e.g.
                        <ref target="#BIB22">[22]</ref>). LR12-SPM binding was pH dependent, consistent with the fact that rhASM has a sharp pH optimum of ∼4.5, and could be
                    inhibited by pretreatment of the enzyme with sulfhydryl reducing reagents or 1,10-phenanthroline. It is notable that a recent report showed that ASM secreted from CHO cell medium
                    could hydrolyze SPM presented in the context of a lipoprotein particle at neutral pH <ref target="#BIB28">[28]</ref>. On the surface, this result may appear
                    contradictory to the findings reported here regarding the pH dependence of substrate binding, however the reaction conditions, substrates used, and purity of the ASM being analyzed
                    were completely different in these two studies, precluding their direct comparison.</p>
               <p>Of note, three other lissamine rhodamine derivatives were tested for their ability to bind rhASM: LR0 and LR6-SPM, and LR12-ceramide. LR0-SPM has the lissamine rhodamine
                    moiety linked directly to the sphingosine backbone, while the LR6 and LR12-ceramide compounds have lissamine rhodamine conjugated via 6 or 12 carbon linkers. LR12-ceramide is the
                    product of LR12-SPM hydrolysis by ASM, and lacks the phosphocholine moiety of sphingomyelin.</p>
               <p>The results of these studies suggested that a fatty acid moiety containing at least six, and more optimally 12 carbons, is required to achieve efficient binding and
                    degradation of sphingomyelin by ASM and that the phosphocholine moiety is essential for substrate binding, suggesting that after hydrolysis of sphingomyelin by ASM, the ceramide
                    produced is released rapidly from the enzyme for further metabolism.</p>
               <p>Investigating some of these features further, we performed an alignment of the amino acid sequences of human and murine ASM, and two ASM sequences obtained from
                        <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>
                    <ref target="#BIB29">[29]</ref>. Of note, 14 of the 16 cysteine residues in human ASM were completely conserved among man, mouse and <hi rend="italic">C.
                        elegans</hi>. Also of interest, a point mutation at one of these conserved cysteine residues (C431 in human ASM), is known to inactivate ASM and lead to NPD (unpublished
                    observation). Cysteine residues, which are important in the formation of intra and/or intermolecular disulfide bonds, also can be involved in zinc binding, as are histidine
                    residues. Of the 18 histidine residues in human ASM, six are completely conserved among man, mouse and <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi>. Mutations causing NPD are known to occur
                    at H425 and H575, and one of these (H425), is within a sequence of five amino acids that is completely conserved. Furthermore, near H425 is another histidine, H421, which is
                    conserved in several zinc metalloenzymes, including a cGMP specific phosphodiesterase <ref target="#BIB30">[30]</ref>, and is also conserved among human, mouse, and
                    one of the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> ASM sequences. Intriguingly, the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> sequence in which H421 is conserved is zinc activated, while the
                    other is not <ref target="#BIB29">[29]</ref>.</p>
               <p>The usefulness of rhASM for the development and evaluation of enzyme replacement therapy for NPD also was studied. Cell culture experiments revealed that the enzyme was
                    rapidly taken up by NPD skin fibroblasts, and that this uptake could be partially inhibited by the addition of M6P to the culture medium. Previous studies have shown that
                    50–70% of rhASM released into the medium of the overexpressing CHO 18 cells binds to a M6P receptor column, consistent with these findings <ref target="#BIB17">[17]</ref>. Moreover, studies reported in this manuscript using Endo H and PNG-F confirmed that this purified form of ASM lacks high mannose containing
                    oligosaccharides and consists of mainly complex and hybrid type carbohydrates. Thus, it appears from these results that while M6P targeting is the primary mechanism by which rhASM
                    is taken up by cells, it is not the only mechanism. This is consistent with previous observations <ref target="#BIB14">[14]</ref>.</p>
               <p>The recombinant enzyme also was fluorescently labeled with FITC and the fluorescent enzyme was shown to be internalized by cells, localized in acidic compartments, and able to
                    degrade SPM in these compartments. To our knowledge this is the first demonstration that a lysosomal sphingolipid hydrolase could be fluorescently labeled and retain its biological
                    activity. The rhASM also was intravenously injected into ASMKO mice, and its clearance from the circulation was monitored. Within 5 min after the injection virtually all of the
                    activity was absent from the plasma. This observation was not due to inactivation by plasma proteases or pH, since incubation of the enzyme with plasma at 37°C for up to 1 h
                    did not lead to inactivation. Moreover, most of the injected activity could be recovered in the liver, followed by small amounts in the spleen, heart and kidney. Since the Kupffer
                    cells of the liver (and to a lesser degree the hepatocytes) are an important site of pathology in NPD, these results suggest that enzyme replacement may be a useful approach for
                    the treatment of patients who do not have major central nervous system involvement (i.e. type B NPD). Studies designed to evaluate this therapeutic approach in the ASMKO mice are
                    currently under way.</p>
               <p>Thus, the data reported in this paper should be of importance to both basic scientists studying the biology of ASM and to researchers involved in the development of enzyme
                    replacement therapy for NPD and other storage diseases. The construction of the CHO 18 overexpressing cell line and the purification methods described within have already provided
                    new reagents and information concerning this enzyme, and it is anticipated that they will lead to interesting new areas of research investigation.</p>
            </div>
        </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>This work was supported by Grants from the National Institutes of Health (HD 28607), March of Dimes Birth Defects Foundation (1-224) and US-Israel Binational Science Foundation
                (93-00015), as well as a Grant (RR 0071) from the National Center for Research Resources for the Mount Sinai General Clinical Research Center. The authors wish to acknowledge the
                expert technical assistance of Mrs. Robyn Cotter, as well as Drs. Ira Tabas (Columbia University) and Dieter Bromme (Mount Sinai School of Medicine) for their insightful
                comments.</p>
        </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="references">
            <head>References</head>
            <listBibl>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB1" n="[1]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kanfer</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">O.M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Young</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Shapiro</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.O.</forename>
                                    <surname>Brady</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">241</biblScope>
                        <date when="1966">1966</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="1081">1081</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="1084">1084</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB2" n="[2]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">Y.</forename>
                                    <surname>Barenholz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Roitman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gatt</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">241</biblScope>
                        <date when="1966">1966</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="3731">3731</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="3737">3737</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <bibl xml:id="BIB3" n="[3]">
                        E.H. Schuchman, R.J. Desnick, in: C.R. Scriver, A.L. Beaudet, W.S. Sly, D. Valle (Eds.), The Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease, McGraw-Hill, New
                            York, 1995, pp. 2601–2624.
                    </bibl>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB4" n="[4]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Horinuchi</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Erlich</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Perl</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ferlinz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">C.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bisgaier</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sandhoff</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Desnick</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">C.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Stewart</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Nature Genet.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">10</biblScope>
                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="288">288</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="294">294</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB5" n="[5]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Otterback</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Stoffel</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Cell</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">81</biblScope>
                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="1053">1053</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="1060">1060</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB6" n="[6]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Callahan</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Khalil</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">754</biblScope>
                        <date when="1975">1975</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="82">82</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="88">88</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB7" n="[7]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Yamanaka</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Neurochem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">38</biblScope>
                        <date when="1982">1982</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="1753">1753</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="1759">1759</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB8" n="[8]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Quintern</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Weitz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Nehrkorn</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tager</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">A.W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schram</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sandhoff</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">922</biblScope>
                        <date when="1987">1987</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="323">323</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="329">329</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB9" n="[9]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Suchi</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sandhoff</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Desnick</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">66</biblScope>
                        <date when="1991">1991</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="8531">8531</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="8539">8539</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB10" n="[10]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">O.</forename>
                                    <surname>Levran</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Desnick</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Genomics</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">12</biblScope>
                        <date when="1992">1992</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="197">197</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="205">205</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB11" n="[11]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Newrzella</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Stoffel</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Biol. Chem. Hoppe-Seyler</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">373</biblScope>
                        <date when="1992">1992</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="1233">1233</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="1236">1236</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB12" n="[12]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Horinouchi</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sakiyama</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Pereira</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">P.A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lalley</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Genomics</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">18</biblScope>
                        <date when="1993">1993</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="450">450</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="451">451</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB13" n="[13]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ferlinz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hurwitz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Moczall</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lansmann</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sandhoff</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Eur. J. Biochem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">243</biblScope>
                        <date when="1997">1997</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="511">511</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="517">517</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB14" n="[14]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hurwitz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ferlinz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Vielhaber</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Moczall</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sandhoff</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">269</biblScope>
                        <date when="1994">1994</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="5440">5440</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="5445">5445</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB15" n="[15]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schissel</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tabas</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">271</biblScope>
                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="18431">18431</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="18436">18436</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB16" n="[16]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Spence</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">D.M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Byers</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">F.B.St.C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Palmer</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">H.W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Cook</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">264</biblScope>
                        <date when="1989">1989</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="5358">5358</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="5363">5363</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB17" n="[17]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schissel</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">G.A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Keesler</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tabas</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">273</biblScope>
                        <date when="1998">1998</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="18250">18250</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="18259">18259</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB18" n="[18]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Cifone</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Roncanioli</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>De Maria</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Camarda</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Santoni</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ruberti</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Testi</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">EMBO J.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">14</biblScope>
                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="5859">5859</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="5868">5868</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB19" n="[19]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Santana</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">L.A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Pena</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Haimovitz-Friedman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Martin</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Green</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>McLaughlin</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Cordon-Cardo</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">Z.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fuks</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kolesnick</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Cell</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">86</biblScope>
                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="189">189</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="200">200</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB20" n="[20]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kaufman</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Methods Enzymol.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">185</biblScope>
                        <date when="1990">1990</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="487">487</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="511">511</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB21" n="[21]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kaufman</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Methods Enzymol.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">185</biblScope>
                        <date when="1990">1990</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="537">537</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="566">566</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB22" n="[22]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">P.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Yeyati</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">V.</forename>
                                    <surname>Agmon</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fillat</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Dinur</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Dagan</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Desnick</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gatt</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schuchman</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Hum. Gene Ther.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">6</biblScope>
                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="975">975</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="982">982</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB23" n="[23]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marchesini</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gatt</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">V.</forename>
                                    <surname>Agmon</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Giudici</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Monti</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Biochem. Int.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">27</biblScope>
                        <date when="1992">1992</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="545">545</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="550">550</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <bibl xml:id="BIB24" n="[24]">
                        L. Mader-Shapiro, T. Dinur, A. Dagan, S. Gatt, M. Horwitz, J. Inher. Metab. Dis. (in press).
                    </bibl>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB25" n="[25]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Little</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">A.B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Otnass</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">391</biblScope>
                        <date when="1975">1975</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="326">326</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="333">333</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB26" n="[26]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">O.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bartelsen</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lansmann</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Nettersheim</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lemm</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ferlinz</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sandhoff</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biotechnol.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">63</biblScope>
                        <date when="1998">1998</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="29">29</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="40">40</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB27" n="[27]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">Y.A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ioannou</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">D.F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bishop</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Desnick</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Cell Biol.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">119</biblScope>
                        <date when="1992">1992</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="1137">1137</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="1150">1150</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB28" n="[28]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schissel</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">X.</forename>
                                    <surname>Jiang</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tweedie-Hardman</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Jeong</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">E.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Camejo</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Najib</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Rapp</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">K.J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tabas</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">30</biblScope>
                        <date when="1998">1998</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="2738">2738</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="2746">2746</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB29" n="[29]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">X.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lin</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">M.O.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hengartner</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kolesnick</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">273</biblScope>
                        <date when="1998">1998</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="14374">14374</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="14379">14379</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="BIB30" n="[30]">
                  <analytic>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">S.H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Francis</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Colbran</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">L.M.</forename>
                                    <surname>McAllister-Lucas</surname>
                                </author>
                                <author>
                                    <forename type="first">J.D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Corbin</surname>
                                </author>
                            </analytic>
                  <monogr>
                     <title type="main">J. Biol. Chem.</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">269</biblScope>
                        <date when="1994">1994</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="22477">22477</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" to="22480">22480</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
