<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "http://www.rsc.org/dtds/rscart36.dtd">
<article dtd="RSCPA3.6" type="ART" price-code="free">
<art-admin>
<ms-id>P19950000635</ms-id>
<doi>10.1039/P19950000635</doi>
</art-admin>
<published type="print">
<journalref>
<link>P1</link>
</journalref>
<volumeref>
<link>
</link>
</volumeref>
<issueref>
<link>6</link>
</issueref>
<pubfront>
<fpage>635</fpage>
<lpage>640</lpage>
<no-of-pages>6</no-of-pages>
<date>
<year>1995</year>
</date>
</pubfront>
</published>
<published type="subsyear">
<journalref>
<link>P1</link>
</journalref>
<pubfront>
<fpage>
</fpage>
<lpage>
</lpage>
<no-of-pages>
</no-of-pages>
<date>
<year>1995</year>
</date>
</pubfront>
</published>
<art-front>
<titlegrp>
<title>Low-temperature addition of hydrogen polysulfides to olefins: formation of 2,2&prime;-dialkyl polysulfides from alk-1-enes and cyclic (poly)sulfides and polymeric organic sulfur compounds from &alpha;,&omega;-dienes</title>
</titlegrp>
<authgrp>
<author>
<person>
<persname>
<fname>Wim</fname>
<surname>de Graaf</surname>
</persname>
</person>
</author>
<author>
<person>
<persname>
<fname>Jaap S. Sinninghe</fname>
<surname>Damst&eacute;</surname>
</persname>
</person>
</author>
<author>
<person>
<persname>
<fname>Jan W.</fname>
<surname>de Leeuw</surname>
</persname>
</person>
</author>
</authgrp>
<abstract>
<p>Hydrogenpolysulfide ions, generated by the reaction of hydrogensulfide ions and elemental sulfur, react in a polar organic solvent with alk-1-enes and alka-&alpha;,&omega;-dienes under very mild conditions: 20&ndash;50 &deg;C for 1&ndash;10 days. The reagent was prepared either in DMF with Na<sup>+</sup> as counter-ion (method A) or in EtOAc&ndash;H<inf>2</inf>O with quaternary ammonium as counter-ion (method B). Hexadec-1-ene yields both by method A and B 2,2&prime;-dihexadecyl polysulfides <it>via</it> a Markownikoff-type addition. The overall selectivity of Markownikoff <it>vs</it>. anti-Markownikoff addition is <it>ca</it>. 35:1. The selectivity decreases at higher temperatures in DMF as solvent probably as the result of a sequence of elimination/readdition reactions. Alka-&alpha;,&omega;-dienes are in a similar way converted (method B) into polymeric polysulfides if the number of methylenes between the double bonds is &ges;4. Monomeric cyclic sulfur compounds are obtained if the number of methylenes is &lt; 4. Penta-1,4-diene yields mainly the cyclic disulfide 3,5-dimethyl-1,2-dithiolane whereas hexa-1,5-diene yields the cyclic monosulfide 2,5-dimethylthiolane as the only product. Hepta-1,6-diene yields cyclic mono- and di-sulfides. Proton-catalysed, simple nucleophilic and radical mechanisms for the &lsquo;hydrosulfurization&rsquo; are excluded. A concerted addition of a hydrogenpolysulfide ion to a double bond is proposed as the actual mechanism. The formation of thiolanes and thianes is explained by the same mechanism operating in an intramolecular fashion.</p>
</abstract>
</art-front>
<art-body>
<section type="PDFExtract">
<title>
</title>
<p> J. CHEM. SOC. PERKIN TRANS. I 1995 Low-temperature addition of hydrogen polysulfides to olefins: formation of 2,2&rsquo;-dialkyl polysulfides from alk-1-enes and cyclic (po1y)sulfides and polymeric organic sulfur compounds from a,m-dienes t Wim de Graaf,*9u*bJaap S. Sinninghe DamstP and Jan W. de Leeuw u9c a Organic Geochemistry Unit, Faculty of Chemical Engineering and Materials Science, Delft University of Technology,De Vries van Heystplantsoen 2, 2628 RZ Delft, The Netherlands Centrefor Limnology, Netherlands Institute of Ecology, Rijksstraatweg 6, 3631 A C Nieuwersluis, The Netherlands Division of Marine Biogeochemistry, Netherlands Institute for Sea Research (NIOZ), PO Box 59, I790 AB Den Burg, Texel, The Netherlands Hydrogenpolysulfide ions, generated by the reaction of hydrogensulfide ions and elemental sulfur, react in a polar organic solvent with alk-1 -enes and alka-a,o-dienes under very mild conditions: 20-50 OC for 1-10 days. </p>
<p>The reagent was prepared either in DMF with Na&rsquo; as counter-ion (method A) or in EtOAc-H,O with quaternary ammonium as counter-ion (method B). Hexadec-1-ene yields both by method A and B 2&rsquo;2&rsquo;-dihexadecyl polysulfides via a Markownikoff-type addition. The overall selectivity of Markownikoff vs. anti-Markownikoff addition is ca. 35: 1. The selectivity decreases at higher temperatures in DMF as solvent probably as the result of a sequence of elimination/readdition reactions. Alka-a,o-dienes are in a similar way converted (method B) into polymeric polysulfides if the number of methylenes between the double bonds is &gt;,4. </p>
<p>Monomeric cyclic sulfur compounds are obtained if the number of methylenes is &lt; 4. Penta-l,4-diene yields mainly the cyclic disulfide 3,5-dimethyl- 1,2-dithiolane whereas hexa- 1&rsquo;5-diene yields the cyclic monosulfide 2,5-dimethylthiolane as the only product. Hepta- 1,6-diene yields cyclic mono- and di-sulfides. Proton-catalysed, simple nucleophilic and radical mechanisms for the &lsquo;hydrosulfurization&rsquo; are excluded. A concerted addition of a hydrogenpolysulfide ion to a double bond is proposed as the actual mechanism. The formation of thiolanes and thianes is explained by the same mechanism operating in an intramolecular fashion. In the course of our studies concerning the formation of organic sulfur compounds in recent sediments, we discovered that sodium hydrogenpolysulfides in an organic solvent react with phytol (3,7,11, I5-tetramethylhexadec-2-enol),its dehydrated counterparts, the phytadienes, and even with alk-1-enes at room temperature within a few The products obtained from phytadienes are polymeric polysulfides and from alk-l- enes 2,2&lsquo;-dialkylpolysulfides. </p>
<p>The reactions followed Mar-kownikoff&rsquo;s rule, at first sight pointing to a proton-catalysed addition of H,S, to a conjugated or isolated double bond. However, to the best of our knowledge, there are no indications from the literature that the reaction of hydrogen(po1y)sulfide with isolated double bonds occurs under these mild, near neutral condition^.^ It was reported recently, though, that hydrogenpolysulfides react with conjugated dienes and enones at low temperat~re.~,~ Here we describe the results from a study focussing on the reaction of hydrogenpolysulfide ions with selected alkenes and alkadienes as substrates under a variety of reaction conditions. </p>
<p>Hexadec-1-ene was selected as the substrate for a study of the reactivity depending on the composition of the hydrogenpolysulfide reagent. Subsequently, the reaction was optimized for phase-transfer conditions. Finally, the behaviour of dec- 1-ene, dec-5-ene, 2-methylundec-1 -ene and apdienes has been studied. The dienes, with varying methylene-spacing between the double bonds, were selected in order to investigate whether intramolecular pathways are involved in the formation of monomeric cyclic sulfur compounds rather than polymeric polysulfides. t NIOZ Department of Marine Biogeochemistry Contribution 310. </p>
<p>Results Hydrosulfurizationin DMF (method A) Hexadec-1-ene was allowed to react at room temperature with a ten-fold excess of NaHS3,5 in DMF. After 5 days, a mixture of 2,2&rsquo;-dihexadecylpolysulfidesand a trace of hexadecane-2-thiol was formed. Since this product mixture cannot be analysed directly by gas chromatography, because of the thermal instability of the polysulfides, it was treated with MeLi in diethyl ether followed by Me1 treatment (Scheme 1). This 12 Scheme 1 Hydrosulfurization of alk- 1-enes and subsequent MeLi- Me1 treatment procedure selectively cleaves polysulfide bridges and trans- forms them into methylsulfanyl groups. </p>
<p>2-Methylsulfanyl-hexadecane was thus obtained in 35% yield. Unchanged hexadec-1 -ene was recovered (60%). The structure of 2-methylsulfanylhexadecane was established by &lsquo;H NMR and GC-MS. The &lsquo;HNMR spectrum shows the hydrogen atom at C-2 as a sextet at 6 3.12 and in the mass spectrum the base peak at m/z 75 originates from a-cleavage between C-2 and C-3. Only a trace of 1-methylsulfanylhexadecane was observed by GC-MS (m/z 61; 1 :35 as determined by integration of the relevant peaks in the gas chromatogram). The addition thus follows Markownikoff&rsquo;s rule with a high selectivity. The influence of the overall composition of the hydro- genopolysulfide reagent was studied by the following experi- ments. </p>
<p>Hexadec-1-ene was allowed to react with a ten-fold   Table 1 Yield of the reaction of hexadec-1-ene with NaHS, in DMF at 50 "C for 24 h  ~  ~  ~~~  Yield of  Recovered  Stoichiometry  products (%)  hexadec-1 -ene (%)  NaHS  0  95  NaHS,  50  24  NaHS3.5  63  13  NaHS,  4  90  excess of NaHS, (x = 1,2,3.5 and 6)at 50 "C for 24 h; the yields as function of the overall composition are compiled in Table 1. It should be noted that a solution of NaHS without additional elemental sulfur is insufficient to induce any reaction. A reaction takes place only after addition of elemental sulfur to the solution of NaHS in DMF. The yield of the addition of hexadec-1-ene is good for compositions of NaHS, and NaHS,., but is considerably lower for NaHS,. The number of sulfur atoms in the 2,2&apos;-dihexadecyl polysulfides obtained from the reaction of hexadec-1 -ene with NaHS, and NaHS,., in DMF at 50 "C was determined by &apos;H NMR spectroscopy. </p>
<p>From the integrated signals of the H atoms at C-2 and C-2&apos; it was found1 that the polysulfide mixture consisted mainly of tri- and tetra-sulfides in a 1 : 1 ratio independent of the reagent composition. Free thiols were also present with the highest amount (ca. 10%) using NaHS, as reagent. Gas chromatographic analyses of the product mixtures confirmed the presence of thiols (10% with NaHS, as reagent and only 2% with NaHS,.,). Selectivity and reversibility of the hydrosulfurization. The addition of the hydrogenpolysulfide reagent to hexadec- 1-ene in DMF at 50 "C leads to a decrease in the Markownikoff us. </p>
<p>anti-Markownikoff selectivity relative to that observed in the reaction at ambient temperature. The selectivity ratio at room temperature was 35: 1 but at 50 "C this ratio decreases to 10: 1 and becomes even lower at higher temperatures or prolonged reaction times. It is noteworthy that the product mixtures of the 50&deg;C reaction also contained a small amount of 3-methyl- sulfanylhexadecane, after MeLi-Me1 treatment. In order to check whether isomerization of initially formed 2,2&apos;-dialkyl polysulfides occurs, octadecane-1-thiol was treated with an excess of NaHS,., in DMF for 1 d at 75 "C. Octadecane-1-thiol was chosen because it is commercially available in sufficiently pure form ( &gt; 99%). </p>
<p>The products, dioctadecyl polysulfides, were treated with MeLi-Me1 and subsequently analysed by GC-MS. Apart from 1-methyl-sulfanyloctadecane (85%), 2-methylsulfanyloctadecane (9%) and 3-methylsulfanyloctadecane (3%) were found. These findings suggest that under these conditions the hydro-sulfurization is to some extent reversible probably due to elimin- ation and readdition reactions with concurrent double-bond isomerization. Hydrosulfurhation in a twephase system (method B) The hydrosulfurization can also be performed under mild conditions (50&deg;C for several days) in a two-phase system consisting of water and ethyl acetate. Hydrogensulfide ions were then extracted from the water phase by a quaternary $The chemical shifts and multiplicities of the H-atoms at C-2 and C-2&apos; recorded at 400 MHz were found to be the most characteristic to unravel the number and distribution of sulfur atoms in the polysulfide linkage. </p>
<p>Reference values for &apos;H and I3CNMR data were obtained from authentic standards synthesized from hexadecane- 2-thiol by reaction with I,, SCI, and S2CI, (see Experimental section; Table 3). J. CHEM. SOC. PERKIN TRANS. 1 1995 ammonium salt. The reactions can easily be performed on a 5 mmol or on a larger scale using readily available chemicals: Optimal conversions of hexadec-1-ene (up to 95% after 10 d of stirring at 50 "C) were only reached with the use of 2 equiv. of phase transfer reagents and 0.5 equiv. of sulfur relative to the substrate. </p>
<p>The reaction mixture contained hexadecane-2-thiol (ca. 20% based on GC-analysis), 2,2&apos;- dihexadecyl polysulfides (ca. 70%) and also 2,2&apos;-dihexadecyl monosulfide (5% based on GC analysis). &apos;H NMR analysis indicated that the polysulfides consisted of a mixture of di-, tri-, tetra- and higher poly-sulfides. The Markownikoff us. anti-Markownikoff selectivity was 35 : 1 as determined after treatment of the reaction mixture with MeLi/MeI. The monosulfides were present as two diastereoisomers in a 1 : 1 ratio and were characterized by the molecular ion at m/z 482 and a major fragment ion at m/z 284 in their mass spectra obtained after GC-MS analysis. Dec-l-ene, dec-5ene and 2-methylundec-l-ene The scope of the hydrosulfurization was further investigated with an alkene with a mid-chain double bond (1rans-dec-5-ene), an alkene with a tertiary carbon at C-2 (2-methylundec-1-ene) and dec-1-ene as control for the effect of the smaller chain length (Table 2, entries 2-4). </p>
<p>In the case of dec-5-ene most of the starting material was recovered; only small amounts of 5-methylsulfanyldecane were obtained after MeLi-Me1 treatment of the reaction mixture. The structure of 5-methylsulfanyldecane was established by the presence of a major fragment ion at m/z 117 in its mass spectrum. In the case of 2-methylundec-1 -ene the yield (after MeLi-Me1 treatment) of 2-methyl-2-methylsulfanylundecanewas 58% whilst 40% of the starting material was recovered. The identification of this product is based on a major fragment ion at m/z 89 in its mass spectrum. Formation of polymeric and heterocyclic sulfur compounds from alka-u,wdienes When alka-a,o-dienes are used as substrates for the hydrosulfurizations (method B), polymeric or monomeric cyclic sulfur compounds are obtained depending on the methylene- spacing between the double bonds (Table 2; entries 5-10). </p>
<p>The long-chain dienes, tetradeca-1 ,13-diene, deca- 179-diene and octa- 1,7-diene, yielded viscous light-yellow oils indicating their polymeric nature. Treatment of these products with MeLi followed by Me1 yielded the corresponding bis-(methylsulfany1)- alkanes 4-6 as the main monomeric products as shown by GC-MS analysis. The methylsulfanyl groups are mainly bonded to the C-2 and penultimate carbon atoms of the alkyl chain as revealed by the dominant fragment at m/z 75 in their mass spectra. </p>
<p>Elemental analysis of the product mixture from deca- l ,9-diene indicates an overall molecular formula CloH20S2.2. The &apos;H NMR spectrum of these polymers showed that the disulfide linkage is dominant but significant amounts of &sect;The nature of the phase transfer reagent is not so important, but generally they are degraded presumably by a nucleophilic attack on one of the alkyl groups. These alkyl groups are transformed into dialkyl or crossed polysulfides with the product of the addition reaction. Methyl groups from the commercial product, Adogen 464 (methyltri[octyl/ decyl]ammonium chloride), are preferably substituted. However, small amounts of octyl and decyl crossed polysulfides are formed and may lead to non-volatile contaminants of the products. </p>
<p>  J. CHEM. SOC. PERKIN TRANS. I 1995 Table 2 Products of the addition of hydrogenpolysulfide ions to alkenes and a,o-alkadienes Entry Substrates ______~ 1 Hexadec-1-ene 2 Dec- 1 -ene 3 Dec-5-ene 4 2-methylundec-1-ene 5 Tetradeca-1 ,13-diene 6 Deca- 1,9-diene 7 Octa- 1,7-diene 8 Hepta-l,6-diene 9 Hexa- 1,Sdiene 10 Penta-1 ,4-diene Products 2,2&apos;-Dihexadecyl polysulfides (A: 80%; B: 65% +15% hexadecane-2-thiol) 2,2&apos;-Didecyl polysulfides (A: 80%; B: 60% +20% decane-2-thiol) $5&apos;-Didecyl polysulfides a (B: 2%) 2,2&apos;-Di(2-methylundecyl)polysulfide" (B: 56%) l,I2-Dimethyldodecamethylenepolysulfide polymer 3 (B: 95%) 1,8-DimethyIoctamethylenepolysulfide polymer 2 (B: 90%) 1,6-DimethylhexamethyIenepolysulfide polymer 1 (B: 95%) 2,QDimethylthiane 11 (B: 35Xb) +3,7-Dimethyl-l,2-dithiepane12 (B: 15%&apos;) 2,5-Dimethylthiolane 9 (B: 46%b, 3,5-Dimethyl-l,2-dithiolane7(B: 40%b, Only determined on the basis of MeLi/MeI treatment. </p>
<p>&apos;Yields of distilled products. thiol groups (1WO%)are present as well. The presence of residual thiol groups was confirmed by oxidation with iodine resulting in an increase of the viscosity of the product and disappearance of the thiolic smell. From these data we conclude that the compounds formed are the linear polysulfide polymers 1-3 (Scheme 2). SH hydrogenpolysulfide anions. </p>
<p>Disproportionation of NaHS, may be expected since it is known that nucleophilic attack on polysulfur chains is fast. There is, however, almost no information available concerning the distribution of species. There are only reports about the composition of Na,S, in water and, in that case, disproportionation takes place resulting in S2-and predominantly S,&apos;-and S, 62-ions, relatively independent of the stoichiometry of Na2S,. Solutions of NaHS, in DMF are very dark, varying from blue (x=2) via black (x =3) to red (x=6). The blue colour has ?Me+SMe 4 n=l 5 n=3 6 n=7 Scheme 2 Hydrosulfurization MeLi-Me1 treatment been observed previously and was attributed to the presence of radical anions of the type S,*-.* These radical anions are formed by thermal dissociation of S62-anions, a process favoured in aprotic solvents. </p>
<p>Disproportionation of NaHS, MeLUMel SH 1 n=l 2 n=3 3 n=7 of alka-a,o-dienes and subsequent Hepta- 1,6-diene and smaller alka-a,o-dienes yielded volatile monomeric sulfur compounds (Table 2; entries 8-10) upon hydrosulfurization as revealed by GC-MS analysis. The reaction mixtures were distilled at low pressure to isolate the pure monomeric products and facilitate interpretation of the NMR spectra (see Experimental section; Table 4). Penta-l,4-diene yielded 40% of 3,5-dimethyl-l,2-dithiolane7 together with a small amount of 4,6-dimethyl-l,2,3-trithiane8. Hexa-13-diene yielded, surprizingly, only 2,5-dimethylthiolane 9. </p>
<p>No trace of 3,6-dimethyldithiane 10 was detected after distillation. Hepta- 1,6-diene yielded both 2,6-dimethylthiane 11 and the cyclic disulfide, 3,7-dimethy- 1,2-thiepane 12. -&amp;As-s 7 8 9QQns-s 10 11 12 Discussion Nature of the hydrogenpolysulfide reagent NaHS dissolves in DMF resulting in a clear, almost colourless solution. Elemental sulfur dissolves quickly in a solution of NaHS in DMF and is most probably transformed into not only produces several hydrogenpolysulfide ions but also hydrogen sulfide or higher sulfanes and divalent poly-sulfide ions which can dissociate further into radical anions. There is, however, no visible evolution of hydrogen sulfide suggesting that this acid-base disproportionation is only small. </p>
<p>The presence of such anionic hydrogenpolysulfides in a rather polar solvent, which is capable of keeping both the reagent and the apolar substrates in solution, appeared important for a good conversion of olefins into sulfur-containing products. For NaHS, the most suitable solvent is DMF, although for (NR,)HS,, a less polar solvent such as EtOAc is appropriate. Inter-versus intra-molecular pathways. The most likely process for the formation of dialkyl, polymeric or cyclic polysulfides is a slow addition of hydrogen(po1y)sulfide to a double bond, followed by a fast formation of a polysulfide linkage via disproportionation or oxidation of the (po1y)thiol or (po1y)thiolate group (route A; Scheme 3). However, the formation of a polysulfide linkage may also occur via an inter- or intra-molecular pathway where the (po1y)thiol group adds to a double bond directly in either the same or another molecule (route B). </p>
<p>The latter pathway is actually the most likely route to the monosulfides 2,2&apos;-dihexadecyl sulfide, 2,5-dimethyl-thiolane and 2,6-dimethylthiane; an alternative possibility for the formation of these monosulfides is nucleophilic substi- tution of a thiolate anion (RS-) on the a-carbon atom of a dialkyl polysulfide. Scheme 3 Proposed reaction pathway for the hydrosuifurization The unlikelihood of proton-or radical-induced additions. The classical view on reactions which follow Markownikoff&apos;s rule is that an ionic mechanism is involved. The Markownikoff rule states that the hydrogen atom of a reagent (H-Z) becomes   638 J. </p>
<p>CHEM. SOC. PERKIN TRANS. 1 1995 Table 3 Characteristic &apos;H and NMR data for hexadecane-2-thiol and 2,2&apos;-dihexadecyl di-, tri- and tetra-sulfides Compound H at C-2 H at C-1 c-1 c-2 C-3 Hexadecane-2- t hi01 2.92 heptet 1.33 doublet 25.61 40.96 35.58 2,2&apos;-Dihexadecyl disulfide 2.77 double sextets" 1.30 doublet 20.65120.70 46.67146.70 36.23 2,2&apos;-Dihexadecyl trisulfide 3.02 sextet 1.36 doublet 20.66 47.18 35.95 2,2&apos;-Dihexadecyl tetrasulfide 3.1 1 double sextets" 1.38 doublet 20.88 47.45 36.18 a In addition to the expected three band &apos;H-&apos;H splitting (J6.6 Hz) there is a further splitting of the signals of the H-atoms at C-2 and C-2&apos; of the di- and tetra-sulfide. This splitting is attributed to the directing influence of the chiral centre at C-2 and C-2&apos; on the axial dissymmetry of the di- and tetra-sulfide linkage. </p>
<p>The trisulfide lacks this axial dissymmetry. The values for this splitting are, therefore, given in ppm: 0.007 pprn for the di- and 0.006 pprn for the tetra-sulfide. The splitting is also observed in the I3C NMR spectrum of 2,2&apos;-dihexadecyl disulfide. Table 4 Selected H and 3C NMR data for cyclic sulfur compounds 6 of H at C-a 6 of H at C-p 6 of H at C-y and C-6 Compound name 6 of C-a 6 of c-p 6 of C-y and C-6 ~~ ~ ~~~ trans-3,5-Dimethyl- 1,2-dithioIane 1.40 d 2.09 t 3.81 sextets 20.51 49.72 50.28 cis-3,5-Dimethyl- 1,2-dithiolane 1.38 d 2.6612.69 t 3.70 m 20.41 51.42 51.49 cis-4,6-Dimethyl- 1,2,3-trithiane 1.44d 1.68 t 3.17513.155 sextets 26.25 33.98 51.42 truns-4,6-Dimethyl- 1,2,3-trithiane 1.447 d 1.78 t 3.08 m truns-2,5-dimethylthiolane 1.33 d 3.48 m 2.O4/1.70 m 23.65 37.96 44.50 cis-2,5-Dimethylthiolane 1.30 d 3.58 m 1.53/2.19 m 22.71 39.54 44.4I trans-2,5-Dimet hyl thiane 1.29 d 2.89 qu of d 1.91 m 1.53 m 21.36 33.33 34.73 20.72 cis-2,5-DimethylthiolaneC 1.17d 2.82 m 1.65 m 1.2-1.4 m 21.64 38.89 35.94 27.00 trans-3,6-Dimethyl- 1,2-dithiepane&apos; 1.25 d 3.09 m 1.4-1.9 m I .4-1.9 m 22.36 48.23 38.22 24. </p>
<p>I7 cis-3,6-Dimethyl-1,Zdithiepane 1.24 d 2.94 m 1 .&amp;I .9 m 1.4-1.9 m 20.90 48.23 39.06 21.2s a The I3C NMR spectrum of the mixture of cis-and trans-3,5-dimethyl-I ,2-dithiolane is in agreement with reported data (M. C. Caserio and J. J. </p>
<p>Kim, Phosphorus, Sulphur and Silicon,1985,23,169). The trans isomer is obtained in a ratio of ca. 4: 1 relative to the cis isomer; the trans isomer was identified by the deceptively simple triplet at 2.09 ppm in the &apos;H NMR spectrum. The ratio of cis-and trans-2,5-dimethylthiolanewas ca. 1 :2. Ratios of cis- and truns-isomers of other products were ca. I :I. bonded to the carbon atom of the double bond that already order hexadec- 1-ene &gt; 2-methylundec- 1 -ene &gt; dec-5-ene indi- bears the most hydrogens. The mechanistic basis for the rule is cates that the steric accessibility of the alkene is important. The that protonation of the double bond generates the most stable most likely mechanism to be considered is a concerted addition carbocation followed by a fast addition of the hetero-of HS,- to a double bond (Fig. </p>
<p>I); a simple nucleophilic substituent (Z-). The addition of H,S to, for example, propene, addition of HS-can be excluded, since NaHS alone is however, needs high temperature ( &gt; 100 "C) and pressure or unreactive towards hexadec- I -ene. Although polysulfide ions strong acid catalyst^,^ whilst the current reactions of hydrogen are more thiophylic, we think that the same holds for a direct polysulfides with olefinic double bonds proceed at much milder, nucleophilic addition of HS,-. More evidence in favour of this slightly basic conditions. The likelihood of protonation of a view is provided by the reactions with the phytadienes.&apos; The double bond must be effectively zero. product distribution (sulfur atoms mainly at the 2-and 3-Indications that a simple proton-catalysed mechanism is not positions of the diene system) is in agreement with two times an operational are also provided by the relative inertness of mid- addition to one of the double bonds rather than a Michael chain alkenes (cf:Table 2, entries I, 2 and 3). </p>
<p>The same reaction addition which would result in a different product distribution. rate should be at least expected if a proton-catalysed mechan- In the concerted mechanism, the new bonds are formed by a 6-ism is involved. Moreover, 2-methylundec- 1-ene, which is the electron rearrangement. Such a process is comparable with the ideal substrate for a proton-catalysed addition, reacts slower Diels-Alder mechanism and with the Claisen, Cope or than hexadec-l-ene as well (Table 2; entry 4). </p>
<p>MacLafferty rearrangements. Most probably x = 3, although At the stoichiometry NaHS, at 50&deg;C in DMF the blue species with x = 2 or x &gt; 3 may be active as well. For that colour has almost disappeared and the rate of the hydro- reason, we think that the optimum yield of the reaction is sulfurization is also strongly reduced (Table I), suggesting the provided by the concentration where most of the polysulfide involvement of a radical mechanism. Characteristic of a radical species will be in the form of HS,-(Table 1). The observed mechanism is, however, the formation of anti-Markownikoff Markownikoff selectivity is probably determined by the charge products. This is clearly not the case and the possibility that a separation of the terminal alkene (hyperconjugation). </p>
<p>Molec- rearrangement from primary to secondary products occurs ular mechanics calculations of alk-l-enes using a newly after initial addition, is excluded based on the experiment with developed force field considering geometry-dependent charges octane-I -thiol. The involvement of a radical chain mechanism confirms the charge distribution indicated in Fig. 1 .9 must, therefore, be ruled out. Formation of thiolunm-The formation of the cyclic mono- Proposal for the actual mechanism. The observation that the sulfides from hexa-l,5-diene and hepta-l$-diene is note-rate of the hydrosulfurization of alkenes decreases in the worthy (Table 2; entries 8 and 9). We believe, however, that   J. </p>
<p>CHEM. soc. PERKIN TRANS. i 1995 Fig. 1 Concerted addition of HS,-to a double bond Fig. 2 Formation of cyclic monosulfides these monosulfides are formed according to a mechanism indicated in Fig. 2. Evidence for this view provided the hydrosulfurization of squalene 13 which resulted in the formation of two thiolanes with structures 14 and 15." In this case a sulfur moiety introduced at a tertiary position initiates the formation of a thiolane ring through reaction with the secondary carbon atom (instead of the tertiary carbon atom) of the nearest double bond; the Markownikoff rule is, therefore, not obeyed. 13 14 /s&bsol; I I 15 The sulfurization of organic matter in marine sediments Hydrosulfurization proceeds in the presence of a water phase with dissolved hydrogensulfide ions and resembles natural conditions in the sulfate-reduction zone of a sediment; in most marine sediments the redox potential is controlled by the reversible half-cell: S2-(as) = S,(rhmb.) + 2e. </p>
<p>Deposited lipids come into contact with hydrogen(po1y)sulfide-containing pore water. We think that the reaction mechanism described in this paper plays an important role in the incorporation of sulfur into sedimentary organic matter. l2 Conclusions 1. Alk-1-enes react with hydrogen polysulfide ions in polar organic solvents and are converted into 2,2&apos;-dialkyl polysulfides. Nearly quantitative conversions take place at 50 "C after several days. 2. Alka-a,o-dienes are converted into polymeric polysulfides if the methylene-spacing between the double bonds is 24. </p>
<p>If the methylene-spacing &lt;4 monomeric cyclic (po1y)sulfides are obtained. Cyclic monosulfides are formed only from hexa-l,Sdiene and hepta-l,6-diene. 3. Proton-catalysed, simple nucleophilic or radical chain mechanisms have to be excluded to explain the current addition reactions. 4. Additions are best explained by a 6-electron rearrangement mechanism involving a carbon-carbon double bond and a hydrogen trisulfide ion or a hydrogentrisulfide group. Experimental General NaHS was prepared by the introduction of H,S (Mattson) in NaOEt, made by the dissolution of sodium in absolute ethanol. Dry NaHS was subsequently precipitated by the addition of dry diethyl ether and filtered off through a sintered glass funnel in an atmosphere of dry nitrogen. </p>
<p>It was stored over P20s in a nitrogen-filled dessicator. l3 To prevent oxidation of the &apos;hydrogenpolysulfide&apos; reagent, all reactions were carried out under an atmosphere of dry nitrogen until the work-up procedure. Hydrated NaHS may be used instead of dry NaHS in DMF but the presence of water lowers the solubility of the apolar substrates and as a consequence reduces the yields of the reactions. Hydrated NaSH, hexadec- 1-ene, dec- 1-ene (purity ca. 90% by GC)and alka-a,o-dienes were obtained from Aldrich. Hydrosulfurizationof alkenes in DMF (method A) A thermostatted reaction vessel (100 cm3) equipped with a magnetic stirring bar was charged with NaHS (0.56 g, 10 mmol), DMF (25 cm3) and hexadec-1-ene (1 .O mmol) or other substrates; the mixture contained 2 mol% of heptadecane as internal standard. </p>
<p>Flowers of sulfur (0, 10, 25 or 50 mmol) were added to the mixture in order to obtain the average compositions NaHS, NaHS,, NaHS,,, or NaHS,. After the specified reaction time and temperature the mixture was stirred with a solution of Na2S203(2.5 g) in water (15 cm3). After 30 min the free sulfur had dissolved and the reaction mixture was extracted three times with hexane. The combined extracts were concentrated with a rotary evaporator (with GC analysis) to give a light-yellow oil (0.25 g) in the case of hexadec-1-ene. The product mixture was analysed by GC and &apos;H NMR spectroscopy (see text). </p>
<p>The remaining reaction mixture was taken up in dry diethyl ether (20 cm3) and a solution of MeLi in diethyl ether (2.0 mol dmP3; 1 cm3) was added to it with gentle stirring at room temperature; after 1 min Me1 (0.25 cm3) was also added. Stirring was continued for 1 h after which the mixture was carefully hydrolysed with water. The organic layer was separated and the water layer was extracted twice with hexane. The combined organic layer and extracts were dried (MgSO,) and evaporated under reduced pressure to give a colourless oil (ca. 0.20 g, 85-90% recovery) in the case of hexadec-1 -ene. The product mixture was analysed by GC, GC- MS and &apos;H NMR spectroscopy. Hydrosulfurization of alkenes mediated by a phase transfer reagent (method B) A thermostatted reaction vessel (100 ern3) equipped with a magnetic stirring bar was charged with hydrated NaHS (6 g, 0.1 mol), water (10 cm3), tetrabutylammonium bromide (3.22 g, 10 mmol), ethyl acetate (50 cm3), sulfur (0.08 g, 2.5 mmol) and the specified alkene (5 mmol). </p>
<p>The reaction mixture was stirred for 10 d at 5OoC after which the contents of the flask were transferred to a separatory funnel. The green-brown organic layer was separated, washed with water and then twice with hydrochloric acid (4 mol dm-3; 5 cm3) and then dried (Na,SO,) and concentrated on a rotary evaporator to leave light-yellow oily liquids. Cyclic sulfur compounds were distilled at low pressure. The products were analysed by GC, GC-MS and NMR spectroscopy, eventually after MeLi-Mel-treatment (Tables 2 and 4). </p>
<p>The product mixture from the reaction of deca-l,9-diene was also subjected to an elemental analysis (Found: C, 56.8; H, 9.2; S, 33.1. Calc. for C,oH20S2.2: C, 56.99; H, 9.57; S, 33.43). Preparation of hexadecane-2-thiol and 2,2&apos;dihexadecyl di-, tri-and tetra-sulfide Reduction of dihexadecyl polysulfides with LiAlH, following a   known procedure14 gave hexadecane-2-thiol (95% of the theoretically expected weight). 2,2&apos;-Oxidation of hexadecane-2- thiol with iodine l5 gave dihexadecyl disulfide. Reaction of hexadecane-2-thiol with SCl, and S2C12, gave tri- and tetra- sulfide. resDectivelv. l6 It was observed that use of diethvl ether instead of iydrocaibons gave purer products. </p>
<p>After reac;ion the solvent and HC1 were removed by a water pump vacuum. Characteristic NMR data are given in Table 2. Gas chromatography (CC) and gas chromatography-Mass spectrometry (GC-MS) GC was performed using a Carlo Erba 5300 instrument equipped with an on-column injector. A fused silica capillary column (25 m x 0.32 mm) coated with CP Sil-5 (film thickness 0.12 mm) was used with helium as carrier gas. The column efluent was monitored simultaneously by both a flame ionization detector (FID) and a sulfur-selective flame photo- metric detector (FPD) using a flow-splitter at the end of the column (split ratio 1 :2). The samples (dissolved in hexane or ethyl acetate) were injected at 70&deg;C and the oven was subsequently programmed to rise to 320 *C at a rate of 10 "C min-&apos;: the oven was held for 5 min at the final temDerature. </p>
<p>GC-MS was performed with an HP 5480 gas ch;omatograph interfaced to a VG-70S spectrometer Operated at 70 eV with a range mlz 40-900 and a time Of 1.8 (resolution 1000). The GC-column and oven program were identical with those described above. NMR spectroscopy NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker 400 MHz spectro-meter using pulse Fourier transformation. Shifts (6) in CDCl, are given in ppm relative to tetramethylsilane as external reference. Broadband proton decoupling was applied during the recording of the NMR spectra. J. CHEM. soc. PERKIN TRANS. I 1995 References w. de Graaf, J. s.Sinninghe Damste and J. w. de Leeuw, Geochim. Cosmochim. </p>
<p>Acta, I992,56,432 I. 2 Neth. Patent 92.02072 Zwaveludditie (1992). 3 W. H. Hoffert and K. Wendtner, J. Inst. fetr., 1949,35, 171. 4 K. Reinartz, PhD dissertation, University of Koln, 1988. 5 E-B* Krein and Z. Aizenshtat, J. 0%.Chem., 19939% 6103. 6 M. E. L. Kohnen, J. S. Sinninghe Damste, A. C. Kock-van Dalen and J. W. de Leeuw, Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 1991,55, 1375. 7 (a) E. Muller and J. B. Hyne, Can. J. Chem. 1968, 46, 2341; (6) J. Boulege, C.J. Lord and T. M.Church, Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 1982,46,453. 8 (a)P. See], H.-J. Guttler, G. Simon and A. Wieckowski, Pure Appl. Chem., 1977,49,45-54; (b)R. J. H. Clark and D. G. Cobbold, Inorg. Chem., 1978,17,3 169. 9 A. C. T. van Duin, J. M.A. Baas and B. van de Graaf, J. Chem. Soc., Furaduy Trans., 1994,90,2881. 10 S. Schouten, W. de Graaf, J. S. Sinninghe Damste, G. van Driel and J. W. de Leeuw, Advances in Organic Geochemistry 1993, Org. Geochem., 1994,22,825. 11 R.A. Berner, Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta, 1963,21,563. 12 M. E. L. Kohnen, J. S. Sinninghe Damste, H. L. ten Haven and J. W. de Leeuw, Nature, 1989,341,640. 13 G. Brauer, Handbuch der Praparativen Anorganischen Chemie, Ferdinand Enke Verlag, Stuttgart, vol. 1, 1960, p. 325. 14 (a)R. C. Arnold, A. P. Lien and R. M. Alm, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 1950, 72,731; (6)J. Strating and H. J. Backer, Red. Trav. Chim. fays-Bas, 1950.69, 638, 909. 15 A, SchGberl and A, Eck, ljebjgs Ann. Chem,, 1936,522, 97. 16 J. D, Clayton and D. H. Etzler, J. Am. Chem. Soc., 1947,69,974. Paper 4107248K Received 28th November 1994 Accepted 28th November 1994  </p>
</section>
</art-body>
<art-back>
<biblist>
<citgroup id="cit1">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>W.</fname>
<surname>de Graaf</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. S.</fname>
<surname>Sinninghe Damst&eacute;</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. W.</fname>
<surname>de Leeuw</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta.</title>
<year>1992</year>
<volumeno>56</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>4321</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit2">
<citation type="patent">Neth. Patent 92.02072 <it>Zwaveladditie</it>(<year>1992</year>).</citation>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit3">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>W. H.</fname>
<surname>Hoffert</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>K.</fname>
<surname>Wendtner</surname>
</citauth>
<title>J. Inst. Petr.</title>
<year>1949</year>
<volumeno>35</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>171</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit4">
<citation type="other">
<citauth>
<fname>K.</fname>
<surname>Reinartz</surname>
</citauth>, PhD dissertation, <citpub>University of K&ouml;ln</citpub>, <year>1988</year>.</citation>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit5">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>E. B.</fname>
<surname>Krein</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>Z.</fname>
<surname>Aizenshtat</surname>
</citauth>
<title>J. Org. Chem.</title>
<year>1993</year>
<volumeno>58</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>6103</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit6">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>M. E. L.</fname>
<surname>Kohnen</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. S.</fname>
<surname>Sinninghe Damst&eacute;</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>A. C.</fname>
<surname>Kock-van Dalen</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. W.</fname>
<surname>de Leeuw</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
<year>1991</year>
<volumeno>55</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>1375</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit7">
<citgroup id="cit7a">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>E.</fname>
<surname>Muller</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. B.</fname>
<surname>Hyne</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Can. J. Chem.</title>
<year>1968</year>
<volumeno>46</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>2341</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit7b">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>J.</fname>
<surname>Boul&egrave;ge</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>C. J.</fname>
<surname>Lord</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>T. M.</fname>
<surname>Church</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
<year>1982</year>
<volumeno>46</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>453</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit8">
<citgroup id="cit8a">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>P.</fname>
<surname>Seel</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>H.-J.</fname>
<surname>G&uuml;ttler</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>G.</fname>
<surname>Simon</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>A.</fname>
<surname>Wieckowski</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Pure Appl. Chem.</title>
<year>1977</year>
<volumeno>49</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>54</lpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit8b">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>R. J. H.</fname>
<surname>Clark</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>D. G.</fname>
<surname>Cobbold</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Inorg. Chem.</title>
<year>1978</year>
<volumeno>17</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>3169</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit9">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>A. C. T.</fname>
<surname>van Duin</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. M. A.</fname>
<surname>Baas</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>B.</fname>
<surname>van de Graaf</surname>
</citauth>
<title>J. Chem. Soc., Faraday Trans.</title>
<year>1994</year>
<volumeno>90</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>2881</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit10">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>S.</fname>
<surname>Schouten</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>W.</fname>
<surname>de Graaf</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. S.</fname>
<surname>Sinninghe Damst&eacute;</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>G.</fname>
<surname>van Driel</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. W.</fname>
<surname>de Leeuw</surname>
</citauth>
<arttitle>Advances in Organic Geochemistry 1993</arttitle>
<title>Org. Geochem.</title>
<year>1994</year>
<volumeno>22</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>825</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit11">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>R. A.</fname>
<surname>Berner</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</title>
<year>1963</year>
<volumeno>27</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>563</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit12">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>M. E. L.</fname>
<surname>Kohnen</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. S.</fname>
<surname>Sinninghe Damst&eacute;</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>H. L.</fname>
<surname>ten Haven</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>J. W.</fname>
<surname>de Leeuw</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Nature</title>
<year>1989</year>
<volumeno>341</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>640</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit13">
<citation type="book">
<citauth>
<fname>G.</fname>
<surname>Brauer</surname>
</citauth>, <title>Handbuch der Pr&auml;parativen Anorganischen Chemie</title>, <citpub>Ferdinand Enke Verlag</citpub>, <pubplace>Stuttgart</pubplace>, vol. 1, <year>1960</year>, <biblscope>p. 325</biblscope>.</citation>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit14">
<citgroup id="cit14a">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>R. C.</fname>
<surname>Arnold</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>A. P.</fname>
<surname>Lien</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>R. M.</fname>
<surname>Alm</surname>
</citauth>
<title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
<year>1950</year>
<volumeno>72</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>731</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit14b">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>J.</fname>
<surname>Strating</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>H. J.</fname>
<surname>Backer</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Recl. Trav. Chim. Pays-Bas</title>
<year>1950</year>
<volumeno>69</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>638</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>J.</fname>
<surname>Strating</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>H. J.</fname>
<surname>Backer</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Recl. Trav. Chim. Pays-Bas</title>
<year>1950</year>
<volumeno>69</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>909</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit15">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>A.</fname>
<surname>Sch&ouml;berl</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>A.</fname>
<surname>Eck</surname>
</citauth>
<title>Liebigs Ann. Chem.</title>
<year>1936</year>
<volumeno>522</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>97</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
<citgroup id="cit16">
<journalcit>
<citauth>
<fname>J. D.</fname>
<surname>Clayton</surname>
</citauth>
<citauth>
<fname>D. H.</fname>
<surname>Etzler</surname>
</citauth>
<title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title>
<year>1947</year>
<volumeno>69</volumeno>
<pages>
<fpage>974</fpage>
</pages>
</journalcit>
</citgroup>
</biblist>
<compoundgrp>
</compoundgrp>
</art-back>
</article>

