<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jcs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jcs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Church and State</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>Journal of Church and State</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-969X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2040-4867</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jcs/43.1.19</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Law, Religion, and the Metaphysics of Abortion: A Reply to Simmons</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Beckwith</surname><given-names>Francis J.</given-names></name><role>associate professor of philosophy, culture and law</role>
</contrib>
<aff><institution>Trinity Graduate School, Trinity International University</institution></aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>B.A., University of Nevada, Las Vegas; M.A., Simon Greenleaf University; M.A., Ph.D., Fordham University; M.J.S. candidate, Washington University School of Law, St. Louis</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>where he holds adjunct appointments in both Trinity Law School and Trinity Evangelical Divinity School. He is author of <italic>Abortion and the Sanctity of Human Life, The Abortion Controversy 25 Years After Roe v. Wade: A Reader</italic>, 2<sup>nd</sup> ed., <italic>Affirmative Action: Social Justice or Reverse Discrimination?, Politically Correct Death: Answering the Arguments for Abortion Rights</italic>, and <italic>The Mormon Concept of God: A Philosophical Analysis</italic>. He and Dennis Hollinger are the general editors of the Eerdman&#x0027;s Critical Issues in Bioethics monograph series. He is author of more than fifty articles in numerous journals such as <italic>Journal of Law, Medicine, and Ethics, Social Theory and Practice, Journal of Social Philosophy, International Philosophical Quarterly, Public Affairs Quarterly, Nexus, A Journal of Opinion, and Logos: Philosophic Issues in Christian Perspective</italic>. Special interests include applied ethics, legal and political philosophy, and philosophy of religion. Special thanks to Trinity International University&#x0027;s Board of Regents for providing me a sabbatical and leave of absence in order to work on this essay as well as other research in law and religion. If not for the support of Winston Frost, Dean, Trinity International University, I would not have been the recipient of the board&#x0027;s graciousness.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<season>Winter</season>
<year>2001</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>19</fpage>
<lpage>33</lpage>
<copyright-statement>Copyright 2001 by the J. M. Dawson Institute of Church-State Studies</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2001</copyright-year>
</article-meta>
</front>
</article>