<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd" []>
<article article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">notesj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">notesj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Notes and Queries</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0029-3970</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1471-6941</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/notesj/gjs162</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gjs162</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group>
<subject>Notes</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Attention and Effort in the Transfer of an Orthographic Detail?</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff>Basingstoke</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp>
<addr-line>
<named-content content-type="sensitive-text">
<email>merriam12484648@hotmail.co.uk</email>
</named-content>
</addr-line>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>19</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>59</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>525</fpage>
<lpage>530</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>&copy; The Author (2012). Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
</permissions>
<counts>
<page-count count="6"/>
</counts>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body><p>DANIEL KAHNEMAN distinguishes between a so-called mental System 1, the automated activity of the associative memory in making intuitive decisions on the one hand, and, on the other, System 2 which requires attention and effort. System 1 entails conditioned patterns and habits of the mind, an unconscious mental &lsquo;default mode&rsquo;; System 2 entails the fully conscious checking and re-checking of facts for accuracy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN1"><sup>1</sup></xref> The distinction of the two systems casts light on textual transference from one literary work to another. By textual transference, I mean the borrowing of themes, concepts, verbatim wordings in context, collocations in or out of context, rare words, frequency of function words and their common juxtapositions, and, in the case of handwritten manuscripts, characteristic orthographic features.</p>
<p>Literary themes can engage System 2: writers of one text may well be conscious of thematic or topical parallels with the texts from which they borrow. Whether there is transference of deliberately chosen thematic material from one author to himself or herself (sometimes referred to as &lsquo;self-plagiarism&rsquo;), or from one author to another, both attention and intention are engaged. At the unconscious level of collocations and function words on the other hand, System 1 may dominate. If, for example, motivation is absent in the choice of words, the choice of phrasal patterns of words, or the choice of orthographic formations, involuntary habit is responsible.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN2"><sup>2</sup></xref></p>
<p>Shakespeare consciously crafted parallels between Hermione in <italic>The Winter&rsquo;s Tale</italic> and Katherine in <italic>Henry VIII</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN3"><sup>3</sup></xref> Shakespeare deliberately imitated Plautus in <italic>The Comedy of Errors</italic> with respect to plot, incident, and character. He literally transcribed Holinshed on occasion with <italic>Henry VIII</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN4"><sup>4</sup></xref> In these three cases there is discernible motivation for the borrowing.</p>
<p>The dating of the Original Text of <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic> in the early 1590s as advocated by Greg, Shapiro, Wentersdorf, Blayney, McMillin, Taylor, Melchiori, and Gabrieli permits the transfer of Shakespeare&rsquo;s phrasal habits (System 1) from <italic>Henry VI, Part 2</italic> (in performance) to the Original Text of <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic> within a short time span.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN5"><sup>5</sup></xref> In contrast, the Original Text&rsquo;s dating by Sch&uuml;cking<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN6"><sup>6</sup></xref> and 3rd Arden <italic>More</italic><xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN7"><sup>7</sup></xref> <italic>c.</italic> 1600 requires a transfer of noted collocations and verbal features by Munday from a performance of <italic>Henry VI, Part 2</italic> (1592 at the latest) to the Original Text over a space of more than seven years&mdash;without a discernible reason (System 2) for their preservation intact.</p>
<p>Additionally, it must be said in parenthesis that the early dating of the Original Text disallows Chettle&rsquo;s plausible involvement in its composition, according to the current state of evidence cited in 3rd Arden <italic>More</italic>. &lsquo;There is no evidence of Munday and Chettle collaborating on a play or any other work before 1598.&rsquo;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN8"><sup>8</sup></xref> Chettle&rsquo;s earliest possible contribution to Elizabethan drama was in 1597. &lsquo;Of the revisers, neither Chettle nor Dekker can be shown to have been active as a dramatist before 1597.&rsquo;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN9"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<disp-quote content-type="extract"><p>There remains a strong suspicion that Munday did not write the Original Text alone. But the clearest potential evidence is too conflicting for confident pronouncement to be made on the pattern or even the presence of collaboration. For those seeking clarity on these issues, the state of knowledge is unsatisfactory&hellip; With early modern playmaking, modern paradigms of literary writing and techniques of investigating authorship, despite their successes, can in some situations break down and leave the question unresolved, for now at least.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN10"><sup>10</sup></xref></p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>A date of 1593 or thereabouts would allow a degree of Shakespearean authorship of the Original Text, thus suggesting composition of an unusual play for Lord Strange&rsquo;s Men with its &lsquo;repertory of varied and unpredictable implications&rsquo;,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN11"><sup>11</sup></xref> plus extended roles for Edward Alleyn.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN12"><sup>12</sup></xref> The 3rd Arden date of <italic>c.</italic> 1600 requires the play&rsquo;s composition by Munday and possibly Chettle for the Earl of Derby&rsquo;s company, for which neither is known to have written.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN13"><sup>13</sup></xref></p>
<p>Levin L. Sch&uuml;cking proposed dating the Original Text by reason of its affinity with <italic>1 Sir John Oldcastle</italic> (1599) and <italic>Thomas Lord Cromwell</italic> (<italic>c.</italic> 1600). The association of the three is based on circumstantial evidence of the similarity of their genre as &lsquo;unroyal&rsquo; histories. They are &lsquo;unroyal&rsquo; in contrast to most Elizabethan history plays that were named after and concerned with kings<italic>.</italic> Sch&uuml;cking&rsquo;s subjective perception of intertextual influence among the three plays is evidenced in his belief that Fletcher&rsquo;s much later <italic>The Woman&rsquo;s Prize</italic> provides a model for the Original Text&rsquo;s &lsquo;feminist&rsquo; Doll Williamson. Sch&uuml;cking&rsquo;s authorial attribution in 1925 of Addition II (Hand D) to Heywood overruled the empirical evidence of the eminent palaeographer Edward Maunde Thompson in favour of his intuitive perception of a shared sentimentality&mdash;&lsquo;at the same time <italic>he</italic> [Heywood] <italic>has</italic> that sentimental vein, so unmistakeable in the Moore speech [Addition II].&rsquo;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN14"><sup>14</sup></xref></p>
<p>But to return to the question of textual transference between plays: what might serve as a good example of unmotivated System 1 habits which are unaccountably transferable between different authors, without attention and effort - with respect to the Original Text of <italic>More</italic>? Munday&rsquo;s <italic>John a Kent and John a Cumber</italic> provides one. Antedating the Original Text by three to eight years, Munday&rsquo;s play has no words ending in a double <italic>t</italic>. Neither do any of his known dramatic works before or after <italic>More</italic>, including the probably co-authored <italic>Downfall</italic> and <italic>Death of Robert Earl of Huntingdon</italic>. Chettle&rsquo;s <italic>Hoffman</italic> has three words ending in <italic>tt</italic>: <italic>kitt</italic>, <italic>smitt</italic>, and <italic>allott</italic>, none of which occurs in the Original Text. The manuscript Original Text of <italic>More</italic> contains 62 tokens ending in <italic>tt</italic>, consisting of these types:<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN15"><sup>15</sup></xref> <italic>comitt</italic>, <italic>cutt</italic> (166, 802), <italic>diett</italic>, <italic>fatt</italic>, <italic>fitt</italic> (1060, 1747), <italic>frett</italic>, <italic>gott</italic> (335), <italic>hott</italic> (359), <italic>markett</italic>, <italic>meritt</italic>, <italic>nett</italic>, <italic>poett</italic>, <italic>riott</italic>, <italic>wett</italic>, <italic>witt (</italic>see below), and <italic>writt</italic>. The text in Hand D, attributed to Shakespeare by Thompson and 3rd Arden, has <italic>cutt</italic> (Addition II, 243), <italic>gott</italic> (191 and 203), <italic>sett</italic> (213), <italic>sytt</italic>, and <italic>whett</italic>. The Quarto of <italic>Love&rsquo;s Labour&rsquo;s Lost</italic> (1598) has four occurrences of <italic>witt.</italic> The Original Text, dated by 3rd Arden <italic>c.</italic> 1600, contains the same spelling &lsquo;witt&rsquo; at 755, 922, 923, 927, 929, 949, 1006, 1007, 1008, 1010, 1016, 1019 (twice), 1020, 1021 (twice), 1025, 1037, 1040, 1041, 1054, 1061, 1064, 1079, 1084, 1092, 1103, 1113, 1119, 1125, 1128, 1131, and 1138 (33 times). The Quarto of <italic>Henry IV, Part 2</italic> (1600) has one occurrence of <italic>sett</italic>; the Folio of <italic>Richard II</italic> (1623) also has one occurrence of <italic>sett</italic>. The Quarto of <italic>Troilus and Cressida</italic> (1609) contains the Original Text&rsquo;s <italic>hott</italic> (twice) and <italic>fitt</italic>, besides <italic>rott</italic> and <italic>bitts</italic>.</p>
<p>If the orthographic habit of the terminal <italic>tt</italic> in <italic>Witt</italic>, the generic absence of which ending was Munday&rsquo;s custom, indeed was transferred from its occurrences in <italic>Love&rsquo;s Labour&rsquo;s Lost</italic> (first printed in 1598) to its predominant use in <italic>More</italic>&rsquo;s Original Text, this was done for a reason sufficient to break the habit of <italic>not</italic> using it. If, however, the habit of doubling the terminal <italic>t</italic> was an orthographic convention of Shakespeare&rsquo;s which surfaced occasionally in the printed quartos, its weaving in and out of the Original Text, Addition II (Hand D) and the printed Shakespeare plays need entail no rationale or &lsquo;motivation&rsquo;. The sequence of <italic>Love&rsquo;s Labour&rsquo;s Lost</italic>, the Original Text, Addition II (Hand D) and <italic>Troilus</italic> is not essential to System 1. Double terminal <italic>t</italic> is found once in Quartos of <italic>Richard III</italic>, four times in <italic>Love&rsquo;s Labour&rsquo;s Lost</italic>, once in <italic>Henry IV, Part 2</italic>, six times in <italic>Troilus</italic>, twice in <italic>Othello</italic>, and three times in <italic>King Lear</italic>, all of which were mediated by printers&rsquo; preference for the more commonly and economically employed single terminal <italic>t</italic>.</p>
<p>Addition I (Hand A) by Chettle has no occurrences of the terminal double <italic>t</italic>. In his seminal work on orthography, A. C. Partridge wrote,
<disp-quote content-type="extract"><p>If a certain spelling of a particular word (or a graphic rendering of a particular sound) occurs with a reasonable regularity in texts that good bibliographical or other evidence leads us to believe are based directly on autograph copy, then the spelling in question may be assumed to derive from Shakespeare himself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN16"><sup>16</sup></xref></p></disp-quote>
The terminal double <italic>t</italic> is &lsquo;a graphic rendering of a particular sound&rsquo; which occurs with reasonable regularity (6 times out of all 141 terminal <italic>t</italic>) in the Shakespeare autograph Addition II (Hand D).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN17"><sup>17</sup></xref> If the ratios of terminal <italic>tt</italic> to terminal <italic>t</italic> in Hand D and the Original Text are compared with each other by using Fisher&rsquo;s Exact Test (6 -<italic>tt</italic>:135 -<italic>t</italic> versus 62 -<italic>tt</italic>:1768 -<italic>t</italic>), the probability is 0.47, virtually the toss of a coin and well within the parameters of likelihood. If the ratios of terminal <italic>tt</italic> to terminal <italic>t</italic> in Hand D and <italic>John a Kent</italic> are compared, (6 -<italic>tt</italic>: 135 -<italic>t</italic> versus 0 -<italic>tt</italic>: 1585 -<italic>t</italic>), the probability is less than 0.0001, less than one chance in ten thousand&mdash;as expected.</p>
<p>If the habit of using the terminal double <italic>t</italic> belongs to Kahneman&rsquo;s subconscious System 1, then the same author may have been responsible for its instinctive use in Hand D and the Original Text of <italic>More</italic>. If the habit of using the terminal double <italic>t</italic> belongs to Kahneman&rsquo;s fully conscious System 2, then Munday&rsquo;s use, entailing effort and attention, for his own and possibly Chettle&rsquo;s Original Text, poses difficult questions that have not been addressed.</p>
<sec sec-type="cases"><title>A Case in Point</title>
<p>Although the double <italic>t</italic> at the end of words was often penned by writers of the period, printers were reluctant to print a redundant letter, and, as a consequence, the terminal double <italic>tt</italic> is rare in modern English spelling.</p>
<p>An initial search of over three hundred early modern printed plays in their original spelling reveals that 273 have no words ending with double <italic>t</italic>, 42 contain a single occurrence, 19 have two, and another 24 have from 3 to 19 occurrences. The average for 358 printed plays is 0.64 occurrences per play.</p>
<p>By contrast, the average number of words with terminal double <italic>t</italic> in thirteen extant &lsquo;manuscript&rsquo; plays is 128.6 per play. These plays were printed years after their composition when antiquarian concerns preserved their original handwritten orthography. The striking contrast between printed and manuscript plays with respect to this habit can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gjs162-F1">Figure 1</xref> where 371 plays are displayed with their numbers of terminal <italic>tt</italic> indicated on the vertical axis. Were it not for a single exception, <italic>John a Kent</italic> with no occurrences, one could say that the search confirms the hypothesis that early modern printers significantly reduced the numbers of terminal <italic>tt</italic> originally penned in manuscripts.
<fig id="gjs162-F1"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>An orthographic difference between manuscript and printed plays</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gjs162f1p"/></fig></p>
<p>The thirteen MS plays are: <italic>Woodstock</italic> (381 <italic>tt</italic>&rsquo;s), Heywood&rsquo;s <italic>The Captives</italic> (320), Dekker&rsquo;s <italic>The Welsh Ambassadors</italic> (192), Heywood&rsquo;s <italic>The Escapes of Jupiter</italic> (170), <italic>Edmund Ironside</italic> (150), Massinger&rsquo;s <italic>The Parliament of Love</italic> (95), the Original Text of <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic> (62), Fletcher&rsquo;s <italic>Sir John Van Olden Barnavelt</italic> (55), Marston&rsquo;s <italic>Masque Entertainment</italic> (36), Middleton&rsquo;s <italic>The Witch</italic> (32), Chapman&rsquo;s <italic>Masque of the Twelve Months</italic> (26), Greene&rsquo;s <italic>John of Bordeaux</italic> (24), and Munday&rsquo;s <italic>John a Kent and John a Cumber</italic> (0).</p>
<p>Munday&rsquo;s MS <italic>John a Kent</italic> is unusual for positioning itself among the printed plays without the final <italic>tt</italic>. It is noteworthy that the Original Text of <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic>, penned in the same hand as <italic>John a Kent</italic>, has 62 words ending in <italic>tt</italic>. Besides these two plays, there are two other MS plays in the same handwriting, Heywood&rsquo;s <italic>The Captives</italic> and <italic>The Escapes of Jupiter</italic>, shown on the right of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gjs162-F1">Figure 1</xref>. The types and tokens they have in common are compared in <xref ref-type="table" rid="gjs162-T1">Table 1</xref>, which lists the relevant orthographic word types in each play with their numbers of occurrence.
<table-wrap id="gjs162-T1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Orthographic word types and rate of occurrence</p></caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th>Escapes</th>
<th>Captives</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>abbatt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>abbott</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>18</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>abett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>acquitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>addmitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>admitt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>att</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>29</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>bankett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>banquett</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>beegett</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>beegott</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>begett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>beneffitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>budgett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>11</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Butt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Canott</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>20</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>caskett</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>chariott</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>closett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>cownterfett</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>cownterffett</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>creditt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>crotchett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>cutt</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>decrepitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>drawenett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>fett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>ffagott</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>ffatt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>ffett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>ffoott</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>fforfett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Fforgett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Ffishemarkett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Fitt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Fforfett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Forfett</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Forgett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Forgott</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Garrett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Gett</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Gott</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>9</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Habitt</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Ha&rsquo;tt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Hitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Hott</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Itt</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>18</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Lett</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>36</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Limitt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Lott</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Markett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Marchantt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Meritt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Mett</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Mullett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Nett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>9</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Nott</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Parrott</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Perffitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Plott</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Pockett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Profitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Putt</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>24</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Rott</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Satt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Secrett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Sett</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>18</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Shott</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Shutt</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Sitt</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Spiritt</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Spitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Splitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Spyritt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Strompett</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Submitt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Surffett</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Surfett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Sweett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Swett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Turbutt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Visitt</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>wether-bett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Wertt</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Wett</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Writt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Yett</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
<p>The correlation coefficient for the two column vectors is 0.79 for 88 items. As expected for habits of the same penman/author, they are highly correlated. Kahneman&rsquo;s System 1 would account for the association.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="gjs162-T2">Table 2</xref> lists the words with terminal <italic>tt</italic> in the Original Text of <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic> and <italic>John a Kent</italic>, both in the handwriting of Anthony Munday.
<table-wrap id="gjs162-T2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Words with terminal <italic>tt</italic> in <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic> and <italic>John a Kent</italic>, original texts</p></caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead align="left">
<tr>
<th/>
<th>More</th>
<th>JaK</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>bett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>comitt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>cutt</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>diett</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>fatt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Fitt</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>frett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>gott</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>hott</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>markett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>meritt</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>nett</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>nott</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>poett</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>riott</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>wett</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>witt</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>writt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>ytt</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
<p>There is no correlation. The contrast here with the comparison between the Heywood plays suggests that the same handwriting does not by itself include the habit of using the terminal <italic>tt</italic>. There is an orthographic factor which separates <italic>John a Kent</italic> from the Original Text of <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic>, and thus asks for an explanation. Random fluctuations in early modern spelling do not account for the systematic difference between the orthography of the Heywood plays on the one hand, and the accepted Munday plays on the other with respect to terminal <italic>tt</italic>. A difference of authorship has been ruled out by some.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="gjs162-FN18"><sup>18</sup></xref> If such an explanation is deemed improbable, what alternatives in terms of System 1 or System 2, or for that matter any other, might be proposed?</p></sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="gjs162-FN1"><p><sup>1</sup> D. Kahneman, <italic>Thinking, Fast and Slow</italic> (New York, 2011), especially 19&ndash;105.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN2"><p><sup>2</sup> Unmotivated habits are radically altered only with the conscious intervention of System 2. The ability to swim, drive a car, play the piano, or speak a foreign language once mastered, constitute unmotivated habits (System 1) They require, however, the motivated intervention of System 2 (attention and effort) for their transfer, i.e. teaching by someone else and overcoming the difficulty of establishing a new habit in the learner.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN3"><p><sup>3</sup> <italic>Henry VIII</italic> (<italic>All is True</italic>), ed. G. McMullan (London, 2000), 119. &lsquo;Generically and iconographically then, <italic>The Winter&rsquo;s Tale</italic> and <italic>Henry VIII</italic> have a great deal in common, and certainly more than &ldquo;late play&rdquo; critics have generally cared to acknowledge. But the principal connection between the two plays is the apparent similarity of the plays&rsquo; spurned and rejected queens&hellip;&rsquo;</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN4"><p><sup>4</sup> <italic>Henry VIII</italic>, II.iv.123. Among many others, &lsquo;Katherine, Queen of England, come into the court!&rsquo; Holinshed: &lsquo;Katherine, queene of England, come into the court.&rsquo;</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN5"><p><sup>5</sup> For collocations which appear in the Original Text of <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic> and relatively adjacent in <italic>Henry VI, Part 2</italic>, see T. Merriam, &lsquo;Conjunction of collocations in <italic>More</italic> and <italic>2H6&rsquo;</italic>, <italic>N&amp;Q</italic>, cclvii (2012), 60. Note should be taken that there are two instances, not one as stated, of the named collocations in the 1594 Quarto, <italic>The First part of the Contention</italic>. The collocation is <italic>God saue the King, God saue the King</italic> at line 1922.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN6"><p><sup>6</sup> L. L. Sch&uuml;cking, &lsquo;Das Datum des Pseudo-Shakespeareschen <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic>&rsquo;, <italic>Englische Studien</italic>, xlvi (1912&ndash;13), 228&ndash;51; &lsquo;Shakespeare and <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic>,&rsquo; <italic>Review of English Studies</italic>, i (1925): 40&ndash;59.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN7"><p><sup>7</sup> <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic>, ed. J. Jowett (London, 2011), 424 ff.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN8"><p><sup>8</sup> Jowett, 426.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN9"><p><sup>9</sup> Jowett, 432.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN10"><p><sup>10</sup> Jowett, 423.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN11"><p><sup>11</sup> S. McMillin, <italic>The Elizabethan Theatre and</italic> The Book of Sir Thomas More (Ithaca, NY, 1987), 60.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN12"><p><sup>12</sup> McMillin, 159. &lsquo;It [Original Text] was originally written for Alleyn and the large, risk-running company of Strange&rsquo;s men in 1592&ndash;93. It was revised and cut down a decade later for the Admiral&rsquo;s men, when they were reviving Alleyn&rsquo;s big roles at the Fortune.&rsquo;</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN13"><p><sup>13</sup> See Jowett, 100&ndash;01.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN14"><p><sup>14</sup> &lsquo;Shakespeare and <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic>&rsquo;, 57. Sch&uuml;cking does raise objections to Thompson&rsquo;s analysis and finds the letters <italic>h</italic> and <italic>s</italic> &lsquo;hopelessly and absolutely dissimilar in signatures and manuscript [Hand D]&rsquo;, 40.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN15"><p><sup>15</sup> Line references are to <italic>The Book of Sir Thomas More</italic>, ed. W. W. Greg, Malone Society (Oxford, 1911 &amp; 1961). These are given for words appearing both in the Original Text and elsewhere.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN16"><p><sup>16</sup> A. C. Partridge, <italic>Orthography in Shakespeare and Elizabethan Drama: a Study of Colloquial Contractions, Elisions, Prosody and Punctuation</italic> (London, 1964), 5. This work does not appear in the bibliography of 3rd Arden <italic>More</italic>. Nor does 3rd Arden include an extended consideration of orthography in the manuscripts of <italic>John a Kent</italic> and <italic>Sir Thomas More</italic>. The suggestion (Jowett, 416) is offered that T. Merriam, &lsquo;Orthographic changes in <italic>John a Kent</italic> and Hand M of <italic>More</italic>&rsquo; <italic>Notes and Queries</italic>, ccli (2006), 475&ndash;78 is idiosyncratic.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN17"><p><sup>17</sup> Shakespeare&rsquo;s authorship of Hand D as established by the editor of 3rd Arden, 437&ndash;53.</p></fn>
<fn id="gjs162-FN18"><p><sup>18</sup> &lsquo;There are no known examples from the period of a dramatist copying a play in which he had no hand&rsquo;. Jowett, 419. The anonymous <italic>Ironside</italic> and <italic>Woodstock</italic> are, of course, unable to support the generalization. The statement cannot be independently proven for the remaining MS plays because of the absence of so-called controls.</p></fn>
</fn-group></back>
</article>