<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<component xmlns="http://www.wiley.com/namespaces/wiley" version="2.0" type="serialArticle" xml:lang="en" xml:id="WENG12059">
    <header>
        <publicationMeta level="product">
            <doi origin="wiley" registered="yes">10.1111/(ISSN)1467-971X</doi>
            <issn type="print">0883-2919</issn>
            <issn type="electronic">1467-971X</issn>
            <idGroup>
                <id type="product" value="WENG"/>
            </idGroup>
            <titleGroup>
                <title type="main" sort="WORLD ENGLISHES">World Englishes</title>
                <title type="short">World Englishes</title>
            </titleGroup>
        </publicationMeta>
        <publicationMeta level="part" position="12104">
            <doi>10.1111/weng.2013.32.issue-4</doi>
            <titleGroup>
                <title type="specialIssueTitle">SYMPOSIUM ON WORLD ENGLISHES AND INTERNATIONAL CALL CENTRES</title>
            </titleGroup>
            <copyright ownership="publisher">Copyright © 2013 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</copyright>
            <numberingGroup>
                <numbering type="journalVolume" number="32">32</numbering>
                <numbering type="journalIssue">4</numbering>
            </numberingGroup>
            <creators>
                <creator xml:id="sped1" creatorRole="guestEditor">
                    <personName>
                        <givenNames>KINGSLEY</givenNames>
                        <familyName>BOLTON</familyName>
                    </personName>
                </creator>
            </creators>
            <coverDate startDate="2013-12">December 2013</coverDate>
        </publicationMeta>
        <publicationMeta level="unit" position="50" type="article" status="forIssue">
            <doi origin="wiley">10.1111/weng.12059</doi>
            <idGroup>
                <id type="unit" value="WENG12059"/>
            </idGroup>
            <countGroup>
                <count type="pageTotal" number="15"/>
            </countGroup>
            <titleGroup>
                <title type="articleCategory">Articles</title>
                <title type="tocHeading1">Papers</title>
            </titleGroup>
            <copyright ownership="publisher">© 2013 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</copyright>
            <eventGroup>
                <event type="manuscriptReceived" date="2013-07-25"/>
                <event type="xmlCreated" agent="Aptara" date="2013-09-10"/>
                <event type="xmlConverted" agent="Converter:WILEY_ML3G_TO_WILEY_ML3GV2 version:3.2.6 mode:FullText" date="2013-11-19"/>
                <event type="firstOnline" date="2013-11-19"/>
                <event type="publishedOnlineFinalForm" date="2013-11-19"/>
                <event type="xmlConverted" agent="Converter:WML3G_To_WML3G version:4.6.4 mode:FullText" date="2015-10-02"/>
            </eventGroup>
            <numberingGroup>
                <numbering type="pageFirst">521</numbering>
                <numbering type="pageLast">535</numbering>
            </numberingGroup>
            <linkGroup>
                <link type="toTypesetVersion" href="file:WENG.WENG12059.pdf"/>


            </linkGroup>
        </publicationMeta>
        <contentMeta>
            <titleGroup>
                <title type="main">English and Cantonese in a bilingual call centre in Hong Kong</title>
                <title type="shortAuthors">Marvin Lam and Carol Yu</title>
                <title type="short">English and Cantonese in a bilingual call centre in Hong Kong</title>
            </titleGroup>
            <creators>
                <creator xml:id="weng12059-cr-0001" creatorRole="author" affiliationRef="#weng12059-aff-0001">
                    <personName>
                        <givenNames>MARVIN</givenNames>
                        <familyName>LAM</familyName>
                    </personName>
                    <contactDetails>
                        <email>marvin.lam@polyu.edu.hk</email>
                    </contactDetails>
                </creator>
                <creator xml:id="weng12059-cr-0002" creatorRole="author" affiliationRef="#weng12059-aff-0002">
                    <personName>
                        <givenNames>CAROL</givenNames>
                        <familyName>YU</familyName>
                    </personName>
                    <contactDetails>
                        <email>yucarol@gmail.com</email>
                    </contactDetails>
                </creator>
            </creators>
            <affiliationGroup>
                <affiliation xml:id="weng12059-aff-0001" countryCode="HK">
                    <orgDiv>Department of English</orgDiv>
                    <orgName>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</orgName>
                    <address>
<country>Hong Kong</country>
</address>
                </affiliation>
                <affiliation xml:id="weng12059-aff-0002">
                    <orgDiv>Centre for Applied English Studies</orgDiv>
                    <orgName>The University of Hong Kong</orgName>
                </affiliation>
            </affiliationGroup>
            <abstractGroup>
                <abstract type="main">
                    <title type="main">ABSTRACT</title>
                    <p>With the rapid development of telecommunications and the business processing outsourcing (BPO) industry, many companies are establishing call centres for customer service in
                        developing countries, where English is the major language used in the industry but often not spoken as the first language. While there is an abundance of research on call
                        centre communication from the perspectives of business and management, sociolinguistics and applied linguistics, there is still a dearth of information about the use of English
                        in the BPO industry with the coexistence of other languages. This paper presents a comparative study on the use of English and Cantonese in call centre communication conducted
                        in an international healthcare insurance organisation in Hong Kong. English and Cantonese calls with apparent conflicts were transcribed and analysed in terms of how customer
                        service representatives (CSRs) respond to complaints, and how customers enact their negative emotions while complaining.</p>
                </abstract>
            </abstractGroup>
        </contentMeta>
    </header>
    <body sectionsNumbered="no">
        <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0010">
            <title type="main">INTRODUCTION</title>
            <p>The emergence of the telephone‐based services industry can be traced back to the late 1950s (see Farberow and Shneidman <link href="#weng12059-bib-0019"/>; Fox <link
                    href="#weng12059-bib-0028"/>; Lester and Brockopp <link href="#weng12059-bib-0044"/>). From then on, different kinds of call centres have been established and this industry has
                diversified and expanded dramatically in recent years. With the rapid development of telecommunications, information technology enabled services (ITES) and business processing
                outsourcing (BPO) industry, many companies, in an attempt to reduce costs, are establishing call centres in developing countries, such as India, the Philippines, Malaysia and China,
                where English is the major language used in the industry but often spoken not as the first language. Many customer service organisations in such countries now have call centres, and
                often an organisation will deliberate whether to outsource, that is, enlist the services to a third party vendor who oversees the customer service business, as opposed to keeping
                customer service in‐house. The range of customer service provided through the ITES industry varies from simple directory enquiries, hot‐lines for trouble shooting problems with
                products, to more professional services such as the maintenance of the organisation's information system, to health care, accounting, mortgages, investment, brokering and other highly
                professional tasks.</p>
            <p>The growth in this global, multilingual industry has in turn given rise to an expanding interest in research from the perspectives of business and management, sociolinguistics, and
                applied linguistics. Much of the research into call centre services is from the domain of business, which has attended to issues of information systems, productivity, work organisation
                and measures of quality assurance (e.g. Amaratunga et al. <link href="#weng12059-bib-0002"/>; O'Neil <link href="#weng12059-bib-0054"/>). Some are more sociological in orientation
                focusing on labour relations and the worker (e.g. Taylor and Bain <link href="#weng12059-bib-0061"/>; <link href="#weng12059-bib-0062"/>; <link href="#weng12059-bib-0063"/>; Taylor et
                al. <link href="#weng12059-bib-0064"/>; Knights and McCabe <link href="#weng12059-bib-0042"/>; Glucksmann <link href="#weng12059-bib-0033"/>; Bolton and Houlihan <link
                    href="#weng12059-bib-0005"/>). There is consensus in these studies that the front line workers in call centres experience considerable stress and pressure (Irish <link
                    href="#weng12059-bib-0041"/>; Knights and McCabe <link href="#weng12059-bib-0042"/>; O'Neill <link href="#weng12059-bib-0054"/>). It is argued that ‘the pressure is intense because
                she (the customer service representative, CSR) knows her work is being measured, her speech monitored, and it often leaves her mentally, physically and emotionally exhausted’ (Taylor
                and Bain <link href="#weng12059-bib-0061"/>: 115).</p>
            <p>This emphasis on productivity and quality in the stressful working environment of call centre service makes communication between CSRs and customers an interesting area for applied
                linguistic research. Previous studies have connected with issues of employment focusing on employee language assessment (Friginal <link href="#weng12059-bib-0029"/>), on training in
                employee accent neutralisation (Cowie <link href="#weng12059-bib-0009"/>) and in the recognition of problematic stages of interactions (Forey and Lockwood <link
                    href="#weng12059-bib-0026"/>). From a sociolinguistic perspective, Cameron (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0007"/>), discusses the similarities between the preferred style of speech in
                call centres and what is popularly thought of as ‘women's language’, and considers the impact of globalisation on the workers in the industry with language being a central concern.
                Adolphs et al. (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0001"/>) focus on call centres within the British National Health Service Helpline, while the book, <i>Calling for help</i> edited by Baker
                et al. (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0003"/>), discusses helpline interactions from a conversational analysis perspective. Murtagh (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0053"/>) analyses calls
                made to a UK mobile phone help centre and focuses on the properties of the instruction/receipt adjacency pair. There are also a number of studies focusing on the English used in call
                centre services (Cameron <link href="#weng12059-bib-0007"/>; Forey and Lockwood <link href="#weng12059-bib-0025"/>, <link href="#weng12059-bib-0026"/>; Forey <link
                    href="#weng12059-bib-0022"/>; <link href="#weng12059-bib-0023"/>; Forey et al. <link href="#weng12059-bib-0027"/>; Cowie <link href="#weng12059-bib-0009"/>; Friginal <link
                    href="#weng12059-bib-0029"/>; Hood and Forey <link href="#weng12059-bib-0040"/>; Lockwood et al. <link href="#weng12059-bib-0046"/>) and other languages, such as Chinese (Xu et al.
                    <link href="#weng12059-bib-0066"/>)</p>
            <p>While there is an abundance of research on call centre communication, there is still a dearth of information about the use of English in the BOP industry in relation to its global and
                multilingual setting. As mentioned above, numerous call centres are set up in countries where English is often the second or foreign language while English is the major language used
                in the service. There are few, if any, studies available that focus on the environment in which the English language co‐exists with other languages. A comparative study on call centre
                communication between the use of English and the use of the first language spoken in the outsourcing destinations may then be beneficial to the multicultural and multilingual
                communities where the BPO industry is situated. With this concern, this paper presents a comparative study of the use of English and Cantonese (a southern dialect of Chinese) in call
                centre communication conducted in Hong Kong, aiming at yielding a better understanding of the nature of English usage in such multilingual and multicultural setting of the BPO
                industry.</p>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0020">
            <title type="main">ENGLISH AND CANTONESE IN A HONG KONG CALL CENTRE</title>
            <p>In the present study, collaboration and co‐operation were obtained from an international healthcare insurance organisation in Hong Kong, which is referred as Healthline in this paper.
                Healthline conducts business interactions mainly in three languages: Cantonese, which is the first language for the majority of people in Hong Kong, English, which serves the
                expatriate community of the region and non‐Chinese‐speaking customers as a lingua franca, and Putonghua, which is the standard variety of the Chinese language spoken by Mainland
                Chinese customers. Access to the customer care unit was provided to the research team. The customer care unit consists of 10 CSRs and one manager and Cantonese was their first language
                and the dominant language used in the unit among colleagues. There were seven females and four males, and the ages of the participants working in the unit ranged from 24 to 45 years
                old. Most of them had obtained high school diplomas and three were university graduates with one graduating from an overseas university. This means that most of them have received
                9‐year compulsory bilingual (Chinese and English) education provided by the Hong Kong Government. Healthline has approximately 185,000 clients in Hong Kong and the 10 CSRs have to
                handle around 600 calls (both inbound and outbound) per day. The majority of the calls (95%) are in Cantonese, 3 per cent of the calls are in English and around 2 per cent are in
                Putonghua. This implies that the CSRs of the unit are required to be trilingual in order to deliver and exchange information with their customers effectively. This complex linguistic
                situation of Healthline is typical for the BPO industry worldwide.</p>
            <p>The unit is relatively small so it does not have a highly automated interactive voice response system. Thus all agents in this unit should be prepared to cope with any type of call in
                any of the three languages offered. This validates the comparative investigation of the use of English and Cantonese because the two languages are spoken by the same team of CSRs,
                instead of having separately teams for different languages. Due to the intrinsic nature of customer care, CSRs are always assumed to be responsible for the communicative and linguistic
                burden, if there are any (Friginal <link href="#weng12059-bib-0029"/>). With the complexity of linguistics and product information requirements, first‐time resolution of the calls,
                according to the assistant manager, reaches up to 90 per cent. Topics of the calls are diverse, with 80 per cent related to claim issues, such as claims procedures, claims status and
                claims benefits. The nature of Healthline as a healthcare insurance organisation also reflects the diversity of services provided by call centres in the BPO industry. Instead of merely
                handling simple directory enquiries or as hotlines for troubleshooting problems with products, BPO call centres like Healthline constitutes part of the (private) healthcare system.
                Thus, this study can be further contextualised within the scope of sociological and linguistic research on healthcare.</p>
            <p>The delivery of care – as a sociological conception (Fine <link href="#weng12059-bib-0020"/>) – has been identified as a key issue to the effectiveness of the delivery and the quality
                of healthcare (Falchuk <link href="#weng12059-bib-0018"/>). Soldato et al. (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0057"/>) shows that caregivers’ distress and dissatisfaction can be associated
                with patients’ depression, suggesting what attitudes are enacted and how they are enacted between healthcare practitioners and healthcare recipients plays an important role in the
                quality of the system. Besides, there is a rich body of research on intercultural communication in healthcare situations, such as Dogra (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0013"/>), Hardoff
                and Schonmann (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0038"/>) and Spencer and Silverman (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0058"/>) addressing the issue of designing specific training and professional
                development for medical students and practitioners in treating culturally and linguistically diverse patients. However, call centre communication is rarely studied with its role as
                constituting part of the healthcare system being addressed, thus the present study on the use of English in the multilingual and multicultural setting of call centres in the BPO
                industry focuses on how care is perceived and how attitudes are enacted by the two parties concerned – the staff of the call centre as practitioners of the private healthcare system,
                and the customers as the recipients of healthcare.</p>
            <p>With the focus of the present study as care and attitude, various methodological approaches have been adopted in this study to investigate the use of English in relation to the
                multilingual environment. Rigour in the present study is achieved by triangulation (Creswell <link href="#weng12059-bib-0011"/>: 174), which is ‘central to achieving credibility’
                (Sturman <link href="#weng12059-bib-0059"/>: 110), with the key methods as ethnography, interviews and texts analysis. Candlin and Candlin (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0008"/>: 134)
                point out that there is a need for ‘collaboration of applied linguists, professional practitioners and researchers from other areas of social science in the exploration of healthcare
                communication in multilingual/multicultural contexts’, which is in line with the methodology adopted in the present study. For the ethnographic aspect of the study, six visits were
                made to the site of enquiry. Immediate observations, field notes taken following the model suggested by Silverman (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0056"/>) and other related data concerning
                with the working environment were collected on site in order to capture an accurate account of the context, that is, the industry, the culture, policy, practice training, etc. For the
                interviews, Fontana and Frey's (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0021"/>: 652) principles of conducting semi‐structured interviews were adopted and various stakeholders such as the CEO of
                Healthline, call centre team managers and front line CSRs were interviewed. These interviews aimed at eliciting the stakeholders’ perceptions on issues such as their definition of
                ‘care’, the different approaches they adopt to dealing with the linguistic demands in providing care via telephonic exchanges in Cantonese, English and Putonghua, the availability of
                relevant training provided to CSRs and the relation between the delivery of ‘care’ and quality assurance. These data collected through ethnographic observation and interviews helped to
                expand our understanding of the authentic calls collected for the text analysis, with which the findings are what this paper principly reports.</p>
            <p>One hundred calls in English and 100 calls in Cantonese (approximately 65,000 and 88,000 words respectively) handled by Healthline were recorded between October and November 2008.
                Consent was obtained from the customers and the CSRs and the calls were transcribed with all the sensitive data masked. As the aim of the present study is to investigate the use of
                English in the multilingual setting of the BPO industry with a particular focus on how care is perceived and how different attitudes are enacted, ‘problematic’ calls were chosen for
                text analysis. The issues raised in the problematic calls are usually not resolved and so tension, frustration and dissatisfaction are more apparent (for discussions of problematic
                calls, see Forey and Lockwood <link href="#weng12059-bib-0026"/>; Hood and Forey <link href="#weng12059-bib-0040"/>) and there is a greater variation in the interpersonal meaning. In
                the 200 calls collected, the majority of the calls are straightforward and on the whole completed without any problems. Nine English and three Cantonese calls from the corpus were
                identified as problematic and thus are included in the text analysis. As the sample size is limited, the discussion on the text analysis focuses on the qualitative aspect, that is, the
                various linguistics strategies related to how care is perceived and how different attitudes are enacted.</p>
            <p>The text analysis aims to combine the conceptual framework of systemic functional linguistics (SFL) and ethnography to take a critical discourse analytic approach. SFL applied to call
                centre discourse allows the correlation between text analysis and the analysis of the social context. The ethnographic studies in turn provide richer picture of the context. Following
                Halliday (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0034"/>; <link href="#weng12059-bib-0036"/>; Halliday and Matthiessen <link href="#weng12059-bib-0037"/>), Martin (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0047"
                />), Eggins and Slade (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0015"/>) and Eggins and Martin (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0014"/>), we present a functional interpretation of the conversational and
                generic structure of call centre interaction, with particular reference to the various linguistic strategies CSRs employ in while responding to complaints, and how customers enact
                emotions in problematic calls.</p>
            <p>Before the findings of the text analysis with the above, two concerns are discussed in the next two sections, it might be interesting to first point out that the average handling times
                of the English and Cantonese problematic calls have a big difference as 7 minutes and 3.5 minutes respectively. In an interview in this present study, a customer care manager commented
                that English calls are ‘usually more detailed and demanding’ and ‘agents have to have the courage to respond’. This suggests that that a multilingual approach in this context can
                elicit insights about the use of English that might not be prominent in studies that only focus on the use of the English language in such settings.</p>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0030">
            <title type="main">HANDLING COMPLAINTS IN ENGLISH AND CANTONESE</title>
            <p>Several linguistic strategies were identified as being adopted by CSRs in order to ease tension while responding to complaints from customers on the telephone. The use of minimal
                feedback was adopted by CSRs in very similar manner in both English and Cantonese calls, whereas the use of silence was unique to the English calls. The negotiation of the
                institutional roles between CSRs and customers also exhibited major differences between how CSRs respond to complaints in the two languages.</p>
            <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0040">
                <title type="main">The use of minimal feedback</title>
                <p>The use of minimal feedback has been identified as a very common strategy for CSRs to respond to complaints in both English and Cantonese calls, especially when the customers are
                    expressing their emotions and narrating their (very often undesirable) experience related to the complaints, as shown in examples (1) and (2) respectively. <list
                        xml:id="weng12059-list-0001" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(1) Customer</label><p> </p><p>I was extremely unhappy.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>             CSR</label><p> </p><p>Mm mm mm.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>     Customer</label><p> </p><p>But obviously gone completely downhill.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>             CSR</label><p> </p><p>Mm.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>     Customer</label><p> </p><p>Erm, now they are trying to get more money $25,000 from me.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>             CSR</label><p> </p><p>Okay.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>(2) Customer</label><p> 你地岩岩呢… 我諗你地公司呢…姐係做野呢，係咪搵 d 好 green 個 d 人黎做呀？ 真係激死我呀真係 （CSR: 唔） 成日都出錯既近來∘ 喇， 我岩岩收張 statement 呢就話我無得 claim 既∘ （CSR: 唔） 10月10號既∘ （CSR: 唔）
                                喇我10月10號呢就睇左兩次醫生既∘ （CSR: 唔） 咁第一次呢就睇…普通醫生，∘ （CSR: 唔） 就 Dr. Johnson既，睇阿陳醫生嫁∘ （CSR: 唔） 咁跟住呢陳醫生就轉介我去睇一個 E‐ N‐T 既，∘ （CSR: 唔） 就睇一個鄭森醫生既∘ （CSR: 唔） 咁點知呢我就本應呢就成套單一齊拎入黎 claim
                                既，點知鄭醫生個到呢個姑娘就寫錯左日子，∘ （CSR: 唔） 寫左07 年∘ （CSR: 唔） 咁我特登去陳醫生個到… er 特登去鄭醫生個到呢，∘ （CSR: 唔） 就給返個印，就改返個日子，咁同埋個張claim form 佢同我再send 入黎呢∘ 我大大隻…姐係搵 highlight pen highlight
                                左係…specialist 黎既∘ （CSR: 唔） 你地宜家呢就寄返張單 statement 俾我，就話一日唔可以睇∘ （CSR: 唔） 兩次醫生，咁何謂一日唔可以睇兩次醫生姐？我有埋 referral letter 嫁上一次∘ （CSR: 唔）</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label> </label><p>        ‘You just…I think your company…I mean for working, are you getting some very inexperienced people for your work? It really irritates me
                                (CSR: Mm.) that they're always making mistakes recently. I just received a statement telling me I can't claim (CSR: Mm.) on October 10. (CSR: Mm.) Okay on October 10 I
                                went to two doctors. (CSR: Mm.) The first time…a general doctor (CSR: Mm.) at Dr. Johnson, it was Dr Chan. (CSR: Mm.) And then this Dr Chan recommended me to see
                                another doctor of E‐N‐T, (CSR: Mm.) to see Dr Cheng Sum. (CSR: Mm.) Who knows, I should have the whole package of document for the claim, and who knows that nurse at Dr
                                Cheng would write the date wrong (CSR: Mm.), wrote the year as 07. (CSR: Mm.) So I particularly went to Dr Chan, err, particularly to Dr Cheng, (CSR: Mm.) to get the
                                stamp for changing the date. Together with the claim form he helped me to hand in. I emphasize – using highlight pen to highlight it's specialist (CSR: Mm.). Now you
                                post a statement back to me and tell me on one day I can't see (CSR: Mm.) two doctors, so what do you mean by can't see two doctors? I also have the referral letter
                                that time. (CSR: Mm.)’</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
                <p>In these situations, the customers seem to occupy a more dominating role as they are the ones who take the floor to speak. However, CSRs as listeners are not at all at a passive
                    position as their responses can also contribute to the construction of spoken discourse. ‘Minimal feedback’ (cf. Coates <link href="#weng12059-bib-0010"/>; Holmes <link
                        href="#weng12059-bib-0039"/>) or ‘listener vocalisation’ as Gardner (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0031"/>) terms it, are resources which CSRs draw on to influence on a
                    conversation. These items function as ‘acknowledgements, brief agreements and continuers, […] news‐marking items, […] evaluative or assessment items and questions directed at
                    clarification’ (Gardner <link href="#weng12059-bib-0031"/>: 204). Receipt tokens as such are very common in everyday verbal communication. Gardner's (<link
                        href="#weng12059-bib-0030"/>) study shows that they can appear more than a thousand times in an hour of talk. However ‘minimal’ they might seem, they play an important role on
                    how service encounters develops and thus can have some influence on the success of CSRs’ responses to complaints.</p>
                <p>As reflected by the examples, receipt tokens such as <i>Mm</i> and <i>Okay</i> have been found in the English calls analysed. In the Cantonese calls, the CSRs used 唔 (which is
                    pronounced and functions similarly to <i>Mm</i> in English) very often to provide minimal feedback. Both <i>Mm</i> and 唔 as nasals involves minimal auditory movements – without any
                    lip, tongue and jaw movement during the production of the sound – and thus they are not perceived by the customers as strong and active from the perspectives of auditory as well as
                    visual communicative channels. According to Gardner (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0032"/>), <i>Mm</i> is one of the most semantically empty tokens in conversation so its functions
                    have to be identified through the co‐texts and environments in which <i>Mm</i> is being used. This is argued to be the similar case for 唔 used by CSRs in the Cantonese calls.</p>
                <p>In Example 1, we can see how <i>Mm mm mm</i> acts as a continuer in the CSR's first turn. It was produced repeatedly (3 times) after the completion of the previous turn and this
                    position signals that the CSR has no problems in hearing and understanding the customer's expression. In terms of intonation, the first <i>Mm</i> in turn the first CSR's response
                    in Example 1 has a rising pitch contour whereas the other 2 have a level intonation contour. On intonation studies there's a general agreement that rising tones signal ‘open’ and
                    ‘continuation’ (Brazil <link href="#weng12059-bib-0006"/>; Cruttenden <link href="#weng12059-bib-0012"/>; McLemore <link href="#weng12059-bib-0052"/>:116). In this example, the CSR
                    has shown that she understood what the customer was feeling and at the same time encouraging the customer to carry on expressing her concern. <i>Mm</i> in the CSR's second turn in
                    example (1) acts as a weak acknowledgement tokens (Gardner <link href="#weng12059-bib-0031"/>: 214) as it maps onto a falling intonation after the completion of the prior turn.
                    This signals clear and problem‐free understanding of the issue from the CSR's perspective. <i>Okay</i> in the CSR's next turn also functions as an acknowledgement token but it has
                    another layer of meaning embedded in it while compared to the acknowledgement token <i>Mm</i>. From the above example, we can see while the CSR is acknowledging and giving neutral
                    response to the customer, she is also trying to assert a small closure to the issue discussed. As Beach (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0004"/>) suggests in his article on the usages
                    of <i>okay</i>, he claims that in some cases (pre‐closing stage of a telephone conversation, for example) <i>okay</i> can be treated as ‘non‐continuative’ and/or ‘closure relevant’
                    and this aspect is also reflected from the data above.</p>
                <p>We can see that CSRs use minimal feedback for several delicate functions to respond to customers’ complaints in the English calls; while 唔 as the receipt token in the minimal
                    feedback in the Cantonese calls, as illustrated in example (2), merely functions as weak acknowledgement token to represent CSR's complete and clear understanding of what is being
                    said by the customer, though it is used in higher frequency than those in the English calls.</p>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0050">
                <title type="main">The use of silence</title>
                <p>One prominent feature in the use of English by CSRs in responding to complaints in contrast with that of Cantonese is the lack of responses. Silence is a very common feature of
                    CSRs’ communication in the English calls, which is not found in the Cantonese calls. As Ephratt (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0016"/>) points out, the notion of silence as ‘an
                    absence of speech’ and is often associated with ‘negativity, passiveness, impotence’ in the speech studies in the 1970s and only until the 1990s did linguists start to be
                    interested in studying the function of silence in human communication. For instance, it is still conceived to be ambiguous in conversation analysis nowadays as it has the ability
                    to positively contribute or to show malfunctions in conversation, namely, positive and negative valuation of silence (Tannen and Saville‐Troike <link href="#weng12059-bib-0060"/>).
                    This issue with silence is also exhibited in the English calls. As shown in example (3), a silence of 8 seconds occurs when it was the CSR's turn to speak, after the customer
                    raised a rhetorical question and handed the floor over to the CSR: ‘So how could you like receive the claim form but not the receipt?’ Through this rhetorical question, the
                    customer expressed her amazement on a situation that seemed to be impossible. <list xml:id="weng12059-list-0002" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(3) Customer</label><p> </p><p>So I'm I'm quite surprised. You know after so many changes then I was asked to provide this receipt because every time every
                                time I am gonna attach the receipt…to you…together with the original claim form. So how could you like receive the claim form but not the receipt?</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label> </label><p>     </p><p>(Silence, from 4:56–5:08, in total 8 seconds)</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>             CSR</label><p> </p><p>(murmuring) the receipt, 15 thousand…</p></listItem></list></p>
                <p>From the customers’ perspective, silence can be interpreted as negative as it might be seen as a sign of the CSR's incapability to deal with problems and conflicts, especially in
                    telephonic encounters when no other means of exchanging meaning (such as nodding) can be used to mediate the communication. Besides, it is often observed that no repairing or
                    interpersonal language is used by CSRs such as the one in example (3) after the silence and that often leads to the multiplication of customers’ frustration. Nonetheless, from the
                    CSRs’ perspective as elicited by the interviews, silence is often adopted for conflict‐avoidance in situations exemplified above and remains to be a prominent feature of CSRs’
                    language use in the English calls.</p>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0060">
                <title type="main">The negotiation of institutional roles</title>
                <p>When analysing telephonic customer service interaction, it is inevitable to investigate the negotiation of interpersonal boundaries and inequalities between the interactants with
                    their institutional roles in the conversation due to the intrinsic nature of the industry, that is, on the one hand CSRs are obliged to provide services which orient the customers;
                    on the other hand CSRs are perceived as possessing more information of the system and customers and act as information‐givers, especially in the case of confusion as they should be
                    able to make use of their professional knowledge to clear any doubts and questions that customers might have. In the situation of conflicts as in customers’ complaints, compliance
                    often serves as a remedy from one of the interactants who appears to be at a less powerful position in the interaction. The calls analysed show drastic differences between English
                    and Cantonese in terms how institutional roles are negotiated in the telephonic service encounters. Example (4) depicts a typical situation in the English calls when a customer
                    complaints, entailing a negotiation of the institutional role of the CSR. <list xml:id="weng12059-list-0003" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>   (4) CSR</label><p> </p><p>Hello, Mr. Johnson, so for for the erm normal procedure member of eh who has…</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>Customer</label><p> </p><p>No it's not normal. If you have a US Healthline, you you don't have to pre‐pay, you pre‐pay because you got a Hong Kong
                                Healthline</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>         CSR</label><p> </p><p>But this is, but this is a Hong Kong Healthline, Hong Kong…</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>Customer</label><p> </p><p>The way you work in international company has no international… erm…similarity.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>         CSR</label><p> </p><p>Er, no. But it is be…be…be…be…be…be…because the different policies between the Healthline US and Healthline Hong
                            Kong.</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
                <p>In the English calls, where the discrepancies of company policies are challenged, CSRs often exert their institutional role by referring to the company policies and suggest that the
                    case is non‐negotiable, based on the policy and regulations of the organisation. As shown in example (4), the CSR is placing the onus of responsibility on the ‘normal’ company
                    policies, and as such the CSR and other personnel are not involved in the decision‐making and are not to blame – it is the policy that is responsible for the complications and not
                    the organisation, customer or individual involved. Though the customer rejects the explanation and keeps challenging the CSR (his second turn in example 4), the CSR sticks to his
                    ground by firmly referring to the company policy.</p>
                <p>This exertion of an institutional role with the emphasis on the established policy as routinisation is the way with which CSRs attempt to make customers to comply as a way to
                    respond customers’ complaints. Hierarchy and power difference is apparent in such situation but that is often naturalised by the CSRs’ act of ideationalising the essence of
                    ‘must‐ness’ of the company policy. As in example (4), The CSR is in fact telling the customer that he has to prepay the medical cost because he has a Healthline Hong Kong policy
                    that is different from the US one. Instead of issuing the command explicitly, the CSR chose to mention the ‘policies’ and the ‘normal procedures’. So on the one hand, the CSR can
                    stay implicit with his command and that he would not be perceived as rude; and on the other hand, he can put the responsibility on the ‘normal’ company policies so that the whole
                    exchange would seem to be more objective. (cf. objective and implicit modal assessment; Halliday and Matthiessen, <link href="#weng12059-bib-0037"/>) Overall CSRs try to strike a
                    balance between the exertion of their institutional role and the avoidance of being face‐threatening to customers.</p>
                <p>Such exertion of institutional role and routinisation by CSRs is rarely found in the Cantonese call. Moreover, the institutional roles between CSRs and customers are sometimes
                    negotiated such that the hierarchy in between seems to be reserved, which is illustrated by example (5). <list xml:id="weng12059-list-0004" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(5) Customer</label><p> </p><p>你係要知道你話吖話 period of break down of medication 吖嘛 ∘咁我淨係寫medication啦, 我唔需話 consultation 另外幾多, 夾埋幾多來埋等如個數啦, 個 difference就係
                                consultation∘</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label> </label><p>        ‘You want to know the period of breakdown of medication; then I only wrote medication. I don't need to say consultation amount…just need to
                                sum up the amount and the difference is consultation.’</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>             CSR</label><p> </p><p>個 difference 就係 consultation 喇 ∘ ‘The difference is consultation.’</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>     Customer</label><p> </p><p>係喇 ∘ ‘Yes.’</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>             CSR</label><p> </p><p>明白，係啱 ∘ ‘Understand, yes, right.’</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
                <p>As discussed above, it should be the CSR that is perceived to be the information‐giver. However, in the encounter in example (5) it is actually the customer who is taking the role
                    of giving information and clearing confusion while the CSR complies with what the customer says. The customer is clearly the one who is more dominant through his use of instructive
                    and authoritative language (e.g. <i>You want to know…</i>, <i>I don't need to say</i>, <i>just need to sum up</i>) while the CSR has a comparatively submissive role and this is
                    also reflected by his use of language, such as his last turn in the example, <i>Understood. Yes. Right</i>.</p>
                <p>Apart from allowing the institutional roles and the hierarchy between the information‐holding CSRs and customers to be negotiated, CSRs in the Cantonese calls also make use of
                    particles, which is uniquely abundant in Cantonese as interpersonal negotiators and with many other linguistic functions (Wang <link href="#weng12059-bib-0065"/>; Li and Thompson
                        <link href="#weng12059-bib-0045"/>; Kwok <link href="#weng12059-bib-0043"/>) to mediate the exchanges of giving and demanding of information and goods‐&amp;‐services (Halliday
                        <link href="#weng12059-bib-0035"/>) in the telephonic encounters. Examples (6) and (7) show that questions and imperative commands (i.e. demands of information and goods &amp;
                    services) in Cantonese by CSRs are always downplayed by the use of particles. <list xml:id="weng12059-list-0005" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(6)</label><p>個 member 叫咩名呀 ？ ‘What is the name of the member + aa3’</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>(7)</label><p>你等我一陣吓 ∘ ‘You wait for a moment + ha2’</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
                <p>The use of particles by CSRs to downplay the exertion of institutional role does not limit to the demand of information and goods‐&amp;‐services. Table <link
                        href="#weng12059-tbl-0001"/> lists some examples of the particles used by CSRs to show their expansive use of particles in all the speech functions in the Cantonese calls.</p>
                <tabular xml:id="weng12059-tbl-0001" pRights="unknown" eRights="yes" copyright="John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.">
                    <title type="main">The use of particles by CSRs in the Cantonese calls</title>
                    <table frame="topbot">
                        <tgroup cols="4">
                            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" align="left"/>
                            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" align="left"/>
                            <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" align="left"/>
                            <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" align="left"/>
                            <thead>
                                <row rowsep="1">
                                    <entry colname="col1">Role</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col2">Commodity</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col3">Speech function</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col4">Particles</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry colname="col1">Giving</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col2">Information</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col3">Statement</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col4">啦 (<i>la1</i>, soften the tone or show lack of definiteness)</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry colname="col1"/>
                                    <entry colname="col2">Goods &amp; services</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col3">Offer</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col4">吖 (<i>aa1</i>, soften the tone)</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry colname="col1">Demanding</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col2">Information</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col3">Question</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col4">(<i>ga3</i>), 呢 (<i>le3</i>), 吖 (<i>aa3</i>) (soften the force)</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry colname="col1"/>
                                    <entry colname="col2">Goods &amp; services</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col3">Command</entry>
                                    <entry colname="col4">吖 (<i>aa1</i>), 吓 (<i>ha2</i>) (soften the force)</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </tabular>
                <p>Customers in the Cantonese calls also make much use of particles but they are mostly for the sake of increasing the degree of assertion, as shown in examples (8) and (9). Since the
                    purpose of this paper is to explore the use of English in the global and multilingual setting of the BPO industry with reference to the use of Cantonese, the findings concerning
                    with the use of particles in Cantonese have to be discussed in detail in further research. Nonetheless, the data reflects that in the Cantonese calls, the institutional roles
                    between CSRs and customers are much more negotiable than in English with the CSRs use of particles to downplay the exertions; whereas in the English calls, CSRs are more assertive
                    and institutional routinisation is often adopted (though downplayed by implicit and objective assessment) to respond to customers’ complaints. <list xml:id="weng12059-list-0006"
                        style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(8)</label><p>其實呢我想反映一下你哋嗰 d 問題呢非常之 er 抵死嘅</p>
                            <p>‘In fact I want to reflect your questions are extremely er ridiculous + ge3’</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>(9)</label><p>唔通我想佢以後會告咩？ ‘Do you think I want her to sue me in the future + me1’</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0070">
            <title type="main">ENACTING EMOTIONS</title>
            <p>The previous section discusses, from the CSRs’ perspective of presenting care, how customers’ complaints are responded to by CSRs’ use of silence and minimal responses, together with
                the negotiation of institutional roles. This section now switches to the customers’ perspective to discuss how they enact negative emotions in the problematic calls. The text analysis
                on customers’ enactment of negative emotion adopts the work on appraisal (Martin <link href="#weng12059-bib-0048"/>; Martin and Rose <link href="#weng12059-bib-0049"/>), which
                ‘concerns with evaluation: the kinds of attitudes that are negotiated in a text, the strength of the feelings involved and the ways in which values are sourced and readers aligned’
                (Martin and Rose <link href="#weng12059-bib-0049"/>: 22). The present discussion focuses on how the three types of attitudes, namely affect, judgement and appreciation, are realised in
                the English and Cantonese calls analysed; and how these attitudes are graded and scaled in the two languages.</p>
            <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0080">
                <title type="main">The realisation of negative affect</title>
                <p>The most straightforward way for customers to express negative emotion is through the realisation of negative affect, which, according to Martin and White (<link
                        href="#weng12059-bib-0050"/>), is concerned with registering human emotion and feelings. As proposed by Martin and White (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0050"/>: 49–52), there are
                    three types of affect: un/happiness in affairs of heart; in/security with emotions concerned with ecosocial well‐being and dis/satisfaction; and emotions concerned with the pursuit
                    of goals. The underlined words in example (10) show how affect, in this case, negative affect, is realised by the connotation of lexical items, which directly reflect the emotion
                    of the speaker. This direct enactment of negative emotion through affect is found to be very common in the English calls, but there is only one instance of this in the Cantonese
                    calls. <list xml:id="weng12059-list-0007" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(10)</label><p>And recently I have received a number of letters from Healthline. To be honest, I'm very <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline"
                                    >confused</span> and <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">not happy</span> with how this matter is dealt with by Healthline.</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Apart from the direct realisation of affect, customers’ negative emotions can also be indirectly enacted through appreciation, which refers to ‘meaning construing our evaluations of
                    “things”, especially things we make and performances we give, but also including natural phenomena’, and is classified in the subtypes of reaction, composition and valuation
                    (Martin and White <link href="#weng12059-bib-0050"/>: 56). This type of attitude is found to be common in both English and Cantonese calls, as underlined in examples (11) and (12).
                    In example (11), the negative appreciation is realised through the contrast between ‘I’ (the customer) getting money and ‘you’ (the company) taking the money, and the assessment of
                    the company being difficult. Moreover, sarcasm is also expressed by the instance <i>it's fine when you take the money</i>, as the customer implies Healthline has been ‘cunning’
                    with its own customers and that they only care about how to make profit. In example (12), the negative appreciation is realised by the negative connotation of the lexical items
                    assessing the company/personnel, in a way similar to how affect is realised in example (10) but for the case of affect what being assessed is the customers’ emotion. <list
                        xml:id="weng12059-list-0008" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(11)</label><p>The letter was attached and it covered all the receipt that I did everything you asked me to do. And then still you…I mean every time I have
                                Healthline, you always always <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">difficult to get money</span> at all. I mean it's fine when <span
                                    cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">you take the money</span>. And you know our company has gone through a merger and we will be we will be reconsidering our our
                                claim overall with 400 people. I will tell my HR department <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">how difficult you are</span>. Because <span
                                    cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">this is not acceptable, this is not what my HR department needs to do</span>.</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>(12)</label><p>Er 其實呢我想反映一下你地果 d 問題呢非常之 er 抵死既 ∘ Er 我喺希望响你地打電話嚟回響下因為你叫呢個問題呢真係好 silly ∘</p>
                            <p>‘Er in fact I want to reflect your questions are extremely er <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">ridiculous</span> + ge3. Er I wish to call and tell you that
                                because your question is really <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">silly</span> + ga3.’</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
                <p>What is rather unique in the Cantonese call is customers’ indirect enactment of negative emotion through the realisation of negative judgement, which is not found in the English
                    problematic calls. Judgement refers to the assessment of people, typically of their behaviour, in terms of social esteem and social sanction (Martin and Rose, <link
                        href="#weng12059-bib-0049"/>: 32–6). In example (13), which is the beginning of example (2), the negative judgement is realised through qualities that are socially considered
                    as negative, that is, being inexperienced and making mistakes. It should be noted that affect is also realised here by <i>真係激死我</i> ‘it really <span
                        cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">irritates</span> me’. In example (14), by saying ‘ask them to be more careful’, the customer is implying that they are not careful and
                    often make mistakes in their work. As shown in examples (12–14) and discussed in the previous section, customers very often use particles to be more assertive, especially in the
                    situation of enacting negative emotion. <list xml:id="weng12059-list-0009" style="custom">
                        <listItem><label>(13)</label><p>你地岩岩呢…我諗你地公司呢…姐係做野呢，係咪搵 d 好 green 個 d 人黎做呀？ 真係激死我呀真係成日都出錯既近來∘</p>
                            <p>‘You just + ne1…I think your company + ne1…I mean for working + ne1, are <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">you getting some very inexperienced people for your
                                    work</span> ± <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">aa3</span>? It really irritates me + aa3 that they're always <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline"
                                    >making mistakes</span> + ge3 recently.’</p></listItem>
                        <listItem><label>(14)</label><p>叫佢地小心 d 啦，成日都咁樣樣∘</p>
                            <p>‘<span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">Ask them to be more careful</span> + la1. It's always like this.’</p></listItem>
                    </list></p>
                <p>As discussed above, the English and Cantonese problematic calls show differences in how customers enact their negative emotions while complaining. Customers in English calls use
                    mostly negative affect and appreciation while those in Cantonese calls use appreciation and judgement. These differences may reflect the difference between English‐speaking
                    cultures and the Chinese culture in terms of the willingness in expressing and making use of personal emotion in the situation of conflicts, and the tendency for English‐speaking
                    customers to keep the complaints personal while the Chinese‐speaking customers also complaint by referring to social values.</p>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0090">
                <title type="main">The graduation of attitudes</title>
                <p>Though the enactment of negative emotions by customers differs between English and Cantonese, as discussed in the previous section, the enactments of negative attitudes in the two
                    languages are often scaled up, and such a phenomenon is studied in terms of graduation in appraisal. There are two axes for scaling attitude: intensity or amount (as force), and
                    how prototypical a category is or how clearly its boundary is drawn (as focus) (Martin and Rose <link href="#weng12059-bib-0049"/>; Matthiessen et al. <link
                        href="#weng12059-bib-0051"/>). Force is what always deployed by customers to scale up negative attitudes in the complaints. Example (11) shows three common ways of scaling up
                    in force by the customer: (1) in terms of what she was required to do for the claim, <i>it covered <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">all the receipt</span> that I did
                            <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">everything</span> you ask me to do</i>; (2) in terms of Healthline being difficult all the time, <i>you <span
                            cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">always always</span> difficult to get money <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">at all</span></i>; and (3) in terms of a threat
                    of reconsidering their contracts with Healthline, quantifying the possible loss of the contracts, <i>we will be reconsidering our our claim <span
                            cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">overall</span> with <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">400 people</span></i>. <i>Overall</i> and <i>400 people</i> act as
                    maximisers here to create the sense of high intensity.</p>
                <p>The Cantonese calls exhibit very similar phenomenon of customers’ scaling up of negative attitude. In example (13) above, the negative judgement of inexperience is scaled up as
                        <span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">好</span> green (‘<span cssStyle="text-decoration:underline">very</span> inexperienced’) and the temporality of the making of the
                    mistakes is scaled by the temporal adjunct 近來 (‘recently’). As shown in examples (13) and (14), 成日 (‘always’) is very often used by customers in the Cantonese calls to scale up the
                    negative attitudes, which is very similar in the English calls. According to Martin and White (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0050"/>), tokens such as <i>always</i> belong to the
                    upper‐most end of the intensification scale and they have been termed ‘maximisers’ by Quirk et al. (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0055"/>). The use of maximisers as such is often not
                    literal as they imply high value of the modal assessment of usuality. Martin and White (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0050"/>: 142) state that ‘this value often operates
                    hyperbolically to convey strong writer/speaker investment in the proposition, rather than any ‘literal’ sense of constancy or uninterrupted repetition’. As in example (11), the
                    customer not only chooses to use <i>always</i> to indicate her strong proposition in the complaint, she also repeats the maximiser (<i>always always</i>) to intensify the
                    effect.</p>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="weng12059-sec-0100">
            <title type="main">CONCLUSION</title>
            <p>Though the discussion in the previous two sections, this paper shows that there are noticeable similarities and differences in terms of how complaints are responded by CSRs as a means
                to present care, and how customers enact negative emotions in complaints in the English and Cantonese problematic calls. CSRs make use of minimal feedback to respond to customers’
                complaints in both English and Cantonese calls, while silence is only used in the English calls by CSRs as a way to deal with customers’ complaints; and CSRs exert their power by
                institutional rountinisation in the English calls while the institutional roles between CSRs and customers are much more negotiable in the Cantonese calls. For the enactment of
                negative emotions, customers in both languages scale up their attitude in force; and they mostly deploy the resources of negative affect and appreciation in English calls while those
                in Cantonese calls deploy the resources of appreciation and judgement.</p>
            <p>The present parallel study of call centre communication in Cantonese and English provides us a glimpse of the multilingual call centre industry in Hong Kong nowadays. It also enables us
                to triangulate data and provides insights as an outside observer to the organisation and it has shown us there are some issues within the organisation about language and bi/tri‐lingual
                demands of the workplace and the needs of the industry. While all these differences and similarities can be further explained by comparative linguistic and cultural studies, they
                elicit very important insights in the particular properties in how English is used in the telephonic service encounter of the BPO industry in its global and multilingual setting.</p>
            <p>Interviews with the organisation's stakeholders demonstrate that they are aware of the situation and are willing to develop CSR's linguistic skills and competence to serve the needs of
                the industry. During an interview, a manager stated that ‘trainer, recruiter are needed, training materials are also needed as they are not formalised and standardised at the moment’.
                The authentic data obtained and the systematic linguistic analysis conducted in the present study not only contribute to the advancement of our understanding of the use of English in
                the BPO industry, but also serve as grounded training materials for frontline CSRs to fulfil the need as stated by the manager. Such dialogic approach of interfacing academic research
                and industrial training is also exemplified by the study of credit collection calls by (<link href="#weng12059-bib-0024">Forey and Lam in preparation</link>).</p>
        </section>
        <bibliography xml:id="weng12059-bibl-0001" style="nameDate">
            <title type="main">REFERENCES</title>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0001">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0001"><author><familyName>Adolphs</familyName>, <givenNames>Svenja</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Brian</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Brown</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Ronald</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Carter</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Paul</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Crawford</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Opinder</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Sahota</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Applying corpus linguistics in a healthcare context</articleTitle>.
                        <journalTitle>Journal of Applied Linguistics</journalTitle>
                    <vol>1</vol>(<issue>1</issue>).<pageFirst>9</pageFirst>–<pageLast>28</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0002">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0002"><author><familyName>Amaratunga</familyName>, <givenNames>Dilanthi</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Richard
                            D.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Haigh</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Marjan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Sarshar</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>David</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Baldry</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2002">2002</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Application of the balanced score‐card concept to develop a conceptual framework to
                        measure facilities management performance within NHS facilities</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>International Journal of Healthcare Quality Assurance</journalTitle>
                    <vol>15</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>141</pageFirst>–<pageLast>51</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0003">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0003"><editor><familyName>Baker</familyName>, <givenNames>Carolyn D.</givenNames></editor>, <editor><givenNames>Michael</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Emmison</familyName></editor>, and <editor><givenNames>Alan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Firth</familyName></editor> (eds.). <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Calling for help: Language and social interaction in telephone
                        helplines</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Amsterdam</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>John Benjamins</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0004">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0004"><author><familyName>Beach</familyName>, <givenNames>Wayne A.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="1993">1993</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Transitional regularities for ‘casual’ ‘Okay’ usages</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Pragmatics</journalTitle>
                    <vol>19</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>325</pageFirst>–<pageLast>52</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0005">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0005"><author><familyName>Bolton</familyName>, <givenNames>Sharon C.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Maeve</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Houlihan</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>. <articleTitle>The (mis)representation of customer service</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Work,
                        Employment and Society</journalTitle>
                    <vol>19</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>685</pageFirst>–<pageLast>703</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0006">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0006"><author><familyName>Brazil</familyName>, <givenNames>David</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1985">1985</pubYear>. <bookTitle>The
                        communicative value of intonation in English discourse analysis. Monographs 8</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Birmingham</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Birmingham University
                        Press</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0007">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0007"><author><familyName>Cameron</familyName>, <givenNames>Deborah</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2000">2000</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>Styling the worker: Gender and the commodification of language in the globalized service economy</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of
                        Sociolinguistics</journalTitle>
                    <vol>4</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>323</pageFirst>–<pageLast>47</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0008">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0008"><author><familyName>Candlin</familyName>, <givenNames>Christopher N.</givenNames></author>, and
                            <author><givenNames>Sally</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Candlin</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2003">2003</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Health care communication: A problematic site for applied linguistics
                        research</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Annual Review of Applied Linguistics</journalTitle>
                    <vol>23</vol>.<pageFirst>134</pageFirst>–<pageLast>54</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0009">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0009"><author><familyName>Cowie</familyName>, <givenNames>Claire</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>The accents of outsourcing: The meanings of ‘neutral’ in the Indian call centre industry</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>World Englishes</journalTitle>
                    <vol>26</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>316</pageFirst>–<pageLast>30</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0010">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0010"><author><familyName>Coates</familyName>, <givenNames>Jennifer</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1986">1986</pubYear>.
                        <bookTitle>Women, men and language: A sociolinguistic account of sex differences in language</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                        <publisherName>Longman</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0011">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0011"><author><familyName>Creswell</familyName>, <givenNames>John W.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="1994">1994</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Research design: Qualitative &amp; quantitative approaches</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisherLoc>:
                        <publisherName>Sage</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0012">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0012"><author><familyName>Cruttenden</familyName>, <givenNames>Alan</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1986">1986</pubYear>.
                        <bookTitle>Intonation</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Cambridge</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Cambridge University Press</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0013">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0013"><author><familyName>Dogra</familyName>, <givenNames>Nisha</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2001">2001</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>The development and evaluation of a programme to teach cultural diversity to medical undergraduate students</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Medical
                        Education</journalTitle>
                    <vol>35</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>197</pageFirst>–<pageLast>205</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0014">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0014"><author><familyName>Eggins</familyName>, <givenNames>Suzanne</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>James R.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Martin</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="1997">1997</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Genres and registers of discourse</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Discourse as structure
                        and process</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Tuen A.</givenNames>
                        <familyNamePrefix>van</familyNamePrefix>
                        <familyName>Dijk</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>230</pageFirst>–<pageLast>56</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Sage</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0015">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0015"><author><familyName>Eggins</familyName>, <givenNames>Suzanne</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Diana</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Slade</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="1997">1997</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Analysing casual conversation</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                        <publisherName>Cassell</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0016">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0016"><author><familyName>Ephratt</familyName>, <givenNames>Michal</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2008">2008</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>The functions of silence</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Pragmatics</journalTitle>
                    <vol>40</vol>(<issue>11</issue>).<pageFirst>1909</pageFirst>–<pageLast>38</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0017">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0017"><author><familyName>Fairclough</familyName>, <givenNames>Norman</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>.
                        <chapterTitle>Critical discourse analysis in researching language in the new capitalism: Overdetermination, transdisciplinarity and textual analysis</chapterTitle>.
                        <bookTitle>Systemic functional linguistics and critical discourse analysis: Studies in social change</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Lynne</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Young</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Claire</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Harrison</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>68</pageFirst>–<pageLast>84</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                    <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0018">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0018"><author><familyName>Falchuk</familyName>, <givenNames>Evan</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>‘Quality’ healthcare: What does it really mean?</articleTitle>
                    <journalTitle>Employee Benefit Plan Review</journalTitle>
                    <vol>61</vol>(<issue>12</issue>).<pageFirst>12</pageFirst>–<pageLast>13</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0019">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0019"><author><familyName>Farberow</familyName>, <givenNames>Norman L.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Edwin S.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Shneidman</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="1961">1961</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>A Survey of agencies for the prevention of suicide</chapterTitle>.
                        <bookTitle>The cry for help</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Norman L.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Farberow</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Edwin S.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Shneidman</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>136</pageFirst>–<pageLast>49</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>New York</publisherLoc>:
                        <publisherName>McGraw‐Hill</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0020">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0020"><author><familyName>Fine</familyName>, <givenNames>Michael</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>Individualization, risk and the body</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Sociology</journalTitle>
                    <vol>41</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>247</pageFirst>–<pageLast>66</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0021">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0021"><author><familyName>Fontana</familyName>, <givenNames>Andrea</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>James H.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Frey</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2000">2000</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>The interview: From structured questions to negotiated text</chapterTitle>.
                        <bookTitle>Handbook of qualitative research</bookTitle>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>., ed. by <editor><givenNames>Norman K.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Denzin</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Yvonna S.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lincoln</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>645</pageFirst>–<pageLast>72</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                    <publisherName>Sage</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0022">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0022"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>.
                        <bookTitle>Interpersonal language in call centre discourse</bookTitle>. Plenary paper presented at the 1st international conference on appraisal systems and 9th national
                    Conference on Systemic Functional Linguistics in China. <publisherLoc>Kaifeng, China</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Henan University</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0023">
                <citation type="other" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0023"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <otherTitle>Call
                        centre communication – analyzing the call, the grammar and the words</otherTitle>. Plenary paper presented at the 2nd International Conference ‘Talking Across the World 2007:
                    English Communication Skills for the ITES Industry’. Manila.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0024">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0024"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Marvin</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lam</familyName></author>. In preparation. <articleTitle>Applying systemic functional linguistics: Understanding the choices of quality in the
                        workplace</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Applied Linguistics and Professional Practice</journalTitle>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0025">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0025"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Jane</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Yes maam: Call centre conversations</bookTitle>. Plenary paper presented at the
                    International Systemic Functional Congress, <publisherName>Doshisha University</publisherName>, <publisherLoc>Kyoto, Japan</publisherLoc>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0026">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0026"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Jane</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <articleTitle>‘I'd love to put someone in jail for this’: An initial investigation of English
                        in the business processing outsourcing (BOP) industry</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>English for Specific Purposes</journalTitle>
                    <vol>26</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>308</pageFirst>–<pageLast>26</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0027">
                <citation type="other" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0027"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Jane</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Helen</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Price</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Susan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Hood</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <otherTitle>Call centre communication in Asia: Language, context, communication and
                        concerns</otherTitle>. Invited colloquium at Diversity and Community in Applied Linguistics: Interface, Interpretation, Interdisciplinarity International Conference, Macquarie
                    University, Sydney.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0028">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0028"><author><familyName>Fox</familyName>, <givenNames>Richard</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1968">1968</pubYear>.
                        <chapterTitle>The Samaritans</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Suicidal behaviors: Diagnosis and management</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>H.L.P.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Resnik</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>405</pageFirst>–<pageLast>17</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Boston, MA</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Little
                        Brown</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0029">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0029"><author><familyName>Friginal</familyName>, <givenNames>Eric</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>Outsourced call centres and English in the Philippines</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>World Englishes</journalTitle>
                    <vol>26</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>331</pageFirst>–<pageLast>45</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0030">
                <citation type="other" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0030"><author><familyName>Gardner</familyName>, <givenNames>Roderik J.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="1995">1995</pubYear>. <otherTitle>On some uses of the conversational token Mm</otherTitle>. PhD thesis, University of Melbourne.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0031">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0031"><author><familyName>Gardner</familyName>, <givenNames>Roderik J.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="1998">1998</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Between listening and speaking: The vocalisation of understandings</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Applied
                        Linguistics</journalTitle>
                    <vol>19</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>204</pageFirst>–<pageLast>24</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0032">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0032"><author><familyName>Gardner</familyName>, <givenNames>Roderik J.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="2001">2001</pubYear>. <bookTitle>When listeners talk</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Amsterdam</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>John Benjamins</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0033">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0033"><author><familyName>Glucksmann</familyName>, <givenNames>Miriam A.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Call configurations: Varieties of call center and divisions of labour</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Work, Employment and
                        Society</journalTitle>
                    <vol>18</vol> (<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>795</pageFirst>–<pageLast>811</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0034">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0034"><author><familyName>Halliday</familyName>, <givenNames>Michael Alexander Kirkwood</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1978"
                        >1978</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Language as a social semiotic: The social interpretation of language and meaning</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                        <publisherName>Edward Arnold</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0035">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0035"><author><familyName>Halliday</familyName>, <givenNames>Michael Alexander Kirkwood</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1979"
                        >1979</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>The ontogenesis of dialogue</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Proceedings of the Twelfth International Congress of Linguists</bookTitle>, ed. by
                            <editor><givenNames>U. Dressler</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Wolfgang</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>144</pageFirst>–<pageLast>54</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Innsbruck</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Innsbrucker Beiträge zur
                        Sprachwissenschaft</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0036">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0036"><author><familyName>Halliday</familyName>, <givenNames>Michael Alexander Kirkwood</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1984"
                        >1984</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Language as code and language as behaviour: A systemic‐functional interpretation of the nature and ontogenesis of dialogue</chapterTitle>.
                        <bookTitle>The semiotics of language and culture, Volume I: Language as social semiotic</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Robin</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Fawcett</familyName></editor>, <editor><givenNames>Michael Alexander Kirkwood</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Halliday</familyName></editor>, <editor><givenNames>Sydney M.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lamb</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Adam</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Makkai</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>3</pageFirst>–<pageLast>35</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                    <publisherName>Printer</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0037">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0037"><author><familyName>Halliday</familyName>, <givenNames>Michael Alexander Kirkwood</givenNames></author>, and
                            <author><givenNames>Christian M.I.M.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Matthiessen</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>. <bookTitle>An introduction to functional grammar</bookTitle>.
                        <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Edward Arnold</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0038">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0038"><author><familyName>Hardoff</familyName>, <givenNames>Daniel</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Shifra</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Schonmann</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2001">2001</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Training physicians in communication skills with adolescents using teenager
                        actors as simulated patients</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Medical Education</journalTitle>
                    <vol>35</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>206</pageFirst>–<pageLast>10</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0039">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0039"><author><familyName>Holmes</familyName>, <givenNames>Janet</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1997">1997</pubYear>.
                        <chapterTitle>Story‐telling in New Zealand women's and men's talk</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Gender and discourse</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Ruth</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Wodak</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>263</pageFirst>–<pageLast>93</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                    <publisherName>Sage</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0040">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0040"><author><familyName>Hood</familyName>, <givenNames>Susan</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Gail</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Forey</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2008">2008</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Co‐constructing emotion: The interpersonal dynamics of call‐centre
                        interactions</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Discourse and Communication</journalTitle>
                    <vol>2</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>389</pageFirst>–<pageLast>409</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0041">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0041"><author><familyName>Irish</familyName>, <givenNames>Chris</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2000">2000</pubYear>.
                        <articleTitle>Web‐enabled call centre</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>BT Technology Journal</journalTitle>
                    <vol>18</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>65</pageFirst>–<pageLast>71</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0042">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0042"><author><familyName>Knights</familyName>, <givenNames>David</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Dareen</givenNames>
                        <familyName>McCabe</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2003">2003</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Governing through teamwork: Reconstituting subjectivity in a call
                        centre</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Management Studies</journalTitle>
                    <vol>40</vol>(<issue>7</issue>).<pageFirst>1587</pageFirst>–<pageLast>619</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0043">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0043"><author><familyName>Kwok</familyName>, <givenNames>Helen</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1984">1984</pubYear>.
                        <bookTitle>Sentence particles in Cantonese</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Hong Kong</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>University of Hong Kong</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0044">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0044"><editor><familyName>Lester</familyName>, <givenNames>David</givenNames></editor>, and <editor><givenNames>Gene W.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Brockopp</familyName></editor> (eds.). <pubYear year="1973">1973</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Crisis intervention and counseling by telephone</bookTitle>.
                        <publisherLoc>Springfield, IL</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Charles C. Thomas</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0045">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0045"><author><familyName>Li</familyName>, <givenNames>Charles N.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Sandra A.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Thompson</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="1981">1981</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Mandarin Chinese: A functional reference grammar</bookTitle>.
                        <publisherLoc>Berkeley, CA</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>University of California Press</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0046">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0046"><author><familyName>Lockwood</familyName>, <givenNames>Jane</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Gail</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Forey</familyName></author> and <author><givenNames>Helen</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Price</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2008">2008</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Englishes in the Philippine business processing outsourcing industry: Issues,
                        opportunities and initial findings</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Philippine English: Linguistic and literacy perspectives</bookTitle>, ed. By <editor><givenNames>M. Lourdes
                            S.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Bautista</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Kingsley</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Bolton</familyName></editor>. <publisherLoc>Hong Kong</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Hong Kong University Press</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0047">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0047"><author><familyName>Martin</familyName>, <givenNames>James R.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="1992">1992</pubYear>. <bookTitle>English text: System and structure</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Amsterdam</publisherLoc>:
                    <publisherName>Benjamins</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0048">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0048"><author><familyName>Martin</familyName>, <givenNames>James R.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="2000">2000</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Close reading: functional linguistics as a tool for critical discourse analysis</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Researching language
                        in schools and communities: Functional linguistic perspectives</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Len</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Unsworth</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>275</pageFirst>–<pageLast>303</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>:
                    <publisherName>Cassell</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0049">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0049"><author><familyName>Martin</familyName>, <givenNames>James R.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>David</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Rose</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2003">2003</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Working with discourse: Meaning beyond the clause</bookTitle>.
                        <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0050">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0050"><author><familyName>Martin</familyName>, <givenNames>James R.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Peter R. R.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>White</familyName></author>, <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>. <bookTitle>The language of evaluation: Appraisal in English</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>New
                        York</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Palgrave Macmillan</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0051">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0051"><author><familyName>Matthiessen</familyName>, <givenNames>Christian M.I.M.</givenNames></author>,
                            <author><givenNames>Kazuhiro</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Teruya</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Marvin</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lam</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Key terms in systemic functional linguistics</bookTitle>.
                        <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0052">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0052"><author><familyName>McLemore</familyName>, <givenNames>Cynthia A.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="1991">1991</pubYear>. <bookTitle>The pragmatic interpretation of English intonation: Sorority speech</bookTitle>. Dissertation, <publisherName>The University of
                        Texas</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0053">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0053"><author><familyName>Murtagh</familyName>, <givenNames>Ged M.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Some initial reflections on conversational structures for instruction giving</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Calling for
                        help</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Carolyn D.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Baker</familyName></editor>, <editor><givenNames>Michael</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Emmison</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Alan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Firth</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>287</pageFirst>–<pageLast>345</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Amsterdam</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>John
                        Benjamins</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0054">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0054"><author><familyName>O'Neill</familyName>, <givenNames>Donald A.</givenNames></author>
                    <pubYear year="2003">2003</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Offshore outsourcing takes hold</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Mortgage Banking</journalTitle>
                    <vol>64</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>38</pageFirst>–<pageLast>43</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0055">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0055"><author><familyName>Quirk</familyName>, <givenNames>Randolph</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Sidney</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Greenbaum</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Geoffrey</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Leech</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Jan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Svartvik</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="1985">1985</pubYear>. <bookTitle>A comprehensive grammar of the English language</bookTitle>.
                        <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Longman</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0056">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0056"><author><familyName>Silverman</familyName>, <givenNames>David</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2000">2000</pubYear>.
                        <chapterTitle>What is qualitative research?</chapterTitle>
                    <bookTitle>Doing qualitative research: A practical handbook</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>David</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Silverman</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>1</pageFirst>–<pageLast>13</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisherLoc>:
                        <publisherName>Sage</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0057">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0057"><author><familyName>Soldato</familyName>, <givenNames>Manuel</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Rosa</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Liperoti</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Francesco</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Landi</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Ian G.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Carpenter</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Roberto</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Bernabei</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Graziano</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Onder</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2008">2008</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Patient depression and caregiver attitudes: Results from the aged in home care
                        study</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Affective Disorders</journalTitle>
                    <vol>106</vol>(<issue>1–2</issue>).<pageFirst>107</pageFirst>–<pageLast>15</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0058">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0058"><author><familyName>Spencer</familyName>, <givenNames>John</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Jonathan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Silverman</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2001">2001</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Education for communication: Much already known, so much more to understand
                        [Editorial]</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Medical Education</journalTitle>
                    <vol>35</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>188</pageFirst>–<pageLast>90</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0059">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0059"><author><familyName>Sturman</familyName>, <givenNames>Andrew</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1999">1999</pubYear>.
                        <chapterTitle>Case study methods</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Issues in educational research</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>John P.</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Keeves</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Gabriele</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Lakomski</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>103</pageFirst>–<pageLast>12</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Amsterdam</publisherLoc>:
                    <publisherName>Pergamon</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0060">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0060"><author><familyName>Tannen</familyName>, <givenNames>Deborah</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Muriel</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Saville‐Troike</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="1985">1985</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Perspectives on silence</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Norwood, NY</publisherLoc>:
                        <publisherName>Ablex Publishing Corporation</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0061">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0061"><author><familyName>Taylor</familyName>, <givenNames>Phil</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Peter</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Bain</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="1999">1999</pubYear>. <articleTitle>An assembly line in the head: Work and employee relations in the call
                        centre</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Industrial Relations Journal</journalTitle>
                    <vol>30</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).1<pageFirst>01</pageFirst>–<pageLast>17</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0062">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0062"><author><familyName>Taylor</familyName>, <givenNames>Phil</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Peter</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Bain</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>. <articleTitle>India calling to the far away towns: The call centre labour process and
                        globalisation</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Work, Employment and Society</journalTitle>
                    <vol>19</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>261</pageFirst>–<pageLast>82</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0063">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0063"><author><familyName>Taylor</familyName>, <givenNames>Phil</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Peter</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Bain</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Call centre reflections: A reply to Glucksmann</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Work,
                        Employment and Society</journalTitle>
                    <vol>21</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>349</pageFirst>–<pageLast>62</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0064">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0064"><author><familyName>Taylor</familyName>, <givenNames>Phil</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Jeff</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Hyman</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Gareth</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Mulvey</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Peter</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Bain</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2002">2002</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Work organization, control and the experience of work in call centers</articleTitle>.
                        <journalTitle>Work, Employment and Society</journalTitle>
                    <vol>16</vol>(<issue>1</issue>).<pageFirst>133</pageFirst>–<pageLast>50</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0065">
                <citation type="book" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0065"><author><familyName>Wang</familyName>, <givenNames>Li</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1955">1955</pubYear>. <bookTitle>中國現代語法(A
                        modern grammar of Chinese)</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Beijing</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Zhonghua</publisherName>.</citation>
            </bib>
            <bib xml:id="weng12059-bib-0066">
                <citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12059-cit-0066"><author><familyName>Xu</familyName>, <givenNames>Xun‐feng</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Yan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Wang</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Gail</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Forey</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Lan</givenNames>
                        <familyName>Li</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Analyzing the genre structure of Chinese call‐center communication</articleTitle>.
                        <journalTitle>Journal of Business and Technical Communication</journalTitle>
                    <vol>24</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>445</pageFirst>–<pageLast>75</pageLast>.</citation>
            </bib>
        </bibliography>
    </body>
</component>
