<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><component xmlns="http://www.wiley.com/namespaces/wiley" version="2.0" type="serialArticle" xml:lang="en" xml:id="WENG12058">
<header>
<publicationMeta level="product">
<doi origin="wiley" registered="yes">10.1111/(ISSN)1467-971X</doi>
<issn type="print">0883-2919</issn>
<issn type="electronic">1467-971X</issn>
<idGroup>
<id type="product" value="WENG"/>
</idGroup>
<titleGroup>
<title type="main" sort="WORLD ENGLISHES">World Englishes</title>
<title type="short">World Englishes</title>
</titleGroup>
</publicationMeta>
<publicationMeta level="part" position="12104">
<doi>10.1111/weng.2013.32.issue-4</doi>
<titleGroup>
<title type="specialIssueTitle">SYMPOSIUM ON WORLD ENGLISHES AND INTERNATIONAL CALL CENTRES</title>
</titleGroup>
<copyright ownership="publisher">Copyright © 2013 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</copyright>
<numberingGroup>
<numbering type="journalVolume" number="32">32</numbering>
<numbering type="journalIssue">4</numbering>
</numberingGroup>
<creators>
<creator xml:id="sped1" creatorRole="guestEditor">
<personName><givenNames>KINGSLEY</givenNames><familyName>BOLTON</familyName></personName>
</creator>
</creators>
<coverDate startDate="2013-12">December 2013</coverDate>
</publicationMeta>
<publicationMeta level="unit" position="40" type="article" status="forIssue">
<doi origin="wiley">10.1111/weng.12058</doi>
<idGroup>
<id type="unit" value="WENG12058"/>
</idGroup>
<countGroup>
<count type="pageTotal" number="18"/>
</countGroup>
<titleGroup>
<title type="articleCategory">Articles</title>
<title type="tocHeading1">Papers</title>
</titleGroup>
<copyright ownership="publisher">© 2013 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</copyright>
<eventGroup><event type="manuscriptReceived" date="2013-07-25"/><event type="xmlCreated" agent="Aptara" date="2013-09-10"/><event type="xmlConverted" agent="Converter:WILEY_ML3G_TO_WILEY_ML3GV2 version:3.2.6 mode:FullText" date="2013-11-19"/><event type="firstOnline" date="2013-11-19"/><event type="publishedOnlineFinalForm" date="2013-11-19"/><event type="xmlConverted" agent="Converter:WML3G_To_WML3G version:4.6.4 mode:FullText" date="2015-10-02"/></eventGroup>
<numberingGroup>
<numbering type="pageFirst">503</numbering>
<numbering type="pageLast">520</numbering>
</numberingGroup>
<linkGroup>
<link type="toTypesetVersion" href="file:WENG.WENG12058.pdf"/>


</linkGroup>
</publicationMeta>
<contentMeta>
<titleGroup>
<title type="main">The impact of call centre employment on women in India</title>
<title type="shortAuthors">Gail Forey</title>
<title type="short">The impact of call centre employment on women in India</title>
</titleGroup>
<creators>
<creator xml:id="weng12058-cr-0001" creatorRole="author" affiliationRef="#weng12058-aff-0001">
<personName><givenNames>GAIL</givenNames><familyName>FOREY</familyName>
</personName>
<contactDetails>
<email>gail.forey@polyu.edu.hk</email>
</contactDetails>
</creator>
</creators>
<affiliationGroup>
<affiliation xml:id="weng12058-aff-0001" countryCode="HK">
<orgDiv>Department of English</orgDiv>
<orgName>Hong Kong Polytechnic University</orgName>
<address>
<city>Hung Hom</city>
<countryPart>Kowloon</countryPart>
<country>Hong Kong</country>
</address>
</affiliation>
</affiliationGroup>
<abstractGroup>
<abstract type="main">
<title type="main">ABSTRACT</title>
<p>The market for global business process outsourcing (BPO) is predicted to triple in size by 2020 (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0041"/>). Such explosive growth has had and will continue to have huge economic benefits for Asia. The benefits are clearly manifest in India and the Philippines, who are both leading offshore outsourcing (O&amp;O) destinations for the BPO industry. In India, this development has resulted in an initiative to increase the number of women in the BPO workforce by a staggering 50 per cent. The implications of such a huge push has tremendous social impact, yet little is known about the BPO industry and the role of language in these O&amp;O destinations. The present paper focuses on the impact of English and the role of women in this global workforce by addressing the following question: ‘What is the impact of the BPO industry, and specifically call centre employment, on women in India?’ Drawing on data collected through interviews, the findings show that women's lives have changed in a number of different ways. Informants reported experiencing greater freedom, financial independence and other significant changes. The findings provide a lucid representation of the role of English language in globalisation within the BPO industry in Asia.</p></abstract>
</abstractGroup>
</contentMeta>
</header>
<body sectionsNumbered="no">
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0010">
<title type="main">INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>The information technology enabled services (ITES) industry in Asia and worldwide has been assessed as tripling in size from US$500 billion in 2009 to US$1.5–1.6 trillion in 2020, an incremental growth of 80 per cent (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0039"/>). However, these figures were estimated prior to the financial crisis of 2008 and should only be taken as an estimation. Nevertheless, the benefits of this industry are clearly visible in a number of economies across Asia, particularly India and the Philippines. In Asia, especially in India and the Philippines, the biggest drawback to growth in the BPO industry is ‘talent’ (Cu <link href="#weng12058-bib-0012"/>; NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0039"/>). The UNDP (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0052"/>: 10) stated in a recent report that the ‘pervasive gender inequality in Asia and the Pacific deprives the region of a significant source of human potential’ and indicated that the need for ‘talent’ is the biggest problem for growth in Asia. They also state that the ratio of the adult labour force participation of women in East Asia is at 66.7 per cent, this includes the Philippines which is above the global average rate of 52.7 per cent. However, according to the UNPD ‘South Asian women are far behind at 35.7 per cent, a statistic that has remained almost unchanged since 1995’ (UNPD 2009: 24). The ‘talent’ referred to here is closely associated not only with professional ability, but with linguistic human capital – proficiency in English. The need to find more ‘talent’, who are qualified and proficient in English is a major concern for the business process outsourcing (BPO) industry.</p>
<p>With respect to English, India's position as one of the ‘outer circles’ in Kachru's model (Kachru <link href="#weng12058-bib-0030"/>; Bolton and Kachru <link href="#weng12058-bib-0007"/>) affords India opportunities to exploit the language talent within the country. As Kachru pointed out ‘English comes through channels which bypass the strategies devised by language planners’ (Kachru <link href="#weng12058-bib-0029"/>: 137). Some of key influential planners involved in the development and expansion of English in the BPO industry are business planners, and here we are particularly focusing on planners or executive decisions within the BPO industry. The BPO, similar to other commercial ventures, aim at increasing financial profit, within the BPO this is often achieved by offshoring and outsourcing work through the Internet to India and other destinations. India is one of the biggest players in the BPO industry, and recently announced record growth in 2012, reporting that the year 2012 was a ‘milestone year for the Indian BPO industry‐aggregate revenues crossed the US$100 billion mark, exports were at US$69 billion’ (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0041"/>). The BPO industry brings financial gain to those involved in India, as well as being one of the largest private sector employers in the country. The National Association of Software and Services Companies (NASSCOM), the trade body representing the BPO industry, issues a number of very impressive statistics to establish the credentials of the industry. NASSCOM states that in 2012 the business in generated employment for many, and that the BPO industry is ‘expected to add 230,000 jobs in FY2012, thus providing direct employment to about 2.8 million, and indirectly employing 8.9 million people’ (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0041"/>). The direct employment are those who are working for the BPO industry and the indirect employment includes the security, transport, food and beverage, cleaners, etc. who are employed to support the BPO industry. We must however, remember when looking at the figures and claims of NASSCOM that the industry aims to impress stakeholders in order to encourage investment, and further growth within the industry.</p>
<p>NASSCOM are also proud about their gender equality and profess to be responsible for recruiting the largest number of qualified women from the overall workforce of 400 million. They state that the industry is involved in ‘empowering the diverse human assets’ of the Indian workforce (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0041"/>). The statistics to support such claims are of those employed within NASSCOM 31 per cent are women, 74 per cent are below 30 years of age, and 5 per cent come from ‘economically backward classes’ (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0041"/>). NASSCOM also states that the BPO industry contributes greatly to the Indian economy providing 6.4 per cent of India's GDP, 14 per cent of the total exports and 10 per cent of India's service sector revenues (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0041"/>). Within the BPO industry, call centres are one sector of the business offered, other sectors include for example, medical transcription, information systems support, radiography, financial analysis, and many more. The phenomenon of outsourcing work to offshore destinations has been around for a few years and is developing. As suggested by Blommaert (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0005"/>: 609) the key to understanding the global phenomenon and the spread of English ‘is to discover what such reorderings or repertoires actually mean, and represent, to the people’. In the present paper, we discuss how the repertoire of gender norms are being reordered due to the potential employment of women in the BPO industry in the context of a very traditional and conservative country like India.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0020">
<title type="main">PREVIOUS RESEARCH</title>
<p>To date the research into the call centre has generally been reported in business research, which has tended to focus on information technology, information systems, economic factors (Gilmore <link href="#weng12058-bib-0022"/>; Bolton and Houlihan <link href="#weng12058-bib-0006"/>) and human resource management (Bain et al. <link href="#weng12058-bib-0002"/>; Porter and Tanner <link href="#weng12058-bib-0043"/>; Taylor and Bain <link href="#weng12058-bib-0051"/>). Research focusing on language in the BPO industry has only recently started to emerge. Within these recent studies many focus on call centre communication, rather than other phenomenon related to the impact of the globalisation of English in the BPO industry. Studies on call centre communication originated on shore and were generally based around interview data (Cameron <link href="#weng12058-bib-0008"/>; <link href="#weng12058-bib-0009"/>) where stakeholders related to the call centre industry discussed their beliefs and reflections. Adolphs et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0001"/>), again from UK based data, published one of the first studies which discussed choices made in authentic call centre interactions.</p>
<p>Subsequent to this, and reflecting the growth and global spread of call centre communication, research emerged in offshore destinations focusing on accent neutralisation (Cowie <link href="#weng12058-bib-0010"/>; <link href="#weng12058-bib-0011"/>) and training (Friginal <link href="#weng12058-bib-0018"/>; <link href="#weng12058-bib-0019"/>). This initial research on the BPO industry illustrated that the ‘native speaker’ model was the model of English adopted within the industry (Bolton 2012). The belief that accents will prevent intelligibility resulted in a tremendous amount of time and effort spent ensuring the norm was a British or an American accent, depending on which market they were serving. Jenkins (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0027"/>; <link href="#weng12058-bib-0028"/>) and Smith's (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0048"/>) model of intelligibility promote local varieties of English which may diverge from the norm – dependent on Inner Circle varieties. However, such non‐standard varieties of English have not been entertained in the boardroom, management meetings, training material nor assessment tools in the BPO industry.</p>
<p>On the whole ‘norms’ based on inner circle models of English are used as benchmarks and targets for the English used in the BPO. Forey and Lockwood (2007), Hood and Forey (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0026"/>) Lockwood et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0037"/>) in an analysis of complaints within BPO texts found that accent is frequently not the cause of a breakdown in communication. More recently Lockwood (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0034"/>; <link href="#weng12058-bib-0035"/>) drawing on systemic functional linguistics (Halliday and Matthiessen <link href="#weng12058-bib-0023"/>) as a tool to analyse the data, has discussed assessment and curriculum issues in these offshore destinations. In these studies, Lockwood demonstrates how assessment has been poorly envisaged and implemented in the rush to offshore and outsourced work to South and South East Asia, where linguistic assessment has tended to test discrete grammar items and the adherence to ‘correct rules of grammar’. Hamp‐Lyons and Lockwood (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0024"/>), Lockwood et al. (2009) and Davies (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0013"/>) call for assessment models which are more holistic and reflect the language demands of the job. Forey and Lam (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0016">forthcoming</link>) point out that regardless of ‘standard’ grammar, it is getting the job done which counts and not how you speak. In these recent studies, where authentic data is the focus, a breakdown in communication in call centre interaction is usually not dependent on accent or grammatical accuracy but rather on sociolinguistic, sociocultural, interpersonal features along with the restrictions on the CSR concerning product knowledge domains and access to information (Lockwood <link href="#weng12058-bib-0034"/>, <link href="#weng12058-bib-0035">b</link>). Within this small circle of studies there have been very few who have reviewed the impact of the BPO from a world Englishes or the global phenomenon, and few have studied the topic from a sociolinguist perspective investigating how English has impacted the lives of those involved. Forey (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0015"/>) introduced a general overview of the impact of the BPO industry on the social, educational, economic and health of those employed within the industry.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0030">
<title type="main">THE ISSUE OF GENDER IN CALL CENTRE WORK</title>
<p>One of the most fascinating areas of study yet to be investigated in these offshore and outsource (O&amp;O) destinations is the issue of gender. Gender and inequalities related to the workplace have been discussed in detail (see Ganguly‐Scrase <link href="#weng12058-bib-0020"/>; Davis et al. <link href="#weng12058-bib-0014"/>; Holmes <link href="#weng12058-bib-0025"/>). As pointed out by Belt (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0003"/>), Belt et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0004"/>) and Scholarios and Taylor (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0045"/>), the call centre industry and the social context where the work takes place may impact inequalities of gendered differences at work. Belt (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0003"/>), Belt et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0004"/>) and Scholarios and Taylor (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0045"/>) all conduct research based in the UK and discuss gender and the constraints in call centre employment. Belt (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0003"/>), Belt et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0004"/>) and Scholarios and Taylor (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0045"/>) make a number of key claims about gender, language and call centre communication. They suggest that the competencies and language used in the call centre is distinctly feminine; and that women tend to be discriminated against in both promotional opportunities and investment in human capital. Belt (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0003"/>) claims that competency in the call centre workplace, here I believe he is referring to linguistic competency, is distinctly gendered to ‘female’ work, and further suggests that women ‘naturally possess an abundance of many social skills’ (Belt et al. <link href="#weng12058-bib-0004"/>: 20), including the desired soft skills required for call centre work. Moreover, an additional claim is the belief that a ‘glass ceiling’ exists in relation to the promotional opportunities for women.</p>
<p>The aim of the typical call centre service encounter is to achieve first time resolution, where customer or client's calls are answered during their first call and whether a male or female CSR responds is secondary to achieving a satisfactory resolution. Furthermore, if there is a collaborative construction and maintenance of good relations between the CSR and customer this is purely secondary. Whether in fact call centre discourse is gendered or whether women have more soft skills appropriate for service roles is perhaps an intuitive appreciation, and yet to be supported by evidence. In our initial research in the Philippines and India, adopting an SFL approach where discrete lexicogrammatical choices within the text have been scrutinised, the language reflects the context and the common goals found in service encounters. The fact that the customer service representative (CSR) is male or female tends to have little impact on the choices made by the CSR. In the context of call centre interactions, we argue that gendered discourse is not an option, and that gender, to a large extent, is not a key factor in the unfolding of the interaction. However, a detailed investigation of whether males or females make different linguistic choices and whether the skills they possess are more appropriate to the job, whether in fact a glass ceiling exists in Asian call centres would be interesting, but unfortunately would be the focus of another paper.</p>
<p>Belt et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0004"/>) point out that in the early 2000s women comprised around two‐thirds of the call centre workforce and the call centre industry was viewed as a ‘female ghetto’. This may be the case in the UK where the call centres are domiciled in the onshore destination, but the ratio of female to male employees is almost the opposite of figures reported by NASSCOM for India, where two‐thirds of the workforce are male (NASSCOM <link href="#weng12058-bib-0040"/>). The need to employ a greater number of women in the workforce was underlined in a NASSCOM report in March 2009 stating that they would be making a concerted effort to increase the female workforce by 50 per cent. The inequalities in the workplace are very different in offshore and outsourced destinations such as India. In Asia the industry itself faces entrenched social stigmatism and the fact that work in call centres involves working through the night provides added stigmatism. In this dominantly patriarchal society, women have traditionally defined roles which are inherently different from men, where men and women have established ways of behaving and doing which are notably very polarised (Patel <link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>). Thus, employment for women in the post‐modern, post‐Fordist Indian BPO industry challenges a number of gender stereotypes and social norms.</p>
<p>Poignant questions related to the issue of gender and inequality in call centre work are raised by Scholarios and Taylor (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0046"/>). In a recent study based on questionnaires from 1,476 CSRs and interviews with 77 CSRs from four industry sectors – financial services, outsourced services, telecom/entertainment and holiday/travel, Scholarios and Taylor (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0046"/>) report that inequalities exist and are related to disadvantages for women in human and educational capital, domestic constraints and supervisor career support. Their detailed study, carried out in the UK, illustrates the disadvantages women experience within the context of the BPO industry. The fact that these questions are posed and responded to reflects social norms in the UK, namely, expected equality between men and women. Active opposition to discrimination has been reported in the UK, however, little is known about the inequalities within the workforce of BPO's that have been O&amp;O to India or the Philippines.</p>
<p>A common and often documented belief is that gender inequalities in the workforce and other social domains are part of the social fabric of India (Sudarshan and Bhattacharya <link href="#weng12058-bib-0049"/>; Kapur <link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>; Patel <link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>) The drive by NASSCOM (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0040"/>) to increase employment opportunities for women to work in the BPO industry reflects the fact that ‘talent’ and recruitment of an employment pool proficient in English is one of the hardest problems facing growth. The drive by NASSCOM and the industry may be motivated by economic profit, however as Sudarshan and Bhattacharya (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0049"/>) argue participation in the workforce by women is key to improving poverty. It seems therefore that the push by NASSCOM is supported by the ‘compelling need‐based’ participation for an increase in the number of women joining the workforce to improve the social position of women in society (Sudarshan and Bhattacharya <link href="#weng12058-bib-0049"/>). The figures on male versus women's participation in the workforce in Delhi, one of the most modern, urbanised centres, and probably one of the most modern thinking cities in India is 84 per cent of males to compared 21 per cent of women working (Sudarshan and Bhattacharya <link href="#weng12058-bib-0049"/>: 10). Such figures are even more staggering than those released by UNPD (2009).</p>
<p>The participation of women in the workforce in India faces entrenched beliefs of inequalities, and furthermore participation in the BPO industry increases some of the concerns about women working in such an industry. Kapur (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>) and Patel (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>) point out the difficulties of encouraging women to work in call centres were increased after the incident of a 24 year old girl was raped by the driver who was employed by the organisation to provide transport to and from work. Kapur (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>) also adds that men and women working side by side throughout the night has been frowned upon, and is viewed as fraternising at work, which is discouraged in a country where socialising between sexes before marriage is widely unacceptable. In addition, the postponement of marriage and the rising divorce rates have also been linked to the increase in the employment of women at work (Kapur <link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>; Patel <link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>).</p>
<p>However, Kapur (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>), who investigates how women negotiate their identities when working in the BPO industry, found the issue of call centres and gender is quite complex. Her findings indicate that employment in this industry is predominantly for the young who are generally upwardly mobile educated, graduates ‘earning about Rs10,000 per month – the equivalent of approximately US$250 – double the salary of graduates across India’ and this financial freedom allows space for gender norms to be challenged (Kapur <link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>: 50). Patel (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>), in a fascinating ethnographic study of the BPO and gender, discusses the BPO, gender and the impact on space, space being conceived as ‘night space’ versus ‘day space’. She presents the reality that the global economic growth of the BPO has opened the door to allow women to be employed and to enter the night space, which has been the domain of men, resulting in a conflict of opinions about the empowerment for women and the negative impact on women's roles and position in society.</p>
<p>The findings of this present study extend the claims made by Patel (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>) and highlight a small but significant paradigm shifts in society directly related to the globalisation of English in this vastly expanding BPO industry. Based on field notes and interview data with 43 employees working in the BPO in India, it is argued that the struggle for women also plays out at an institutional level where the industry faces a great deal of social stigmatism due to a lack of appreciation and knowledge of this relative new industry. The social stigmatism of the profession is compounded by the discrimination related to women working at night. Furthermore, not only do women face inequality through their choice of work, but the traditions and culture of India has constrained access to the workplace and the general advancement for women (Ganguly‐Scrase <link href="#weng12058-bib-0020"/>; Singh and Pandey <link href="#weng12058-bib-0047"/>; Ray and Qayum, <link href="#weng12058-bib-0044"/>). Patel (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>) states that women who travel to work at night are sometimes interrogated by the police, questioned by the community, and that this may tarnish the reputation of the women and her family. Patel (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>: 54) states it is clear that ‘patriarchal regimes of surveillance and mobility‐morality narratives remain entrenched’. First in the paper, I outline how the BPO struggles to be accepted due to the work involved and the night shift restrictions. I point out how the family and the patriarchal society perceive work in the BPO. I move on to illustrate how some of these constraints are shifting, even if minimally, and how the globalisation of language has impacted the life and opportunities for women in the BPO bringing economic, professional and social benefits, along with potential hope.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0040">
<title type="main">METHODOLOGY</title>
<p>The data for the present study have been collected over a number of years involvement with members of the industry as part of a larger research project (Call Centre Communication Research, CCCR, at the Hong Kong Polytechnic University, <url href="http://www.engl.polyu.edu.hk/">http://www.engl.polyu.edu.hk/</url> call_centre). Initial research focused on the BPO industry in the Philippines, and has since been extended to include studies in India, Hong Kong and China. In the larger project the research team visited more than 20 call centres from a range of organisations, observing and discussing industry processes, interviewing a range of stakeholders and collecting data on call centre interactions. To date, over 400 calls have been transcribed in English, 200 English calls from the Philippines, over 100 calls in Cantonese, 100 English calls from Hong Kong. In addition, the CCCR has organised five international conferences in the Philippines, India and Hong Kong providing additional opportunities to interact with representatives from a wide range of BPO organisations. Data for the present study are taken from field notes and interview data collected in a large multinational bank, called BankA, in India. We occasionally draw from interviews and field notes from the Philippines in order to illustrate specific points or to highlight the differences between the two outsourcing destinations.</p>
<p>In the BankA study, interviews were conducted at a ‘captive’ call centre, where employees are hired directly by the organisation, and the BPO related back office business is run in‐house. Compared to a third party provider who is contracted to run the BPO/call centre work for a vendor, BankA is one call centre site of part of a larger global bank, which directly runs the operations of their call centres and back office support around the world. At BankA, the data includes interviews with: three senior managers who work in the area of Communication and Learning and Development (female), Leadership and Development (male), Human Resources (female), six fully operating CSRs (four male and two female), as well as three trainers, and seven students working and studying at BankA. In addition, focus group interviews were also conducted with 24 newly hired trainee CSRs (12 male and 12 female) who were currently receiving training and not yet working on the floor; and eight students who were studying for the Bachelor of Business Adminstration (BBA). These students had won a studentship and spent 50 per cent of their time in university and 50 per cent in BankA's call centre as an internship. Thus a total of 51 BPO employees were interviewed. The aim of the interviews were wide ranging regarding the new assessment procedure, BUPLAS, that had been introduced at BankA (see Lockwood <link href="#weng12058-bib-0036">forthcoming</link> for an outline of BUPLAS), training, language needs and human capital factors which involved a discussion of issues related to gender, social factors, family and life outside the BPO workplace in India. For the purpose of the present paper, we focus on the findings from the interview data that is relevant to the broader social impact of the industry from an insider's perspective.</p>
<p>The interviews lasted from 30–60 minutes and were conducted in English. The purpose of the interviews was made clear to all involved. The interviews took place at the workplace and the interviewees were informed that the interviews would be completely confidential and anonymous, and that only the research team would have access to the data. Informed written consent was obtained. For the purpose the present paper the interviewees are identified with respect to their post manager (M), trainer (T), CSR, trainee CSR (TCSR), student (S) and a number to differentiate between the interviewees. Some background biographical information about each interviewee is given if it is known.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0050">
<title type="main">INTERVIEW RESULTS</title>
<p>In general terms, the findings that emerged from the interviews highlighted the negative status and stigmatisation attached to the BPO industry in Indian society. This stigmatism formed around the type of work associated with call centres, and the negative associations related to night work by females in particular. An additional, more deep‐rooted constraint was patriarchal control and the role of the family and marriage with respect to women working in this industry and working at night.</p>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0060">
<title type="main">The stigmatisation of call centre work</title>
<p>Call centres in India and the Philippines both face a tremendous amount of stigmatism related to the nature of the work and the fact that it often involves nighttime work (Taylor and Bain <link href="#weng12058-bib-0051"/>). Many informants we interviewed in both locations stated that employment in the BPO industry was seen often as menial and a dead end job. As one trainee CSR stated, ‘in India, what happens are people are still a bit of orthodox’ (TCSR9, Female New Delhi, 22 years of age). Little is known within social circles about this emerging industry, and many of the news reports sensationalise the night shift and dangers of these newly imported job roles. Interviews in both India and the Philippines suggest that influential members of society have a lack of appreciation of BPO work and many teachers and university professors advise their students to apply for a ‘normal’ job rather than work in the BPO.</p>
<p>Employees’ long‐term commitment to the industry is also questionable, given that many do not see themselves having a future career in the industry. As one informants stated, ‘for men it's a stop gap for better career opportunities, for women it's a stop gap between education and marriage’ (TCSR 3, female, middle aged, MA in Sociology, lived in the USA, worked as a Senior Financial Analyst, returned to India 12 years ago). This lack of long‐term commitment to the BPO is a well known phenomenon within the industry (Taylor and Bain <link href="#weng12058-bib-0051"/>). As two informants stated:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>While doing the job you can pursue some other course. I can study as well as study, preparing for my postgraduate courses an MTech. (TCSR9, male, home town unknown, Degree in Engineering, studying for Masters in Technology part‐time)</p>
<p>I'm doing this job right now because I can't quit at this point of time, because I need the money, I cannot be, I don't want to be supported by my parents. So that's the only reason why. I can study if I have my money, otherwise I'd be a burden. I wouldn't want to go back to my parents, not that they wouldn't have me. (T2, female, Shanti from Karela, MA in linguistics, hired directly as a trainer from hiring drive at her university, worked as Lecturer for 6 months)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>Many of the young employees were working to save money towards their studies in order to advance their development in an alternative career. In addition to earning money, becoming a proficient English speaker was an added attraction motivating short‐term employment. One trainee succinctly stated ‘if you know English, you have other options’ (TCSR 10, male, home town unknown, Engineering graduate, MBA graduate from Southall College, London, lived in the UK for 2 years). A number of other interviewees stated that they took the job, mainly to ensure that their English proficiency was good enough to study overseas. This quotation also illustrates the fact that many of the young people employed in the BPO industry are from middle‐class backgrounds in India (Patel <link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>). Stop‐gap jobs are only part of the reason why attrition rates are frequently reported to soar into surprising figures such as 100 per cent or more (Taylor and Bain <link href="#weng12058-bib-0051"/>). Attrition may also be related to job‐hopping, the CSR leaves one job in the BPO for a higher wage or better working conditions within another competitor. In BankA many of the employees had left their previous job in a BPO to join BankA, because ‘most stable company, stability is good, environment is good’ (TCSR8). BankA is one of the most highly respectable companies and has an esteemed international reputation. The novelty of banking was also an attraction for many employees, as reflected in the comment that ‘I'm a person who loves to learn new things, banking has got a lot of future and there's something that I'm learning new things’ (TCSR7, male, home town and whether he has a degree unknown, previously worked for Amazon).</p>
<p>As pointed out by Bain et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0002"/>) surveillance, tight quality assurance measures, night shift and facing a barrage of customers that sometimes complain and abuse the CSR add to the level of stress. Surveillance has been discussed in a number of studies and is highly evident when walking around a BPO. Every call starts with a recorded message ‘this call may be recorded for quality and training purposes’, and every call is recorded. In a call centre there is a huge amount of money and research invested in the information systems and in the complex and up‐to‐date surveillance mechanisms. These surveillance systems produce a tremendous amount of quantifiable statistics and matrixes, which report the level of productivity from various perspectives. These statistics drive the workforce management, i.e. the staffing, the ratio of employees to manager, the aim to achieve quotas and targets, etc. However as pointed out by Bain et al. (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0002"/>) and Gilmore (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0022"/>) the quantification of the service offered through the business may not necessarily equate to quality. The quality of the call and the attention given to language and the extent to which language is incorporated into the training has tended to take second fiddle to the quantification of statistics. The surveillance and the automatic logging of each call provide a rich source which is tapped for training purposes. It is common within a call centre that a team of CSRs (10–15 usually) have one ‘coach’, and that coach has a duty to listen to four calls from each CSR per month and provide on the floor training. The operations officer (Ops), in charge of how the business operates on the floor, also listens to calls and recommends training or follow‐up action. Any of the managers involved in the business can listen to any of the calls they deem necessary. Trainers are also asked to listen to provide support to CSR's that have been identified as ‘in need’ of attention. This surveillance can happen in real‐time, when the person listening simply ‘barges’ in to a call and listens to the real‐time call, or it can happen through selective or random sampling of the audio files stored within the organisation. This element of surveillance is one factor that adds to the level of stress. As a trainee CSR pointed out:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>Every call is an assessment, because they could record it, they could barge your call monitor your call. Every feedback that we get on any call is an assessment. (TCSR3, male, home town and whether graduate unknown, worked in a call centre for large computer company previously)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>The assessment of the call by the coach, manager, operations manager, trainer, etc., is usually linked to renewal of service, financial incentives or promotion. Thus on a minute‐by‐minute basis the CSR knows that they may be under scrutiny. Such a level of scrutiny is uncommon in other workplaces, and increases the level negative feedback among employees who work in the industry.</p>
<p>The low social acceptance of the industry, and the stress through surveillance is also combined with the dread of many of working through the night. One quote that represents how the surveillance merges with the need to perform at a high standard throughout the night was:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>If your at the end of the shift and you've got a another call and your about to log off in 4 or 5 minutes, how would your tone be? You should always sound as though you just logged on as your entrusted. It doesn't matter whoever the customer is, doesn't matter if you have an irate customer, or if the customer is not interested in speaking to an Indian. You should still sound polite, pleasant, and desperate to deliver a solution. (TCSR1, male, home town and whether he has a degree unknown, previously worked with General Electric call centre)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>Here the trainee CSR is well aware of the need to perform at a high standard throughout the night. Another CSR stated that often their coach would choose to select and assess calls that take place right at the end of the shift, in order to review the quality. The issues of dealing with irate customers or customers not inclined to speak to an Indian CSR also increases the level of stress experienced by those working in call centers.</p>
<p>Sometimes the operations manager, and less frequently the coach, may have a lower proficiency in English than the CSR (Forey and Lam <link href="#weng12058-bib-0016">forthcoming</link>). Or the person conducting the surveillance may be listening for pronunciation errors or grammatical mistakes which may not interfere with the communicative purpose of the service encounter (Lockwood et al. <link href="#weng12058-bib-0037"/>). The training and feedback that is given to CSR's has its problems and has been reported in many studies (see Cowie <link href="#weng12058-bib-0010"/>; <link href="#weng12058-bib-0011"/>; Friginal <link href="#weng12058-bib-0018"/>; <link href="#weng12058-bib-0019"/>; Lockwood et al. <link href="#weng12058-bib-0037"/>; 2009).</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0070">
<title type="main">The night shift</title>
<p>The negative impact of night shift work has been seen to significantly affect the social life of women. Patel (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0042"/>: 53) argues that in order for women to ‘manufacture respectability, mitigate risk and maintain their reputations they must abide by a mobility‐morality narrative that requires the presence of a male counterpart to justify a woman's presence in the urban nightscape’, thus even though freedom is experienced it only occurs within a world dominated and controlled by male norms. Patriarchal control was rarely acknowledged by the men and women working the night shift, rather short‐term concerns were voiced by the employees, one trainee CSR stated:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>The main reasons people don't want to work the night shift is because they are cut off from the society. They can't join in cultural events. They have to have their weddings on a Saturday, that's what happens when you work in a BPO (TCSR 13, female from Hyderabad, graduated in 2004, then mother and housewife, daughter now grown up and returned to work)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>These unsociable hours deprive the young single fresh graduates of opportunities to meet their potential life partner. One trainee CSR, who had been working the night shift, stated the reason why he came to BankA was the attraction of working the day shift, he said due to his recent marriage that he was ‘not interested in doing night shifts. I looked for a day shift; I got BankA and got day shifts. I couldn't get a better company than BankA here’ (TCSR11, male, home town unknown, worked for call centre previously, now studying part‐time). TCSR 11 thus implies that a change in marital status also changes his view about working at night.</p>
<p>Working on the night shift (‘graveyard shift’) impacts family life and creates additional stigmatisation such as concerns over personal safety and dangers of working at night, and health implications due to lack of sleep and exercise. Personal safety is a key factor for females in India, the fact that one female Indian worker was raped by the company driver does little to reduce the stigmatisation of such employment (Kapur <link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>). However, some acceptance to the industry has been given in popular movies such as <i>Slum Dog Millionaire</i> and <i>The Beautiful Exotic Marigold Hotel</i>. These movies have raised the profile and given public acceptance to call centre work. The drive for a 50 per cent increase in the number of working women in the BPO has encouraged organisations to be actively involved in promoting and working towards a reduction of such stigmatism.</p>
<p>However, the social implications of working a night shift are complex and often result in different levels of acceptance for men compared to women. The different standards for men and women, was pointed out by Trainee CSR9:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>For ladies the main problem with the BPO is the night shift. People don't prefer. But now simultaneously, in talking about the IT sector or talking about medical background, If you're a doctor you need to go on some emergency calls at night, so be it a lady, be it a gent you have to go. You have to serve. Again being in IT there is some urgency, you need to go, the mentality of the parents are changing a bit. If an IT girls is allowed to go in at night, why not a BPO? So that's what. The percentage of girls are on the increase right now. (TCSR9, female, home town unknown, Engineering degree, housewife for a few years, this is her first job)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>As pointed out by this trainee, the CSR's face discrimination through gender and the choice of this profession. Not one person we interviewed stated that they enjoyed working the night shift. Although many of them realise that it is the nature of the job and that they have little choice if they want to continue to work in the BPO. Social pressure is placed on women who work at night and this tends to be compounded by a lack of family acceptance for women to work at night.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0080">
<title type="main">Family control</title>
<p>Family control over daughters was a significant theme that emerged during the interviews. As one trainer pointed out her choice of a profession was initially decided by her parents, which may often be the case for women. However, due to financial incentives the trainer persuaded her parents to allow her to move away from home:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>Actually I got the job and I had to go back home, because my mum wasn't too happy about me moving, because I'm from Karela, and this was in Vizag. So she didn't want me to go away from home. So I was told not to take this job up. So I went back home and taught for a couple of months. So I did that for about 6 months, I was getting paid peanuts. So then when I called back up to see if they still had the job on. Then I took it up then […] Then when I moved they probably thought I'd stick around for a month or so, then I ended up staying here for longer than that. (T2, Shanti)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>The talent pool in India is shrinking, BPO's have moved to second and third tier cities to set up business. They are also spreading the net wide to find suitable candidates to take up positions. Trainer 2 was hired after completing a Masters degree in linguistics. She is one of the few trainers, who we have met throughout our association with the industry, who has qualifications and training in applied linguistics. Trainer 2 enjoyed her job, but did not view it as a long‐term career. She stated that she was only doing the job as it provided the finances for future studies. Her future was in an education related field, and she added ‘I don't want to be supported by my parents’.</p>
<p>The call centres have also been seen as a negative influence eroding traditional courtship and marriage norms. The CSR's male and female are exposed to western culture, both the culture of the institute, in the way the business is organised, and culture in the more general sense in the cultural exchanges with customers on a minute by minute basis. Such western cultural experiences are generally at odds with the predominantly patriarchal Indian society. In a country where women are not allowed to fraternise with the opposite sex before marriage and women are often seen to represent the family name, that is, the ‘daughter's misbehavior can become a problematic source of disrepute for the family’ (Tara and Ilavarasan <link href="#weng12058-bib-0050"/>: 199). Traditionally, marriage has been a social matter where the predominant consideration has generally been the alliance of two families. However, as Tara and Ilavarasan (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0050"/>: 119) point out this societal influence is being replaced by more personal concerns of ‘intimacy and companionship’. Call centres provide a space where integration between male and female, social status, regional status is no longer a boundary. Medora (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0038"/>), Kapur (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>), Tara and Ilavarasan (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0050"/>) and others all report in their studies that women are breaking away from the tradition of arranged marriages and the control of their parents. Again more research is needed to verify such waves of change in family patterns and beliefs.</p>
<p>In addition, similar to the findings of Scholarios and Taylor (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0046"/>) in the UK where they found that even if women are working in call centres they still carry the majority of the burden of domestic duties. In our interviews with Indian CSRs we found that female CSRs still played a dominant role in performing domestic duties. Night shift work has been blamed for increasing the level of divorce currently found in India. As one trainee CSR told us ‘Indian husbands want their wife to be waiting when they get home’ (TCSR 11). However, when the wife is working a night shift this is often not possible. In the interviews with CSRs they expressed that they were pleased if they were married to someone working in the same industry because then their shifts and lifestyle would be compatible.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0090">
<title type="main">Changing views</title>
<p>The result of a more mature industry in India has led to a change in the views of some within society. Naturally, there are still those who are sceptical and who will be resistant to change. However, in India, more so than the Philippines, there seems to be a paradigm shift in beliefs related to the BPO. The possible development of the BPO industry from initially the menial, back office processing such as voice (call centres), and administration, to more knowledge based processing, where professionals are employed in a capacity that draws on their professional knowledge and skill, thus increasing the remuneration for such qualified employees.
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>Parents have changed their views, my mother wanted to join the BPO's but my grandfather told her ‘no way’, then I got this place and my family have changed their views about the industry. Even my mum has now got a job in the BPO. (S1, female, hometown Vizag, Andrapadesh, 50% studying at university for a degree in Communication, 50% employed as a trainee at BankA)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>The student was a proud role model for her family, creating a more liberal view of the BPO industry, which in turn supports advances in the beliefs held by the family. As reported by Forey (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0015"/>) a limited number of major multinational corporations are offering exciting initiatives such as a ‘pay as you learn’ collaborative degree. For example, BankA is collaborating with a university and the students receive a scholarship where the students receive US$65 each month. During their studies, the students spend 50 per cent of their time at University and 50 per cent as an internship at the one of the bank's BPO units. These students who gain a studentship from a major bank are the interviewees (S) included in the present study. The students were extremely appreciative of the support and actually stated that they had increased their social status with friends and families due to the studentship that they had received (Forey <link href="#weng12058-bib-0015"/>). Positive publicity by word‐of‐mouth is perhaps one of the strongest networks to remove the existing social stigmatism.</p>
<p>Mirroring current trends, there seems to be some shift in the public appreciation of employment in this industry. As pointed out by one Trainer from BankA:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>5 years ago, it was a challenge for families to send their children to a call centre. There have been some changes, and families are more open to call centre work, exposure is developing. In Bangalore and other more mature venues this obstacle has been overcome. (T1, female, middle aged, MA in Sociology, lived in the USA, worked as a Senior Financial Analyst, returned to India 12 years ago)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>As indicated by this trainer and many others we interviewed, general acceptance to working in the BPO industry and working in call centres is changing. Another trainer with a background in law added:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>[My family] they're quite happy, because they see that you get a lot of opportunity to interact with people and they also feel that I am doing something that I like to do. So they're really happy. (T3, female, from Calcutta, MA in Communication from Punjab, been with BankA for 5 years, wanted to be a trainer but initially employed as a CSR)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>Initially call centres were viewed as the modern day sweat‐shops, now with the development from business processing to more professional work, opinions about working in call centres have changed. One CSR we met had left the police after 18 years of employment for the BPO industry as the pay, benefits and lifestyle was deemed to be better. As pointed out by T1, this change has been expressed in major urban areas such as Bangalore, the Silicon Valley of India, and other major cities. Due to a need for expansion the BPO has moved to 2nd and 3rd tier cities, where reservations about working in the BPO industry still persist. For women this expansion in the market and the constant need for new employees provides potential employment opportunities for women at all stages of their life. The diversification and the upscaling from simple to more complex, professional work in India allows for qualified graduates and postgraduates to find a role within the BPO. However, regardless of academic qualifications or professional experience, one of the main criteria for employment is English language proficiency.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0100">
<title type="main">Economic, professional and social benefits</title>
<p>The direct economic, profession and social benefits enable the employees a certain degree of independence. As one of the trainee CSRs commented ‘by studying we can earn money ourselves, we no longer are dependent on our parents, we can have our own pocket money’ (TCSR11). During our field visits to over 30 BPO organisations over the years, we have been involved in working and interviewing trainers, in order to understand the language needs of those involved (see Forey and Lockwood 2007; Lockwood et al. <link href="#weng12058-bib-0037"/>; Lockwood <link href="#weng12058-bib-0034"/>). Often we find that those employed as trainers were previously secondary or tertiary educators who have moved to now being employed within the BPO industry. All ex‐teachers stated how their work in the BPO allowed them greater freedom to teach in a more organised and supportive environment. Many complained of the poor funding, poor status and poor pay when they worked as teachers in secondary or tertiary institutions. As Trainer 3 stated, above, ‘I earned peanuts as a teacher’ (T3). Another trainer, Shanti pointed out:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>I was appointed as a Lecturer. I earned 5,000 Rupees, when I came here I got 15,000 Rupees. If you're a lecturer with a permanent job you'd definitely not get 15,000 Rupees … Here there's lots of learning, lots of good things that I wouldn't have done in college. In college I would do my PhD and that's it … At the University I used to have to wear a sari, even when I was so young, I felt so old … I'm happy. (T2)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>Shanti referred to a monthly salary 5,000 Indian Rupees which is roughly equivalent to US$105. Shanti also raised the topic of the positive shift of her own identity within the industry. This comparison between the conservative and ‘bookish’, sometimes even referred to as ‘backward’ environment of educational institutions to the modern, challenging, well‐funded training facilities within the BPO. Shanti, continued to discuss her domestic burden during the interview and talked about how she still had to prepare dinner for her husband and herself and how she enjoyed the time that she spent with her spouse, although time together was dependent upon the allocation of Shanti's shifts. All the trainers CSRs, trainee CSRs and informants appeared to be extremely happy with their workplace. Stating that the positive economic rewards defied the negative stigmatism. All believed that it would not belong before such stigmatism had disappeared.</p>
<p>The situation was very similar in the Philippines, where trainers and CSRs also reported similar benefits to working in the industry. As one Filipino CSR pointed out ‘the salary of a new CSR is even higher than an experienced business manager’ (Ph CSR1). The relationship between the stress of the work and the benefits are openly discussed within the industry. As pointed out by another Filipino CSR:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>working in call centre is stressful, but it can allow you to purchase the house, the car and support the family (Ph CSR2, male, mid‐twenties, hometown unknown, Engineering degree)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>However, regardless of the stress, it seems that for many employed in BPOs in India and the Philippines the work is preferred to other employment options. During our interviews with the CSRs in India the agents we interviewed came from a mixed background, some had chosen a change of career, many had joined the industry as fresh graduates. We can look at the background of some of the female trainers, for example, (T1) Shanti, an ex‐university lecturer, T2 an MA in applied linguistics, T3 a returnee from the USA, with an MA in sociology and used to work with Deloittes, and T4 used to work in a law firm. For these women the BPO offered great opportunities including an increase in work status, economic benefits, and prospect of working for a highly recognised bank. Many saw a future career as a trainer or language expert within the industry. However, as illustrated from their background only a few of these trainers have either an educational or applied linguistics background. Often the trainers within the industry have no English language qualification. The trainers have higher status than a CSR.</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0110">
<title type="main">Potential and hope</title>
<p>These employment opportunities provide potential hope for all women from all different social backgrounds. As T3 pointed out:
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>Before the BPO started it was unheard of for women to live by themselves or for women to move from their hometown for job opportunities, like in call centres … till 15 years ago you wouldn't be allowed by your parents to move to a different town. And even if you are allowed you'd probably share a room with other girls. But now things have changed. (T3)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>The trainer who discussed how life has changed for women had spent quite some time in the USA, and had experienced independence in a very western society. Returning to India T3 was pleased to see how opportunities had improved for women since she was a child. She also stated that she believed part of her role within the industry was to encourage women to strive for success and she could now provide opportunities to women which had not been available before. T3 stated that work in the BPO may be seen as a ‘stop gap’ but if women want to pursue a career it provides ‘unlimited opportunities’. This sentiment of potential and hope was expressed by many of the informants. Both the male and female informants agreed with this emancipation of women. One male trainee CSR eloquently stated that the BPO provides :
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>a great hope for women to achieve equal rights with the men in India. These days we can find that call centre culture has not only brought freedom for women to work with men in any shift, but also drastically made a way for the western culture to creep into Indian culture. It definitely brought about change and improved lifestyle, but it has brought some dilution of culture and behavioural patterns. (TCSR 23, male, home town unknown, Computer Science graduate, lived in the UK for 3 years doing voluntary work, first job on returning to India)</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>As noted by TCSR 23, this change has afforded benefits and greater equality to women, but is this at the detriment to tradition and culture? An area of study that needs far greater attention is the focus on the erosion of tradition, culture and mother tongue dialects in both India and the Philippines. The powerhouse and economic benefit which the BPO brings with it encourages politicians and business investors to call for more English to be taught in schools and more English to be spoken in the homes. Such a cry for economic development and advancement has little objection among the masses. Little if no research has been carried out on how the development of English through the BPO industry impacts mother tongue dialects in these locations.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="weng12058-sec-0120">
<title type="main">CONCLUSION</title>
<p>To conclude, it is evident from the data collected and the findings discussed that the globalisation of English through this ‘megatrend’ in the expansion of the BPO industry has had a tremendous effect on the lives of those involved. In countries such as India, where women have traditionally faced historical and ingrained discrimination, BPO employment provides challenges to traditional stereotypes, opportunity and potential hope. It may be cynical to suggest that changes that have occurred have been economically motivated rather than triggered by other social concerns. The social impact on women has been significant, and the findings suggest that women have been given opportunities that were not previously available through other means. Change due to the economic benefit of English in the BPO industry is clearly underway and is having direct impact on women. Women by working in the industry have experienced economic benefit, new independence, opportunities which perhaps were not so readily available before the introduction of the BPO.</p>
<p>However, with change comes the question about the impact of this change. Positive and progressive changes for women by their increased participation in the workforce needs to be assessed with respect to the cost of such changes to the traditions and fabric of society. If women join the BPO workforce and are employed on the night shift how will this impact on the role of women within society and the family? It emerged that although women had greater participation in the BPO workforce this did not equate to a reduction in their domestic duties. The findings suggested that women continued to be the main carer and now had the added load of work entailing unsociable hours and evidentially a level of stress. Working on the night shift also raises questions of health risks. As suggested by Kapur (<link href="#weng12058-bib-0032"/>) working on the night shift and in close proximity to male co‐workers has an impact on the social life, courtship, marriage and divorce for some involved.</p>
<p>The majority of individuals joining the BPO are fresh graduates who are looking for a future career and at a personal level many are also looking for a life‐partner. Finally from a language and educational perspective there are two key caveats that must be considered. An initial concern is the exodus of teachers from poorly supported but essential roles in schools and universities to the BPO industry, where the environment and economic benefits are much more conducive. What happens to the education of the future children who will one day want to join this or another employment sector? Second, from a linguistic perspective what is the impact on indigenous languages? While BPOs are having an impact on gender inequality in India, there are also challenges to women's progress in the field of employment, as noted by the United Nations Procurement Division (UNPD 2009: 27):
<blockFixed type="quotation"><p>No single measure itself is sufficient to take on entrenched and persistent gender inequalities. Policies to stimulate growth must be accompanied by measures to change norms that block women's progress.</p></blockFixed></p>
<p>Perhaps a change is imminent or even currently underway, but as observers and academics involved in world Englishes we have had minimal participation to reveal the true picture of the current situation; or support equality by understanding the issue at hand. Research on world Englishes needs improved collaboration with varying industries around the world. This kind of research will hopefully develop bridges between industry and education and increase investment in language teaching education, and through education we may be able to work towards reducing gender inequality as well as ther inequities.</p>
</section>
<bibliography xml:id="weng12058-bibl-0001" style="nameDate">
<title type="main">REFERENCES</title>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0001">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0001"><author><familyName>Adolphs</familyName>, <givenNames>Svenja</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Brian</givenNames> <familyName>Brown</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Ronald</givenNames> <familyName>Carter</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Paul</givenNames> <familyName>Crawford</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Opinder</givenNames> <familyName>Sahota</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Applying corpus linguistics in a healthcare context</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Applied Linguistics</journalTitle> <vol>1</vol>(<issue>1</issue>).<pageFirst>9</pageFirst>–<pageLast>28</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0002">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0002"><author><familyName>Bain</familyName>, <givenNames>Peter</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Aileen</givenNames> <familyName>Watson</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Gareth</givenNames> <familyName>Mulvey</familyName></author>, <author><givenNames>Phil</givenNames> <familyName>Taylor</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Gregor</givenNames> <familyName>Gall</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2002">2002</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Taylorism, targets and the pursuit of quantity and quality by call centre management</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>New Technology Work and Employment</journalTitle> <vol>17</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>170</pageFirst>–<pageLast>85</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0003">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0003"><author><familyName>Belt</familyName>, <givenNames>Vicki</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2002">2002</pubYear>. <articleTitle>‘A female ghetto?’ Women's careers in call centers</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Human Resource Management Journal</journalTitle> <vol>12</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>51</pageFirst>–<pageLast>66</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0004">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0004"><author><familyName>Belt</familyName>, <givenNames>Vicki</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Ranald</givenNames> <familyName>Richardson</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Juliet</givenNames> <familyName>Webster</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2002">2002</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Women, social skill and interactive work in telephone call centres</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>New Technology, Work and Employment</journalTitle> <vol>17</vol>(<issue>1</issue>).<pageFirst>20</pageFirst>–<pageLast>34</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0005">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0005"><author><familyName>Blommaert</familyName>, <givenNames>Jan</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2003">2003</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Commentary: A sociolinguistics of globalization</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Sociolinguistics</journalTitle> <vol>7</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>607</pageFirst>–<pageLast>23</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0053">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0053"><author><familyName>Bolton</familyName>, <givenNames>Kingsley</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. ‘<chapterTitle>Thank you for calling': Asian Englishes and ‘native‐like’ performance in Asian call centres</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>The Routledge handbook of world Englishes</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Andy</givenNames> <familyName>Kirkpatrick</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>550</pageFirst>–<pageLast>64</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Routledge</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0006">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0006"><author><familyName>Bolton</familyName>, <givenNames>Sharon C.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Maeve</givenNames> <familyName>Houlihan</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>. <articleTitle>The (mis)representation of customer service</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Work, Employment and Society</journalTitle> <vol>19</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>685</pageFirst>–<pageLast>703</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0007">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0007"><editor><familyName>Bolton</familyName>, <givenNames>Kingsley</givenNames></editor>, and <editor><givenNames>Braj</givenNames> <familyName>Kachru</familyName></editor>. (eds.). <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <bookTitle>World Englishes: Critical concepts in linguistics, Volume 5</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Routledge</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0008">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0008"><author><familyName>Cameron</familyName>, <givenNames>Deborah</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2000">2000a</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Styling the worker: Gender and the commodification of language in the globalized service economy</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Sociolinguistics</journalTitle> <vol>4</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>323</pageFirst>–<pageLast>47</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0009">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0009"><author><familyName>Cameron</familyName>, <givenNames>Deborah</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2000">2000b</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Good to talk? Living and working in a communication culture</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Sage</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0010">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0010"><author><familyName>Cowie</familyName>, <givenNames>Claire</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <articleTitle>The accents of outsourcing: The meanings of ‘neutral’ in the Indian call centre industry</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>World Englishes</journalTitle> <vol>26</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>316</pageFirst>–<pageLast>30</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0011">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0011"><author><familyName>Cowie</familyName>, <givenNames>Claire</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Anyone doing something phonetic can attract business these days: The demand and supply of accents in the Indian call centre industry</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Language and the market</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Helen</givenNames> <familyName>Kelly‐Holmes</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Gerlinde</givenNames> <familyName>Mautner</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>20</pageFirst>–<pageLast>32</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Palgrave Macmillan</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0012">
<citation type="other" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0012"><author><familyName>Cu</familyName>, <givenNames>E. L.</givenNames></author> <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <otherTitle>Philippine BPO industry: 2005 Scorecard</otherTitle>. Online: <url href="http://www.bpap.org/bpap/bpapresearch.asp">http://www.bpap.org/bpap/bpapresearch.asp</url> (February 27, 2006).</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0013">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0013"><author><familyName>Davies</familyName>, <givenNames>Alan</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Language assessment in call centres</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Globalization, Communication and the Workplace: Talking Across the World</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Gail</givenNames> <familyName>Forey</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Jane</givenNames> <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>242</pageFirst>–<pageLast>50</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0014">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0014"><editor><familyName>Davis</familyName>, <givenNames>Kathy</givenNames></editor>, <editor><givenNames>Mary</givenNames> <familyName>Evans</familyName></editor>, and <editor><givenNames>Judith</givenNames> <familyName>Lorber</familyName></editor> (eds.). <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Handbook of gender and women's studies</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Sage</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0015">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0015"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Language, globalization and the workplace: Education and social implications</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Globalisation, communication and the workplace</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Gail</givenNames> <familyName>Forey</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Jane</givenNames> <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>251</pageFirst>–<pageLast>70</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0016">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0016"><author><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Marvin</givenNames> <familyName>Lam</familyName></author> (forthcoming). <pubYear year="2013">2013</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Applying systemic functional linguistics: Understanding the choices of quality in the workplace. The impact of SFL on professional discourse</articleTitle>. Special focus issue. <journalTitle>Journal of Applied Linguistics and Professional Practice</journalTitle>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0017">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0017"><editor><familyName>Forey</familyName>, <givenNames>Gail</givenNames></editor>, and <editor><givenNames>Jane</givenNames> <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></editor>. (eds.). <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Globalisation, communication &amp; the workplace</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0018">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0018"><author><familyName>Friginal</familyName>, <givenNames>Eric</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Outsourced call centres and English in the Philippines</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>World Englishes.</journalTitle> <vol>26</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>331</pageFirst>–<pageLast>45</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0019">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0019"><author><familyName>Friginal</familyName>, <givenNames>Eric</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Call centre training and language in the Philippines</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Globalisation, Communication &amp; the Workplace</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Gail</givenNames> <familyName>Forey</familyName></editor>, and <editor><givenNames>Jane</givenNames> <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>190</pageFirst>–<pageLast>203</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0020">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0020"><author><familyName>Ganguly‐Scrase</familyName>, <givenNames>Ruchira</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2003">2003</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Class in West Bengal, India. Paradoxes of globalization, liberalization, and gender equality: The worldviews of the lower middle</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Gender &amp; Society</journalTitle> <vol>17</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>544</pageFirst>–<pageLast>66</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0021">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0021"><author><familyName>Graddol</familyName>, <givenNames>David</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <bookTitle>English next</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>British Council</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0022">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0022"><author><familyName>Gilmore</familyName>, <givenNames>Audrey</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2001">2001</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Call centre management: is service quality a priority?</articleTitle> <journalTitle>Managing Service Quality</journalTitle> <vol>11</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>53</pageFirst>–<pageLast>159</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0023">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0023"><author><familyName>Halliday</familyName>, <givenNames>Michael A. K.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Christian M. I. M.</givenNames> <familyName>Matthiessen</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>. <bookTitle>An introduction to functional grammar</bookTitle>, <edition>3rd edition</edition>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Edward Arnold</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0024">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0024"><author><familyName>Hamp‐Lyons</familyName>, <givenNames>Liz</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Jane</givenNames> <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2009">2009</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>The workplace, the society and the wider world: The offshoring and outsourcing industry in language policy and language assessment</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Annual Review of Applied Linguistics</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Bernard</givenNames> <familyName>Spolsky</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>145</pageFirst>–<pageLast>67</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Cambridge</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Cambridge University Press</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0025">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0025"><author><familyName>Holmes</familyName>, <givenNames>Janet</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Gendered talk at work: Constructing gender identity through workplace discourse</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Blackwell</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0026">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0026"><author><familyName>Hood</familyName>, <givenNames>Susan</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Gail</givenNames> <familyName>Forey</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2008">2008</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Co‐constructing emotion: The interpersonal dynamics of call‐centre interactions</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Discourse and Communication</journalTitle> <vol>2</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>389</pageFirst>–<pageLast>409</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0027">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0027"><author><familyName>Jenkins</familyName>, <givenNames>Jennifer</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <bookTitle>English as a lingua franca: Attitude and identity</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Oxford</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Oxford University Press</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0028">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0028"><author><familyName>Jenkins</familyName>, <givenNames>Jennifer</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2009">2009</pubYear> <articleTitle>English as a lingua franca: Interpretations and attitudes</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>World Englishes</journalTitle> <vol>28</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>200</pageFirst>–<pageLast>7</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0029">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0029"><author><familyName>Kachru</familyName>, <givenNames>Braj</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1996">1996</pubYear>. <articleTitle>The paradigms of marginality</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>World Englishes</journalTitle> <vol>15</vol>(<issue>3</issue>).<pageFirst>241</pageFirst>–<pageLast>55</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0030">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0030"><author><familyName>Kachru</familyName>, <givenNames>Braj</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="1997">1997</pubYear>. <articleTitle>World Englishes and English‐using communities</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Annual Review of Applied Linguistics</journalTitle> <vol>16</vol>.<pageFirst>66</pageFirst>–<pageLast>87</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0031">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0031"><author><familyName>Kachru</familyName>, <givenNames>Braj</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Yamuna</givenNames> <familyName>Kachru</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Cecil</givenNames> <familyName>Nelson</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <bookTitle>The handbook of world Englishes</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Hoboken, NJ</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>John Wiley and Sons</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0032">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0032"><author><familyName>Kapur</familyName>, <givenNames>Cari C</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Rethinking courtship, marriage and divorce in an Indian Call centre</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Everyday life in South Asia</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Diane P.</givenNames> <familyName>Mines</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Sarah</givenNames> <familyName>Lamb</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>50</pageFirst>–<pageLast>61</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Bloomington, IN</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Indiana University Press</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0033">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0033"><author><familyName>Lockwood</familyName>, <givenNames>Jane</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>What causes communication breakdown in the call centres? The discrepancies in BPO workplace training and academic research</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Globalization, Communication and the Workplace</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>Gail</givenNames> <familyName>Forey</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Jane</givenNames> <familyName>Lockwood</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>204</pageFirst>–<pageLast>20</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>London</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Continuum</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0034">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0034"><author><familyName>Lockwood</familyName>, <givenNames>Jane</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2012">2012a</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Are we getting the right people for the job? A study of English language recruitment assessment practices in the business processing outsourcing sector: India and the Philippines</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Journal of Business Communication</journalTitle> <vol>49</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>107</pageFirst>–<pageLast>27</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0035">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0035"><author><familyName>Lockwood</familyName>, <givenNames>Jane</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2012">2012b</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Developing an English for specific purpose curriculum for Asian call centres: How the theory can inform practice</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>English for Specific Purposes</journalTitle> <vol>31</vol>(<issue>1</issue>).<pageFirst>14</pageFirst>–<pageLast>24</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0036">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0036"><author><familyName>Lockwood</familyName>, <givenNames>Jane</givenNames></author>. (forthcoming). <chapterTitle>Assessment of business and professional Language for Specific Purposes</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>The encyclopedia of applied linguistics</bookTitle>, ed. By <editor><givenNames>Carol A.</givenNames> <familyName>Chapelle</familyName></editor>. <publisherLoc>Oxford</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Wiley‐Blackwell</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0037">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0037"><author><familyName>Lockwood</familyName>, <givenNames>Jane</givenNames></author>, <author><givenNames>Gail</givenNames> <familyName>Forey</familyName></author>, and <author><givenNames>Helen</givenNames> <familyName>Price</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2008">2008</pubYear>. <chapterTitle>Englishes in the Philippine business processing outsourcing industry: Issues, opportunities and research</chapterTitle>. <bookTitle>Philippines English: Linguistic and literary perspectives</bookTitle>, ed. by <editor><givenNames>M.</givenNames> <familyName>Lourdes</familyName></editor> <editor><givenNames>S.</givenNames> <familyName>Bautista</familyName></editor> and <editor><givenNames>Kingsley</givenNames> <familyName>Bolton</familyName></editor>, <pageFirst>157</pageFirst>–<pageLast>72</pageLast>. <publisherLoc>Hong Kong</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Hong Kong University Press</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0038">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0038"><author><familyName>Medora</familyName>, <givenNames>Nilufer P</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Strengths and challenges in the Indian Family</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Marriage &amp; Family Review</journalTitle> <vol>41</vol>(<issue>1–2</issue>).<pageFirst>165</pageFirst>–<pageLast>93</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0039">
<citation type="other" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0039"><groupName>NASSCOM</groupName>. <pubYear year="2009">2009a</pubYear>. <otherTitle>Gender inclusivity in India: Building an empowered organisation</otherTitle>. Online: <url href="http://www.nasscom.in">http://www.nasscom.in</url> (December 1, 2012)</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0040">
<citation type="other" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0040"><groupName>NASSCOM</groupName>. <pubYear year="2009">2009b</pubYear>. <otherTitle>Impact of IT‐BPO Industry in India: A decade in review</otherTitle>. Online: <url href="http://www.nasscom.in/impact-itbpo-industry-india-decade-review">http://www.nasscom.in/impact‐itbpo‐industry‐india‐decade‐review</url> (February 4, 2013)</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0041">
<citation type="other" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0041"><groupName>NASSCOM</groupName>. <pubYear year="2012">2012</pubYear>. <otherTitle>The IT‐BPO sector in India: Strategic review 2012</otherTitle>. Online: <url href="http://www.nasscom.org">www.nasscom.org</url> <i>(December 8, 2012)</i></citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0042">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0042"><author><familyName>Patel</familyName>, <givenNames>Reena</givenNames></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Working the night shift: Women in India's call center industry</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Stanford, CA</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Stanford University Press</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0043">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0043"><author><familyName>Porter</familyName>, <givenNames>Les J.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Steve J.</givenNames> <familyName>Tanner</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2004">2004</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Assessing business excellence</bookTitle>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisherLoc>Oxford</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Butterworth‐Heinemann</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0044">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0044"><author><familyName>Ray</familyName>, <givenNames>Raka</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Seemin</givenNames> <familyName>Qayum</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2009">2009</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Cultures of servitude: Modernity, domesticity, and class in India</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Stanford, CA</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Stanford University Press</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0045">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0045"><author><familyName>Scholarios</familyName>, <givenNames>Dora</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Phil</givenNames> <familyName>Taylor</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2010">2010</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Gender, choice and constraint in call centre employment</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>New Technology, Work and Employment</journalTitle> <vol>25</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>101</pageFirst>–<pageLast>16</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0046">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0046"><author><familyName>Scholarios</familyName>, <givenNames>Dora</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Phil</givenNames> <familyName>Taylor</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2011">2011</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Beneath the glass ceiling: Explaining gendered role segmentation in call centres</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Human Relations</journalTitle> <vol>64</vol>(<issue>10</issue>).<pageFirst>1291</pageFirst>–<pageLast>19</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0047">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0047"><author><familyName>Singh</familyName>, <givenNames>Preeti</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Anu</givenNames> <familyName>Pandey</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2006">2006</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Women in call centres</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Economic Political Weekly</journalTitle> <vol>40</vol>(<issue>7</issue>).<pageFirst>684</pageFirst>–<pageLast>88</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0048">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0048"><editor><familyName>Smith</familyName>, <givenNames>Jackie</givenNames></editor> (ed.). <pubYear year="2007">2007</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Social movements for global democracy</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>Baltimore, MD</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0049">
<citation type="book" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0049"><author><familyName>Sudarshan</familyName>, <givenNames>Ratna M.</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Shrayana</givenNames> <familyName>Bhattacharya</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2008">2008</pubYear>. <bookTitle>Through the magnifying glass: Women's work and labour force participation in urban Delhi</bookTitle>. <publisherLoc>New Delhi</publisherLoc>: <publisherName>International Labour Organization</publisherName>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0050">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0050"><author><familyName>Tara</familyName>, <givenNames>Shelly</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>P. Vigneswara</givenNames> <familyName>Ilavarasan</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2011">2011</pubYear>. <articleTitle>Marriage and midnight work: A qualitative study of unmarried women call center agents in India</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Marriage &amp; Family Review</journalTitle> <vol>47</vol>(<issue>4</issue>).<pageFirst>197</pageFirst>–<pageLast>212</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0051">
<citation type="journal" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0051"><author><familyName>Taylor</familyName>, <givenNames>Phil</givenNames></author>, and <author><givenNames>Peter</givenNames> <familyName>Bain</familyName></author>. <pubYear year="2005">2005</pubYear>. <articleTitle>India calling to the far away towns: The call centre labour process and globalisation</articleTitle>. <journalTitle>Work, Employment and Society</journalTitle> <vol>19</vol>(<issue>2</issue>).<pageFirst>261</pageFirst>–<pageLast>82</pageLast>.</citation></bib>
<bib xml:id="weng12058-bib-0052">
<citation type="other" xml:id="weng12058-cit-0052"><groupName>United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)</groupName>. <pubYear year="2009">2009</pubYear>. <otherTitle>Human development report 2009 overcoming barriers: Human mobility and development</otherTitle>. Online: <url href="http://hdr.undp.org/en/reports/global/hdr2009/">http://hdr.undp.org/en/reports/global/hdr2009/</url> (January 10, 2013).</citation></bib>
</bibliography>
</body>
</component>