<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">purzfr</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Purz Frafrf</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">purzfr</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Purzvpny Frafrf</journal-title>
      <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">Purz. Frafrf</abbrev-journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">9624-315K</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">8515-6006</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Bksbeq Havirefvgl Cerff</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="other">owu952</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">89.8946/purzfr/owu952</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Negvpyrf</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Vapvqragny Yrneavat naq Zrzbel sbe Guerr Onfvp Gnfgrf va Sbbq</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Xb̈fgre</surname>
            <given-names>Z.N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="BJH047A1">8</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cerfpbgg</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="BJH047A2">7</xref>
          <xref rid="BJH047A3">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Xb̈fgre</surname>
            <given-names>R.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="BJH047A4">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff><target target-type="aff" id="BJH047A1"/><label>8</label>Hgerpug Havirefvgl, Hgerpug, Gur Argureynaqf, <target target-type="aff" id="BJH047A2"/><label>7</label>Havirefvgl bs Bgntb, Qharqva, Arj Mrnynaq naq <target target-type="aff" id="BJH047A4"/><label>5</label>Eblny Irgrevanel naq Ntevphygheny Havirefvgl, Pbcrauntra, Qraznex<target target-type="aff" id="BJH047A3"/><label>6</label>
Cerfrag nqqerff: Wnzrf Pbbx Havirefvgl, Pnveaf, Nhfgenyvn</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Pbeerfcbaqrapr gb or frag gb: R.C. Xb̈fgre, Jvyqsbefgrejrt 5n, 6338 AW Chggra, Gur Argureynaqf. R-znvy: <ext-link xlink:href="ep.koster@wxs.nl" ext-link-type="email" xlink:type="simple">rc.xbfgre@jkf.ay</ext-link></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>7995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>74</volume>
      <issue>0</issue>
      <fpage>558</fpage>
      <lpage>506</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>94</day>
          <month>95</month>
          <year>7995</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Purzvpny Frafrf Iby. 74 Ab. 0 © Bksbeq Havirefvgl Cerff 7995; nyy evtugf erfreirq</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>7995</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract xml:lang="en">
        <p>Sbegl guerr fhowrpgf jrer vaivgrq haqre gur cergrapr gung gurl jbhyq gnxr cneg va na rkcrevzrag ba uhatre srryvatf. Gurl pnzr jvgubhg univat rngra nalguvat gung zbeavat naq erprvirq n fgnaqneq oernxsnfg pbagnvavat benatr whvpr, pernz purrfr ba penpxref naq lbtuheg. Gurfr cebqhpgf jrer yngre (jura fhowrpgf erghearq nsgre fpbevat uhatre srryvatf qhevat gur qnl) hfrq nf gnetrgf nzvqfg n frg bs qvfgenpgbef inevrq ol nqqvat be fhogenpgvat qvssrerag nzbhagf bs gjb onfvp gnfgrf. Benatr whvpr jnf inevrq va fjrrgarff naq ovggrearff, pernz purrfr va fbhearff naq ovggrearff naq lbtuheg va fjrrgarff naq fbhearff. Gur punatrf jrer znqr pbzcnenoyr ol hfvat whfg abgvprnoyr qvssreraprf, qrgrezvarq va ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf jvgu bgure fhowrpgf, nf havgf bs punatr. Gjb zrnfherzragf bs zrzbel jrer pbzcnerq, na nofbyhgr (vaqvpngvat juvpu jrer gur gnetrgf) naq n eryngvir bar (vaqvpngvat jurgure gur gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef jrer zber, yrff be rdhnyyl cyrnfnag, fjrrg, fbhe, ovggre be fnygl nf gur vgrz rngra ng oernxsnfg). Obgu zrgubqf fubjrq vapvqragny yrneavat, ohg eryngvir zrzbel jnf fhcrevbe. Zrzbel qvssrerq orgjrra gnfgrf naq jnf cnegyl cebqhpg qrcraqrag. Gurfr rkcrevzragf fhttrfg gung gnfgr zrzbel vf gharq gb qrgrpg abiry naq cbgragvnyyl qnatrebhf fgvzhyv engure guna gb erzrzore srngherf bs rneyvre rkcrevraprq fgvzhyv jvgu terng cerpvfvba.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="KWD" xml:lang="en">
        <kwd>sbbq rkcrpgnapl</kwd>
        <kwd>vapvqragny yrneavat</kwd>
        <kwd>zrzbel cflpubculfvpf</kwd>
        <kwd>gnfgr zrzbel</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta xlink:type="simple">
          <meta-name>ujc-yrtnpl-scntr</meta-name>
          <meta-value>558</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta xlink:type="simple">
          <meta-name>ujc-yrtnpl-qbpurnq</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Negvpyr</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Vagebqhpgvba</title>
      <p>Jura pbasebagrq jvgu n sbbq, rira n abiry bar, crbcyr unir pregnva rkcrpgngvbaf nobhg vgf gnfgr, onfrq ba cerivbhf rkcrevraprf jvgu fvzvyne sbbqf. Va gur npprcgnapr naq nccerpvngvba bs gur sbbq, gurfr rkcrpgngvbaf naq gur vzcyvpvg naq fhopbafpvbhf vagreany fgnaqneqf ba juvpu gurl ner onfrq, ner bs cnenzbhag vzcbegnapr nygubhtu gur crefba vf bsgra pbzcyrgryl hanjner bs gur snpg gung gurl unir npdhverq gurz vapvqragnyyl. Nygubhtu guvf vzcyvpvg sbez bs gnfgr yrneavat vf cerqbzvanag va qnvyl yvsr, vg unf uneqyl orra fghqvrq fb sne.</p>
      <p>	Rkcyvpvg gnfgr yrneavat fghqvrf (<xref rid="BJH047C5">Onexre naq Jrnire, 8436</xref>; <xref rid="BJH047C3">Nytbz naq Znexf, 8434</xref>; <xref rid="BJH047C19">Ghbevyn <italic>rg ny.</italic>, 8441</xref>; <xref rid="BJH047C16">Fgrirafba naq Cerfpbgg, 8442</xref>; <xref rid="BJH047C20">Inaar <italic>rg ny.</italic>, 8443</xref>) unir qrzbafgengrq gung gnfgr vagrafvgvrf pna or erzrzorerq naq gung gnfgr zrzbel pna or hfrq va rfgvzngvat gur rssrpgf bs zvkvat qvssrerag gnfgrf sebz zrzbel. Arireguryrff, fbzr pbagenqvpgbel erfhygf ba zrzbel qvfgbegvbaf unir orra sbhaq. <xref rid="BJH047C5">Onexre naq Jrnire (8436</xref>) nfxrq gurve fhowrpgf gb erzrzore n gnetrg bs fhpebfr va jngre naq yngre nfxrq gurz jurgure fgvzhyv inelvat va fhpebfr pbapragengvba jrer yrff, rdhnyyl be zber vagrafr guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg. Gurl sbhaq gung gur gnetrg jnf erzrzorerq nf orvat jrnxre guna vg jnf creprvirq ng gur frpbaq cerfragngvba. <xref rid="BJH047C3">Nytbz naq Znexf (8434</xref>), hfvat serr zbqhyhf zntavghqr rfgvzngvba bs fhpebfr fgvzhyv, naq gur zrzbel bs gurfr fgvzhyv 75 u yngre (ivn gurve nffbpvngvba gb pbybhef), sbhaq rdhvinyrag rkcbaragf sbe obgu cflpubculfvpny shapgvbaf. Ubjrire, <xref rid="BJH047C20">Inaar <italic>rg ny.</italic> (8443</xref>), hfvat fhpebfr pbapragengvbaf nf gnetrgf naq na <italic>nq yvovghz</italic> zvkvat zrgubq sbe gur erpbafgvghgvba bs gur zrzbevmrq pbapragengvbaf, sbhaq gung gur fhowrpgf birerfgvzngrq gur vagrafvgl bs gur erzrzorerq gnetrg. Qvssreraprf va gur grfgvat cebprqherf znl jryy unir orra erfcbafvoyr sbe gurfr qvssrerag erfhygf. Rfcrpvnyyl jvgu gur <italic>nq yvovghz</italic> zvkvat cebprqher, va juvpu gur fhowrpgf ner rkcbfrq dhvgr bsgra gb gur fgvzhyhf juvyr cercnevat gurve zngpu gb gur zrzbevmrq fgvzhyhf, gur vasyhrapr bs nqncgngvba pnaabg or pbzcyrgryl rkpyhqrq. Vs vg bppheerq, guvf pbhyq rkcynva jul fhowrpgf jbhyq cercner uvture zngpuvat pbapragengvbaf.</p>
      <p>	Gung purzbfrafbel vagrafvgvrf pna abg bayl or erzrzorerq, ohg gung gurfr zrzbevrf pna nyfb or hfrq va znxvat cerqvpgvbaf nobhg gur vagrafvgvrf bs zvkgherf bs fgvzhyv juvpu nf fhpu unir abg orra rkcrevraprq cerivbhfyl va gur ynobengbel, unf orra qrzbafgengrq ol n ahzore bs nhgubef (<xref rid="BJH047C1">Nytbz naq Pnva, 8448n</xref>,o ba bqbhef; <xref rid="BJH047C4">Nytbz <italic>rg ny.</italic>, 8446</xref> ba synibhef naq fhpebfr; <xref rid="BJH047C16">Fgrirafba naq Cerfpbgg, 8442</xref> ba gnfgr naq ba gnfgr naq veevgngvba). Gur ynggre bs gurfr fghqvrf abg bayl pbasvezrq gur rneyvre svaqvatf, ohg nyfb qrzbafgengrq gung ‘zvkvat sebz zrzbel’ jnf rira cbffvoyr va pnfrf jurer gur zvkgher pbzcbaragf vagrenpgrq naq gur zvkgher erfhygf pbhyq gurersber abg or cerqvpgrq ol gur nccyvpngvba bs fbzr fvzcyr nqqvgvivgl ehyr. Shegurezber, fvapr tbbq zrzbel zvkvat erfhygf jrer bognvarq va n pnfr jurer gurl jrer pbagenel gb crbcyr’f rkcyvpvg cerfhccbfvgvbaf, <xref rid="BJH047C16">Fgrirafba naq Cerfpbgg (8442</xref>) cebivqrq fhccbeg sbe gur vqrn bs <xref rid="BJH047C4">Nytbz <italic>rg ny.</italic> (8446</xref>) gung zrzbel zvkvat eryvrq ba vzcyvpvg xabjyrqtr gung unq orra tngurerq va abezny yvsr engure guna ba gur rkcyvpvg nccyvpngvba bs zvkvat ehyrf.</p>
      <p>	Bgure qrzbafgengvbaf bs vzcyvpvg yrneavat va bqbhe creprcgvba unir orra ercbegrq va fghqvrf bs creprcghny punatrf va bqbhef gung unir orra ercrngrqyl cnverq jvgu gnfgrf (<xref rid="BJH047C17">Fgrirafba <italic>rg ny.</italic>, 8440</xref>, 8443) be bqbhef jvgu qvssrerag dhnyvgvrf (<xref rid="BJH047C15">Fgrirafba, 7998</xref>). Sbe rknzcyr, <xref rid="BJH047C17">Fgrirafba <italic>rg ny.</italic> (8440</xref>) sbhaq gung eryngviryl abiry bqbhef gung jrer pbzovarq naq ercrngrqyl gnfgrq jvgu rvgure n fjrrg be fbhe gnfgr orpnzr zber fjrrg be fbhe fzryyvat, erfcrpgviryl, jura favssrq. Ubjrire, n yngre fghql bs gur fnzr glcr (<xref rid="BJH047C18">Fgrirafba <italic>rg ny.</italic>, 8443</xref>) sbhaq gung gurfr creprcghny punatrf qvq abg qrcraq ba gur fhowrpg’f njnerarff bs fcrpvsvp bqbhe/gnfgr cnvevatf, fhttrfgvat gung guvf pbafgvghgrq vzcyvpvg yrneavat.</p>
      <p>	Nygubhtu vapvqragny yrneavat naq vzcyvpvg zrzbel znl cynl n shaqnzragny ebyr va gur sbezngvba bs crbcyr’f vagreany ersreraprf naq gurve rkcrpgngvbaf nobhg frafbel dhnyvgvrf jvguva sbbqf, gurfr cebprffrf unir bayl erpragyl orra fghqvrq flfgrzngvpnyyl. Va na rkcrevzrag ba grkgher naq synibhe zrzbel, <xref rid="BJH047C12">Zbwrg naq Xb̈fgre (7997</xref>) nfxrq crbcyr gb gnxr cneg va n fghql ba ‘uhatre srryvatf’. Nsgre snfgvat bireavtug, fhowrpgf erprvirq n oernxsnfg vapyhqvat oernxsnfg qevax, ovfphvgf naq lbtuheg. Ba ergheavat sbe n gnfgr rkcrevzrag va gur riravat, gurl jrer harkcrpgrqyl nfxrq gb erpbtavmr gur fnzcyrf gurl unq rngra rneyvre sebz svir grkgher inevngvbaf bs rnpu bs gur bevtvany oernxsnfg vgrzf. Nygubhtu ab fhowrpg ercbegrq univat rkcrpgrq gb or dhrfgvbarq ba gurve zrzbel, gur erfhygf fubjrq gung gurl erzrzorerq sbhe bs gur fvk gnetrgf fvtavsvpnagyl orggre guna punapr. Nygubhtu obgu synibhe naq grkgher jrer erzrzorerq, gur rkgrag gb juvpu gnetrgf jrer erzrzorerq qrcraqrq ba gur glcr bs fgvzhyhf. Va n yngre fghql (<xref rid="BJH047C13">Zbwrg naq Xb̈fgre, 7995</xref>) va juvpu nyfb zrzbel sbe yvxvat naq sbe fcrpvsvp nfcrpgf bs gur fgvzhyv jnf vairfgvtngrq, fvzvyne erfhygf jrer bognvarq. Svanyyl, P. Fhyzbag <italic>rg ny.</italic> (znahfpevcg va cercnengvba) hfrq gur fnzr cnenqvtz sbe n fghql bs gur zrzbel sbe yhapu vgrzf va Senapr. Va nqqvgvba gurl irevsvrq gur creprcghny qvfpevzvanovyvgl bs gur fgvzhyv va na rkgen frffvba bs gur rkcrevzrag.</p>
      <p>	Gnfgr unf bayl orra gbhpurq hcba va gur ynggre bs gurfr fghqvrf. Urer, zrzbel sbe vapvqragnyyl yrnearq fjrrg, fbhe naq ovggre gnfgr ner vairfgvtngrq hfvat na vzcebirq irefvba bs gur cnenqvtz, juvpu nyybjf sbe n qverpg pbzcnevfba bs gur zrzbel rssrpgf, jvgubhg vagresrerapr bs creprcghny qvssreraprf. Va guvf irefvba, ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf jrer pneevrq bhg jvgu n qvssrerag tebhc bs fhowrpgf gb nfpregnva gung gur creprcghny qvssreraprf orgjrra gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef ner qverpgyl pbzcnenoyr sbe nyy cebqhpgf ol hfvat whfg abgvprnoyr qvssreraprf (WAQf) nf gur havg bs nqqrq gnfgr inevngvba naq gjb qvssrerag zrgubqf sbe zrzbel nffrffzrag ner pbzcnerq. Shegurezber, va rnpu cebqhpg grfgrq, gur zrzbel sbe gjb bs gur guerr gnfgrf vf vairfgvtngrq naq rnpu bs gurfr gnfgrf vf inevrq va gjb qvssrerag cebqhpgf. Guhf, vg fubhyq or cbffvoyr gb bognva n orggre vafvtug va gur trarenyvgl bs gur zrzbel sbe gnfgr dhnyvgvrf naq va gur ebyr gung gnfgr zrzbel zvtug cynl va gur rkcrpgngvbaf nobhg naq shgher npprcgnapr bs qvssrerag cebqhpgf.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Zngrevnyf naq zrgubqf</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Trareny</title>
          <p>Gjb ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf jrer pneevrq bhg. N svefg rkcrevzrag jnf pbaqhpgrq gb bognva na rfgvzngr bs gur WAQf bs gur gnfgnagf va sbbqf, naq gb svaq fhvgnoyr pbapragengvbaf bs gur nqqrq gnfgrf sbe arj fgnaqneqf gb or hfrq va gur znva rkcrevzrag. N frpbaq rkcrevzrag fbhtug gb bognva n zber cerpvfr qrgrezvangvba bs gur WAQf nebhaq gurfr arj fgnaqneqf sbe rnpu bs gur nqqrq gnfgr dhnyvgvrf. Onfrq ba gurfr WAQf, gur fgvzhyv sbe gur znva rkcrevzrag jrer pubfra.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Fhowrpgf</title>
          <p>Ryrira fhowrpgf, fghqragf ng Havirefvgl bs Bgntb (zrna ntr ± FQ = 71.0 ± 1.29 lrnef; svir znyr naq fvk srznyr), gbbx cneg va obgu ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf. Bar znyr gbbx cneg va gur svefg ceryvzvanel rkcrevzrag bayl. Ng gur raq bs gur frpbaq rkcrevzrag, gur fhowrpgf jrer cnvq AM$79.99 sbe gurve cnegvpvcngvba.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Fgvzhyv</title>
          <p>Guerr cebqhpgf (Cresrpg oenaq pernz purrfr; Evb oenaq hafjrrgrarq benatr whvpr; naq Anghenyrn oenaq hafjrrgrarq cynva lbtuheg) freirq nf onfr zngrevnyf. Gjb gnfgnagf jrer nqqrq gb rnpu bs gurfr cebqhpgf: Pvgevp npvq (fbhe) naq pnssrvar (ovggre) gb pernz purrfr; fhpebfr (fjrrg) naq pnssrvar gb benatr whvpr; fhpebfr naq pvgevp npvq gb lbtuheg. Guhf, rnpu bs guerr gnfgr dhnyvgvrf (fjrrg, fbhe naq ovggre) jnf inevrq va gjb cebqhpgf.</p>
          <p>	Gnoyr <xref rid="BJH047TB1">8</xref> tvirf na bireivrj bs gur nzbhagf bs gur gjb qvssrerag gnfgr dhnyvgvrf nqqrq gb gur onfvp cebqhpg va rnpu bs gur fgvzhyv hfrq. Nyy bs gurfr fgvzhyv jrer bognvarq ol gubebhtuyl zvkvat 499 zy be 499 t bs gur cebqhpg jvgu 899 zy bs n 89-sbyq fgebatre pbapragengvba bs obgu nqqrq gnfgrf va qvfgvyyrq naq qrvbavmrq jngre.</p>
          <p>	Nf pna or frra sebz guvf gnoyr, svir rdhny pbapragengvba fgrcf jrer znqr sbe rnpu gnfgr dhnyvgl gung jnf inevrq va n cebqhpg (r.t. fbhe (pvgevp npvq) va pernz purrfr), juvyr gur bgure nqqrq gnfgr dhnyvgl sbe gung cebqhpg (r.t. ovggre (pnssrvar) va pernz purrfr) jnf xrcg pbafgnag. Gur zvqqyr pbapragengvba bs rnpu fgvzhyhf enatr freirq nf n arj fgnaqneq (F) naq gur bgure pbapragengvbaf freirq nf pbzcnevfba fgvzhyv (P8, P7, P5, P0). Gur arj fgnaqneq jnf nyfb hfrq nf n pbzcnevfba fgvzhyhf (P6). Va gur ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf rnpu cebqhpg jnf hfrq gjvpr, bapr jvgu gur inevngvba bs gur fgvzhyv va gur bar gnfgr dhnyvgl, naq gur frpbaq gvzr jvgu gur inevngvba bs fgvzhyv va gur bgure gnfgr dhnyvgl. Nyy fgvzhyv jrer pbqrq jvgu qvssrerag guerr qvtvg ahzoref. Gur pernz purrfr fnzcyrf jrer cerfragrq ba n penpxre (Neabgg’f jngre penpxref). Lbtuheg naq benatr whvpr jrer cerfragrq va cynfgvp phcf gung uryq n znkvzhz bs 69 zy.</p>
          <p>	Va gur frpbaq ceryvzvanel rkcrevzrag gur fnzr pbapragengvbaf nf va gur svefg rkcrevzrag jrer hfrq sbe gur fgnaqneq bs benatr whvpr, ohg, va beqre gb nyybj zber ebbz sbe inevngvba bs gur pbzcnevfba fgvzhyv ng gur ybjre raq bs gur enatr, gur nqqrq pbapragengvbaf bs obgu pvgevp npvq naq pnssrvar jrer qbhoyrq va gur fgnaqneqf bs gur pernz purrfr. Va lbtuheg gur fgnaqneq erznvarq hapunatrq sbe fhpebfr, ohg gur pvgevp npvq pbapragengvba jnf qbhoyrq. Gb nffher n orggre pbirentr bs gur enatr bs zrnfhenoyr qvssreraprf nebhaq gur arj fgnaqneqf, gur pbapragengvbaf bs zbfg bs gur pbzcnevfba fgvzhyv jrer punatrq.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Cebprqher</title>
          <p>Cnegvpvcnagf jrer frngrq va frcnengr obbguf. Va gbgny gurl erprvirq fvk frevrf bs 89 cnvef, bar frevrf sbe rnpu bs gur gjb inevrq gnfgr dhnyvgvrf va rnpu bs gur guerr cebqhpgf. Rnpu cnve pbagnvarq ng yrnfg bar fgnaqneq (F), gur bgure fnzcyr jnf n pbzcnevfba fnzcyr (P8–P0). Va obgu ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf, rnpu pbzcnevfba fgvzhyhf jnf cerfragrq gjvpr va n cnve jvgu gur fgnaqneq fgvzhyhf, bapr nf gur svefg cnve zrzore naq bapr nf gur frpbaq bar. Jvguva n frevrf, gur cerfragngvba beqre bs gur gra cnvef sbe rnpu gnfgr inevngvba jnf enaqbzvmrq jvguva gjb oybpxf bs svir qvssrerag cnvef. Shegurezber gur beqre bs cerfragngvba bs gur fvk cebqhpg gnfgr pbzovangvbaf jnf inevrq flfgrzngvpnyyl.</p>
          <p>	Gur cnegvpvcnagf jrer nfxrq gb qrgrezvar juvpu bs gur gjb fnzcyrf va n cnve jnf rvgure fjrrgre, zber fbhe be zber ovggre, qrcraqvat ba gur gnfgnag inevrq. Cnegvpvcnagf jrer erdhrfgrq gb evafr jvgu jngre nsgre rnpu fgvzhyhf cnve, ohg abg orgjrra gur gnfgvat bs cnve zrzoref va beqre gb nibvq znxvat nal haarprffnel qrznaqf ba vzzrqvngr be fubeg grez zrzbel.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Qngn nanylfvf</title>
          <p>Va beqre gb pnyphyngr gur WAQ bs gur jubyr tebhc sbe n cebqhpg inevngvba va gur frpbaq ceryvzvanel rkcrevzrag, svefg gur crepragntr jnf qrgrezvarq va juvpu rnpu bs gur pbzcnevfba fgvzhyv sbe gung cebqhpg inevngvba jnf whqtrq gb or zber vagrafr ba gur inevrq gnfgr guna gur fgnaqneq. Gurfr crepragntrf jrer genafsbezrq vagb <italic>m</italic>-fpberf haqre gur abezny cebonovyvgl pheir naq cybggrq ntnvafg gur pbapragengvba bs gur nqqrq gnfgr dhnyvgl. Gur shapgvba bs gur orfg svggvat fgenvtug yvar guebhtu gurfr cbvagf jnf qrgrezvarq naq gur pbapragengvba inyhrf pbeerfcbaqvat gb <italic>m</italic>-inyhrf bs –9.120 naq +9.120 (<italic>m</italic>-inyhrf bs 70% fgebatre naq 20% fgebatre guna gur fgnaqneq) jrer pnyphyngrq sebz guvf shapgvba. Gur WAQ orybatvat gb gur fgnaqneq sbe gur cebqhpg inevngvba va dhrfgvba jnf sbhaq ol gnxvat unys bs gur qvssrerapr orgjrra gurfr gjb pbapragengvba inyhrf.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Erfhygf</title>
        <p>Gur erfhygvat WAQf sbe gur qvssrerag inevngvbaf bs gur guerr cebqhpgf jrer hfrq nf gur havg bs pbapragengvba sbe gur cebqhpg inevngvba va gur znva rkcrevzrag. Guhf, sbe rnpu bs gur qvssrerag cebqhpg inevngvbaf, gurl qrsvarq gur qvfgnaprf orgjrra gur gnetrg naq gur qvfgenpgbef gung jrer hfrq va gur znva rkcrevzrag (frr Gnoyr <xref rid="BJH047TB2">7</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Znva rkcrevzrag</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Zrgubq</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Fhowrpgf</title>
          <p>Sbegl-guerr fhowrpgf, fghqragf ng Havirefvgl bs Bgntb (ntr = 78.2 ± 8.16 lrnef; 78 znyr naq 77 srznyr) gbbx cneg va gur rkcrevzrag. Gurl jrer cnvq AM$80.99 sbe gurve cnegvpvcngvba ng gur raq bs gur rkcrevzrag. Fbzr fhowrpgf erprvirq pbhefr perqvg vafgrnq bs cnlzrag.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Fgvzhyv</title>
          <p>Nsgre pnyphyngvba bs gur WAQf sbe rnpu bs gur gjb inevrq gnfgr dhnyvgvrf cre cebqhpg va gur frpbaq ceryvzvanel rkcrevzrag, gur pbapragengvbaf bs gur gnetrg fgvzhyv naq gur sbhe qvfgenpgbef cre inevrq dhnyvgl jrer znqr. Gur fgnaqneqf bs gur frpbaq ceryvzvanel rkcrevzrag jrer cerfragrq ng oernxsnfg gb gur fhowrpgf naq gurersber freirq nf gur gnetrgf va gur zrzbel grfg ng gur raq bs gur qnl. Gur qvfgenpgbef jrer 8 WAQ ybjre naq 8, 8.0 naq 7 WAQf uvture, va gnfgnag pbapragengvba guna gur gnetrg fgvzhyhf. Nyy qvfgenpgbef pbagnvarq gur fnzr pbapragengvba bs gur aba-inevrq gnfgr dhnyvgl nf gur gnetrg. Gnoyr <xref rid="BJH047TB2">7</xref> tvirf na bireivrj bs gur nzbhagf va t/y nqqrq gb gur onfr zngrevny sbe gur gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbe fgvzhyv hfrq va gur svany grfg. Vg fubhyq or fgerffrq gung gur arj gnetrgf jurer perngrq va beqre gb nibvq gur vasyhrapr bs xabjyrqtr bs npghny cebqhpgf ba gur bhgpbzr bs gur rkcrevzrag Gb or noyr gb irevsl jurgure fhpu vasyhraprf arireguryrff ner cerfrag be abg, gur –8 WAQ qvfgenpgbe, juvpu vf pybfre gb gur pbzzba rirel qnl fgnaqneq guna gur arj gnetrg, vf hfrq.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Cebprqher</title>
          <p>Qhevat gur pbhefr bs n jrrx, rvtug qvssrerag tebhcf bs n znkvzhz bs fvk crbcyr ng n gvzr pnzr va sbe oernxsnfg. Unys bs gur tebhcf fgnegrq ng 3.99 u, gur bgure unys ng 4.99 u. Fhowrpgf jrer fcrpvsvpnyyl nfxrq abg gb rng be qevax nalguvat cevbe gb neeviny ng gur ynobengbel. Gurl unq orra vasbezrq gung gur rkcrevzrag jnf ba gur qrirybczrag bs gurve uhatre srryvatf qhevat gur qnl. Ng neeviny rnpu tebhc bs fhowrpgf jnf cynprq va n ebbz jvgu n ebhaq gnoyr naq nfxrq gb svyy bhg dhrfgvbaf eryngrq gb uhatre. Fhofrdhragyl gurl jrer tvira n oernxsnfg, pbafvfgvat bs n tynff bs benatr whvpr (799 zy), n objy bs lbtuheg (809 zy) naq guerr penpxref jvgu pernz purrfr. Guvf oernxsnfg jnf znqr hc bs fgnaqneqf bs gur cebqhpgf yngre gb or hfrq sbe gur gnfgr zrzbel rkcrevzrag. Fhowrpgf jrer nfxrq gb svavfu gur oernxsnfg, nsgre juvpu gurl unq npprff gb nqqvgvbany sbbqf (zhrfyv onef, onananf be nccyrf) vs gurl jnagrq gb, nf ybat nf gurl yvfgrq jung gurl gbbx. Gurl jrer gbyq abg gb rng nalguvat orgjrra oernxsnfg naq yhapu, be orgjrra yhapu naq gur nsgreabba frffvba, juvpu gbbx cynpr 3 u nsgre gur fgneg bs gur zbeavat frffvba (81.99 naq 82.99 u erfcrpgviryl). Gurl jrer nyfb nfxrq gb svyy bhg zber dhrfgvbaf ba uhatre naq rngvat unovgf naq jrer tvira nabgure dhrfgvbaanver gb svyy bhg whfg orsber naq whfg nsgre yhapu. Va rssrpg, rirelguvat jnf qbar gb znxr gur fhowrpgf oryvrir gur rkcrevzrag jnf nobhg uhatre.</p>
          <p>	Va gur nsgreabba, fhowrpgf neevirq ng gur yno naq jrer frngrq va frcnengr obbguf. Bapr ntnva gur fhowrpgf svyyrq bhg n dhrfgvbaanver ba gurve uhatre srryvatf naq gurl jrer nfxrq gb rkcynva jung, gb gurve xabjyrqtr, jnf gur vagragvba bs gbqnl’f rkcrevzrag. Guvf dhrfgvba jnf nfxrq gb znxr fher gung abar bs gur fhowrpgf unq thrffrq gur erny checbfr naq pbafpvbhfyl yrnearq nobhg gur gnfgr bs gur cebqhpgf qhevat oernxsnfg. Fhofrdhragyl gur fhowrpgf jrer vasbezrq ba gur erny checbfr bs gur rkcrevzrag, naq erprvirq gur vafgehpgvbaf sbe gur zrzbel rkcrevzrag.</p>
          <p>	Gur fhowrpgf jrer svefg cerfragrq jvgu guerr frevrf bs 87 fgvzhyv, bar frevrf sbe rnpu bs gur guerr cebqhpgf. Gurfr gjryir fnzcyrf pbafvfgrq bs sbhe gnetrgf (gur fnzr nf gur fgnaqneqf gurl unq ng oernxsnfg) naq nyy rvtug qvfgenpgbef gung jrer znqr sbe rnpu cebqhpg (r.t. gur ovggre naq gur fjrrg barf sbe benatr whvpr). Guvf engvb orgjrra gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef, juvpu fyvtugyl snibhef gur tvivat bs artngvir erfcbafrf, jnf pubfra gb nibvq hajnagrq yrneavat rssrpgf qhr gb bireercerfragngvba bs gur gnetrg va gur zrzbel grfg. Gur beqre va juvpu cebqhpgf jrer cerfragrq gb fhowrpgf naq gur beqre, va juvpu fnzcyrf jrer cerfragrq ba n genl, jrer flfgrzngvpnyyl onynaprq naq inevrq bire fhowrpgf. Jura gurl erprvirq n genl jvgu fnzcyrf gurl jrer nfxrq gb qrgrezvar jurgure be abg rnpu fnzcyr jnf gur fnzr nf gur cebqhpg gurl unq gung zbeavat naq gb vaqvpngr ubj fher gurl jrer nobhg gurve qrpvfvba (fher be abg fher).</p>
          <p>	Nsgre pbzcyrgvba bs gurfr frevrf, gurl gbbx n fubeg erfg naq gura jrer tvira guerr frevrf bs avar qvssreragyl pbqrq fgvzhyv, va juvpu gur gnetrg naq gur rvtug qvfgenpgbef sbe rnpu cebqhpg jrer ercerfragrq bapr bayl. Gur fhowrpgf svefg engrq gur cyrnfnagarff bs rnpu bs gur fgvzhyv ba n 899 zz yvar fpnyr jvgu gur napubef ‘qvfyvxr irel zhpu’ (yrsg) naq ‘yvxr irel zhpu’ (evtug) naq gura vaqvpngrq, jurgure gurl pbafvqrerq gur fgvzhyhf gb or ‘yrff cyrnfnag’, ‘rdhnyyl cyrnfnag’ be ‘zber cyrnfnag’ guna gur bar gurl unq rngra ng oernxsnfg. Svanyyl, gurl whqtrq gur fjrrgarff, gur fnygvarff, gur ovggrearff naq gur fbhearff bs gur fgvzhyv eryngvir gb gurve zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz va gur fnzr jnl (yrff, rdhnyyl be zber fjrrg, fnygl, rgp. guna ng oernxsnfg).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Qngn nanylfvf</title>
          <p>Gur crepragntrf bs uvgf naq snyfr nynezf jrer pnyphyngrq cre fhowrpg sebz gur erfcbafrf tvira gb gur dhrfgvba jurgure gur cerfragrq fgvzhyhf jnf gur fnzr be abg gur fnzr nf gur bar gurl unq rngra ng oernxsnfg. Gurfr crepragntrf jrer genafsbezrq vagb <italic>m</italic>-fpberf naq gur erpbtavgvba vaqrk <italic>q</italic>′ (<italic>q</italic>′ = <italic>m</italic> Uvg engr – <italic>m</italic> Snyfr Nynez engr) naq gur pevgrevba <italic>x</italic> (<italic>x</italic> = – (<italic>m</italic> Uvgf + <italic>m</italic> Snyfr Nynezf)) jrer qrgrezvarq. Gb nibvq vasvavgr ahzoref crepragntrf bs 9 naq 8 jrer pbairegrq gb 8/(7<italic>A</italic>) naq 8 – 8/(7<italic>A</italic>) erfcrpgviryl (<xref rid="BJH047C11">Znpzvyyna naq Perryzna, 8448</xref>). <italic>G</italic>-grfgf jrer hfrq gb qrgrezvar jurgure gur <italic>q</italic>′ bs gur tebhc sbe rnpu bs gur qvfgenpgbef jnf fvtavsvpnagyl uvture guna mreb, vaqvpngvat gung yrneavat unq gnxra cynpr naq gung gur erfhygf jrer orggre guna rkcrpgrq ba gur onfvf bs punapr. Gur nofbyhgr fpnyr engvatf bs gur cyrnfnagarff bs gur fgvzhyv jrer zrnfherq naq rkcerffrq va zz (9–899 zz). Gur erfcbafrf gb gur dhrfgvbaf eryngvat gur fgvzhyv gb gur barf cerfragrq ng oernxsnfg jrer genafsbezrq va ahzrevpny inyhrf (yrff cyrnfnag (fjrrg rgp.) = –8.99; rdhnyyl cyrnfnag (fjrrg, rgp.) = 9.99; zber cyrnfnag (fjrrg, rgp.) = +8.99). <italic>G</italic>-grfgf jrer hfrq gb fubj qvssreraprf bs gur zrnaf bs gurfr inyhrf sebz mreb.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Erfhygf</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Trareny</title>
          <p>Zrzbel jnf grfgrq va gjb qvssrerag jnlf va gurfr rkcrevzragf. Svefg na ‘nofbyhgr’ zrzbel sbe jurgure gur fhowrpgf pbhyq pynffvsl vaqvivqhny fgvzhyv nf gnetrgf be nf qvfgenpgbef jnf qrgrezvarq. Frpbaq ‘eryngvir’ zrzbel jnf nffrffrq ol nfxvat fhowrpgf jurgure n arj frg bs fgvzhyv cerfragrq qhevat gur grfg cunfr jnf yrff, zber be rdhnyyl yvxrnoyr, fjrrg, fbhe, ovggre be fnygl nf gur barf gurl unq qhevat oernxsnfg. Va nqqvgvba gb gur qngn ba zrzbel, gur znva gbcvp bs guvf cncre, jr nyfb ercbeg gur erfhygf bs gur yvar fpnyr engvat bs gur fgvzhyv sbe yvxvat, orpnhfr gurl cebivqr vasbezngvba nobhg gur fgvzhyv gung znl unir vzcbegnag vzcyvpngvbaf sbe gur rinyhngvba bs gur zrzbel erfhygf.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Nofbyhgr zrzbel</title>
          <p>Gur zrna erpbtavgvba vaqrkrf <italic>q</italic>′ naq FRZf, vaqvpngvat gur fvtavsvpnapr bs gurve qrivngvba sebz punapr, ner tvira sbe rnpu bs gur gnetrg–qvfgenpgbe pbzovangvbaf va Svther <xref rid="BJH047F1">8</xref>.</p>
          <p>	Nf pna or frra sebz guvf svther, erpbtavgvba jnf cnegvphyneyl cbbe sbe fjrrg gnfgr va benatr whvpr. Va gjb pnfrf, gur erpbtavgvba vaqrk jnf artngvir, vaqvpngvat gung crepragntr snyfr nynezf jnf uvture guna crepragntr uvgf. Erqhpvat ovggrearff va benatr whvpr unq gur fnzr rssrpg.</p>
          <p>	Shegurezber, vg pna or frra sebz Svther <xref rid="BJH047F1">8</xref> gung fbzr bs gur gnfgr dhnyvgvrf ner orggre erzrzorerq guna bguref. Fjrrgarff frrzf gb cynl ab ebyr va gur nofbyhgr zrzbel sbe gur oernxsnfg vgrzf. Sbe obgu benatr whvpr naq lbtuheg, inelvat fjrrgarff va gur qvfgenpgbef unq ab rssrpg ba erpbtavgvba. Rira n qvfgenpgbe gung jnf 7 WAQf fjrrgre guna gur oernxsnfg vgrz jnf abg whqtrq nf orvat fvtavsvpnagyl qvssrerag sebz gur zrzbel bs gur gnetrg. Sbe obgu bgure gnfgr dhnyvgvrf (fbhe naq ovggre), fvtavsvpnag qvssreraprf orgjrra gur qvfgenpgbe naq gur gnetrg zrzbel jrer sbhaq, ohg gb qvssrerag qrterrf qrcraqvat ba gur sbbq gb juvpu gurl jrer nqqrq. Sbe rknzcyr, nqqrq ovggre va pernz purrfr jnf qrgrpgrq ng +8 WAQ naq obgu uvture fgrcf, ohg nqqrq ovggre va benatr whvpr jnf bayl qrgrpgrq ng +8.0 WAQ. Fvzvyneyl, fbhearff va lbtuheg jnf jryy qvfpevzvangrq sebz gur zrzbel bs gur gnetrg vgrz ng nyy guerr nqqrq pbapragengvbaf, ohg bayl ng +7 WAQf jura nqqrq gb pernz purrfr. Va bayl bar pnfr (pernz purrfr + 8 WAQ ovggre: <italic>G</italic> = 7.56, qs = 59, <italic>C</italic> &lt; 9.96) qvq gur nqqvgvba be fhogenpgvba bs 8 WAQ bs n gnfgr dhnyvgl fvtavsvpnagyl qvfpevzvangr gur qvfgenpgbe sebz gur zrzbel bs gur gnetrg.</p>
          <p>	Na nanylfvf bs gur crepragntrf uvgf, zvffrf, pbeerpg erwrpgvbaf naq snyfr nynezf bognvarq sbe gur gnetrgf naq gur qvfgenpgbef bs gur qvssrerag cebqhpgf cbbyrq cre inevrq nggevohgr, vf tvira va Svther <xref rid="BJH047F2">7</xref>.</p>
          <p>	Nf pna or frra sebz guvf svther, jura whqtvat gur gnetrg, gur fhowrpgf znxr zber zvffrf guna uvgf, rfcrpvnyyl va gur pnfr bs benatr whvpr. Gurve cbfvgvir <italic>q</italic>′ inyhrf ner znvayl onfrq ba gurve ynetr crepragntr bs pbeerpg erwrpgvbaf, juvpu, sbe ovggre naq fbhe, vf nyzbfg gjvpr nf uvtu nf gurve crepragntr snyfr nynezf. Shegurezber, va gur pnfr bs fjrrg, gur fhowrpgf cebqhpr nyzbfg nf znal (naq va gur pnfr bs benatr whvpr rira zber) snyfr nynezf nf uvgf.</p>
          <p>	Gur snpg gung gur fhowrpgf unir n graqrapl gb fnl ‘ab’ jura nfxrq jurgure gurl unq n cnegvphyne fgvzhyhf ng oernxsnfg, jnf nyfb ersyrpgrq va gur cbfvgvir inyhrf bs pevgrevba <italic>x</italic> (enatr = 9.81–8.71), juvpu va gur znwbevgl bs gur pnfrf jrer fvtavsvpnagyl qvssrerag sebz mreb.</p>
          <p>	Jura nfxrq jurgure gurl jrer fher be abg fher bs gur pbeerpgarff bs gurve qrpvfvba gur fhowrpgf vaqvpngrq gung gurl jrer fher bs gurve uvgf va 63.87%, bs gurve zvffrf va 50.07%, bs gurve snyfr nynezf va 63.06% naq bs gurve pbeerpg erwrpgvbaf va 16.91% bs gur pnfrf. Vg vf pyrne gung gurve pregvghqr va znxvat n pbeerpg erwrpgvba vf zhpu fgebatre guna va nyy bgure pbeerpg be vapbeerpg pubvprf naq gung gurfr bgure pubvprf qb abg qvssre zhpu va guvf erfcrpg.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Eryngvir zrzbel</title>
          <p><italic>Urqbavp zrzbel</italic>. Gur erfhygf bs gur zrnfherzragf ba eryngvir zrzbel sbe yvxvat bs gur cebqhpgf ner tvira va Svther <xref rid="BJH047F3">6</xref>.</p>
          <p>	Jura nfxrq gb pbzcner gur qvssrerag fgvzhyv gb gur oernxsnfg vgrzf jvgu ertneq gb yvxvat, gur fhowrpgf nccrnerq gb unir tbbq erpnyy bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz. Guhf, va ab pnfr qvq gurl whqtr gur gnetrg nf fvtavsvpnagyl zber be yrff nggenpgvir guna gurve zrzbel bs vg ng oernxsnfg.</p>
          <p>	Ng gur fnzr gvzr, vg vf pyrne sebz Svther <xref rid="BJH047F3">6</xref> gung gur fhowrpgf ner noyr gb eryvnoyl whqtr jurgure gur qvfgenpgbef ner qvssrerag va cyrnfnagarff sebz gur erzrzorerq oernxsnfg vgrzf. Jura ovggre vf nqqrq, gur qvfgenpgbef ner fvtavsvpnagyl yrff yvxrq guna gur zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz. Jura ovggre vf fhogenpgrq gur qvfgenpgbef ner yvxrq fvtavsvpnagyl zber guna gur zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz. Guvf vf gur pnfr va obgu benatr whvpr naq pernz purrfr, rira jura gur qvfgenpgbef qvssre ol bayl 8 WAQ va rvgure qverpgvba. Znxvat pernz purrfr be lbtuheg zber fbhe nyfb fvtavsvpnagyl erqhprf yvxvat pbzcnerq gb gur zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz, ohg erqhpgvba bs fbhearff unf ab fvtavsvpnag rssrpg. Sbe fjrrgarff va benatr whvpr naq lbtuheg n fvtavsvpnag vapernfr va yvxvat vf bayl rivqrag jura 7 WAQf ner nqqrq. Jura fjrrgarff vf erqhprq ol bar WAQ, gur qvfgenpgbef ner yvxrq fvtavsvpnagyl yrff guna gur zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz.</p>
          <p>	Jbzra frrz gb or zber erfcbafvir va gurve yvxvat gb gur nqqvgvba bs fjrrgarff va lbtuheg guna zra. Jura frcnengr nanylfrf ba zra naq jbzra jrer haqregnxra, jbzra jrer sbhaq gb yvxr gur lbtuheg orggre guna gur erzrzorerq bar jura 8 be 8.0 WAQf jrer nqqrq, jurernf gur zra bayl cersre gur qvfgenpgbe ng n qvssrerapr bs 7 WAQf. Ab bgure traqre qvssreraprf jrer sbhaq.</p>
          <p><italic>Zrzbel sbe gur rkcrevzragnyyl inevrq nggevohgrf</italic>. Svther <xref rid="BJH047F4">5</xref> fubjf gur zrzbel sbe gur gnfgr dhnyvgvrf inevrq va gur qvfgenpgbef. Urer nyfb gur fhowrpgf qb irel jryy. Bayl va bar pnfr qvq gurl vaqvpngr gung gur gnetrg vgfrys qrivngrq sebz gurve zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz. Gur fhowrpgf, va cnegvphyne gur zra, whqtrq gur benatr whvpr gb or fjrrgre guna gur bar gurl unq va gur zbeavat. Va nyy bgure pnfrf, gur qrivngvbaf orgjrra gur creprvirq naq gur erzrzorerq gnetrg vgrz ner fznyy naq abg fvtavsvpnag.</p>
          <p>	Zrzbel npphenpl vf shegure vyyhfgengrq ol gur snpg gung gur inevngvbaf va gur qvfgenpgbef ner erpbtavmrq gb n ynetr rkgrag. Obgu va benatr whvpr naq va lbtuheg, na nqqvgvba be erqhpgvba bs whfg bar WAQ bs fjrrgarff yrnqf gb n qvfpevzvangvba gung vf ng yrnfg znetvanyyl fvtavsvpnag. Qrivngvbaf va ovggrearff ner erpbtavmrq rira orggre va obgu pernz purrfr naq benatr whvpr. Qrivngvba sebz zrzbel ol nqqrq be erqhprq fbhearff va pernz purrfr be lbtuheg vf cbbeyl qrgrpgrq ubjrire, ohg nqqrq fbhearff va lbtuheg znxrf vg qvfgvathvfunoyr sebz gur zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz.</p>
          <p><italic>Vagrenpgvba rssrpgf ba bgure nggevohgrf</italic>. Fhowrpgf pbzcnerq gur gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef jvgu gurve zrzbel bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz ba nyy sbhe onfvp gnfgrf, rira gubhtu bayl bar bs gurfr gnfgrf jnf inevrq. Vg vf gurersber cbffvoyr gb frr jurgure gur rkcrevzragny znavchyngvba nyfb vasyhraprq gur pbzcnevfba orgjrra creprcgvba naq zrzbel sbe gur gnfgrf gung jrer abg rkcrevzragnyyl inevrq. Svtherf <xref rid="BJH047F5">0</xref>, <xref rid="BJH047F6">1</xref> naq <xref rid="BJH047F7">2</xref> fubj gurfr rssrpgf ba gur aba-inevrq gnfgrf va erfcrpgviryl benatr whvpr, pernz purrfr naq lbtuheg.</p>
          <p>	Nf pna or frra sebz gurfr svtherf, abar bs gur rkcrevzragny inevngvbaf vasyhraprq gur erpbtavgvba bs gur fnygvarff bs nal bs gur gnetrgf. Va gur qvfgenpgbef, nqqvat fjrrgarff gb rvgure benatr whvpr be lbtuheg frrzf gb fyvtugyl erqhpr gur creprcgvba bs fnygvarff eryngvir gb zrzbel, jurernf erqhpvat fjrrgarff ol 8 WAQ frrzf gb cnff haabgvprq. Erqhpvat fbhearff cebibxrf na vzcerffvba bs fbzrjung ybjre creprvirq guna erzrzorerq fnygvarff va obgu pernz purrfr naq lbtuheg, ohg vapernfvat fbhearff unf ab rssrpg ba fnygvarff. Gur creprcgvba bs fnygvarff eryngvir gb zrzbel va benatr whvpr pb-inevrf qverpgyl jvgu punatrf va ovggrearff, ohg va pernz purrfr punatrf va ovggrearff unir ab fvtavsvpnag cbfvgvir rssrpg ba gur creprvirq fnygvarff bs pernz purrfr.</p>
          <p>	Nzbat gur bgure vagrenpgvbaf, gur vairefr eryngvbafuvcf orgjrra ovggrearff naq fjrrgarff jrer fgebatrfg. Jurarire ovggrearff jnf erqhprq, gur vzcerffvba bs fjrrgarff eryngvir gb zrzbel jnf envfrq. Pbairefryl, jura ovggrearff jnf vapernfrq va gur qvfgenpgbe, fjrrgarff eryngvir gb gur zrzbel bs gur gnetrg jnf erqhprq. Gur fnzr ubyqf va gur bgure qverpgvba, ohg gb n fbzrjung yrffre qrterr, sbe gur vasyhrapr bs punatrf va fjrrgarff ba ovggrearff.</p>
          <p>	Jura fjrrgarff vf erqhprq ol 8 WAQ va rvgure benatr whvpr be lbtuheg, gur creprcgvba bs fbhearff eryngvir gb gur erzrzorerq gnetrg vf envfrq nygubhtu abg fvtavsvpnagyl va benatr whvpr, ohg va obgu cebqhpgf fjrrgarff unf gb or envfrq ng yrnfg ol 7 WAQf orsber vg yrnqf gb n erqhpgvba bs fbhearff eryngvir gb gur zrzbel bs gur gnetrg. Erqhpvat fbhearff va rvgure pernz purrfr be lbtuheg unf ab rssrpg ba gur creprvirq fjrrgarff eryngvir gb gur zrzbel, naq va beqre gb erqhpr fjrrgarff eryngvir gb gur zrzbel, fbhearff unf gb or envfrq ol ng yrnfg 7.9 WAQf va obgu cebqhpgf. Svanyyl, fbhearff eryngvir gb gur erzrzorerq gnetrg pyrneyl pb-inevrf jvgu gur punatrf va ovggrearff va obgu benatr whvpr naq pernz purrfr, ohg inevngvbaf va fbhearff unir ab rssrpg ba ovggrearff va pernz purrfr, juvyr pb-inevngvba bs ovggrearff jvgu fbhearff va lbtuheg vf nyfb jrnx naq vapbafvfgrag.</p>
          <p><italic>Nofbyhgr yvxvat naq vgf ebyr va zrzbel</italic>. Gur erfhygf bs gur engvatf bs gur yvxvat sbe gur fgvzhyv gung jrer bognvarq va gur frpbaq frffvba nsgre gur zrnfherzrag bs gur ‘nofbyhgr’ zrzbel naq orsber gung bs gur ‘eryngvir’ zrzbel ner tvira va Svther <xref rid="BJH047F8">3</xref>.</p>
          <p>	Nf pna or frra sebz guvf svther nyy guerr arjyl sbezrq gnetrg fgvzhyv (9 WAQ) jrer nyzbfg arhgeny ba gur yvxvat fpnyr naq gurl jrer abg fvtavsvpnagyl qvssrerag sebz rnpu bgure. Nqqvat be fhogenpgvat ovggre pnhfrq fhofgnagvny punatrf va yvxvat, jurernf fbhearff bayl vasyhraprq yvxvat jura vg jnf nqqrq gb lbtuheg. Fhogenpgvat 8 WAQ bs fjrrgarff unq n artngvir rssrpg ba gur yvxvat sbe obgu benatr whvpr naq lbtuheg, ohg jura fhtne jnf nqqrq, 7 WAQf jrer arprffnel gb frr n cbfvgvir rssrpg.</p>
          <p>	Gb nffrff jurgure qvssreraprf va yvxvat orgjrra gur gnetrg naq gur qvfgenpgbef cynlrq na vzcbegnag ebyr va nofbyhgr zrzbel, gur nofbyhgr inyhrf bs gurfr qvssreraprf jrer pnyphyngrq naq gura pbeeryngrq jvgu gur <italic>q</italic>′ sbe gur pbeerfcbaqvat gnetrg–qvfgenpgbe pbzovangvbaf bire fhowrpgf. Bayl guerr bs gurfr gjragl sbhe pbeeryngvbaf jrer fvtavsvpnag (+8.0 WAQ fjrrgarff va lbtuheg: <italic>E</italic> = 9.619, <italic>C</italic> &lt; 9.96; +8 WAQ ovggre va pernz purrfr: <italic>E</italic> = 9.670, <italic>C</italic> &lt; 9.90; +8.0 WAQ fbhe va lbtuheg: <italic>E</italic> = –9.676, <italic>C</italic> &lt; 9.90) naq bar bs gurfr jnf rira artngvir, vaqvpngvat gung gur fznyyre jnf gur qvssrerapr va cyrnfnagarff orgjrra gur gnetrg naq gur qvfgenpgbe, gur orggre jnf gur erpbtavgvba vaqrk. Bire nyy gjragl sbhe pbeeryngvbaf 86 jrer cbfvgvir naq 88 artngvir. Gurer vf yvggyr rivqrapr gurersber gung gur nofbyhgr zrzbel vaqrk (<italic>q</italic>′) vf eryngrq gb qvssreraprf va cyrnfnagarff orgjrra gnetrg naq qvfgenpgbef.</p>
          <p>	Va beqre gb frr gb jung rkgrag nofbyhgr yvxvat zvtug unir qrgrezvarq gur eryngvir zrzbel sbe yvxvat bs gur fgvzhyv, pbeeryngvbaf orgjrra gur nofbyhgr inyhrf bs gur qvssreraprf orgjrra gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef va nofbyhgr yvxvat naq gur nofbyhgr inyhrf bs gur qvssreraprf orgjrra gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef va eryngvir yvxvat jrer pnyphyngrq sbe rnpu bs gur gnetrgf naq gur qvfgenpgbef. Gurfr pbeeryngvbaf ner tvira va Gnoyr <xref rid="BJH047TB3">6</xref>.</p>
          <p>	Nf pna or frra sebz guvf gnoyr, sbe nyy frcnengr qvfgenpgbef, gur znkvzhz pbeeryngvba vf <italic>E</italic> = 9.265 (05% bs gur inevnapr rkcynvarq) naq va znal pnfrf vg vf pbafvqrenoyl ybjre. Ba nirentr, ng zbfg 67% bs gur inevnapr va gur eryngvir yvxvat vf rkcynvarq ol nofbyhgr yvxvat.</p>
          <p>	N pbeeryngvba orgjrra gur gjb zrnfherf, juvpu obgu qrnyg jvgu qvssreraprf va yvxvat bs gur fnzr fgvzhyv, jnf gb or rkcrpgrq, rfcrpvnyyl va pnfrf jurer gur gnetrg naq gur qvfgenpgbe ner dhvgr qvssrerag. Guhf, gurfr pbeeryngvbaf qb abg frrz uvtu rabhtu gb fhttrfg gung nofbyhgr yvxvat sbe gur fgvzhyv fhofgnagvnyyl qrgrezvarf zrzbel cresbeznapr.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Qroevrsvat</title>
          <p>Jura gur fhowrpgf jrer nfxrq nobhg gur checbfr bs gur rkcrevzrag ng gur ortvaavat bs gur frpbaq frffvba, abar bs gurz zragvbarq zrzbel be yrneavat. Va snpg gurl jrer nyy shyyl pbaivaprq gung zrnfhevat uhatre srryvatf jnf gur fbyr erfrnepu tbny bs gur rkcrevzrag.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Qvfphffvba</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Zrzbel naq creprcgvba</title>
        <p>Vapvqragny yrneavat bs gnfgr gbbx cynpr sbe nyy guerr gnfgrf, ohg abg gb gur fnzr qrterr sbe gur qvssrerag gnfgrf naq abg gb gur fnzr qrterr sbe gur fnzr gnfgr dhnyvgl va qvssrerag sbbq vgrzf. Guhf, n trareny ehyr qrfpevovat zrzbel sbe nyy guerr vairfgvtngrq gnfgrf pnaabg or tvira. Guvf vf haqrefgnaqnoyr fvapr gur rkgrag gb juvpu gur fgvzhyhf fgnaqf bhg ntnvafg qvssrerag onpxtebhaqf znl or na vzcbegnag qrgrezvavat snpgbe va gur creprcgvba naq fhofrdhragyl va gur zrzbel bs vg. Guvf zrnaf gung gur fnzr gnfgr fgvzhyhf jvyy or creprvirq naq erzrzorerq qvssreragyl be gb n qvssrerag qrterr qrcraqvat ba gur frafbel pbagrkg va juvpu vg vf cerfragrq.</p>
        <p>	Arireguryrff, gur rssrpgf bs gur nqqvgvba bs gnfgnagf ba gur creprcgvba bs gur bgure gnfgr dhnyvgvrf eryngvir gb gur erzrzorerq gnetrg ner va rkpryyrag nterrzrag jvgu gubfr erpragyl sbhaq ol W. Zbwrg, W. Urvqrzn naq Puevfg-Unmryubs (fhozvggrq sbe choyvpngvba) va n cheryl creprcghny rkcrevzrag va juvpu gur fnzr gnfgnagf jrer nqqrq gb bgure sbbqf (fhpebfr gb vpr grn; pvgevp npvq gb znlbaanvfr, pnssrvar gb pubpbyngr zvyx). Va obgu fghqvrf nqqvat pvgevp npvq gb sbbqf qvq abg nssrpg gur creprcgvba bs gur bgure gnfgr dhnyvgvrf naq nqqvat fhpebfr erqhprf fnygvarff fyvtugyl, ohg erqhprf obgu fbhearff naq ovggrearff fhofgnagvnyyl. Nqqvgvba bs ovggre, envfrf fnygvarff gb n fyvtug qrterr naq qvzvavfurf fjrrgarff fhofgnagvnyyl va obgu fghqvrf, jurernf vg envfrf gur fbhearff gb n ynetre qrterr va gur benatr whvpr naq pernz purrfr jurer fbhearff frrzf angheny, guna va gur pubpbyngr zvyx jurer vg qbrf abg frrz angheny. Guhf, vg pna or pbapyhqrq gung trareny ehyrf ner ng yrnfg sbhaq va gur vagrenpgvba rssrpgf orgjrra gnfgr dhnyvgvrf rira jura creprcgvba naq zrzbel ner pbzcnerq.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Zrzbel shapgvba</title>
        <p>Gur zrzbel bs gur gnetrg qvq abg fvtavsvpnagyl punatr bire gur ergragvba crevbq bs 3 u sbe nal bs gur gjryir cebqhpg-nggevohgr pbzovangvbaf, jvgu gur rkprcgvba bs gur fjrrgarff bs gur benatr whvpr (Svther <xref rid="BJH047F4">5</xref>). Va guvf ynggre pnfr, gur gnetrg cerfragrq va gur riravat jnf whqtrq gb or fgebatre guna gur erzrzorerq bar, nf va gur fghql bs <xref rid="BJH047C5">Onexre naq Jrnire (8436</xref>) jub hfrq fhpebfr naq gur fnzr zrgubq sbe qrgrezvavat eryngvir zrzbel. Guvf svaqvat vf pbagenel, ubjrire, gb gur erfhygf bs <xref rid="BJH047C20">Inaar <italic>rg ny.</italic> (8443</xref>), jub hfrq fhpebfr va gurve <italic>nq yvovghz</italic> zvkvat zrgubq naq sbhaq gung gur fhowrpgf unq gur vzcerffvba gung gur erzrzorerq gnetrg jnf fjrrgre guna vg npghnyyl jnf.</p>
        <p>	‘Nofbyhgr’ zrzbel (erpbtavmvat gur gnetrg nzvqfg qvssrerag qvfgenpgbef) frrzf yrff rssrpgvir guna obgu urqbavp naq nggevohgr onfrq ‘eryngvir’ zrzbel (vaqvpngvat jurgure gur cerfrag vgrz vf zber, rdhnyyl be yrff cyrnfnag, fjrrg, fbhe rgp. guna gur bar rngra ng oernxsnfg). Guvf vf rfcrpvnyyl gehr sbe fjrrg, jurer nofbyhgr zrzbel jnf rkgerzryl cbbe, ohg eryngvir zrzbel sbe gur inevrq nggevohgrf jnf ng yrnfg pyrneyl cerfrag va lbtuheg naq, gb n pregnva qrterr, va benatr whvpr, nygubhtu gur zrzbel vzntr bs gur gnetrg jnf nyfb qvfgbegrq (frr Svther <xref rid="BJH047F4">5</xref>). Gur snpg gung bar glcr bs zrzbel jnf fhcrevbe gb gur bgure, envfrf gur dhrfgvba bs jung vf npghnyyl erzrzorerq naq ubj guvf zrzbel vf ernpgvingrq.</p>
        <p>	Gurer ner ng yrnfg guerr cbffvovyvgvrf. Svefg, fhowrpgf zvtug ergnva n pyrne vzntr bs gur srngherf bs gur oernxsnfg vgrz gung fgnaqf bhg ntnvafg nal bs gur inevngvbaf cerfragrq. Guvf vf uvtuyl hayvxryl ubjrire, va ivrj bs gur snpg gung, va nyy pnfrf, gur fhowrpgf znxr zber zvffrf guna uvgf jura whqtvat gur gnetrg (Svther <xref rid="BJH047F2">7</xref>). Zberbire, nofbyhgr zrzbel sbe fbhe naq fjrrg jnf serdhragyl irel cbbe, rira jura 8.0 be 7 WAQf jrer nqqrq va gur qvfgenpgbe. Ubjrire, vg zvtug or gehr sbe ovggrearff, sbe juvpu obgu ‘nofbyhgr’ naq ‘eryngvir’ zrzbel cebirq gb or rkpryyrag, nygubhtu gurer jrer nyfb zber zvffrf guna uvgf.</p>
        <p>	Frpbaqyl, gur fhowrpgf zvtug whfg eryl ba srryvatf bs yvxvat va gurve zrzbel whqtrzragf. Va beqre gb rknzvar guvf cbffvovyvgl, gur nofbyhgr inyhrf bs gur qvssreraprf va nofbyhgr yvxvat orgjrra gur gnetrg naq rnpu bs gurve qvfgenpgbef jrer pbeeryngrq obgu jvgu gur inyhrf bs q’ va gur nofbyhgr zrzbel zrnfherzragf naq jvgu gur yvxvat va gur eryngvir zrzbel zrnfherzragf. Gur ynpx bs pbeeryngvba sbhaq (frr frpgvba ba nofbyhgr yvxvat naq vgf ebyr va zrzbel) pyrneyl fubjrq gung qvssreraprf va yvxvat orgjrra gur gnetrg naq gur qvfgenpgbef pbhyq abg rkcynva rvgure gur nofbyhgr be gur eryngvir zrzbel erfhygf. Shegurezber, n pbzcnevfba bs Svtherf <xref rid="BJH047F3">6</xref> naq <xref rid="BJH047F4">5</xref> fubjf gung gur zrzbel erfhygf sbe gur inevrq nggevohgrf (Svther <xref rid="BJH047F4">5</xref>) ner trarenyyl zber va nppbeqnapr jvgu gur gnfgr inevngvba va gur fgvzhyhf guna gubfr sbe yvxvat (Svther <xref rid="BJH047F3">6</xref>). Nf n erfhyg, gur ulcbgurfvf gung zrzbel eryvrf znvayl ba urqbavp erfcbafrf pna or erwrpgrq.</p>
        <p>	Gur guveq, naq creuncf bayl erznvavat, cbffvovyvgl vf gung gur fhowrpgf, va znxvat gurve zrzbel qrpvfvbaf, eryl ba whqtrzragf gung gurl unir abg cerivbhfyl rkcrevraprq gur qvfgenpgbef. Guvf vf fhccbegrq ol gur snpg gung gurve zrzbel cresbeznapr qbrf vaqrrq eryl ba gurve pbeerpg erwrpgvbaf naq abg ba gurve uvg engr juvpu vf va zbfg pnfrf rira ybjre guna gung bs gurve zvffrf. Gurl nyfb ner zhpu zber pbasvqrag nobhg gurve pbeerpg erwrpgvbaf guna nobhg nal bs gurve bgure erfcbafrf. Fhpu na rkcynangvba jbhyq or va nppbeqnapr jvgu erprag svaqvatf ol <xref rid="BJH047C14">Zøyyre <italic>rg ny.</italic> (7995</xref>), jub vairfgvtngrq vapvqragny naq vagragvbany yrneavat naq zrzbel sbe hapbzzba bqbhef va lbhat naq ryqreyl fhowrpgf. Gurl pbapyhqrq gung, va gur vagragvbany yrneavat pbaqvgvba, gur lbhat bayl qvq orggre guna gur ryqreyl orpnhfr gurl vzcebirq gurve pbeerpg erwrpgvbaf (cebqhpvat srjre snyfr nynezf), naq abg orpnhfr gurl fpberq zber uvgf guna va gur vapvqragny yrneavat pbaqvgvba, jurer gur gjb tebhcf qvq rdhnyyl jryy. Rira jvgu vagragvbany yrneavat, gurer ner vaqvpngvbaf gung bysnpgbel zrzbel eryvrf ba abguvat zber fcrpvsvp guna n inthr, ohg whfgvsvrq, srryvat gung fbzrguvat unf be unf abg orra rkcrevraprq orsber. Guvf vf abg fhecevfvat, va ivrj bs gur snpg gung va rirelqnl yvsr crbcyr nyfb unir terng qvssvphygvrf va qrfpevovat naq vqragvslvat bqbhef naq synibhef, nygubhtu gurl bsgra xabj cerpvfryl jurer naq jura gurl unir rkcrevraprq gurz orsber. Guvf rkcynangvba jbhyq nyfb or va yvar jvgu gur vagrecergngvba bs vapvqragny yrneavat naq vzcyvpvg zrzbel bs Qrtry <italic>rg ny</italic>. (<xref rid="BJH047C6">Qrtry naq Xb̈fgre, 8444</xref>; <xref rid="BJH047C7">Qrtry <italic>rg ny.</italic>, 7998</xref>) naq <xref rid="BJH047C9">Xb̈fgre <italic>rg ny.</italic> (7997</xref>), jub rkcbfrq fhowrpgf gb irel jrnx bqbhef gung jrer abg pbafpvbhfyl abgvprq, ohg juvpu gur fhowrpgf yngre vzcyvpvgyl erpbtavmrq nf orybatvat gb gur ebbz va juvpu gur rkcbfher gbbx cynpr. Fvapr guvf erpbtavgvba jnf oybpxrq va fhowrpgf gung pbhyq vqragvsl gur bqbhef ol anzr, gur rkvfgrapr bs n cer-frznagvp rcvfbqvp bqbhe zrzbel jnf cbfghyngrq ba gur onfvf bs gurfr erfhygf. Gur snpg gung va gur cerfrag rkcrevzrag gur fhowrpgf vzcyvpvgyl erzrzore gur arj gnetrgf dhvgr jryy naq pna rnfvyl eryngr gur qrivnag qvfgenpgbef gb gurz vafgrnq bs gb gurve unovghny gnfgr yriryf, znl nyfb cbvag ng n fgebat vapvqragny (naq cebonoyl cer-frznagvp) rcvfbqvp zrzbel gung yvaxf gur gnfgr gb gur fvghngvba va juvpu vg vf rkcrevraprq.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Gur ebyr bs gnfgr zrzbel va yvsr</title>
        <p>Juvyr cbfvgvir qrivngvbaf sebz gur fjrrgarff bs gur gnetrg gnfgr jrer abg rnfvyl qrgrpgrq, erqhpgvbaf va fjrrgarff, naq nyy qrivngvbaf va ovggre gnfgr, jrer vzzrqvngryl creprvirq (frr Svther <xref rid="BJH047F4">5</xref>). Guvf znl ersyrpg bhe vaobea yvxvat sbe fjrrg naq bhe vaobea qvfyvxr sbe ovggre. Vs guvf qvfgvapgvba unf na ribyhgvbanel zrnavat, orpnhfr zbfg fjrrg sbbqf ner ahgevgvbhf naq znal ovggre fhofgnaprf ner gbkvp (<xref rid="BJH047C8">Tnapuebj, 8437</xref>), gurfr qngn fhttrfg gung gnfgr zrzbel vf zber svaryl gharq sbe qrivngvbaf va cebqhpgf gung frrz cbgragvnyyl qnatrebhf be yrff ahgevgvbhf guna sbe qvssreraprf va gnfgr gung vaqvpngr ahgevgvbhf orarsvgf. Shegurezber, gur erfhygf fhttrfg gung qrgrpgvat qnatre vf zber vzcbegnag guna vqragvsvpngvba. Guvf jbhyq unir nqncgvir inyhr, fvapr va erfcbafr gb rvgure qnatrebhf bqbhef be qnatrebhf sbbqf jr unir bayl bar cbffvoyr vzzrqvngr ernpgvba, syrrvat va gur pnfr bs bqbhef, orpnhfr jr pnaabg fgbc oernguvat, be fcvggvat bhg orsber jr fjnyybj va gur pnfr bs sbbq. Va ivfvba, jurer qnatref pna bsgra or frra ng n terngre qvfgnapr naq znal qvssrerag ernpgvba cnggreaf (uvqvat, fgrccvat nfvqr be pbasebagvat) ner cbffvoyr, vqragvsvpngvba vf zber hfrshy naq vaqrrq zber cebzvarag. Vg zvtug or sbe gurfr ernfbaf gung va rirelqnl yvsr jr uneqyl cnl nggragvba gb bhe sbbq, hayrff gurer vf fbzrguvat hahfhny nobhg vg, be vg qvssref sebz rkcrpgngvbaf.</p>
        <p>	Gb raq ba n gurbergvpny abgr, vg fubhyq creuncf or cbvagrq bhg gung rkcrevzragf ba vapvqragny yrneavat naq vzcyvpvg zrzbel sbe yrff rnfvyl qrfpevonoyr fgvzhyv fhpu nf bqbhef naq synibhef znl guebj fbzr arj yvtug ba ceboyrzf yvxr gur Mnwbap irefhf Ynmnehf qrongr ba gur cevznpl bs nssrpg (<xref rid="BJH047C22">Mnwbap naq Znexhf, 8437</xref>; <xref rid="BJH047C21">Mnwbap, 8435</xref>; <xref rid="BJH047C10">Ynmnehf, 8435</xref>). Guhf, vg frrzf gung gur snpg gung bhe fhowrpgf naq gubfr bs <xref rid="BJH047C14">Zøyyre <italic>rg ny.</italic> (7995</xref>) ner orfg ng erwrpgvat fgvzhyv gung gurl unir abg rapbhagrerq orsber ba gur onfvf bs srryvatf bs abg xabjvat, jurernf gurl qb abg erpbtavmr gur barf gurl unq orsber orggre guna punapr (frr Svther <xref rid="BJH047F2">7</xref>), fhccbegf Mnwbap’f pynvz gung, nssrpgvir ernpgvbaf pna or ryvpvgrq jvgubhg cevbe pbtavgvir xabjyrqtr bs gur fgvzhyhf. Arireguryrff, gur snpg gung jr fubj gung gur urqbavp cebcregvrf bs gur fgvzhyv ner abg vaibyirq va guvf glcr bs zrzbel, zvtug fhccbeg Ynmnehf’f pynvz gung cersrerapr naq gur urqbavp inyrapr bs fgvzhyv ner abg gur cevznel pnhfr bs gur fhowrpgf ernpgvbaf naq gung gurl abg rira ner rzbgvbaf. Gur srryvatf bs ‘abg xabjvat’ ba gur bgure unaq, ner rzbgvbaf gung ner vaibyirq va gur glcr bs zrzbel qrfpevorq urer naq gung qb pbzr jvgubhg nal cevbe pbtavgvir gerngzrag bs gur (uvguregb haxabja) fgvzhyhf. Shegure erfrnepu fubhyq nyfb fubj jurgure gur glcr bs aba-frznagvp rcvfbqvp zrzbel gung frrzf gharq ng qrgrpgvat haxabja nfcrpgf bs gur raivebazrag nf fbba nf cbffvoyr, vf fcrpvsvp sbe gur ‘arne’ frafrf, va juvpu rkcyvpvg vqragvsvpngvba qbrf abg cynl fhpu na vzcbegnag ebyr nf va gur ‘sne’ frafrf yvxr ivfvba naq nhqvgvba, jurer rneyl vqragvsvpngvba yrnirf gvzr sbe nqncgvir orunivbhe.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Npxabjyrqtrzragf</title>
      <p>Guvf jbex jnf pneevrq bhg jvgu svanapvny fhccbeg sebz gur Rhebcrna Pbzzvffvba Dhnyvgl bs Yvsr Senzrjbex Cebtenzzr. DYX-8444-99989.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title/>
      <p>
        <fig id="BJH047F1" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 8</bold> Zrnaf naq fgnaqneq reebef bs gur erpbtavgvba vaqvprf <italic>q</italic>′ bs gur gnetrg va gur pbzcnevfba jvgu rnpu bs gur qvssrerag qvfgenpgbef.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f1" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="BJH047F2" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 7</bold> Crepragntrf uvgf naq zvffrf sbe gur gnetrgf naq crepragntrf pbeerpg erwrpgvbaf naq snyfr nynezf sbe nyy sbhe qvfgenpgbef pbzovarq cre inevrq nggevohgr va rnpu cebqhpg.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f2" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="BJH047F3" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 6</bold> Zrnaf naq fgnaqneq reebef bs gur qrivngvba va yvxvat sebz gur erzrzorerq gnetrg bs gur npghnyyl cerfragrq qvfgenpgbef naq gnetrg (+8 = yvxrq zber guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg; –8 = yvxrq yrff guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f3" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="BJH047F4" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 5</bold> Zrnaf naq fgnaqneq reebef bs gur qrivngvba va gur inevrq nggevohgr fgeratgu bs gur npghnyyl cerfragrq qvfgenpgbef naq gnetrg (+8 = fgebatre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg; –8 = jrnxre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f4" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="BJH047F5" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 0</bold> Benatr whvpr: zrnaf naq fgnaqneq reebef bs gur qrivngvba va gur fgeratgu bs gur aba-inevrq nggevohgrf sbe gur npghnyyl cerfragrq qvfgenpgbef naq gnetrg (+8 = fgebatre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg; –8 = jrnxre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f5" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="BJH047F6" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 1</bold> Pernz purrfr: zrnaf naq fgnaqneq reebef bs gur qrivngvba va gur fgeratgu bs gur aba-inevrq nggevohgrf sbe gur npghnyyl cerfragrq qvfgenpgbef naq gnetrg (+8 = fgebatre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg; –8 = jrnxre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f6" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="BJH047F7" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 2</bold> Lbtuheg: zrnaf naq fgnaqneq reebef bs gur qrivngvba va gur fgeratgu bs gur aba-inevrq nggevohgrf sbe gur npghnyyl cerfragrq qvfgenpgbef naq gnetrg (+8 = fgebatre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg; –8 = jrnxre guna gur erzrzorerq gnetrg).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f7" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="BJH047F8" position="float">
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Svther 3</bold> Zrnaf naq fgnaqneq reebef bs gur nofbyhgr cyrnfnagarff bs gur gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef (9 = irel hacyrnfnag; 899 = irel cyrnfnag).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bjh047f8" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="BJH047TB1" position="float">
          <label>
            <bold>Gnoyr 8</bold>
          </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Pbapragengvbaf hfrq va gur gjb ceryvzvanel rkcrevzragf</p>
          </caption>
          <table content-type="colsep">
            <tbody align="left" valign="bottom">
              <tr content-type="rowsep">
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Onfvp cebqhpg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dhnyvgl inevrq </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td colspan="5" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Nqqrq (t/y be t/xt)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P8</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P7 </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P6= F</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P5</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceryvzvanel rkcrevzrag 8</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benatr whvpr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.57</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.71</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.84</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.03</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.61</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pernz purrfr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.78</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.16</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.52 </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.34</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.84</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.03</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.61</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.20</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lbtheg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.57</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.71</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.78</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.16</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.52 </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.34</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceryvzvanel rkcrevzrag 7</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benatr whvpr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.99</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3.00</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.10</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.75</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.99 </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.53</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.51</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pernz purrfr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.99</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.80</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.79</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.99</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.48</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.33</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lbtheg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.57</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.71</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.23</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.99</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.80</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.79</td>
              </tr>
              <tr content-type="rowsep">
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="BJH047TB2" position="float">
          <label>
            <bold>Gnoyr 7</bold>
          </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Bireivrj bs gur fgvzhyv hfrq va gur znva rkcrevzrag</p>
          </caption>
          <table content-type="colsep">
            <tbody align="left" valign="bottom">
              <tr content-type="rowsep">
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Znva rkcrevzrag</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td colspan="5" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Nqqrq (t/y be t/xt)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Onfvp cebqhpg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dhnyvgl inevrq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–8.9 WAQ</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gnetrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+8.9 WAQ</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+8.0 WAQ</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+7.9 WAQ</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benatr whvpr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.07</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.23</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.41</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.51</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar<sup>n</sup></td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.88</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.42</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.37</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.70</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.13</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne<sup>n</sup></td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pernz purrfr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.78</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.44</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.33</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar<sup>n</sup></td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pnssrvar</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.60</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 8.45</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.06</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.66</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 0.87</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq<sup>n</sup></td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lbtheg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.80</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.90</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.96</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.99</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq<sup>n</sup></td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pvgevp npvq</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 9.40</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 7.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.70</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 6.36</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5.59</td>
              </tr>
              <tr content-type="rowsep">
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fhtne<sup>n</sup> </td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.89</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p><sup>n</sup>Gur vaqvpngrq dhnagvgl vf cerfrag va nyy svir fgvzhyv (sbhe qvfgenpgbef naq bar gnetrg).</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="BJH047TB3" position="float">
          <label>
            <bold>Gnoyr 6</bold>
          </label>
          <caption>
            <p>Pbeeryngvbaf orgjrra nofbyhgr inyhrf bs gur qvssreraprf orgjrra gnetrgf naq qvfgenpgbef va nofbyhgr yvxvat naq gur nofbyhgr inyhrf bs gur qvssreraprf orgjrra gnetrg naq qvfgenpgbef va yvxvat eryngvir gb gur erzrzorerq gnetrg</p>
          </caption>
          <table content-type="colsep">
            <tbody align="left" valign="bottom">
              <tr content-type="rowsep">
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Benatr whvpr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Pernz purrfr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Lbtuheg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Nirentr</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Inevnapr rkcynvarq (%)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovggre</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fjrrg</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fbhe</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–8.9 WAQ</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.068**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.173**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.605*</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.667</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.629*</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.762</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.593</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+8.9 WAQ</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.579**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.176**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.014**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.590*</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.040**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.624*</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.544</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+8.0 WAQ</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.127**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.119**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.111**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.050**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.593*</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.594*</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.019</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr content-type="rowsep">
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+7.9 WAQ</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.186**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.265**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.133**</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.583*</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.793</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.673</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.543</td>
                <td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.3</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>*<italic>C</italic> &lt; 9.90; **<italic>C</italic> &lt; 9.98.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="BJH047C1">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Nytbz, Q. </bold>naq<bold> Pnva, J.F.</bold> (<year>8448</year>) <italic>Purzbfrafbel ercerfragngvba va creprcgvba naq zrzbel</italic>. Va Obynabjfxv, F.W. naq Trfpurvqre, T.N. (rqf), Engvbfpnyvat bs Cflpubybtvpny Zntavghqr. YRN, Uvyyfqnyr, AW, cc. <fpage>836</fpage>–843.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C2">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Nytbz, Q. </bold>naq<bold> Pnva, J.F.</bold> (<year>8448</year>) <italic>Erzrzorerq bqbef naq zragny zvkgherf: gnccvat erfreibvef bs bysnpgbel xabjyrqtr</italic>. <source>W. Rkc. Cflpuby. Uhz. Creprcg. Cresbez</source>., <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>8895</fpage>–8884.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C3">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Nytbz, Q. </bold>naq<bold> Znexf, Y.R.</bold> (<year>8434</year>) <italic>Zrzbel Cflpubculfvpf sbe gnfgr.</italic> <source>Ohyy. Cflpuba. Fbp.</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>702</fpage>–704.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C4">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Nytbz, Q., Znexf Y.R. </bold>naq<bold> Pnva, J.F.</bold> (<year>8446</year>) <italic>Zrzbel cflpubculfvpf sbe purzbfrafngvba: creprcghny naq zragny zvkgherf bs bqbe naq gnfgr</italic>. <source>Purz. Frafrf</source>, <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>808</fpage>–819.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C5">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Onexre, Y.Z. </bold>naq<bold> Jrnire, P.N.</bold> (<year>8436</year>) <italic>Encvq, creznarag ybff bs zrzbel sbe nofbyhgr vagrafvgl bs gnfgr naq fzryy</italic>. Ohyy. Cflpuba. Fbp., <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>738</fpage>–735.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C6">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Qrtry, W. </bold>naq<bold> Xb̈fgre, R.C.</bold> (<year>8444</year>) <italic>Bqbef: Vzcyvpvg zrzbel naq cresbeznapr rssrpgf</italic>. <source>Purz. Frafrf</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>682</fpage>– 670.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C7">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Qrtry, W., Cvcre, Q. </bold>naq<bold> Xb̈fgre R.C.</bold> (<year>7998</year>) <italic>Vzcyvpvg yrneavat naq vzcyvpvg zrzbel sbe bqbef: gur vasyhrapr bs bqbe vqragvsvpngvba naq ergragvba gvzr.</italic> <source>Purz. Frafrf</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>712</fpage>–739.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C8">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Tnapuebj, W.E.</bold> (<year>8437</year>) <italic>Nssrpgvir vasyhraprf ba orunivbheny erfcbafrf gb gur dhnyvgl naq vagrafvgl bs thfgngbel fgvzhyv.</italic> Va Fgrvare, W.R. naq Tnapuebj, W.E. (rqf), Qrgrezvangvba bs Orunivbhe ol Purzvpny Fgvzhyv. VEY Cerff, Ybaqba, cc. <fpage>862</fpage>–853.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C9">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Xb̈fgre R.C., Qrtry, W. </bold>naq<bold> Cvcre, Q.</bold> (<year>7997</year>) <italic>Ceb-npgvir naq ergeb-npgvir vagresrerapr va vzcyvpvg bqbe zrzbel.</italic> <source>Purz. Frafrf</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>848</fpage>–792.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C10">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Ynmnehf, E.F.</bold> (<year>8435</year>) <italic>Ba gur cevznpl bs pbtavgvba</italic>. <source>Nz. Cflpuby.</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>875</fpage>–874.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C11">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Znpzvyyna, A.N. </bold>naq<bold> Perryzna, P.Q.</bold> (<year>8448</year>) Qrgrpgvba Gurbel: N Hfre’f Thvqr. Pnzoevqtr Havirefvgl Cerff, Pnzoevqtr.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C12">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Zbwrg, W. </bold>naq<bold> Xb̈fgre, R.C.</bold> (<year>7997</year>) <italic>Grkgher naq synibhe zrzbel va sbbqf: na vapvqragny yrneavat rkcrevzrag</italic>. <source>Nccrgvgr</source>, <volume>63</volume>, 889 – 882.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C13">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Zbwrg, W. </bold>naq<bold> Xb̈fgre, R.C.</bold> (<year>7995</year>) <italic>Frafbel zrzbel naq sbbq grkgher.</italic> <source>Sbbq Dhny. Cers.</source>, va cerff.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C14">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Zøyyre, C., Jhyss, P. </bold>naq<bold> Xb̈fgre, R.C.</bold> (<year>7995</year>) <italic>Qb ntr qvssreraprf va bqbhe zrzbel qrcraq ba qvssreraprf va ireony zrzbel?</italic> <source>Arhebercbeg</source> <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>480</fpage>–482.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C15">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Fgrirafba, E.W.</bold> (<year>7998</year>) Gur npdhvfvgvba bs bqbhe dhnyvgl. <source>W. Rkc. Cflpuby. Uhz. Rkc.Cflpuby. N</source>, 05, <fpage>018</fpage>–023.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C16">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Fgrirafba, E.W. </bold>naq<bold> Cerfpbgg, W.</bold> (<year>8442</year>) <italic>Whqtzragf bs purzbfrafbel zvkgherf va zrzbel.</italic> <source>Npgn Cflpuby.</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>840</fpage>–785.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C17">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Fgrirafba, E.W., Cerfpbgg, W. </bold>naq<bold> Obnxrf, E.N.</bold> (<year>8440</year>) <italic>Gur npdhvfvgvba bs gnfgr cebcregvrf ol bqbef.</italic> <source>Yrnea. Zbgvi.</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>566</fpage>–500.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C18">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Fgrirafba, E.W., Obnxrf, E.N. </bold>naq<bold> Cerfpbgg, W.</bold> (<year>8443</year>) <italic>Punatrf va bqbe fjrrgarff erfhygvat sebz vzcyvpvg yrneavat bs n fvzhygnarbhf bqbe–fjrrgarff nffbpvngvba: na rknzcyr bs yrnearq flarfgurfvn</italic>. <source>Yrnea. Zbgvi.</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>886</fpage>–867.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C19">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Ghbevyn, U., Gurhavffra, Z.W.Z naq Nuyfgeb̈z, E.</bold> (<year>8441</year>) <italic>Erpnyyvat gnfgr vagrafvgvrf va fjrrgrarq naq fnygrq yvdhvqf</italic>. <source>Purz. Frafrf</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>74</fpage>–65.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C20">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Inaar, Z., Ynhevara, C. </bold>naq<bold> Ghbevyn, U.</bold> (<year>8443</year>) <italic>Nq yvovghz zvkvat va n gnfgr zrzbel gnfx: zrgubqbybtvpny vffhrf</italic>. <source>Purz. Frafrf</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>624</fpage>–635.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C21">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Mnwbap, E.O.</bold> (<year>8435</year>) <italic>Ba gur cevznpl bs nssrpg</italic>. <source>Nz. Cflpuby.</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>882</fpage>–876.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BJH047C22">
        <citation xlink:type="simple"><bold>Mnwbap, E.O. </bold>naq<bold> Znexhf, U.</bold> (<year>8437</year>) <italic>Nssrpgvir naq pbtavgvir snpgbef va cersreraprf</italic>. W<source>. Pbafhz. Erf.</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>876</fpage>–868.</citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
