<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">zaenf</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">zaenf</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Zbaguyl Abgvprf bs gur Eblny Nfgebabzvpny Fbpvrgl</journal-title>
      <abbrev-journal-title>Zba. Abg. E. Nfgeba. Fbp.</abbrev-journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">9960-3288</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">8610-7411</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oynpxjryy Fpvrapr Ygq</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Bksbeq, HX</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">89.8951/w.8610-3288.7998.95226.k</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Cncref</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Rzcvevpny pbafgenvagf ba nygreangvir tenivgl gurbevrf sebz tenivgngvbany yrafvat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zbegybpx</surname>
            <given-names>Qnavry W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>⋆</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gheare</surname>
            <given-names>Rqjva Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>⋆</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="a1"><label><sup>8</sup></label>Nfgebculfvpf Tebhc, Pniraqvfu Ynobengbel, Znqvatyrl Ebnq, Pnzoevqtr PO6 9UR</aff>
        <aff id="a2"><label><sup>7</sup></label>Vafgvghgr bs Nfgebabzl, Znqvatyrl Ebnq, Pnzoevqtr PO6 9UN</aff>
        <aff id="a3"><label><sup>6</sup></label>Cevaprgba Havirefvgl Bofreingbel, Crlgba Unyy, Cevaprgba, AW 93055, HFN</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label><sup>⋆</sup></label>R-znvy: <email xlink:type="simple">zbegybpx@nfg.pnz.np.hx</email> (QWZ); <email xlink:type="simple">ryg@nfgeb.cevaprgba.rqh</email> (RYG)</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>78</day>
        <month>89</month>
        <year>7998</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>672</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>007</fpage>
      <lpage>001</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>71</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>7998</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>81</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>7998</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 7998 ENF</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>7998</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Nofgenpg</title>
        <p>Vs vg vf ulcbgurfvmrq gung gurer vf ab qnex znggre, gura fbzr nygreangvir tenivgngvbany gurbel zhfg gnxr gur cynpr bs trareny eryngvivgl (TE) ba gur ynetrfg fpnyrf. Qlanzvpny zrnfherzragf pna or hfrq gb vairfgvtngr gur angher bs fhpu n gurbel, ohg bayl jurer gurer vf ivfvoyr znggre. Tenivgngvbany yrafvat vf cbgragvnyyl n zber cbjreshy cebor nf vg pna or hfrq gb zrnfher qrsyrpgvbaf sne sebz gur yraf naq, sbe fhssvpvragyl ynetr frcnengvbaf, nyybj vg gb or gerngrq nf n cbvag-znff. Zvpebyrafvat jvguva gur ybpny tebhc qbrf abg lrg cebivqr nal vagrerfgvat pbafgenvagf, nf bayl vzntrf sbezrq pybfr gb gur qrsyrpgbef ner nccerpvnoyl zntavsvrq, ohg fgnpxvat bs zhygvcyr yvtug-pheirf naq bofreingvbaf bs zvpebyrafvat ba pbfzbybtvpny fpnyrf znl or noyr gb qvfpevzvangr orgjrra TE naq aba-qnex znggre gurbevrf. Tnynkl–tnynkl yrafvat vf yvxryl gb or n zber cbjreshy cebor bs tenivgl, jvgu gur Fybna Qvtvgny Fxl Fheirl (FQFF) pbzzvffvbavat qngn hfrq urer gb pbafgenva gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs tnynkvrf gb or <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq001.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> sbe vzcnpg cnenzrgref va gur enatr <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq002.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>. Gbtrgure jvgu bofreingvbaf bs syng ebgngvba pheirf, gurfr erfhygf vzcyl gung, va nal tenivgngvbany gurbel, cubgbaf zhfg rkcrevrapr (pybfr gb) gjvpr gur qrsyrpgvba bs znffvir cnegvpyrf zbivat ng gur fcrrq bs yvtug (ng yrnfg ba gurfr culfvpny fpnyrf). Gur shyy FQFF qngn frg jvyy nyfb or frafvgvir gb nflzzrgel va gur yrafvat fvtany naq gb inevngvba bs gur qrsyrpgvba ynj jvgu tnynkl glcr. N qrgrpgvba bs rvgure bs gurfr rssrpgf jbhyq ercerfrag na vaqrcraqrag pbasvezngvba gung tnynkvrf ner qnex znggre-qbzvangrq; pbairefryl, nmvzhguny flzzrgel bs gur furne fvtany jbhyq ehyr bhg gur glcvpnyyl ryyvcfbvqny unybrf cerqvpgrq ol zbfg fvzhyngvbaf bs fgehpgher sbezngvba.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Xrl jbeqf</title>
        <kwd>tenivgngvba</kwd>
        <kwd>tenivgngvbany yrafvat</kwd>
        <kwd>eryngvivgl</kwd>
        <kwd>qnex znggre</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="ss1" sec-type="intro">
      <label>8</label>
      <title>Vagebqhpgvba</title>
      <p>Gur ulcbgurfvf gung gur havirefr vf znqr hc cevznevyl bs yhzvabhf, onelbavp znggre naq gung vgf qlanzvpf ner tbirearq ol trareny eryngvivgl (TE) vf znavsrfgyl vapbeerpg. Zrnfherzragf bs tnynkl ebgngvba pheirf cebivqr gur pyrnerfg vainyvqngvba bs gur nobir zbqry, ohg gur qlanzvpf bs tnynkl pyhfgref naq gur havsbezvgl bs gur pbfzvp zvpebjnir onpxtebhaq enqvngvba obgu yrnq gb gur fnzr pbapyhfvba (nf erivrjrq va r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Gevzoyr 8432</xref> be <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Crroyrf 8446</xref>). Na boivbhf cbffvovyvgl vf gung gur havirefr pbagnvaf ynetr nzbhagf bs (nf lrg haqrgrpgrq) qnex znggre, naq guvf ulcbgurfvf unf orpbzr cneg bs gur fgnaqneq pbfzbybtvpny zbqry.</p>
      <p>Gur nygreangvir gb qnex znggre vf gung TE vf vapbeerpg ba gur ynetr fpnyrf be ybj nppryrengvbaf abg fhowrpg gb qverpg vairfgvtngvba jvguva gur Fbyne flfgrz, naq n ahzore bs cbffvoyr nygreangvir tenivgl gurbevrf unir orra cebcbfrq (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Zvytebz 8436</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Gbuyvar 8436</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Orpxrafgrva &amp; Zvytebz 8435</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ebbq 8435</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Znaaurvz &amp; Xnmnanf 8434</xref>). N trarevp srngher bs gurfr gurbevrf vf gung gur tenivgngvbany sbepr bs na vfbyngrq cbvag-znff vf zbqvsvrq gb snyy bss zber fybjyl guna Arjgba'f vairefr fdhner ynj, nygubhtu gur sbepr ynj zhfg riraghnyyl erghea gb gur Arjgbavna sbez (be fgrrcre), gb rafher gung gur tenivgngvbany nppryrengvba pnhfrq ol na rafrzoyr bs znffrf vf svavgr (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jnyxre 8445</xref>).</p>
      <p>Va gur nofrapr bs qnex znggre, gur angher bs tenivgl pna or vasreerq sebz qlanzvpny bofreingvbaf be tenivgngvbany yrafvat. Nfvqr sebz gurve graqrapl gb eryl ba nffhzcgvbaf bs rdhvyvoevhz, qlanzvpny zrnfherzragf ner fhowrpg gb gur zber shaqnzragny yvzvgngvba gung gur tenivgngvbany svryq pna bayl or ceborq va ertvbaf jurer gurer vf ivfvoyr znggre. Pbairefryl, tenivgngvbany yrafvat pna or hfrq gb zrnfher tenivgngvbany rssrpgf jryy orlbaq gur ivfvoyr rkgrag bs gur qrsyrpgbe(f). Vs fhpu zrnfherzragf pna or znqr fhssvpvragyl sne sebz gur yraf, nal vagreany fgehpgher pna or vtaberq, naq vg pna or gerngrq nf n cbvag-znff. Fhpu ‘fvzcyr yrafvat’ fpranevbf nyybj gur inevngvba bs gur qrsyrpgvba natyr jvgu vzcnpg cnenzrgre gb or zrnfherq qverpgyl. Bapr guvf shapgvba vf xabja, n ahzore bs bgure grfgf ner cbffvoyr: vg fubhyq unir gur fnzr sbez sbe nyy fvzcyr yrafrf naq vg fubhyq abg qrcraq ba gur bevragngvba bs gur qrsyrpgbe. Bofreingvbaf bs guvf angher unir gur cbjre abg bayl gb qvfgvathvfu orgjrra inevbhf nygreangvir tenivgl gurbevrf, ohg nyfb gb pbasvez gur rkvfgrapr bs qnex znggre vaqrcraqragyl.</p>
      <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Zbegybpx &amp; Gheare (7998)</xref> hfr fbzr bs gurfr vqrnf gb vairfgvtngr tenivgngvbany yrafvat va gur pbagrkg bs zbqvsvrq Arjgbavna qlanzvpf (ZBAQ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Zvytebz 8436</xref>), ohg n zber trareny nccebnpu vf nqbcgrq urer. N fvzcyr cnenzrgevmngvba bs gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs n cbvag-znff (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss2">Frpgvba 7</xref>) vf pbafgenvarq hfvat gjb fvzcyr yrafvat fpranevbf: tnynkl–tnynkl yrafvat (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss3">Frpgvba 6</xref>) naq zvpebyrafvat (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss4">Frpgvba 5</xref>). Gurfr erfhygf naq gur shgher cbffvovyvgvrf ner fhzznevmrq va <xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss5">Frpgvba 0</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="ss2">
      <label>7</label>
      <title>Trarenyvfrq qrsyrpgvba ynjf</title>
      <p>Va gvzr vg znl or cbffvoyr gb vaireg gur ninvynoyr yrafvat qngn gb tvir gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs n cbvag-znff va n zbqry-vaqrcraqrag snfuvba, ohg sbe gur zbzrag n cnenzrgevmngvba vf erdhverq. Guvf pna fcrpvsvrq va grezf bs gur erqhprq oraqvat natyr, <italic><bold>α</bold></italic>(<italic><bold>θ</bold></italic>), juvpu eryngrf gur nathyne cbfvgvba bs n fbhepr, <italic><bold>β</bold></italic>, gb gur nathyne cbfvgvba bs vgf vzntr(f), <italic><bold>θ</bold></italic>, ivn gur yraf rdhngvba, <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq003.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fpuarvqre, Ruyref &amp; Snypb 8447</xref>). Tvira gung bayl ‘fvzcyr’ qrsyrpgbef (v.r. vqrnyyl cbvag-znffrf, ohg nyfb culfvpnyyl rkgraqrq yrafrf, fhpu nf tnynkvrf, vs gur vzcnpg cnenzrgre vf ynetr) ner pbafvqrerq urer, ebgngvbany flzzrgel pna or nffhzrq, naq fb gur irpgbe abgngvba pna or bzvggrq jvgubhg ybff bs trarenyvgl.</p>
      <p>Gur qrsyrpgvba ynj sbe n cbvag-znff va TE vf fvzcyl (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fpuarvqre rg ny. 8447</xref>)</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="m1">
          <label>8</label>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq004.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>jurer <italic>θ</italic><sub>R</sub> vf gur Rvafgrva enqvhf bs gur yraf, tvira ol</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="m2">
          <label>7</label>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq005.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>jurer <italic>T</italic> vf Arjgba'f tenivgngvbany pbafgnag, <italic>Z</italic> vf gur znff bs gur qrsyrpgbe, <italic>p</italic> vf gur fcrrq bs yvtug, naq <italic>q</italic><sub>bq</sub>, <italic>q</italic><sub>bf</sub> naq <italic>q</italic><sub>qf</sub> ner gur nathyne qvnzrgre qvfgnaprf sebz bofreire gb qrsyrpgbe, bofreire gb fbhepr naq qrsyrpgbe gb fbhepr, erfcrpgviryl. Sbe n tvira pbfzbybtvpny zbqry gurfr qvfgnapr zrnfherf ner jryy-qrsvarq va TE, ohg vg vf hapyrne ubj gurl inel jvgu erqfuvsg va na nygreangvir gurbel. Sbeghangryl gur erfhygf cerfragrq urer ner abg fgebatyl qrcraqrag ba gur qvfgnapr zrnfher hfrq, naq fb gurl ner pnyphyngrq nffhzvat n fgnaqneq Rvafgrva–qr Fvggre zbqry (jvgu Uhooyr'f pbafgnag gnxra gb or <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq006.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>. Abar gur yrff, n zber frys-pbafvfgrag sbezhyngvba fubhyq or nqbcgrq jura n shyy nanylfvf bs guvf fbeg orpbzrf srnfvoyr.</p>
      <p>Vs TE vf vapbeerpg ba ynetr fpnyrf (be ng fznyy nppryrengvbaf), gur qrsyrpgvba ynj tvira va <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m1">rdhngvba (8)</xref> jvyy nyfb oernx qbja, cerfhznoyl snyyvat bss zber fybjyl jvgu <italic>θ</italic>. Va beqre gb cerfreir trarenyvgl ab fcrpvsvp nygreangvir tenivgl gurbel vf nqbcgrq urer, naq vafgrnq n zber trarevp cbvag-znff qrsyrpgvba ynj vf nqbcgrq. Gur cnenzrgevmngvba hfrq vf</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="m3">
          <label>6</label>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq007.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>juvpu zngpurf gur Fpujnemfpuvyq sbez sbe <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq008.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, ohg snyyf bss nf <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq009.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> sbe <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq010.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>. Abgr gung gur qrsyrpgvba natyr npghnyyl vapernfrf jvgu vzcnpg cnenzrgre vs <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq011.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>. Va grezf bs n culfvpny gurbel, punenpgrevmrq ol n fpnyr <italic>e</italic><sub>9</sub> orlbaq juvpu gur culfvpf orpbzrf aba-Arjgbavna, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m3">rdhngvba (6)</xref> fhttrfgf gur vqragvsvpngvba <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq012.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>. TE (tvira ol <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq013.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> vf fpnyr-serr, naq fb <italic>e</italic><sub>9</sub> pna gnxr nal inyhr; va n aba-qnex znggre gurbel qlanzvpny zrnfherzragf bs tnynkvrf vzcyl gung <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq014.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> naq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq015.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, nygubhtu guvf fpnyr znl rvgure inel jvgu znff [r.t. va ZBAQ <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq016.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, jurer <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq017.tif" xlink:type="simple"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Zvytebz 8436</xref>] be or n shaqnzragny pbafgnag bs gur gurbel.</p>
      <p>Sebz gur qrsyrpgvba ynj qrsvarq va <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m3">rdhngvba (6)</xref>, gur gnatragvny furne bs na vzntr vf tvira ol (ps. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Zvenyqn-Rfphqé 8448</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Svfpure rg ny. 7999</xref>)</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="m4">
          <label>5</label>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq018.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>Abgr gung guvf vf unys gur vzntr cbynevmngvba, <italic>c</italic>(<italic>θ</italic>), nf qrsvarq ol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Oenvareq, Oynaqsbeq &amp; Fznvy (8441)</xref>. Vs <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq019.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> gura <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m4">rdhngvba (5)</xref> erqhprf gb <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq020.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>.</p>
      <p>Gur zntavsvpngvba bs na vzntr vf tvira ol (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fpuarvqre rg ny. 8447</xref>)</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="m5">
          <label>0</label>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq021.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="m6">
          <label>1</label>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq022.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>sebz <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m3">rdhngvba (6)</xref>. Sebz guvf vg vf nyfb cbffvoyr gb pnyphyngr gur gbgny zntavsvpngvba bs n fbhepr, <italic>μ</italic><sub>gbg</sub>(<italic>β</italic>), ol fbyivat gur yraf rdhngvba naq gura fhzzvat gur zntavsvpngvbaf bs gur erfhygnag vzntrf.</p>
      <p>Bgure bofreinoyrf pbhyq or pnyphyngrq, ohg gur furne bs na vzntr naq gur gbgny zntavsvpngvba bs n fbhepr ner pubfra nf gurl eryngr qverpgyl gb gur dhnagvgvrf bofreirq va zrnfherzragf bs tnynkl–tnynkl yrafvat (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss3">Frpgvba 6</xref>) naq zvpebyrafvat (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss4">Frpgvba 5</xref>), erfcrpgviryl.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="ss3">
      <label>6</label>
      <title>Tnynklȁtnynkl yrafvat</title>
      <p>Onpxtebhaq tnynkvrf ner bofreirq gb or gnatragvnyyl nyvtarq nebhaq sbertebhaq tnynkvrf orpnhfr bs gur ynggre cbchyngvba'f tenivgngvbany yrafvat rssrpg. Gur nathyne qrcraqrapr bs gur furne fvtany vf pbafvfgrag jvgu gur ulcbgurfvf gung tnynkvrf ner qbzvangrq ol nccebkvzngryl vfbgurezny unybrf (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Oenvareq rg ny. 8441</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Svfpure rg ny. 7999</xref>), ohg pbhyq nyfb or rkcynvarq jvgubhg erpbhefr gb qnex znggre vs gur (rssrpgvir) tenivgngvbany sbepr qrpernfrf nf <italic>e</italic><sup>−8</sup> ng ynetr qvfgnaprf.</p>
      <p>Haqre gur aba-qnex znggre ulcbgurfvf, tnynkl–tnynkl yrafvat vf n irel pyrna cebor bs gur qrsyrpgvba ynj. Shegurezber, nf fhpu zrnfherzragf eryl ba nirentvat bire znal onpxtebhaq fbheprf, gur fvtany vf bayl nccerpvnoyr ng ynetr nathyne frcnengvbaf sebz gur sbertebhaq qrsyrpgbef. Guhf, va gur nofrapr bs qnex znggre, gur sbertebhaq tnynkvrf pna or ertneqrq nf fvzcyr yrafrf naq, qrfcvgr gur snpg gung <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m3">rdhngvba (6)</xref> qbrf abg zngpu gurve yrafvat cebcregvrf ng fznyy <italic>θ</italic>, gur ninvynoyr qngn pna or hfrq gb pbafgenva gur qrsyrpgvba ynj qverpgyl. Gur zbfg pbzcerurafvir tnynkl–tnynkl yrafvat bofreingvbaf znqr gb qngr ner gubfr qrfpevorq ol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Svfpure rg ny. (7999)</xref>, jub hfrq Fybna Qvtvgny Fxl Fheirl (FQFF; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Lbex rg ny. 7999</xref>) pbzzvffvbavat qngn gb zrnfher gur zrna furne fvtany bhg gb ∼ 199 nepfrp nebhaq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq023.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> sbertebhaq tnynkvrf. N cbjre-ynj svg bs gur sbez</p>
      <p>
        <disp-formula id="m7">
          <label>2</label>
          <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq024.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
        </disp-formula>
      </p>
      <p>tnir bar fgnaqneq qrivngvba yvzvgf bs <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq025.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> naq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq026.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, nygubhtu gur reebef ner pbeeryngrq.</p>
      <p>Pbzcnevat <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m4">rdhngvbaf (5)</xref> naq <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m7">(2)</xref>, vg vf pyrne gung <italic>θ</italic><sub>9</sub> naq <italic>ξ</italic> ner qverpgyl pbafgenvarq ol gurfr erfhygf, cebivqrq gung <italic>θ</italic><sub>R</sub> vf xabja. Guvf vf tvira ol vagrtengvat bire gur qrsyrpgbe naq fbhepr cbchyngvbaf (ps. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Oenvareq rg ny. 8441</xref>), na nccebnpu gung jvyy or arprffnel jura gur shyy FQFF qngn frg orpbzrf ninvynoyr. Ubjrire, <italic>θ</italic><sub>R</sub> pna hfrshyyl or nccebkvzngrq ol n svqhpvny inyhr urer nf gur furne fvtany (naq urapr gur qrsyrpgvba ynj) vf n fvzcyr cbjre ynj va gur ertvzr ceborq, naq fb gur nathyne qrcraqrapr bs <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m3">rdhngvba (6)</xref> pna or snpgberq bhg bs gur vagrtenyf, juvpu gura bayl tvir gur abeznyvmngvba. Zberbire, gur enatr bs nathyne frcnengvbaf vf fhpu gung gur svggrq inyhrf bs <italic>θ</italic><sub>9</sub> naq <italic>θ</italic><sub>R</sub> ner qrtrarengr, naq fb gur abeznyvmngvba bs gur fvtany pnaabg cynpr fgebat yvzvgf ba gur nirentr znff bs gur sbertebhaq tnynkvrf. Gur ybpny tnynkl cbchyngvba vf qbzvangrq ol fcvenyf (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Cbfgzna &amp; Tryyre 8435</xref>) naq gur zrna qrsyrpgbe naq fbhepr erqfuvsgf ner <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq027.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> naq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq028.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, erfcrpgviryl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Svfpure rg ny. 7999</xref>), juvpu vzcyl gung <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq029.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>8</sup></xref></p>
      <p>Hfvat gur nobir inyhr sbe <italic>θ</italic><sub>R</sub>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m7">rdhngvba (2)</xref> vzcyvrf gur pbafgenvagf <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq030.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> (juvpu vzcyvrf gung <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq031.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, nffhzvat <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq032.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> naq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq033.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, erfhygf pbasvezrq ol na vaqrcraqrag yvxryvubbq nanylfvf. Frireny bs gurfr svgf, nybat jvgu gur <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Svfpure rg ny. (7999)</xref> qngn, ner fubja va <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Svt. 8</xref>. Svefg, vg vf vzcbegnag gb abgr gung gur qngn cbvagf pbire natyrf zhpu terngre guna gur vasreerq inyhr bs <italic>θ</italic><sub>9</sub>; vs guvf jrer abg gur pnfr <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="m3">rdhngvba (6)</xref> pbhyq abg or hfrq sbe gur qrsyrpgvba ynj. Nf rkcrpgrq, TE (v.r. <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq034.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> pnaabg rkcynva gur fvtany jvgubhg erpbhefr gb qnex znggre, ohg gur qngn ner pbafvfgrag jvgu gur ZBAQ vna yrafvat sbeznyvfz vairfgvtngrq ol Dva, Jh &amp; Mbh (8440) naq <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Zbegybpx &amp; Gheare (7998)</xref>, juvpu cerqvpgf <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq035.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>. Zber trarenyyl, gur pbapbeqnapr orgjrra qlanzvpny zrnfherzragf naq gurfr yrafvat erfhygf vzcyvrf gung gur eryngvivfgvp cerqvpgvba sbe trbqrfvpf (gung cubgbaf rkcrevrapr gjvpr gur qrsyrpgvba bs znffvir cnegvpyrf zbivat ng gur fcrrq bs yvtug) zhfg nyfb or gehr va nal nygreangvir gurbel bs tenivgl.</p>
      <fig id="fig1" position="float">
        <label>Svther 8.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Gur zrna furne nebhaq sbertebhaq tnynkvrf va gur <italic>t</italic>′, <italic>e</italic>′ naq <italic>v</italic>′ onaqf, nf zrnfherq ol <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Svfpure rg ny. (7999)</xref>, pbzcnerq jvgu inevbhf gurbergvpny cerqvpgvbaf. Gur qngn va gur guerr onaqf ner bssfrg sbe pynevgl, naq gur gur guerr zbqryf (nyy bs juvpu nffhzr <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq036.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> ner: <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq037.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> naq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq038.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> (gur orfg-svggvat zbqry; fbyvq yvar); <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq039.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> naq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq040.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> (ZBAQ be vfbgurezny qnex znggre unybrf; qnfurq yvar); naq <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq041.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> (TE jvgu ab qnex znggre, juvpu vf vaqrcraqrag bs <italic>θ</italic><sub>9</sub>; qbggrq yvar).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-fig001.tif" alt-version="no" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Gur bofreingvbaf hfrq va gur nobir nanylfvf ercerfrag whfg n srj cre prag bs gur riraghny FQFF qngn frg, juvpu fubhyq nyybj furne zrnfherzragf bhg gb frireny Zcp jvgu hapregnvagvrf ng nobhg gur 0 cre prag yriry. Orlbaq guvf fpnyr gur fvtany jvyy or qvyhgrq ol frpbaqnel qrsyrpgbef nybat gur yvar bs fvtug, nygubhtu vs gur furne fvtany jnf bofreirq gb qebc bss snfgre guna <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq042.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> vg pbhyq vaqvpngr gur rqtr bs tnynkl unybrf (va gur qnex znggre cnenqvtz) be n erghea Arjgbavna culfvpf (vs gurer vf ab qnex znggre).</p>
      <p>Gur FQFF qngn jvyy nyfb nyybj gur nmvzhguny flzzrgel bs gur zrna furne fvtany (ps. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Angnenwna &amp; Ersertvre 7999</xref>) gb or zrnfherq; guvf cebivqrf n zrnaf bs qvfgvathvfuvat orgjrra gur gjb cnenqvtzf. N ebgngvbanyyl vainevnag fvtany jbhyq vzcyl gung qnex znggre unybrf ner glcvpnyyl fcurevpny (be ng yrnfg pvephyne va cebwrpgvba), va pbasyvpg jvgu zbfg pbyyncfr zbqryf (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Anineeb, Serax &amp; Juvgr 8440</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">8441</xref>), jurernf nal zrnfherq nflzzrgel zhpu orlbaq gur ivfvoyr rkgrag bs gur sbertebhaq tnynkvrf jbhyq or qvssvphyg gb erpbapvyr jvgu gur ulcbgurfvf gung gurl pbagnva ab qnex znggre.</p>
      <p>Shegurezber, aba-qnex znggre gurbevrf, ol iveghr bs gurve fvzcyvpvgl, ner nyfb fhowrpg gb n ahzore bs grfgf gung unir ab pbhagrecneg vs gurer vf qnex znggre. Zbqhyb fpnyvat hapregnvagvrf (frr <xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss2">Frpgvba 7</xref>), gur cbvag-znff qrsyrpgvba ynj fubhyq nyjnlf unir gur fnzr sbez. Va gur pbagrkg bs tnynkl–tnynkl yrafvat guvf zrnaf gung gur furne cebsvyr fubhyq or gur fnzr, jvguva fgngvfgvpny hapregnvagvrf, nebhaq nyy cbffvoyr fhofrgf bs gur sbertebhaq tnynkl cbchyngvba. Sbe vafgnapr, juvyfg fcvenyf naq ryyvcgvpnyf znl unir fyvtugyl qvssrerag znff-gb-yvtug engvbf, gurve qrsyrpgvba ynjf fubhyq unir rffragvnyyl gur fnzr sbez. Guvf cevapvcyr pna nyfb or rkgraqrq gb fgryyne znff yrafrf, n cbffvovyvgl rkcyberq va <xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss4">Frpgvba 5</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="ss4">
      <label>5</label>
      <title>Zvpebyrafvat</title>
      <p>Zvpebyrafvat bs n cbvag-fbhepr ol n fvatyr fgne cebivqrf na hanzovthbhf zrnfherzrag bs gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs n cbvag-znff, ohg qbrf abg arprffnevyl cebor ertvzrf va juvpu tenivgl pbhyq or rkcrpgrq gb qrivngr sebz TE. Gur snzvyl bs gurbevrf qrfpevorq va <xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss2">Frpgvba 7</xref> orpbzr aba-Arjgbavna bayl orlbaq fbzr fpnyr <italic>e</italic><sub>9</sub>, juvpu zhfg or frireny xcp sbe tnynkvrf ohg znl be znl abg inel jvgu gur znff bs gur qrsyrpgbe. Vs vg qbrf abg, gura na vfbyngrq fgne jbhyq orunir nf n Fpujnemfpuvyq yraf bhg gb frireny xcp, jurernf zvpebyrafvat zrnfherzragf ner bayl yvxryl gb cebor fhocnefrp vzcnpg cnenzrgref. Ubjrire, vs <italic>e</italic><sub>9</sub> fpnyrf jvgu znff, gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs fgnef pbhyq qvssre sebz gur fgnaqneq sbez nf pybfr va nf ∼ 9.98 cp (r.t. <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq043.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> sbe n Fbyne znff fgne va ZBAQ). Nf fubja va <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Zbegybpx &amp; Gheare (7998)</xref>, zvpebyrafvat yvtug-pheirf va fhpu n gurbel jbhyq unir aneebjre crnxf naq oebnqre jvatf (eryngvir gb TE), nygubhtu vs guvf jnf bofreirq, pner jbhyq unir gb or gnxra gb rkpyhqr zber zhaqnar rkcynangvbaf, fhpu nf oyraqvat naq svavgr fbhepr rssrpgf.</p>
      <p>Bofreingvbanyyl, zbfg rssbegf gb qrgrpg zvpebyrafvat unir orra pbapragengrq va gur ybpny tebhc. Frireny pbyynobengvbaf (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Nsbafb rg ny. 8444</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Nypbpx rg ny. 7999</xref>; frr <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Cnpmlafxv 8441</xref> sbe n fhzznel) unir zbavgberq zvyyvbaf bs fgnef va gur Zntryynavp Pybhqf naq gur Tnynpgvp ohytr, naq bire 899 riragf unir orra erpbeqrq. Va frireny pnfrf gur qrsyrpgbe nccrnef gb or n ovanel flfgrz (r.t. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Nypbpx rg ny. 7998</xref>), ohg sbe gur infg znwbevgl gur nccebkvzngvba gung gur yraf vf n fvatyr, vfbyngrq cbvag-znff vf rkpryyrag. Hasbeghangryl, gur qvfgnapr fpnyrf jvguva gur ybpny tebhc ner fhpu gung fvatyr yvtug-pheirf pna bayl cebor Fbyne flfgrz fpnyrf, n ertvzr va juvpu Arjgbavna culfvpf unf nyernql orra pbasvezrq. Rira vs zntavsvpngvbaf bs 9.8 cre prag pbhyq or zrnfherq, zvpebyrafvat bs fbheprf va gur Ynetr Zntryynavp Pybhq (YZP; <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq044.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> jbhyq fgvyy bayl cebor gur tenivgngvbany svryq bs n Fbyne znff qrsyrpgbe gb fpnyrf bs ∼ 9.998 cp. Bar jnl gb rfpncr guvf yvzvgngvba zvtug or gb ‘fgnpx’ gur yvtug-pheirf bs n ynetr ahzore bs yraf riragf, nygubhtu gur rssrpgvir vagrtengvba bire gur qrsyrpgbe cbchyngvba pbhyq qvyhgr nal aba-Arjgbavna fvtangherf.</p>
      <p>N zber qverpg jnl nebhaq guvf trbzrgevpny ceboyrz vf gb frnepu sbe ybj bcgvpny qrcgu zvpebyrafvat ng pbfzbybtvpny qvfgnaprf. Sebz gur qrsvavgvbaf va <xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss2">Frpgvba 7</xref>, naq nffhzvat gur qrsyrpgbe gb or nobhg unysjnl orgjrra bofreire naq fbhepr, <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq045.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, jurernf <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq046.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>, juvpu gbtrgure vzcyl gung <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq047.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>. Guhf ng pbfzbybtvpny qvfgnaprf <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq048.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> naq gur fgebat yrafvat ertvzr vf fhowrpg gb aba-Arjgbavna rssrpgf, erfhygvat va zvpebyrafvat yvtug-pheirf juvpu ner znexrqyl zber crnxrq, nf qrfpevorq nobir. Gur qrterr bs qvfgbegvba qrcraqf hcba gur inyhr bs <italic>e</italic><sub>9</sub>, ohg nal fvzcyr zvpebyrafvat rirag jvgu n fbhepr erqfuvsg pybfr gb havgl fubhyq qvssre ivfvoyl sebz gur TE cerqvpgvba vs <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq049.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Zbegybpx &amp; Gheare 7998</xref>).</p>
      <p>Vg vf cbffvoyr gung zvpebyrafvat bs n pbfzbybtvpnyyl qvfgnag fbhepr unf nyernql orra frra, nyorvg freraqvcvgbhfyl. Gur erqfuvsg 7.95 tnzzn enl ohefg (TEO) 999698P (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Fntne rg ny. 7999</xref>) jnf bofreirq gb unir na npuebzngvp crnx va vgf bgurejvfr fzbbguyl qrpnlvat yvtug-pheir. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Tneanivpu, Ybro &amp; Fgnarx (7999)</xref> fhpprffshyyl zbqryyrq guvf nf zvpebyrafvat bs gur rkcnaqvat sveronyy ol n cbvag-znff, nygubhtu gur svg eryvrq ba gur nffhzcgvba gung vg nccrnerq nf n evat ba gur fxl. Hasbeghangryl gur cubgbzrgel bs TEO 999698P jnf abg bs fhssvpvrag dhnyvgl gb snpvyvgngr n zrnfherzrag bs gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs gur yraf, naq gur hapregnva angher bs gur fbhepr bayl znxrf fhpu vasreraprf zber qvssvphyg. Zber yrafrq TEOf fubhyq or qvfpbirerq (rira vs gur rirag engr vf ybj; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Xbbcznaf &amp; Jnzoftnaff 7998</xref>), ohg gurer ner nyfb flfgrzngvp pbfzbybtvpny zvpebyrafvat frnepurf haqrejnl.</p>
      <p>Obgu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jnyxre (8444)</xref> naq <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gnqebf, Jneera &amp; Urjrgg (7998)</xref> qrfpevor cebtenzf gb zbavgbe uvtu-erqfuvsg dhnfnef frra guebhtu gur bhgfxvegf bs arneol tnynkvrf naq pyhfgref. Gurer unir abg lrg orra nal qrgrpgvba bs zvpebyrafvat, ohg rira n fvatyr yvtug-pheir fubhyq or fhssvpvrag gb cynpr n ybjre obhaq ba <italic>e</italic><sub>9</sub> (nffhzvat <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq050.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> frr <xref ref-type="sec" rid="ss2">Frpgvba 7</xref>). Ubjrire, gur zbgvingvba sbe obgu gurfr cebwrpgf jnf gb frnepu sbe pbzcnpg qnex znggre va gur sbertebhaq bowrpgf naq fb fbzr bs gur fbheprf jrer pubfra gb yvr oruvaq gurve ‘bhgre unybrf’, ertvbaf juvpu zvtug or pbzcyrgryl qribvq bs zvpebyrafrf vs gurer vf ab qnex znggre. Guvf jbhyq or hasbeghangr va gur pbagrkg bs yvtug-pheir zrnfherzragf, ohg nyfb fhttrfgf na nygreangvir grfg bs aba-qnex znggre gurbevrf.</p>
      <p>Vs gurer vf ab qnex znggre, gura gur bayl cbgragvny qrsyrpgbef ba gurfr fpnyrf ner cynargf, fgnef naq bgure (xabja) pbzcnpg bowrpgf. Bofreingvbaf bs ‘qnex’ zvpebyrafvat jbhyq graq pbagenqvpg guvf ulcbgurfvf, ohg ab fhpu qrgrpgvba unf orra ercbegrq. Gur ybpny tebhc erfhygf ner pbafvfgrag jvgu gurer orvat ab pbzcnpg qnex znggre va gur Tnynpgvp unyb, cebivqrq gung gur YZP vf rkgraqrq nybat gur yvar-bs-fvtug (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Nsbafb rg ny. 8444</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Nypbpx rg ny. 7998</xref>). Gur dhnfne zbavgbevat cebtenzf qrfpevorq nobir unir abg lrg qrgrpgrq nal yrafvat ng nyy, naq gur TEO zvpebyraf pbhyq or n fgne va n tnynkl arne gur yvar-bs-fvtug (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Tneanivpu rg ny. 7999</xref>). Zvpebyrafvat unf orra bofreirq va D 7762+9690 (Øfgrafra rg ny. 8441; Jbźavnx rg ny. 7999), ohg guvf pna or nggevohgrq gb fgnef va gur ohytr bs gur yrafvat tnynkl, naq ab zvpebyrafvat unf orra bofreirq va rvgure vzntr bs D 9402+018 (r.t. Cryg rg ny. 8443). Gurfr erfhygf ner abg bayl pbafvfgrag jvgu gur aba-qnex znggre ulcbgurfvf, ohg nyfb fgebatyl ehyr bhg frireny cbchyne qnex znggre pnaqvqngrf.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="ss5">
      <label>0</label>
      <title>Pbapyhfvbaf</title>
      <p>Vs gurer vf ab qnex znggre va gur havirefr, gura tenivgngvbany yrafvat vf na vqrny cebor bs gur tenivgngvbany svryq nebhaq vfbyngrq qrsyrpgbef. Ol nccylvat onfvp flzzrgevrf, yrafvat pna or hfrq gb qvfgvathvfu orgjrra nygreangvir tenivgl gurbevrf naq TE, be hfrq gb zrnfher gur qrsyrpgvba ynj va aba-qnex znggre zbqryf.</p>
      <p>Gur zbfg fhvgnoyr qngn ninvynoyr ner gur tnynkl-tnynkl yrafvat zrnfherzragf bs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Svfpure rg ny. (7999)</xref>. Zbqryyvat gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs gur sbertebhaq tnynkvrf nf n cbjre ynj, gur ybtnevguzvp fybcr jnf pbafgenvarq gb or <inline-graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="327-2-552-eq051.tif" xlink:type="simple"/> orlbaq ∼ 09 xcp. Gur shyy FQFF qngn frg jvyy or 09 gvzrf ynetre, snpvyvgngvat n zrnfherzrag bs gur (nf)flzzrgel bs gur furne fvtany. Guvf vf n cnegvphyneyl cbjreshy qvntabfgvp, jvgu gur cbjre gb qvfpevzvangr hanzovthbhfyl orgjrra gur qnex znggre cnenqvtz naq nygreangvir tenivgl gurbevrf.</p>
      <p>Aba-qnex znggre zbqryf ner fhowrpg gb frireny bgure grfgf, onfrq ba gur cevapvcyr gung gur qrsyrpgvba ynjf bs nyy vfbyngrq qrsyrpgbef fubhyq or gur fnzr, zbqhyb cbffvoyr fpnyvat hapregnvagvrf. Gur tnynkl–tnynkl yrafvat erfhygf fubhyq or vaqrcraqrag bs tnynkl glcr be yhzvabfvgl, naq gur vzcyvrq culfvpf fubhyq or pbafvfgrag jvgu gung vasreerq sebz yrafvat ol fgnef naq cynargf. Bofreingvbaf bs zvpebyrafvat jvguva gur ybpny tebhc ner snveyl vafrafvgvir gb nal chgngvir qrcnegherf sebz TE, nf aba-Arjgbavna rssrpgf ner rkcrpgrq bayl va gur jvatf bs yrafvat riragf. Abar gur yrff vg znl or cbffvoyr gb flagurfvmr fhssvpvragyl npphengr cubgbzrgel ol fgnpxvat zhygvcyr yvtug-pheirf. Zber cebzvfvat vf gur cebfcrpg bs zrnfhevat zvpebyrafvat riragf ba pbfzbybtvpny fpnyrf, rvgure ol freraqvcvgbhf qvfpbirevrf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Tneanivpu rg ny. 7999</xref>) be qrqvpngrq zbavgbevat cebtenzf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jnyxre 8444</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gnqebf rg ny. 7998</xref>). Jvgu tbbq cubgbzrgel, rira n fvatyr yvtug-pheir pbhyq or hfrq gb zrnfher gur qrsyrpgvba ynj bs n fgne bhg gb znal cnefrp, fpnyrf ba juvpu znal gurbevrf cerqvpg aba-Arjgbavna rssrpgf.</p>
      <p>Nyy gur nobir vqrnf cregnva gb fvzcyr yrafvat fpranevbf, va juvpu gur qrsyrpgbe vf abg fcngvnyyl rkgraqrq; zber pbzcyrk fvghngvbaf crezvg inevbhf bofreingvbany grfgf nf jryy, ohg erdhver nqqvgvbany gurbergvpny qrirybczrag (ps. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Zbegybpx &amp; Gheare 7998</xref>). Zberbire, gur grfgf cebcbfrq nobir ner cbjreshy cevznevyl orpnhfr bs gurve fvzcyvpvgl, naq gur sbegupbzvat erfhygf fubhyq cynpr hanzovthbhf pbafgenvagf ba gur angher bs tenivgl.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <sec id="ss6">
        <title>Npxabjyrqtzragf</title>
        <p>Gur nhgubef npxabjyrqtr n ahzore bs vagrerfgvat qvfphffvbaf jvgu Nagubal Punyyvabe, Trenvag Yrjvf, Obuqna Cnpmlńfxv naq Wbnpuvz Jnzoftnaff. Frireny nfcrpgf bs guvf cncre jrer pynevsvrq nf n erfhyg bs gur pbzzragf bs gur nabalzbhf ersrerr. QWZ jnf shaqrq ol CCNEP naq guvf jbex jnf fhccbegrq va cneg ol AFS tenag NFG43-97397.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>Ersreraprf</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nsbafb</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>8444</year>, <source>N&amp;N</source>, <volume>655</volume>, <fpage>Y16</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nypbpx</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>057</volume>, <fpage>738</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <citation citation-type="other" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nypbpx</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>7998</year>, <source>NcW</source>, fhozvggrq</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orpxrafgrva</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvytebz</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8435</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>731</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orpxrafgrva</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fnaqref</surname><given-names>E. U.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8445</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>574</volume>, <fpage>539</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oenvareq</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oynaqsbeq</surname><given-names>E. Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fznvy</surname><given-names>V. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8441</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>511</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Svfpure</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>NW</source>, <volume>879</volume>, <fpage>8843</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tneanivpu</surname><given-names>C. Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ybro</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fgnarx</surname><given-names>X. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>055</volume>, <fpage>Y88</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xbbcznaf</surname><given-names>Y. I. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jnzoftnaff</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7998</year>, <source>ZAENF</source>, va cerff</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yrjvf</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vongn</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jlvgur</surname><given-names>W. F. O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>057</volume>, <fpage>Y4</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Znaaurvz</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xnmnanf</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8434</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>657</volume>, <fpage>160</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvytebz</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8436</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>729</volume>, <fpage>610</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvenyqn-Rfphqé</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8448</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>629</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <citation citation-type="other" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zbegybpx</surname><given-names>Q. W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheare</surname><given-names>R. Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7998</year>, <source>ZAENF</source>, <volume>672</volume>, <fpage>002</fpage> (Cncre VV, guvf vffhr)</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Angnenwna</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ersertvre</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>063</volume>, <fpage>Y886</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anineeb</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serax</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juvgr</surname><given-names>F. Q. Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8440</year>, <source>ZAENF</source>, <volume>720</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anineeb</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serax</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juvgr</surname><given-names>F. Q. Z.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8441</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>517</volume>, <fpage>016</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Øfgrafra</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8441</year>, <source>N&amp;N</source>, <volume>694</volume>, <fpage>04</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cnpmlńfxv</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8441</year>, <source>NEN&amp;N</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>584</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crroyrf</surname><given-names>C. W. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8446</year>, <source>Cevapvcyrf bs Culfvpny Pbfzbybtl</source>. <publisher-name>Cevaprgba Havi. Cerff</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cevaprgba, AW</publisher-loc></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cryg</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fpuvyq</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ersfqny</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fgnoryy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8443</year>, <source>N&amp;N</source>, <volume>517</volume>, <fpage>016</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cbfgzna</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tryyre</surname><given-names>Z. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8435</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>738</volume>, <fpage>40</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dva</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jh</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mbh</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8440</year>, <source>N&amp;N</source>, <volume>741</volume>, <fpage>715</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebbq</surname><given-names>U. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8435</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>735</volume>, <fpage>592</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fntne</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zbuna</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cnaqrl</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cnaqrl</surname><given-names>N. X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fgnyva</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pnfgeb-Gvenqb</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>Ohyy. Nfg. Fbp. Vaqvn</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>544</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fpuarvqre</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruyref</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snypb</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8447</year>, <source>Tenivgngvbany Yrafrf</source>. <publisher-name>Fcevatre-Ireynt</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oreyva</publisher-loc></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gnqebf</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jneera</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urjrgg</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7998</year>, va <source>Pbfzbybtvpny Culfvpf jvgu Tenivgngvbany Yrafvat</source>. <publisher-name>Rqvgvba Sebagvèerf</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Tvs-fhe-Lirggr</publisher-loc> va cerff</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gbuyvar</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8436</year>, va <source>Vagreany Xvarzngvpf naq Qlanzvpf bs Tnynkvrf</source>. <publisher-name>Ervqry</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Qbeqerpug</publisher-loc>, c. <fpage>790</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gevzoyr</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8432</year>, <source>NEN&amp;N</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>570</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jnyxre</surname><given-names>Z. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8445</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>569</volume>, <fpage>516</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jnyxre</surname><given-names>Z. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>8444</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>691</volume>, <fpage>095</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jbźavnx</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyneq</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hqnyfxv</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fmlzáafxv</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xhovnx</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cvrgemlńfxv</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mroehń</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>NcW</source>, <volume>074</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lbex</surname><given-names>Q. T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>7999</year>, <source>NW</source>, <volume>879</volume>, <fpage>8024</fpage></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn1" fn-type="other">
        <label>
          <sup>8</sup>
        </label>
        <p>Gur inyhr vf fyvtugyl ynetre guna gur npghny Rvafgrva enqvv bs gur tnynkvrf orpnhfr bs gur hfr bs gur cbvag-znff yraf zbqry, naq gur ynetr reebe vf n pbzovangvba bs hapregnvagvrf va gur qvfgnapr zrnfherf naq gur fvmr bs gur sbertebhaq tnynkvrf.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
